The Essays

Or, Moral, Political, and Military Discourses

of Lord Michael de Montaigne,

Knight of the noble Order of Saint Michael, and one of the Gentlemen in Ordinary of the French Kings Chamber

The Author to the Reader

Reader, behold here a well-meaning book. It does at the first entrance forewarn you, that in contriving the same I have proposed unto myself no other than a familiar and private end. I have no respect or consideration at all, either to your service, or to my glory; my forces are not capable of any such design. I have vowed the same to the particular commodity of my kinsfolk and friends, to the end that losing me (which they are likely to do ere long) they may therein find some lineaments of my conditions and humors, and by that means reserve more whole, and more-lively foster, the knowledge and acquaintance they have had of me. Had my intention been to forestall and purchase the world’s opinion and favor, I would surely have adorned myself more quaintly, or kept a more grave and solemn march. I desire therein to be delineated in my own genuine, simple, and ordinary fashion, without contention, art, or study—for it is myself I portray. My imperfections shall therein be read to the life, and my natural form discerned, so far as public reverence has permitted me. For if my fortune had been to have lived among those nations which yet are said to live under the sweet liberty of Nature’s first and uncorrupted laws, I assure you I would most willingly have portrayed myself fully and naked. Thus, gentle Reader, myself am the groundwork of my book: it is then no reason you should employ your time about so frivolous and vain a subject. Therefore farewell, From Montaigne, the first of March, 1580.

Chapter I:
By diverse means men come to a like end.

The most usual way to appease those minds we have offended (when revenge lies in their hands and we stand at their mercy) is, by submission, to move them to commiseration and pity. Nevertheless, courage, constancy, and resolution (means altogether opposite) have sometimes wrought the same effect. Edward the black Prince of Wales (who so long governed our country of Guyenne, a man whose conditions and fortune were accompanied with many notable parts of worth and magnanimity) having been grievously offended by the Limosins, though he by main force took and entered their city, could by no means be appeased, nor by the wailful outcries of all sorts of people (as of men, women, and children) be moved to any pity, they prostrating themselves to the common slaughter, crying for mercy, and humbly submitting themselves at his feet, until such time as, in triumphant manner passing through their city, he perceived three French gentlemen, who alone, with an incredible and undaunted boldness, gainstood the enraged violence and made head against the fury of his victorious army. The consideration and respect of so notable a virtue did first abate the dint of his wrath, and from those three he began to relent, and to show mercy to all the other inhabitants of the said town. Skanderbeg, Prince of Epirus, following one of his soldiers with purpose to kill him, who by all means of humility and submissive entreaty had first offered to pacify him, in such an unavoidable extremity resolved at last resolutely to encounter him with his sword in his hand. This resolution did immediately stay his captain’s fury, who seeing him undertake so honorable an attempt, not only forgave, but received him into grace and favor. This example may perhaps, of such as have not known the prodigious force and matchless valor of the said Prince, admit another interpretation.

The Emperor Conrad, third of that name, having besieged Welf, Duke of Bavaria, whatever vile or base satisfaction was offered him, would yield to no other milder conditions, but only to suffer such gentlewomen as were with the Duke in the city (their honors safe) to issue out of the town afoot, with such things as they could carry about them. They with an unrelenting courage advised and resolved themselves (neglecting all other riches or jewels) to carry their husbands, their children, and the Duke himself, on their backs. The Emperor perceiving the quaintness of their device, took so great pleasure at it that he wept for joy, and forthwith converted that former inexorable rage and mortal hatred he bare the Duke, into so mild a relenting and gentle kindness, that thenceforward he entreated both him and his with all favor and courtesy.

Either of these ways might easily persuade me: for I am much inclined to mercy, and affected to mildness. So it is, that in my opinion, I should more naturally stoop unto compassion, than bend to estimation. Yet is pity held a vicious passion among the Stoics. They would have us aid the afflicted, but not to faint and co-suffer with them. These examples seem fittest for me, forasmuch as these minds are seen to be assaulted and environed by these two means, in undauntedly suffering the one, and stooping under the other. It may perhaps be said that to yield ones heart unto commiseration is an effect of facility, tenderness, and meekness: whence it proceedes, that the weakest natures, as of women, children, and the vulgar sort are more subject unto it. But (having contemned tears and wailings) to yield unto the only reverence of the sacred image of virtue is the effect of a couragious and employable mind, holding a masculine and contant vigor in honor and affection. Notwithstanding, amazement and admiration may in less generous minds work the like effect. Witness the Thebans, who having accused and indicted their captains, as of a capital crime, forasmuch as they had continued their charge beyond the time prescribed them, absolved and acquitted Pelopidas of all punishment, because he submissively yielded under the burden of such objections, and to save himself, employed no other means but suing requests and demiss entreaties; where on the contrary, Epaminondas boldly relating the exploits achieved by him, and with a fierce and arrogant manner upbraiding the people with them, had not the heart so much as to take their lots into his hands, but went his way, and was freely absolved; the assembly much commending the stoutness of his courage.

Dionysius the elder, after extreme difficulties, having taken the city of Rhegium, and in it the Captain Phyton (a worthy honest man) who had so obstinately defended the same, would show a tragical example of revenge. First, he told him how the day before he had caused his son and all his kinsfolk to be drowned. To whom Phyton, stoutly out-staring him, answered nothing but that they were more happy than himself by the space of one day. Afterward he caused him to be stripped, and by his executioners to be taken and dragged through the city most ignominiously, whipping him, charging him besides with contumelious speeches. All which notwithstanding, as one no whit dismayed, he ever showed a constant and resolute heart, and with a cheerful and bold countenance went on still, loudly recounting the honorable and glorious cause of his death, which was that he would never consent to yield his country into the hands of a cruel tyrant, menacing him with an imminent punishment of the Gods. Dionysius plainly reading in his soldiers looks, that in lieu of animating them with braving his conquered enemy, they in contempt of him, and scorn of his triumph, seemed by the astonishment of so rare a virtue, to be moved with compassion, and inclined to mutiny, indeed, and to free Phyton from out of the hands of his sergeants or guard, caused his torture to cease, and secretly sent him to be drowned in the sea.

Surely, man is a wonderful, vain, diverse, and wavering subject: it is very hard to ground any directly-constant and uniform judgement upon him. Behold Pompey, who freely pardoned all the city of the Mamertines (against which he was grievously enraged) for the love of the magnanimity and consideration of the exceeding virtue of Zeno, one of their fellow-citizens, who took the public fault wholly upon himself and desired no other favor, but alone to bear the punishment thereof; whereas Sylla’s host having used the like virtue in the city of Perugia, obtained nothing, neither for himself nor for others. And directly against my first example, the hardiest amongst men, and so gracious to the vanquished, Alexander the Great, after many strange difficulties forcing the city of Gaza, encountered by chance with Betis, that commanded therein, of whose valor (during the siege) he had felt wonderful and strange exploits, being then alone, forsaken of all his followers, his arms all broken, all besmeared with blood and wounds, fighting amongst a number of Macedonians, who pell-mell laid still upon him; provoked by so dear a victory (for among other mishaps he had newly received two hurts in his body) said this unto him: Betis, you shall not die as you would, for make account you must endure all the torments may possibly be devised or inflicted upon a captive wretch, as you are. But he, for all his enemy’s threats, without speaking one word, returned only an assured, stern, and disdainful countenance upon him; which silent obstinacy Alexander noting, said thus unto himself: What? would he not bend his knee? could he not utter one suppliant voice? I will assuredly vanquish his silence, and if I can not wrest a word from him, I will at least make him to sob or groan. And converting his anger into rage, commanded his heels to be pierced through, and so all alive with a cord through them, to be torn, mangled, and dismembered at a cart’s tail. May it be, the force of his courage, was so natural and peculiar unto him, that because he would no whit admire him, he respected him the less? or deemed he it so proper unto himself, that in his height he could not, without the spigot of envious passion, endure to see it in another? or was the natural violence of his rage incapable of any opposition? Surely, had it received any restraint, it may be supposed that, in the ransacking and desolation of the city of Thebes, it should have felt the same; in seeing so many worthies lost, and valiant men put to the sword, as having no means of public defense; for above six thousand were slain and massacred, of which not one was seen either to run away or beg for grace. But on the contrary, some here and there seeking to affront, and endeavoring to check their victorious enemies, urging and provoking them to force them die an honorable death. Not one was seen to yield, and that to his last gasp did not attempt to revenge himself, and with all weapons of despair, with the death of some enemy comfort and sweeten his own misery. Yet could not the affliction of their virtue find any ruth or pity, nor might one day suffice to glut or assuage his revengeful wrath. This butcherous slaughter continued unto the last drop of any remaining blood; where none were spared but the unarmed and naked, the aged and impotent, the women and children; that so from amongst them, they might get thirty thousand slaves.

Chapter II:
Of sadness or sorrow

No man is more free from this passion than I, for I neither love nor regard it: albeit the world has undertaken, as it were upon covenant, to grace it with a particular favor. Therewith they adorn age, virtue, and conscience. Oh foolish and base ornament! The Italians have more properly with its name entitled malignity: for it is a quality ever hurtful, ever sottish, and as ever base and coward. The Stoics inhibit their elders and sages to be therewith tainted, or have any feeling of it.

But the story says that Psammetichus, king of Egypt, having been defeated and taken by Cambyses king of Persia, seeing his own daughter pass before him in base and vile array, being sent to draw water from a well, his friends weeping and wailing about him (he, with his eyes fixed on the ground, could not be moved to utter one word), and shortly after beholding his son led to execution, held still the same undaunted countenance. But perceiving a familiar friend of his hauled amongst the captives, he began to beat his head, and burst forth into extreme sorrow.

This might well be compared to that which one of our Princes was lately seen to do, who being at Trent, and receiving news of his elder brother’s death—but such a brother as on him lay all the burden and honor of his house—and shortly after tidings of his younger brother’s decease, who was his second hope—and having with an unmatched countenance and exemplar constancy endured these two affronts, it fortuned not long after, that one of his servants dying, he by this latter accident suffered himself to be so far transported, that quitting and forgetting his former resolution, he so abandoned himself to all manner of sorrow and grief, that some argued, only this last mischance had touched him to the quick. But truly the reason was that being otherwise full, and over-plunged in sorrow, the least surcharge broke the bounds and bars of patience.

The like might (I say) be judged of our story, were it not that it follows that Cambyses enquiring of Psammetichus why, when he was not distempered at the misfortune of his son and daughter, he did so impatiently bear the disaster of his friend: “It is,” answered he, “because this last displeasure may be manifested by weeping whereas the two former exceed by much all means and compass to be expressed by tears.”

The invention of that ancient painter might happily fit this purpose, who in The Sacrifice of Iphigenia, being to represent the grief of the by-standers according to the quality and interest each one bare for the death of so fair, so young, and innocent a lady, having ransacked the utmost skill and effects of his art, when he came to the virgin’s father, as if no countenance were able to represent that degree of sorrow, he drew him with a veil over his face. And that is the reason why our poets feign miserable Niobe, who first having lost seven sons and immediately as many daughters, as one over-burdened with their losses, to have been transformed into a stone;

Diriguisse malis:
―Ovid, Metamorphoses 1, book 6, 303.

And grew as hard as stone,
But misery and moan.

Thereby to express this mournful, silent stupidity, which so does pierce us when accidents surpassing our strength overwhelm us. Verily the violence of a grief, being extreme, must astound the mind and hinder the liberty of her actions. As it happens at the sudden alarm of some bad tidings, when we shall feel ourselves surprised, benumbed, and as it were deprived of all motion, so that the soul, bursting afterward forth into tears and complaints, seems at more ease and liberty to loose, to clear, and dilate itself.

Et via vix tandem voci laxata dolore est,
―Virgiil Ænid 1, book 11, 151.

And scarce at last for speech, By grief was made a breach.

In the wars which king Ferdinand made against the widow of John, king of Hungary, about Buda, a man at arms was particularly noted of all men, as in a certain skirmish he had shown exceeding prowess of his body, and, though unknown, being slain, was highly commended and much bemoaned of all; but yet of none so greatly as of a German lord, called Raisciac, as he that was amazed at so rare virtue. His body being recovered and had off, this Lord, led by a common curiosity, drew near unto it to see who it might be, and having caused him to be disarmed, perceived him to be his own son, which known, did greatly augment the compassion of all the camp. He only, without framing word or closing his eyes, but earnestly viewing the dead body of his son, stood still up upright, till the vehemence of his sad sorrow, having suppressed and choked his vital spirits, felled him stark dead to the ground.

Chi puo dir com’ egli arde è in picciol fuoco,
―Petrarch p. 1, Sonnet 140.

He that can say how he does fry,
In petty-gentle flames does lie,

say those Lovers that would lively represent an intolerable passion.

misero quod omnes
Eripit sensus mihi; Nam simul te
Lesbia aspexi, nihil est super mî
Quod loquar amens
Lingua sed torpet, tenuis sub artus
Flamma dimanant, sonitu suopte
Tinniunt aures, gemina teguntur Lumina nocte.

―Catul. Epig. xlviii. 5.

miserably from one
This bereaves all sense: for I can no sooner
Eye you my sweet heart, but I wot not one word to speak amazed.
Tongue-tied as in a trance, while a sprightly thin flame
Flows in all my joints with a self-resounding
Both my ears tingle, with a night redoubled
Both mine eyes are veiled.

Nor is it in the liveliest and most ardent heat of the fit that we are able to display our plaints and persuasions, the soul being then aggravated with heavy thoughts, and the body suppressed and languishing for love. And thence is sometimes engendered that casual faintness, which so unseasonably surprises passionate lovers, and that childlikeness, which by the

Curae leves loquuntur, ingentes stupent.
―Seneca Hippolytus, act 2, scene 2.

Light cares can freely speak,
Great cares heart rather break.

The surprise of an unexpected pleasure astonishes us likewise.

Ut me conspexit venientem, et Troja circum
Arma amens vidit, magnis exterrita monstris,
Deriguit visu in medio, calor ossa relinquit,
Labitur, et longo vix tandem tempore fatur.

―Virgil Ænid 1, book 3, 306.

When she beheld me come, and round about
Senseless saw Trojan arms, she stood afraid
Stone-still at so strange sights: life heat flew out.
She faints: at last, with long pause thus she said.

Besides the Roman lady, who died for joy to see her son return alive from the battle of Cannae; Sophocles and Dionysius the Tyrant, who deceased through overgladness; and Talva, who died in Corsica, reading the news of the honors the Roman Senate had conferred him; it is reported that in our age, Pope Leo the tenth having received advertisement of the taking of the city of Milan, which be had so exceedingly desired, entered into such excess of joy, that he fell into an ague whereof he shortly died. And for a more authentic testimony of humane imbecility, it is noted by our Ancients that Diodorus the Logician, being surprised with an extreme passion or apprehension of shame, fell down stark dead (because neither in his School, nor in public, had he been able to resolve an argument propounded to him). I am little subject to these violent passions. I have naturally a hard apprehension, which by discourse I daily harden more and more.

Chapter III:
Our affections are transported beyond ourselves.

Those who still accuse men for ever gaping after future things, and go about to teach us to take hold of present fortunes and settle ourselves upon them, as having no hold of that which is to come—indeed much less than we have of that which is already past—touch and are ever harping upon the commonest human error, if they dare call that an error, to which Nature herself, for the service of the continuation of her work, does address us, imprinting (as it does many others) this false imagination in us, as more jealous of our actions than of our knowledge. We are never in ourselves, but beyond. Fear, desire, and hope, draw us ever towards that which is to come, and remove our sense and consideration from that which is, to amuse us on that which shall be, indeed when we shall be no more. Calamitosus est animus futuri anxius. A mind in suspense of what is to come is in a pitiful case.

This noble precept is often cited in Plato: “Follow your business and know yourself.” Each of these two members does generally imply all our duty, and likewise enfolds his companion. He that should do his business might perceive that his first lesson is to know what he is, and what is convenient for him. And he that knows himself, takes no more another’s matters for his own, but, above all other things, loves and corrects himself, and rejects superfluous occupations, idle imaginations, and unprofitable propositions. As if you grant folly what it desires it will no whit be satisfied, so is wisdom content with that which is present, and never displeased with itself.

Epicurus does dispense with his age touching the foresight and care of what shall insue. Amongst the laws that regard the deceased, that which ties the actions of Princes to be examined when they are dead, seems to me very solid. They are companions, if not masters of the laws: That which justice could not work on their heads, it is reason it effect upon their reputation, and goods of their successors: things we many times prefer before our lives. It is a custom brings many singular commodities unto nations that observe it, and to be desired of all good Princes: who have cause to complain that the memory of the wicked is used as theirs. We owe a like obedience and subjection to all Kings, for it respects their office; but estimation and affection, we owe it only to their virtue. If they be unworthy, we are to endure them patiently, to conceal their vices, and to aid their indifferent actions with our commendations, as long as their authority has need of our assistance, and that ought to be ascribed unto political order. But our commerce with them being ended, there is no reason we should refuse the unfolding of our felt wrongs unto justice and our liberty. And specially to refuse good subjects the glory to have reverently and faithfully served a master whose imperfections were so well known unto them, exempting posterity from so profitable an example. And such as for the respect of some private benefit or interest, do wickedly embrace the memory of an unworthy Prince, do particular justice at the charge of public justice.

Titus Livius speaks truly, where he says that the speech of men brought up under a royalty is ever full of vain ostentations and false witness—every man indifferently extolling the King, to the furthest strain of valor and sovereign greatness. The magnanimity of those two soldiers may be reproved, one of which, being demanded of Nero why he hated him, answered him to his teeth: I loved you while you were worthy of love, but since you becamest a parricide, a firebrand, a jester, a player, and a coachman, I hate you, as you deserve. The other being asked why he sought to kill him, answered: Because I find no other course to hinder your incessant outrages and impious deeds. But can any man, that has his senses about him, justly prove the public and general testimonies that since his death have been given, and so shall be forever, both against him and all such like reprobates, of his tyrannical and wicked demeanours?

I am sorry that, in so sacred a policy as the Lacedaemonian was, so feigned and foolish a ceremony at the death of their Kings was ever devised and brought in use. All their confederates and neighbors, all the slave-helots, men and women pell-mell, for a testimony of their grief and sorrow, did mangle and gash their foreheads, and in their outcries and lamentations exclaimed that their deceased King, however he had lived, was and had been the best Prince that ever they had, ascribing in order the commendations due unto desert, and to the last and latter rank what belongs unto the first merit.

Aristotle, who has an oar in every water and meddles with all things, makes a question about Solon’s speech, who says that no man can truly be counted happy before his death: Whether he that lived and died according to his wish may be named happy, whether his renown be good or ill, and whether his posterity be miserable or no. While we stir and remove, we transport ourselves by preoccupation wherever we list: but no sooner are we out of being, but we have no communication at all with that which is. And it were better to tell Solon, that never man is happy then, since he never is so, but when he is no more.

—Quisquam
Vix radicitus e vita se tollit, et ejicit:
Se facit esse qui quiddam super inscius ipse,
Nee removet satis a projecto corpora sese, et
Vindicat.—

―Lucretius De Rerum Natura book 3, 912

Scarce any rids himself of life so clear
But leaves unwitting some part of him here:
Nor frees or quits himself sufficiently
From that his body which forlorn does lie.

Bertrand du Guesclin died at the siege of the castle of Randon, near unto Puy in Avergne: the besieged, yielding afterwards, were forced to carry the keys of the Castle upon the decease of the Captain. Bartholomew d’Alviano, General of the Venetian forces, dying in their service and wars about Brescia, and his body being to be transported to Venice through the territory of Verona, which was then enemy unto them, the greatest part of the army thought it expedient to demand a safe conduct for their passage of those of Verona, to which Teodoro Trivulzio stoutly opposed himself, and chose rather to pass it by main force and to hazard the day, saying it was not convenient that he who in his lifetime had never apprehended fear of his enemies should now, being dead, seem to fear them. Verily in like matters, by the laws of Greece he that required a dead body of his enemies, with intent to bury the same, renounced the victory and might no more erect any trophy of it—and he, who was so required, purchased the title of honor and gain. So did Nicias lose the advantage he had clearely gained of the Corinthians; and contrariwise, Agesilaus assured that, he doubtfully had gotten of the Boeotians.

These actions might be deemed strange, if in all ages it were not a commonly received opinion, not only to extend the care of ourselves beyond this life, but also to believe, that heavenly favors do often accompany us into our grave, and continue in our posterity. Whereof there are so many examples (leaving our modern apart) that I need not wade far into it.

Edward the first, King of England, in the long wars he had with Robert, King of Scotland—having by trial found how greatly his presence advantaged the success of his affairs, and how he was ever victorious in any enterprise he undertook in his own person—when he died, bound his son by solemn oath, that being dead he should cause his body to be boiled until the flesh fell from the bones, which he should cause to be interred, and, carefully keeping the bones, ever carry them about him, whenever he should happen to have wars with the Scots. As if destiny had fatally annexed the victory unto his limbs.

Jan Žižka, who for the defense of Wycliffe’s opinions so much troubled the state of Bohemia, commanded that after his death his body should be flayed, and a drum made of his skin, to be carried and sounded in all the wars against his enemies—deeming the sound of it would be a means to continue the advantages which in his former wars he had obtained of them. Certain Indians did likewise carry the bones of one of their Captains in the skirmishes they had with the Spaniards, in regard of the good success he had while he lived, against them. And other nations of that new-found world, do likewise carry the bodies of such worthy and fortunate men with them as have died in their battles, to serve them in stead of good fortune and encouragement.

The first examples reserve nothing else in their tombs but the reputation acquired by their former achievements: but these will also adjoin unto it the power of working. The act of Captain Bayard is of better composition, who perceiving himself deadly wounded by a shot received in his body, being by his men persuaded to come off and retire himself from out of the throng, answered: he would not now so near his end begin to turn his face from his enemy—and having stoutly fought so long as he could stand, feeling himself to faint and stagger from his horse, commanded his steward to lay him against a tree, but in such sort that he might die with his face toward the enemy, as indeed he did.

I may not omit this other example, as remarkable for this consideration, as any of the preceding. The Emperor Maximilian, great grandfather to Philip, now King of Spain, was a Prince highly endowed with many noble qualities, and amongst others with a well-nigh matchless comeliness of body; but with other customs of his, he had this one much contrary to other Princes (who to dispatch their weightiest affairs make often their chamber pot their regal Throne or Council-Chamber) which was that he would not permit any groom of his chamber (were he never so near about him) to see him in his inner chamber, who if he had occasion but to make water, would as nicely and as religiously withdraw himself as any maiden, and never suffer so much as a physician, much less any other whatsoever, to see those private parts that all in modesty seek to keep secret and unseen. My self, that am so broad-mouthed and lavish in speeches, am notwithstanding naturally touched with that bashfulness. And unless it be by the motion of necessity or of voluptuousness, I never willingly imparted those actions and parts (which custom wills to be concealed) to the view of any creature. I endure more compulsion than I deem befitting a man, especially of my profession. But he grew to such superstition, that by express words in his last will and Testament, he commanded that being dead he should have underclothes put about them. He should by codicil have annexed unto it, that he who should put them on might have his eyes blindfolded.

The instruction which Cyrus gives his children, that neither they nor any other should either see or touch his body after the breath were once out of it, I ascribe it unto some motive of devotion in him. For both his historian and himself, amongst many other notable qualities they are endowed with, have throughout all the course of their life seemed to have a singular respect and awful reverence unto religion.

That story displeased me very much, which a nobleman told me of a kinsman of mine (a man very famous and well known both in peace and war), which is, that dying very aged in his court, being much tormented with extreme pangs of the stone, he, with an earnest and unwearied care, employed all his last hours to dispose the honor and ceremony of his funerals, and summoned all the nobility that came to visit him, to give him assured premise to be as assistants, and to convey him to his last resting place. To the very same Prince who was with him at his last gasp, he made very earnest suit he would command all his household to wait upon him at his interment, enforcing many reasons, and alleging diverse examples to prove that it was a thing very convenient and fitting a man of his quality: which assured promise when he had obtained, and had at his pleasure marshalled the order how they should march, he seemed quietly and contentedly to yield up the ghost. I have seldom seen a vanity continue for so long.

This other curiosity, entirely opposite unto it (which to prove I need not labor for home-examples) seems in my opinion first cousin to this, that is, when one is ever ready to breathe his last, carefully and passionately to endeavor how to reduce the convoy of his obsequies unto some particular and unwonted parcimony, to one servant and to one lantern. I hear the humor and appointment of Marcus Æmilius Lepidus commended, who expressly forbade his heirs to use those ceremonies about his interment, which in such cases were formerly accustomed. Is it temperance and frugality, to avoid charge and voluptuousness, the use and knowledge of which is imperceptible unto us? See here an easy reformation, and of small cost. Were it requisite to appoint any, I would be of opinion that, as well in that as in all other actions of man’s life, every man should refer the rule of it to the quality of his fortune. And the Philosopher Lycon did wisely appoint his friends to place his body where they should think it fittest and for the best: and for his obsequies, they should neither be superfluous and over-costly, nor base and sparing. For my part, I would wholly rely on custom, which should dispose this ceremony, and would yield myself to the discretion of the first or next into whose hands I might chance to fall. Totus hic locus est contemnendus in nobis, non negligendus in nostris: “All this matter should be despised of us, but not neglected of ours.” And religiously said a holy man: Curatio funeris, conditio sepulturae, pompa exequiarum, magis sunt vivorum solatia, quam subsidia mortuorum: “In the procuration of funerals, the manner of burial, the pomp of obsequies, are rather comforts to the living, than helps to the dead.” Therefore Socrates answered Criton, who at the hour of his death asked him how he would be buried: Even as you please, said he.

Were I to meddle further with this subject, I would deem it more gallant to imitate those who, yet living and breathing, undertake to enjoy the order and honor of their sepulchres, and that please themselves to behold their dead countenance in marble. Happy they that can rejoice and gratify their sense with insensibility, and live by their death!

A little thing would make me conceive an inexpiable hatred against all popular domination—although it seem most natural and just unto me—when I call to mind that inhumane injustice of the Athenians, who, without further trial or remission, indeed without suffering them so much as to reply or answer for themselves, condemned those noble and worthy Captains that returned victoriously from the sea battle, which they (near the Arginusæ islands) had gained of the Macedenonians—the most contested, bloody, and greatest fight the Greeks ever obtained by sea with their own forces—forasmuch as after the victory, they had rather followed those occasions which the law of war presented unto them, for their avail, than to their prejudice stayed to gather and bury their dead men. And the success of Diomedon makes their ruthless execution more hateful, who being a man of notable and exemplary virtue, both military and political, and of them so cruelly condemned; after he had heard the bloody sentence, advancing himself forward to speak, having fit opportunity and plausible audience; he, I say, instead of excusing himself, or endeavoring to justify his cause, or to exasperate the evident iniquity of so cruel a doom, expressed but a care of the Judges preservation, earnestly beseeching the Gods to turn that judgement to their good, praying that for want of not satisfying the vows which he and his companions had vowed in acknowledgement and thanksgiving for so famous a victory and honorable fortune, they might not draw the wrath and revenge of the Gods upon them, declaring what their vows were. And without more words, or any further reasons, courageously addressed himself to his execution. But fortune some years after punished him likewise, and made him taste of the very same sauce. For Chabrias, Captain General of their sea fleet, having afterward obtained a famous victory of Pollis, Admiral of Sparta, in the Isle of Naxos, lost absolutely the benefit of it, and only contented with the day (a matter of great consequence for their affairs) fearing to incur the mischief of this example, and to save a few dead carcasses of his friends, that floated up and down the sea, gave leisure to an infinite number of his living enemies, whom he might easily have surprised, to sail away in safety, who afterward made them to purchase their importunate superstition, at a dear-dear rate.

Quaeris, quo jaceas, post obitum, loco
Quo non nata jacent.

―Seneca Troades, chorus, act 2, verse 30.

Where shall you lie when you are dead?
Where they lie that were never bred.

This other restores the sense of rest unto a body without a soul,

Neque sepulchrum, quo recipiat, habeat portum corporis.
Ubi remi ssa humana vita, corpus requiescat a malis?

―Cicero Tusculanæ Quæstiones book 1. Enni.

To turn in as a haven, have he no grave,
Where life left, from all grief he rest may have.

Even as Nature makes us to see that many dead things have yet certain secret relations unto life. Wine does alter and change in cellars, according to the changes and alterations of the seasons of its vineyard. And the flesh of wild beasts and venison does change quality and taste in the salting-tubs, according to the nature of living flesh, as some say that have observed it.

Chapter IV: How the soul discharges her passions upon false objects when the true fail it.

A gentleman of ours, exceedingly subject to the gout, being instantly solicited by his physicians to leave all manner of salt-meats, was wont to answer pleasantly, that when the fits or pangs of the disease took him, he would have somebody to quarrel with; and that crying and cursing, now against baloney-sausage, and sometimes by railing against salt beef-tongues, and gammons of bacon, he found some ease. But in good earnest even as the arm being lifted up to strike, if the stroke hit not, but fall void, we feel some pain in it, and many times strike it out of joint; and that to yield our sight pleasant, it must not be lost and dispersed in the vast air, but ought rather to have a limited bound to sustain it by a reasonable distance.

Ventus ut amittit vires, nisi robore densæ,
Occurrant silvæ, spatio diffasus inani.

―Lucan, Pharsalia book 3, 362.

As winds in empty air diffus’d, strength lose,
Unless thick-old-grown woods their strength oppose.

So seems it that the soul moved and tossed, if she have not some hold to take, loses itself in itself, and must ever be stored with some object, on which it light and work. Plutarch says fitly of those who affectionate themselves to monkeys and little dogs, that the loving part which is in us, for want of a lawful hold, rather than it will be idle, does forge a false and frivolous hold unto itself. And we see that the soul in her passions does rather deceive itself, by framing a false and fantastic subject unto itself, indeed against her own conceit, than not to work upon something. So does their own rage transport beasts to set upon the stone or weapon that has hurt them—indeed sometimes with irefull teeth to revenge themselves against themselves—for the hurt or smart they feel.

Pannonis haud aliter post ictum sævior ursa
Cum jaculum parva Libys amentavit habena,
Se rotat in vulnus, telumque irata receptum
Impetit, et secum fugientem circuit hastam.

―Lucan, Pharsalia book 6, 220.

Even so the wound-enraged Austrian bear,
On whom a Moor has thir’ld his slinged spear,
Wheels on her wound, and raging bites the dart,
Circling that flies with her, and cannot part.

What causes do we not invent for the crosses that happen unto us? Be it right or wrong: what take we not hold of, to have something to strive with? It is not the golden locks you tear, nor the whiteness of the breast, which you through vexation so cruelly do smite, that have by means of an unlucky bullet lost your dear-beloved brother. On something else should you avenge yourself. Livius, speaking of the Roman army in Spain, after the loss of two great Captains that were brethren: Flere omnes repente, et offensare capita: “They all wept and often beat their heads.” It is an ordinary custom. And the philosopher Bion was very pleasant with the king, who for grief tore his hair, when he said, “Does this man think that baldness will assuage his grief?” Who has not seen some to chew and swallow cards, and well-nigh choke themselves with pairs of dice, only to be revenged for the loss of some money? Xerxes whipped the sea, and wrote a challenge of defiance to the hill Athos. And Cyrus for many days together amused his whole army to be revenged of the river Gyndus, for the fear he took passing over the same. And Caligula caused a very fair house to be defaced, for the pleasure his mother had received in the same.

When I was young, my countrymen were wont to say that one of our neighbor-Kings, having received a blow at Gods hand, swore to be revenged on him, and ordained that for ten years space no man should pray unto him, nor speak of him, nor (so long as he were in authority), believe in him. By which report, they do not so much publish the sottishness, as the ambitious glory, peculiar unto that nation of whom it was spoken. They are vices that ever go together, but in truth such actions incline rather unto self-conceit than to foolishness. Augustus Cæsar, having been beaten by a tempest on the sea, defied the God Neptune, and in the celebration of the Circensian games, that so he might be avenged on him, he caused his image to be removed from the place, where it stood amongst the other Gods; wherein he is also less excusable than the former, and less than he was afterward, when having lost a battle under Quintilius Varus in Germany, all in a rage and desperate, he went up and down beating his head against the walls, mainly crying out: “Oh! Varus, restore me my soldiers again.” For those exceed all folly (forasmuch as impiety is joined unto it) that will avenge themselves against God, or fortune, as if she had ears subject to our battery. In imitation of the Thracians, who when it lightens or thunders, begin with a Titanian revenge to shoot against heaven, thinking by shooting of arrows to draw God to some reason. Now, as says that ancient Poet in Plutarch,

Point ne se faut courroucer aux affaires,
Il ne leur chaut de toutes nos choleres.

&qdash;Plutarch Of Contentment, chapter 4 in Amyot’s translation

We ought not angry be at what God dooth,
For he cares not who bears an angry tooth.

But we shall never rail enough against the disorder and unruliness of our mind.

Chapter V.
Whether the captain of a place besieged ought to sally forth to parlay

Lucius Marcius, Legate of the Romans, in the war against Perseus, King of Macedon, desirous to get so much time as he wanted to prepare his army, gave out some motives of accord, wherewith the king inveagled, yielded unto a truce for certain days: by which means he furnished his enemy with opportunity and leisure to arm himself: whereof proceeded the Kings last ruine and over-throw. Yet is it, that the elders of the Senate, mindfull of their fore-fathers customs, condemned this practice as an enemy to their ancient proceedings, which was, said they, to fight with virtue, and not with craft, not by surprises, or stratagems by night, nor by set-flights, and unlookt-for approches, never undertaking a war, but after it was proclaimed, indeed many times after the appointed hour and place of the battle. With this conscience did they send backe to Pirrhus his traitorous Physitian, and to the Phalisci their disloyall schoolemaster. These were true Roman proceedings, and not Greek policies, nor Punike whes, with whom to vanquish by force is less glorious than to conquer by treacherie. To deceive may serve for the instant but he only is judged to be overcome, that knowes he was not vanquished by craft or deceit, nor by fortune or chance, but by meere valor, betweene troupe and troupe, in an overt and just war. It appeareth manifestly by the speech of these good men, they had not yet received this sentence. Dolus, an virtus, quis in hoste requirat? -- VIR. æn. 1. ii. 390. Deceit, or virtue, either, in foes, it skills not whether. The Achaians, says Polibius, detested all manner of deceit in their wars, deeming that no victory, where their enemies courages were not quelled. Eam vir sanctus, et sapiens sciat esse victoriam veram, quæ salva fide, et integra dignitate parabitur. ’A wise and religious man will know that is victory indeed, which shall be attained with credit unimpeached, and dignitie untainted,’ says another. Vos ne velit, an me regnare hera, quid-ve ferat fors, Virtute experiamur. -- CIC. Offic. If fortune will have you to raigne, or me, And what chance brings, let virtue’s trial be. In the Kingdome of Ternates, among those nations, which we so full-mouthed, call barbarous, the custom beareth, that they never undertake a war, before the same be denounced; thereunto adding an ample declaration of the means they have to employ therein, what manner, and how many men, what munition, and what Armes either offensive or defensive: which done, they also establish as a law, that without reproach or imputation, it shall be lawfull for any man, in their wars, to use what advantage soever, may in any sort further or help them to vanquish. The ancient Florentines were so far from desiring any advantage of their enemies by sudden surprises, that a moneth before they could bring their Armie into the field, they would give them warning, by the continuall sound of their common bell, which they called Martinella. As for us, who are less superstitious, and deem him to have the honor of the war, that has the profit of it, and according to Lisander, say, that ’Where the Lions-skinne will not suffice, we must adde a scantling of the Foxes;’ the most ordinary occasions of surprises are drawne from this practice, and as we say, there is no time, wherein a Captain ought to be more warie and circumspect to looke about him, than that of parlies, and treaties of accord: And therefore is it a common rule in the mouth of all our modern men of war, that the Governour or Commaunder of a besieged place, ought never to sallie forth himself to parlie. In the time of our forefathers, the same was cast in the teeth (as a reproach) unto the Lord of Montmord and Assigni, who defended Mouson, against the Earle of Nanseaw. Yet in this case it were excusable in him, that should so sallie out, that the assurance and advantage, might still be on his side. As did the Earle Guido Rangoni in the city of Rhegium (if credit may be given to Bellay: for Guicciardin affirmeth, that it was himself) when as the Lord of Escute, coming to parlie made his approaches unto it; for he did so little forsake his fort, that while they were in parlie, a commotion being raised, the Lord of Escute and the troupes which came with him, in that tumult found himself to be the weakest, so that Alexander Trivultio was there slain, and he deeming it the safest way, was forced to follow the Earle, and on his word to yield himself to the mercy and shelter of blowes, into the City. Eumenes in the City of Nera, being urged by Antigenus, that besieged him, to sallie forth to parlie, alleging that there was reason he should come to him, sith he was the better man, and the stronger: after he had made, this noble answer, ’I will never think any man better than myself, so long as I can hold or rule my sword;’ nor did he ever yield until Antigonus had delivered him Ptolomey, his own nephew for a pledge, whom he required. Yet shall we see some to have prospered well in sallying foorth of their holdes to parlie, upon the word and honor of the assailant; witnes Henrie of Vaulx, a knight of Champaigns, who being beleagred by the English-men in the Castle of Commercie, and Bartholmew of Bones, who at that siege commaunded as Chiefe having caused the greatest part of the Castle to be undermined, so that there wanted nothing but the giving of fire, utterly to subvert the same, under the ruines of it, summoned the said Henrie to issue out, and for his own good to parlie with him, which he did, accompanied but with three more, who manifestly seeing the evident ruine, wherein he was undoubtedly like to fall, acknowledged himself infinitely beholding to his enemies unto whose discretion, after he had yielded together with his troup, and that fire the Castle was given to the Mine, the main props of the Castle failing, it was utterly overthrowne and carried away. I am easily persuaded to yield to other mens words and faith, but hardly would I do it, when I should give other men cause to imagine, that I had rather done it through despare and want of courage, than of a free and voluntary choise, and confidence in his honestie and well-meaning. Return to Book I: Chapter VI. THAT THE HOURE OF PARLIES IS DANGEROUS THAT THE HOURE OF PARLIES IS DANGEROUS OTWITHSTANDING I saw lately, that those of Musidan, a place not far from me, who with others of their partie were by our forces compelled to dislodge thence, exclaimed, they were betraid, because during the speech of accord, and the treatie yet continuing, they had been surprised and defeated; which thing might perhaps other ages have had some apparence of truth; but, I say, our manner of proceeding in such cases, is altogether differing from these rules, and no man ought to expect performance of promise from an enemy, except the last seale of bond be fully annexed thereunto, wherein notwithstanding is then much care and vigilancie required, and much adoe shall be found. And it was ever a dangerous counsell to trust the performance of word or oath given unto a City, that yields unto gentle and favourable composition, and in that fury to give the needie, bloudthirstie, and prey-greed Souldier free entrance into it, unto the free choise and licence of a victorious army. Lucius Emilius Regulus a Roman Proctor, having lost his time in attempting by force to take the City of the Phocens by reason of the singular prowess, which the inhabitants showed, in stoutly defending themselves, covenanted to receive them as friends unto the people of Rome, and to enter their City as a place confederate, removing all fear of hostile-action from them. But to the end he might apeare more glorious and dreadfull, having caused his army to enter with him, do what he might, be could not bridle the rage of his Soldiers; and with his own eyes saw most part of the City ransacked and spoiled: the rights of covetousnesse and revenge supplanting those of his authority and militarie discipline. Cleomenes was wont to say, that ’What hurt soever a man might do his enemies in time of war, was beyond justice, and not subject unto it, as well towards the Gods as towards men:’ who for seven dayes having made truce with those of Argos, the third night, while they were all asleepe mistrusting no harme, he charged and overthrew them, aleaging for his excuse, that in the truce no mention had been made of nights. But the Gods left not his perfidious policy unrevenged: For during their enter-parlie and business about taking hostages, the City of Casilinum was by surprise taken from him: which happened in the times of the justest Captains, and of the most perfect Roman discipline: For it is not said, that time and place serving, we must not make use and take advantage of our enemies foolish oversight, as we do of their cowardise. And verily war has naturally many reasonable privileges to the prejudice of reason. And here failes the rule; Neminem id agere, ut ex alterius prædetur inscitia: ’That no man should endeavour to prey upon another mans ignorance.’ But I wonder of the scope that Xenophon allowes them, both by his discourse, and by diverse exploits of his perfect Emperor: an Author of wonderful consequence in such things, as a great Captain and a Philosopher, and one of Socrates chiefest Disciples, nor do I altogether yield unto the measure of his dispensation. The Lord of Aubigny besieging Capua, after he had given it a furious battery, the Lord Fabritius Colonna, Captain of the town, having from under a bastion or skonce begunne to parlie, and his men growing negligent and carelesse in their offices and guard, our men did suddenly take the advantage offered them, entered the town, over-ranne it, and put all to the sword. But to come to later examples, indeed in our memory, the Lord Iulio Romero at Yvoy, having committed this oversight to issue out of his holde, to parlie with the Constable of France, at his return found the Town taken, and himself jack-out- of-doores. But that we may not pass out unrevenged, the Marques of Pescara beleagering Genova, where the Duke Octavian Fregoso commanded under our protection, and an accord between them having so long been treated, and earnestly solicited, that it was held as ratified, and upon the point of conclusion, the Spaniards being entered the Town, and seeing themselves the stronger, took their opportunity and used it as a full and compleate victory: and since at Lygny in Baroe, where the Earle of Brienne commanded, the Emperor having besieged him in person, and Bartholemy Lieutenant to the said Earle, being come foorth of his hold to parlie, was no sooner out, while they were disputing, but the Town was surprised, and he excluded, They say, Fu il vincer sempre mai laudabil cosa, Vincasi o per fortuna o per ingegno. -- ARIST. cant. xv. stan. 1. To be victorious, evermore was glorious, Be we by fortune or by wit victorious. But the Philosopher Chrsippus would not have been of that opinion; nor I neither, for be was wont to say, ’That those who run for the masterie may well employ all their strength to make speed, but it is not lawfull for them to lay hands on their adversaries, to stay him, or to crosse legs, to make him trip or fall.’ And more generously answered Alexander the Great, at what time Polypercon persuaded him to use the benefit of the advantage which the darknesse of the night afforded him, to charge Darius. ’No, no,’ said he, ’it fits not me to hunt after night-stolne victories;’ mato me fortunæ pæniteat, quam tictoriæ pudeat. (CURT. 1. iv.) I had rather repent me of my fortune, than be ashamed of my victory. Atque idem fugientem haud est dignatus Orodem Sternere, nec jacta cæcum dare cuspide vulnus: Obvius adversoque occurrit, seque viro vir Contulit, haud furto melior, sed fortibus armis. -- VIRG. æn.1.x.732. He deign’d not to strike down Orodes flying, Or with his throwne-launce blindely-wound him running: But man to man afront himself applying, Met him, as more esteem’d for strength than cunning. Return to Book I. Chapter VII. THAT OUR INTENTION JUDGETH OUR ACTIONS THAT OUR INTENTION JUDGETH OUR ACTIONS HE common saying is, that ’Death acquits us of all our bonds.’ I know some that have taken it in another sence. Henry the seventh, King of England, made a composition with Philip, son to Maximilian the Emperor or (to give him a more honorable title) father to the Emperor Charles the fifth, that the said Philip should (deliver into his hands the Duke of Suffolke, his mortal enemy, who was fled out of England, and saved himself in the Low countries, always provided the king should attempt nothing against the Dukes life; which promise notwithstanding, being near his end, he expresly by will and testament commanded his succeeding-son, that immediately after his decease, he should cause him to be put to death. In the late tragedie, which the Duke of Alva presented us withall at Brussels, on the Earles of Horne and Egmond were many remarkable things and worthy to be noted: and amongst others, that the said Count Egmond upon whose faithfull word and assurance, the Earle of Horne was come in and yielded himself to the Duke of Alva, required very instantly to be first put to death, to the end his death might acquit and free him of the word and bond, which he ought and was engaged for, to the said Earle of Horne. It seems that death has no whit discharged the former of his word given, and that the second, without dying was quit of it. We cannot be tied beyond our strength and means. The reason is, because the effects and executions are not any way in our power,and except our will, nothing is truly in our power: on it only are all the rules of man’s dutie grounded and established by necessitie. And therefore Count Egmond, deeming his mind and will indebted to his promise, how beit the power to effect it, lay not in his hands; was no doubt cleerely absolved of his debt and dutie, although be had survived the Count Horne. But the King of England failing of his word by his intention, cannot be excused, though he delaide the execution of his disloyaltie until after his death. No more than Herodotus his Mason who during his natural life, having faithfully kept the secret of his Master the King of Egypts treasure, when he died discovered the same unto his children. I have in my dayes seen many convicted by their own conscience, for detaining other men’s goods, yet by their last will and testament to dispose themselves, after their decease to make satisfaction. This is nothing to the purpose. Neither to take time for a matter so urgent, nor with so small interest or show of feeling, to go about to establish an injurie. They are indebted somewhat more. And by how much more they pay incommodiously and chargably, so much the more just and meritorious is their satisfaction. Penitence ought to charge, yet do they worse, who reserve the revealing of some heinous conceit or affection towards their neighbour, to their last will and affection, having while they lived ever kept it secret. And seem to have little regard of their own honor, by provoking the partie offended against their own memory, and less of their conscience, since they could never for the respect of death cancell their ill-grudging affection, and in extending life beyond theirs. Oh wicked and ungodly judges, which refer the judgement of a cause to such time as they have no more knowledge of causes! I will as near as I can prevent, that my death reveale or utter any thing, my life has not first publikely spoken. Return to Book I: Chapter VIII. OF IDLENESSE OF IDLENESSE S we see some idle-fallow grounds, if they be fat and fertile, to bring foorth store and sundry roots of wild and unprofitable weeds, and that to keep them in use we must subject and employ them with certain seeds for our use and service; and as we see some women, though single and alone, often to bring foorth lumps of shapelesse flesh, whereas to produce a perfect and natural generation, they must be manured with another kind of seed; so is it of mindes, which except they be busied about some subject, that may bridle and keep them under, they will here and there wildely scatter themselves through the vast field of imaginations. Sicut aquæ tremulum labris ubi lumnen ahenis Sole repercwsum, aut radiantis imagine Lunæ, Omnia pervolitat late loca jamque sub auras Erigitur, summique ferit laquearia tecti. -- VIRG. Æn. viii. 22 As trembling light reflected from the Sunne, Or radiant Moone on water-fild brasse lavers, Flies over all, in aire unpraised soone, Strikes house-top beames, betwixt both strangely wavers. And there is no folly, or extravagant raving, they produce not in that agitation. velut ægri somnia, vanæ Finguntur species.-- HOR. Art. Poet. vii. Like sicke mens dreames, that feigne Inaginations vain. The mind that has no fixed bound, will easily loose itself: For, as we say, ’To be everiewhere, is to be nowhere.’ Quisquis ubigue habitat, Maxime, nusquam habitat.-- MART. vii. Epig. 72, 6. Good sir, he that dwels everywhere, No where can say, that he dwels there. It is not long since I retired myself unto my own house, with full purpose, as much as lay in me, not to trouble myself with any business, but solitarily and quietly to weare out the remainder of my well-nighspent life; where me thought I could do my spirit no greater favor, than to give him the full scope of idlenesse, and entertaine him as he best pleased, and withall, to settle himself as he best liked: which I hoped he might now, being by time become more setled and ripe, accomplish very easily: but I find, Variam semper dant otia mentem. -- LUCAN, L iv. 704. Evermore idlenesse, Does wavering mindes addresse. That contrariwise playing the skittish and loosebroken jade, he takes a hundred times more cariere and liberty unto himself, than he did for others, and begets in me so many extravagant Chimeræs, and fantastic monsters, so orderlesse, and without any reason, one hudling upon another, that at leisure to view the foolishnesse and monstrous strangenesse of them, I have begun to keep a register of them, hoping, if I live, one day to make him ashamed, and blush at himself. Return to Book I. Chapter IX. OF LYERS OF LYERS HERE is no man living, whom it may less beseeme to speak of memory, than myself, for to say truth, I have none at all: and am fully persuaded that no mans can be so weake and forgetfull as mine. All other parts are in me common and vile, but touching memory, I think to carrie the prise from all other, that have it weakest, nay and to gain the reputation of it, besides the natural want I endure (for truely considering the necessitie of it, Plato has reason to name it a great and mighty goddesse). In my countrie, if a man will imply that one has no sense, he will say, such a one has no memory: and when I complain of mine, they reprove me, and will not believe me, as if I accused myself to be mad and senselesse. They make no diference betweene memory and wit: which is an empairing of my market: But they do me wrong, for contrariwise it is commonly seen by experience, that excellent memories do rather accompany weake judgements. Moreover they wrong me in this (who can do nothing so well as to be a perfect friend) that the same words which accuse my infirmitie, represent ingratitude. From my affection they take hold of my memory, and of a natural defect, they infer a want of judgement or conscience. Some will say, he has forgotten this entreaty or request, or that promise, he is not mindful of his old friends, he never remembered to say, or do, or conceal this or that, for my sake. Verily I may easily forget, but to neglect the charge my friend has committed to my trust, I never do it. Let them bear with my infirmitie, and not conclude it to be a kind of malice; which is so contrary an enemy to my humor. Yet am I somewhat comforted. First, because it is an evil, from which I have chieflie drawne the reason to correct a worse mischief, that would easily have grown upon me, that is to say, ambition; which defect is intolerable in them that meddle with worldly negotiations. For as diverse like examples of natures progresse, say, she has happily strengthened other faculties in me, according as it has grown weaker and weaker in me, and I should easily lay down and wire-draw my mind and judgement, upon other mens traces, without exercising their proper forces, if by the benefit of memory, forren inventions and strange opinions were present with me. That my speech is thereby shorter for the Magazin of Memorie is perhaps more stored with matter, than is the store- house of Invention. Had it held out with me, I had ere this wearied all my friends with pratling: the subjects rouzing the meane facultie I have to manage employ them, strengthening and wresting my discourses. It is pity; I have assayed by the trial of some of my private friends: according as their memory has ministered them a whole and perfect matter, who recoile their narration so far-backe, and stuff it with so many vain circumstances, that if the story be gqod, they smoother the goodnesse of it: if bad, you must needs either curse the good fortune of their memory, or blame the misfortune of their judgement. And it is no easy matter, being in the midst of the cariere of a discourse, to stop cunningly, to make a sudden period, and to cut it off. And there is nothing whereby the cleane strength of a horse is more known, than to make a readie and cleane stop. Among the skilfull I see some that strive, but cannot stay their race. While they labor to find the point to stop their course, they stagger and falter, as men that faint through weaknesse. Above all, old men are dangerous, who have only the memory of things past left them, and have lost the remembrance of their repetitions. I have heard some very pleasant reports become most irkesome and tedious in the mouth of a certain Lord, forasmuch as all the bye-standers had many times been cloyed with them. Secondly (as said an ancient Writers that I do not so much remember injuries received. I had need have a prompter as Darius had, who not to forget the wrong he had received of the Athenians, whensoever he sate down at his table, caused a page to sing unto him, ’Sir, remember the Athenians,’ and that the places or bookes which I read over, do ever smile upon me with some new noveltie. It is not without reason, men say, that be who has not a good and readie memory should never meddle with telling of lies, and fear to become a liar. I am not ignorant how the Grammarians make a difference betweene speaking untrue and lying; and say that to speak untruly is to speak that which is false, but was reputed true; and that the definition of the Latin word, mentiri, whence the French word, mentir, is derived, which in English is to lie, implieth and meaneth to go against ones conscience: and by consequence it concerneth only those, who speak contrary to that which they know, of whom I speak. Now, these, either invent, seale, stampe and all, or else they disguise and change a true ground. When they disguise or change, if they be often put to the repetition of one thing, it is hard for them to keep still in one path, and very strange if they lose not themselves: because the thing, as it is, having first taken up her stand in the memory, and there by the way of knowledge and witting, imprinted itself, it were hard it should not represent itself to the imagination, displacing and supplanting falshood, which therein can have no such footing, or setled fastnesse; and that the circumstances of the first learning, still diving into the mind, should not cause it to disperse the remembrance of all false or bastardizing parts gotten together. Where they altogether invent, forasmuch as there is no certain impression, to front their falshood, they seem to have so much the lesser fear to mistake or forget themselves, which also notwithstanding being an airie body, and without hold-fast may easily escape the memory, except it be well assured, whereof I have often do my no small pleasure) seen the experience, at the cost of those, who professe never to frame their speech, but as, best shall fit the affairs they negotiate, and as best shall please the great men they speak unto. For the circumstances to which they will subject their credit and conscience, being subject to many changes, their speech must likewise diversifie and change with them, whence it followeth that of one selfsame subject they speak diversly, as now yellow, now gray, to one man thus, and thus to another. And if perhaps these kind of men hoard-up their so contrary instructions, what becomes of this goodly art? Who besides, often most foolishly forget themselves, and run at randon: For what memory shall suffice them, to remember so many different formes they have framed to one same subject? I have in my dayes seen diverse that have envied the reputation of this worthy kind of wisdom, who perceive not, that if there be a reputation, there can be no effect. Verily, lying is an ill and detestable vice. Nothing makes us men, and no other means keeps us bound one to another, but our word; knew we but the horror and weight of it, we would with fire and sword pursue and hate the same, and more justly than any other crime. I see all men generally busied (and that very improperly) to punish certain innocent errours in children which have neither impression nor consequence, and chastice and vex them for rash and foolish actions. Only lying and stubbornnesse somewhat more, are the faults whose birth and progresse I would have severely punished and cut off; for they grow and increase with them: and if the tongue have once gotten this ill-habit, good Lord how hard, nay how impossible it is to make her leave it? whereby it ensueth, that we see many very honest men in other matters, to be subject and enthralled to that fault. I have a good lad to my tailour, whom I never heard speak a truth, no not when it might stand him instead of profit. If a lie had no more faces but one, as truth had, we should be in far better termes than we are: For whatsoever a lier should say, we would take it in a contrary sense. But the opposite of truth has many shapes, and an undefinite field. The Pythagoreans make good to be certain and finite and evil to be infinite and uncertain. A thousand by-ways misse the marke, one only hits the same. Surely I can never assure myself to come to a good end, to warrant an extreme evident danger, by a shamelesse and solemn lie. An ancient father says, ’We are better in the companie of a known dogge, than in a mans societie, whose speech is unknown to us. Vt externus alieno non sit hominis vice: ’A stranger to a stranger is not like a man.’ And how much is a false speech less sociable than silence? King Francis the first, vaunted himself to have by this means brought Francis Taverna, ambassador to Francis Sforza, Duke of Milan, to a non-plus; a man very famous for his rare eloquence, and facilitie in speech, who had been dispatched to excuse his master, toward his Majestie, of a matter of great importance, which was this. The King to keep ever some intelligence in Italy, whence he had lately been expelled, but especially in the Dukedome of Milan, thought it expedient to entertaine a Gentleman of his about the Duke, in effect as his Ambassador, but in apparence as a private man; who should make show to reside there about his particular affairess, forasmuch as the Duke, who depended much more of the Emperor (chiefely then that he was treating a marriage with his niece, daughter of the King of Denmarke, who is at this day Dowager of Loraine) could not without great prejudice unto himself discover to have any correspondencie and conference with us. For which commission and purpose a Gentleman of Milan, named Merveille, then serving the King in place of one of the Quiers of his Quierie, was deemed fit. This man being dispatched with secret letters of credence, and instructions of an Ambassador, together with other letters, of commendation to the Duke in favor of his particular affairs, as a maske and pretence of his proceedings, continued so long about the Duke, that the Emperor began to have some suspition of him; which as we suppose was cause of what ensued, which was, that under colour of a murther committed, the Duke one night caused the said Merveille to be beheaded, having ended his processe in two dayes. Master Francis being come to the Court fraught with a long counterfet deduction of this story (for the King had addressed himself to all the Princes of Christendome, indeed to the Duke himself for justice, for such an outrage committed upon his servant had one morning audience in the Kings councell-chamber: who for the foundation of his cause having established and to that end projected many goodly and colourable apparences of the fact: namely, that the Duke his master had never taken Merveille for other than a private gentleman, and his own subject, and who was come thither about his private busines, where he had never lived under other name, protesting he had never known him to be one of the King’s houshold, nor never heard of him, much less taken him for his Majesties Agent. But the King urging him with diverse, objections and demands, and charging him on every side, prest him so far with the execution done by night, and as it were by stealth, that the seely man, being much entangled and suddenly surpised, as if he would set an innocent face on the matter answered, that for the love and respect of his Majestie, the Duke his Master would have been very loth that such an execution should have been done by day. Here every man may guesse whether he were taken short or no, having tripped before so goodly a nose, as was that of our King Francis the first. Pope Iulius the second, having sent an ambassador to the King of England to animate him against our aforesaid King: the Ambassador having his audience touching his charge, and the King in his answer urging and insisting upon the difficultie he found and foresaw in levying such convenient forces, as should be required to withstand so mightie, and set upon so puisant a King, and alleging certain pertinent reasons: The Ambassador fondly and unfitly replied, that himself had long before maturely considered them and had told the Pope of them. By which answer so far from his proposition (which was with all speed, and without more circumstances to undertake and undergoe a dangerous war) the King of England took hold of the first argument which in effect he afterward found true, which was, that the said Ambassador, in his own particular intent, was more affected to the French side, whereof advertising his master, his goods were all confiscate, himself disgraced, and he very hardly escaped with life. Return to Book I: Chapter X. OF READIE OR SLOW SPEECH OF READIE OR SLOW SPEECH NC ne furent a tous toutes qraces donnees. All God’s good graces are not gone To all, or of all anyone. So do we see that in the gift of eloquence, some have such a facility and promptitude, and that which we call utterance, so easy and at command, that at all assaies, and upon everie occasion, they are ready and provided; and others more slow, never speak anything except much laboured and premeditated, as Ladies and daintie Dames are taught rules to take recreations and bodily exercises, according to the advantage of what they have fairest about them. If I were to give the like counsel, in those two different advantages of eloquence whereof Preachers and pleading-lawiers of our age seem to make profession; the slow speaker in mine opinion should be the better preacher, and the other the better lawier. Forasmuch as charge of the first allowes him as much leisure as he pleaseth to prepare hims elfe; moreover his cariere continueth still in one kind without interruption: whereas the lawyers occasions urging him still upon any accident to be ready to enter the lists: and the unexpected replies and answers of his adverse parlie, do often divest him from his purpose, wher he is enforced to take a new course. Yet is it, that at the last enterview which was at Marseilles betweens Pope Clement the seventh, and Francis the first, our King, it hapned cleane contrary, where Monsieur Poyet, a man of chief reputation, and all dayes of his life brought up to plead at the bar, whose charge being to make an Oration before the Pope, and having long time before premeditated and con’d the remaineth mute, if he have no leisure to prepare himself, and he likewise to whom leisure gives no advantage to say better, are both in one self degree of strangeness. It is reported that Severus Cassius spake better extempore, and without premeditation. That he was more beholding to fortune, than to his diligence; that to be interrupted in his speech redounded to his profit: and that his adversaries feared to urge him, lest his sudden anger should redouble his eloquence. I know this condition of nature by experience, which cannot abide a vehement and laborious premeditation: except it hold a free, a voluntarie, and self pleasing course, it can never come to a good end. We commonly say of some compositions, that they smell of the oile, and of the lampe, by reason of a certain harshnesse, and rudenesse, which long plodding labor imprints in them that be much elaborated. But besides the care of well-doing, and the contention of the mind, overstretched to her enterprise, does breake and impeach the same; even as it happens unto water, which being closely pent in, through its own violence and abundance, cannot find issue at an open gullet. In this condition of nature, whereof I now speak, this also is joined unto it, that it desires not to be pricked forward by these strong passions, as the anger of Cassius (for that motion would be overrude) it ought not to be violently shaken, but yieldingly solicited: it desires to be rouzed and prickt forward by strange occasions, both present and casual. If it go alone, it does but languish and loyteron is her life and grace. I canuot well conataine myself in my own possession and disposition, chance has more interest in it than myself; occasion, company, indeed the change of my voice draws more from my mind than I can find therein, when by myself I second and endevor to employ the same. My words likewise are better than my writings, if choice may be had in so worthless things. This also hapheth unto me, that where I seek myself, I find not myself: and I find myself more by chance, than by the search of my own judgement. I shall perhaps have cast foorth some suttletie in writing, perhaps dull and harsh for another, but smooth and curious for myself. Let us leave all these complements and quaintness. That is spoken by everie man, according to his own strength, I have so lost it, that I wot not what I would have said, and strangers have sometilnes found it before me. Had I alwayes a razor about me, where that happens, I should cleane raze myself out. Fortune may at some other time make the light thereof appeare brighter unto me than that of mid-day, and will make me wonder at my own faltring or sticking in the myre. Return to CHAPTER XI: OF PROGNOSTICATIONS Send CHAPTER XI: OF PROGNOSTICATIONS S touching Oracles it is very certain, that long before the coming of our Saviour Iesus Christ, they had begun to lose their credit: for we see that Cicero laboureth to find the cause of their declination: and these be his words: Cur isto modo jam oracula Delphis non eduntur, non modo nostra ætate, sed jamdiu, ut nihil possit esse contemptius? ’Why in like sort are not oracles now uttered, not only in our t imes, but a good while since, so as now nothing can be more contemptible?’ But as for other Prognostikes, that were drawne from the anatomie of beasts in sacrifice, to which Plato does in some sort ascribe the natural constitution of the intermall members of them, of the scraping of chickens, of the flight of birds, Aves quasdam rerum augurandarum causa natas esse putamus: ’We are of opinion’, certain birds were even bred to prognosticate some things; of thunders, of turnings and backe-recourse of rivers.’ Multa cernunt aruspices: multa augures provident: multa oraculis declarantur: multa vaticinationibus: multa somniis: multa portentis: ’Soothsayers see much: bird-prophets foresee as much: much is foretold by Oracles; much by prophecies; much by portentuous signes,’ and others, upon which antiquitie grounded most of their enterprises, as well public as private: our religion has abolished them. And albeit there remaine yet amongst us some means of divination in the starres, in spirits; in shapes of the body in dreames, and elsewhere a notable example of the mad and foolish curiosity of our nature, ammusing itself to preoccupate future things, as if it had not enough to do to digest the present. -------cur hanc titi, rector Olympi Sollicitis mortalibus addere curam, Noscant venturas ut dira per omnia cla des Bit subitum quodcunque paras, sit cæca futuri Mens hominum fati, liceat sperare timenti. Why pleas’d it you, you ruler of the spheares, To adde this care to mortals care-clog’d mind; That they their misery know, ere it appeares? Let your drifts sudden come; let men be blinde T’wards future fate: oh let him hope that feares. Ne utile quidem est scire quid futurum sit: Miserum est enim, nihil profidentem angi: It is not so much as profitable for us to know what is to come, for it is a miserable thing, a man should fret and be vexed, and do no good.’ Yet is it of much less authority, lo here, why the example of Francis Marquis of Salum has seemed remarkable unto me: who being Lieutenant General unto Francis our King, and over all his forces, which he then had beyond the Mountaines in Italie, a man highly favoured in al our court, and otherwise infinitly beholding to the King for that very, Mar quisate, which his brother had forfeited: and having no occasion to do it, indeed his mind and affections contradicting the same, buffered himself to be frighted and deluded (as it has since been manifestly prooved) by the foolish Prognostications which then throughout all Europe were given out to the advantage of the Emperor Charles the fift and to our prejudice in Italy, where these foolish predictions so much possesed the Italians, that in Rome there were laid great wagers, and much money give n out upon the exchange, that we should utterly be overthrowne) that after he had much condoled, indeed complained with his secret friends, the unavoidable miseries which he foresaw prepared by the fates against the Crowne of France, and the many friends he had there, he unkindly revolted, and became a turn-cote on the Emperors side, to his intolerable loss and destraction, notwithstanding all the constellations then reigning. But be was drawne unto it as a man encompassed and beset by diverse passions; for having both strong castles, and all manner of munition and strength in his own hands, the enemies army under Antonio Leva about three paces from him, and we nothing mistrusting him, it was in his power to do worse than he did. For notwithstanding his treason, we lost neither man nor town, except Fossan, which long after was by us stoutly contested and defended. Prudens futuri temporis exitum Caliginosa nocte premit Deus, Ridetque, si mortalis ultra Fas trepidat. Our wise God hides in pitch- darke night Of future time the event decreed, And laughes at man, if man (affright) Fear more than he to fear has need. Ille potens sui Lætqusue deget, cui licet in diem Dixisse, vixi, cras vel atra Nube polum pater occupato, Vel sole puro. He of himself lives merily, Who each day, I have liv’d, can say, To morrow let God charge the skiee With darke clouds, or fair sun-shine-ray. Lætus in præsens animus, quod ultra est, Oderit curare.3 For present time a mery mind Hates to respect what is behind. And those which take this word in a contrary sense are in the wrong. Ista sic reciprocantur ut et si divinatio sit dii sint, et si dii sint sit divinatio: quence is so reciprocall as if there be any divination, there are Gods: and if there be Gods, there is divination.’ Much more wisely Pacuvius. Nam istis linguam avium intelligunt, Plusque ex alieno jecoresapiunt, quam ex suo Magis audiendum, quam auscultandum c ensio.1 Who understand what language birds express, By their own than beasts-livers knowing less, They may be heard, not hearkned to, I guesse. This so famous art of divination of the Tuskanes grew thus. A husband-man digging very deepe intothe ground saw Tages, a demy-God appear out of it, with an infantine face, yet fraught with an age-like wisdom. All men ran to see him, and both his words and knowledgee were for many ages after remembred, and collecte d, containing the principles and means of this art. An ofspring suitable to her progresse. I would rather direct affairs by the chance of dice, than by such frivolous dreames. And truly in all common-wealths, men have ever ascribed much authority unto lot. Plato in the policy which he imagineth by discretion, ascribed the deciding of many important effects unto it, and amongst other things would have marriages betweene the good to be contrived by lot. And gives so large privileges unto thi s casual election, that he appoints the children proceeding from them to be brought up in the countrie; and those borne of the bad to be banished and sent abroad. Notwithstanding if any of those so exiled shall by fortune happen, while he is growing, to show some good hope of himself, that he may be revoked and sent- for backe, and such amongst the first as shall in their youth give small hope of future good to be banished. I see some that studie, plod, and glosse their Almanackes, and in all accidents alleage their authority. A man were as good to say, they must needs speak truth and lies. Quis est enim qui totum diem . jaculans, non aliquando conlincet? ’For who is he that, shooting all day, sometimes hits not the white?’ I think not the better of them, though what they say proove sometimes true. It were more certain, if there were either a rule or a truth to lie ever. Seeing no man rec ordeth their fables, because they are ordinary and infinit; and their predictions are made to be of credit, because they are rare, incredible and prodigious; so answered Diagoras surnamed the Atheist (being in Samothrace) to him, who in shewing him diver’s vows and offrings hanging in the Temple, brought thither by such as had escaped shipwracke, said thus unto him: ’You that think the Gods to have no care of humane things, what say you by so many men saved by their grace and helpe?’ ’Thus is it done,’ answered he: ’Those which were drowned far exceeding their number, are not here set-forth.’ Cicero says, That amongst all other Philosophers that have avowed and acknowledged the Gods, only Xenophanes the Colophonian has gone about to root out all manner of divination. It is so much the less to be wondred at, if at any time we have seen some of our Princes mindes, to their great damage, rely upon such like vanities. I would to God, I had with my own eyes seen those two wonders, mentioned in the book of Ioachin the Abbat of Calabria, who foretold all the Popes that should ensue, together with their names and shapes: And that of Leo the Emperor, who fore-spake all the Emperors and Patriarkes of Greece. This have I seen with my own eyes, that in public confusions, men amazed at their own fortune, give themselves head-long, as it were to all manner of superstition, to search in heaven the causes and ancient threats of their ill-lucke; and in my time are so strangely s uccessefull therein, as they have persuaded me, that it is an ammusing of sharpe and idle wits; that such as are inured to this subtletie, by folding and unfolding them, may in all other writings be capable to find out what they seek-after. But above all, their dark, ambiguous, fantastic, and propheticall, gibrish, mends the matter much, to which their authors never give a plaine sense, that posterity may apply what mean ing and construction it shall please unto it. The Dæmon of Socrates was perhaps a certain impulsion or will, which without the advice of his discourse presented itself unto him. In a mind so well purified, and by continuall exercise of wisdom and virtue so well prepared, as his was, it is likely, his inclinations (though rash and inconsiderate) were ever of great moment, and worthie to be followed. Every man feeleth in himself some image of such agitations, of a prompt, vehement and casual opinion. It is in me to give them some authority, that affoord so little to our wisdom. And I have had some, equally weake in reason, and violent in persuasion and disswasion (which was more ordinary to Socrates) by which I have so happily and so profitably suffred my self to be transported, as they might perhaps be thought to containe some matter of divine inspiration. Return to CHAPTER XIl. OF CONSTANCIE CHAPTER XIl. OF CONSTANCIE HE law of resolution and constancy implieth not, we should not, as much as lieth in o ur power shelter ourselves from the chiefes and inconveniences that threaten us, nor by consequence fear, they should surprise us. Contrariwise, all honest means for a man to warrant himself from evils are not only tolerable, but commendable. And the part of constancy is chiefly acted, in firmely bearing the inconveniences, against which no remedie is to be found. So that there is no nimblenesse of body, nor wealding of hand-weapons, that we will reject, if it may in any sort defend us from the blow, meant at us. Many most warlike nations in their conflicts and fights, used retreating and flight as a principal advantage, and showed their backs to their enemy much more dangerously than their faces. The Turkes at this day retaine something of that humor. And Socrates in Plato does mocke at Laches, because he had defined fortitude, to keep herself steadie in her rancke against her enemies; ’What,’ says he, ’were it then cowardise to beat them in giving them place?’ And alleage th Homer against him, who commendeth in æneas his skill in flying and giving ground. And because Laches being better advised, avoweth that custom to be amongst the Scithians, and generally amongst all horsemen, he alleageth further unto him the example of the Lacedemonian footmen (a nation above all other used to fight on foot who in the battle of Plateæ, to open and to put to rowt the Persian Phalanx, advised themselves to scatter and put themselves backe, that so by the opinion of their flight, they might if they should pursue them, rush in upon them, and put that so combined-masse to rout. By which means they gained the victory. Touching the Scithians, it is reported, that when Darius went to subdue them, he sent their King many reproachfull speeches, for so much as he ever saw him retire and give ground before him, and to avoid the main battle. To whom Indathirsez (for so was his name) answered, that ’They did it not for f eare of him, nor any other man living, but that it was the fashion of his nation to march thus: as having neither cities, nor houses, nor manured land to defend, or to fear their enemies should reape any commoditie by them.’ But if he had so great a desire to feed on them, he might draw nearer to view the place of their ancient Sepulchers, and there he should meet with whom to speak his belly-full. Notwithstanding when a man is once within reach of cannonshot, and as it were point-blancke befor e them, as the fortune of war does diverse times bring men unto, it ill beseemeth a resolute mind to start-aside, or be daunted at the threat of a shot, because by the violence and suddennesse thereof we deem it inevitable: and there are some, who by lifting up of a hand, or stooping their head have sometimes given their fellowes cause of laughter: yet have we seeene in the voyage, the Emperor Charles the fifth made against us in Provence, the Marquis of Guasto, being gone out to survey the citie of Arles, and shewn himself out of a winde- mill, under colour of which he was come somewhat near the Town, he was discovered by the Lord of Bonevall, and the Seneshall of Agenois, who were walking upon the Theatre Aux arenes (so called in French because it is fall of sand) who shewing him to the Lord of Villiers, Commissarie of the Artillerie, he mounted a culverin so levell, that had not the Marquis perceived the fire, and so started aside, it was constantly affirmed, he had been shot th rough the body likewise not many yeeres before, Lorence of Medici, Duke of Vrbin, and father to the Queene- mother of France, besieging Mondolphe, a place in Italie, in the province named Vicariate, seeing fire given to a piece that stood upright upon him, stooped his head, and well befell him that he plaide the duck, for otherwise the bullet, which wenr right over, and within a little of his head, had doubtlesse shot him through the paunch. But t o say truth, I will never think these motions were made with discourse, for what judgement can you give of an aime, either high or low, in a matter so sudden? It may rather be thought that fortune favoured their fear: and which an other time might as well be a meane to make them fall into the cannons-mouth, as to avoid the same. I cannot chuse, if the cracke of a musket do suddenly streeke mine ears, in a place where I least looke for it, but I must needs start at it: which I have seen ha ppen to men of better sort than myself. Nor do the Stoices meane, that the Soule of their wisest man in any sort resist the first visions and sudden fantasies, that surprise the same: but rather consent that, as it were unto a natural subjection, he yields and shrinks unto the loud clattering and roare of heaven, or of some violent downefall; for example-sake, unto palenesse, and contraction. So likewise in other passions, alwayes provided, his opinion remaines safe and whole, and the situati on of his reason, admit no tainting or alteration whatsoever: and he no whit consent to his fright and sufferance. Touching the first part; the same happens to him, that is not wise, but far otherwise concerning the second. For the impression of passions does not remaine superficiall in him: but rather penetrates even into the secret of reason, infecting and corrupting the same. He judgeth according to them and conformeth himself to them. Consider precisely the state of the wise Stoice: Mens immota manet, lachrymæ volvuntur inanes. His mind does firme remaine, Teares are distill’d in vain. the wise Peripatetike does not exempt himself from perturbations of the mind, but does moderate them. Return to CHAPTER XIII: OF CEREMONIES IN THE ENTERVIEW OF KINGS CHAPTER XIII: OF CEREMONIES IN THE ENTERVIEW OF KINGS HERE is no subject so vain, that deserveth not a place in this rapsodie. It were a notable discourtesy unto our common rules, both towards an equa ll, but more toward a great person, not to meete with you in your house, if he have once warned you that he will come: And Margaret Queene of Navarre, was wont to say to this purpose, ’That it was a kind of incivilitie in a gentleman, to depart from his house, as the fashion is, to meet with him that is coming to him, how worthy soever he be: and that it more agrees with civilitie and respect, to stay for him at home, and there to entertain him: except it were for fear the stranger should misse his way: and that it sufficeth to companie and wait upon him, when he is going away again.’ As for me, I oftentimes forget these vain offices; as one that endevoureth to abolish all manner of ceremonies in my house. Some will be offended at it, what can I do withall? I had rather offend a stranger once, than my self everie day; for it were a continuall subjection. To what end do men avoid the servitude of Courts, and entertaine the same in their own houses? Moreover it is a common rule in all assemblies, that he who is the meaner man, commeth first to the place appointed, forasmuch as it belongs to the better man to be stayed- for and waited upon by the other. Nevertheless we saw that at the enterview, prepared at Merceilles betweene Pope Clement the seventh, and Francis the first, King of France, the King having appointed all necessarie preparation, went him-self out of the Town, and gave the Pope two or three dayes leisure, to make his entrie into it, and to refresh himself, before he would come to meet him there. Likewise at the meeting of the said Pope with the Emperor at Bologna, the Emperor gave the Pope advantage and leisure to be first there, and afterward came himself. It is (say they) an ordinary ceremony at enter- parlies betweene such Princes, that the better man should ever come first to the place appointed indeed before him in whose countrey the assembly is and they take it in this sence, tha t it is, because this complement should testifie, he is the better man, whom the meaner goeth to seek, and that he sueth unto him. Not only each countrey, but every City, indeed, and every vocation has his own particular decorum I have very carefully been brought up in mine infancie, and have lived in very good company, because I would not be ignorant of the good maners of our countrey of France, and I am persuaded I might keep a schoole of them. I love to follow them, but not so cowardly, as my life remaine thereby in subjection. They have some painfull formes in them, which if a man forget by discretion, and not by error, he shall no whit be disgraced. I have often seen men proove unmanerly by too much maners, and importunate by over-much courtesy. The knowledge of entertainment is otherwise a profitable knowledge. It is, as grace and beautie are, the reconciler of the first accoastings of society and familiarity: and by consequence, it openeth the entrance to instruct us by the example of others, and to exploit and produce our example, if it have any instructing or communicable thing in it. Return to CHAPTER XIV: MEN ARE PUNISHED BY TO MUCH OPINIONATING THEMSELVES IN A PLACE WITHOUT REASON CHAPTER XIV: MEN ARE PUNISHED BY TO MUCH OPINIONATING THEMSELVES IN A PLACE WITHOUT REASON ALOUR has his limits, as other vertues have: which if a man out-go, he shall find himself in the traine of vice: in such sort, that unless a man know their right bounds, which in truth are not on a sudden easily hit upon, he may fall into rashnesse, obstinacy and folly. For this consideration grew the custom we hold in wars, to punish, and that with death, those who wilfully opiniate themselves to defend a place, which by the rules of war cannot be kept. Otherwise upon hope of impunitie, there should be no cottage that might not entertaine an Armie. The Lord Constable Momorancie at the siege of Pavia, having been appointed to pass over the river Tesine, and to quarter himself in the suburbs of Saint Antonie, being impeached by a tower that stood at the end of the bridge. and which obstinately would needs hold out, indeed to be battered, caused all those that were with-in it, to be hanged. The same man afterward, accompanying my Lord the Dolphin of France in his iourney beyond the Alpes, having by force taken the Castle Villane, and all those that were within the same, having by the fury of the Soldiers bin put to the sword, except the Captain, and his Ancient, for the same reason, caused them both to be hanged and strangled: As did also Captain Mart in du Bellay, the Governour of Turin, in the same conntrey, the Captain of Saint Bony: all the rest of his men having been massacred at the taking of the place. But forasmuch as the judgement of the strength or weaknesse of the place is taken by the estimate and counterpoise of the forces that assaile it (for som might justly opinionate himself against two culverins, that wold play the mad-man to expect thirty cannons) where also the greatness of the Prince conquering must be considered, his reputation, and the rest that is due unto him: there is danger a man should somewhat bend the balance on that side. By which termes it happens, that some have so great an opinion of themselves, and their means, and deeming it unreasonable, anything should be worthie to make head against them, that so long as their fortune continueth, they overpasse what hill or difficultie soever they find to withstand or resist them: As is seen by the formes of sommonings and challenges, that the Princes of the East, and their successors yet remaining, have in use, so fierce, so haughtie and so full of a barbarous kind of commandement. And in those places where the Portugales abated the pride of the Indians, they found some states observing this universall and inviolalile law, that what enemy soever he be, that is overcome by the King in person, or by his Lieutenant, is exempted from all composition of ransome or mercy. So above all, a man who is able should take heed, lest he fall into the hands of an enemy-judge, that is victorious and armed. Return to CHAPTER XV: OF THE PUNISHMENT OF COWARDISE CHAPTER XV: OF THE PUNISHMENT OF COWARDISE HAVE heretofore heard a Prince, who was a very great Captain, hold opinion, that a souldier might not for cowardise of heart be condemned to death: who, sitting at his table heard report of the Lord of Vervins’ sentence, who for yielding up of Bollein, was doomed to lose his head. Verily there is reason a man should make a difference bet ween faults proceeding from our weaknesses and those that grow from our malice. For in the latter we are directly bandied against the rules of reason, which nature has imprinted in us; and in the former, it seems, we may call the same nature, as a warrant, because it has left us in such imperfection and defect. So as diverse nations have judged that no man should blame us for anything we do against our conscience. And the opinion of those which condemne heretikes and miscreants unto capital punishments, is partly grounded upon this rule: and the same which establisheth, that a Judge or an Advocate may not be called to account for any matter, committed in their charge through oversight or ignorance. But touching cowardise, it is certain the common fashion is, to punish the same with ignominie and shame. And some hold that this rule was first put in practice by the Law-giver Charondas, and that before him the laws of Greece were wont to punish those with death, who for fear did run a way from a Battell: where he only ordained, that for three dayes together, clad in womens attire, they should be made to sit in the market-place: hoping yet to have some service at their hands, and by means of this reproch, they might recover their courage again. Suffundere malis hominis sanguinem quam effundere: ’Rather move a man’s blood to blush in his face, than remove it by bleeding from his body.’ It appeareth also t hat the Roman laws did in former times punish such as had run away by death. For Ammius Marcellinus reporteth, that Iulian the Emperor condemned ten of his Souliliers, who in a charge against the Parthians, had but turned their backs from it; first to be degraded, then to suffer death, as he says, according to the ancient laws, who nevertheless, condemneth others for a like fault, under the ensigne of bag and baggage, to be kept amongst the common prisoners. The sharp punishment of the Romans against those Soldiers that escaped from Cannæ: and in the same war against those that accompanied Cn. Fulvius in his defeat, reached not unto death, yet may a man fear, such open shame may make them despaire, and not only prove faint and cold friends, but cruel and sharpe enemies. In the time of our forefathers, the Lord of Franget, whilom Lieutenant of the Marshall of Chastillions company, having by the Marshall of Chabanes been placed Governor of Fontarabie, in stead of the Earle of Lude and having yielded the same unto the Spaniards, was condemned to be degraded of all Nobilitie, and not only himself, but all his succeeding posterity declared villains and clownes, taxable and incapable to bear arms; which severe sentence was put in execution at Lyons. The like punishment did afterward all the Gentlemen suffer, that were within Guise, when the Earle of Nansaw enired the town: and others since. Nevertheless if there were so grosse an ignorance, and so apparent cowardize, as that it should exceed all ordinary, it were reason it should be taken for a sufficient proofe of inexcusable treacherier and knaverie, and for such to be punished. Renascence Editions Return to CHAPTER XVI: A TRICKE OF CERTAINE AMBASSADORS Send comments and corrections to the CHAPTER XVI: A TRICKE OF CERTAINE AMBASSADORS IN all my travels I did ever observe this custom, that is, alwaies to learne something by the communication of others (which is one of the best schooles that may be) to reduce those I confer withall to speak of that wherein they are most conversant and skilfull. Basti al nocch iero ragionar de’ venti, Albifolco de’ tori, e le sue piaghe Conti ’l guerrier, conti ’l pastor gl’ armenti.-- Idem PROPERT. ii. El. i. 43. Sailers of winds plow-men of beasts take keep, Let Soldiers count their woundes, shepherds their sheepe. For commonly we see the contrary, that many chuse rather to discourse of any other trade than their own; supposing it to be so much new reputation gotten: witnes the quip Archidamus gave Periander, saying that he forsooke the credit of a good Physitian, to become a paltry Poet. Note but how Cæsar displaieth his inventiton at large, when he would have us conceive his inventions how to build bridges, and devices, how to frame other war-like engins; and in respect of that how close and succinct he writes, when he speaks of the offices belonging to his profession, of his valor, and of the conduct of his war-fare. His exploits prove him a most excellent Captain, but he would be known for a skilfull Ingenier, a quality somewhat strange in him. Dionysius the elder was a very great chieftaine and Leader in war, as a thing best fitting his fortune; but be greatly laboured by means of Poetry, to assume high commendation unto himself, howbeit he had but little skill in it. A certain Lawier was not long since brought to see a study, stored with all manner of bookes, both of his own, and of all other faculties, wherein he found no occasion to entertaine him self withal, but like a foolish cunning clarke earnestly busied himself to glosse and censure a fence or a barricado, placed over the screw of the study, which a hundred Captains and Soldiers see everie day, without obsererving or taking offence at them. Optat ephippia bos piger, optat arare caballus. --Hor. i. Epist. xiv. 43. The Oxe would trappings weare, The Horse, ploughs-yoake would bear. By this course you never come to perfection, or bring any thing to good pass. Thus m ust a man endeavor to induce the Architect, the Painter, the Shoemaker, to speak of their own trade, and so of the rest, every man in his vocation. And to this purpose am I wont, in reading of histories (which is the subject of most men) to consider who are the writers: If they be such as professe nothing but bare learning, the chief thing I learne in them, is their stile and language: if Physitians, I believe them in whatsoever they shall report concerning the temperatenesse of the aire, the h ealth and complexion of Princes, or of hurts and infirmities: If Lawiers, we should observe the controversies of rights, titles, and pretenses of laws and customs, the establishment of policies, and such like things: If Divines, we may note the affairs of the Church, the Ecclesiasticall censures, dispensations, cases of conscience, and marriages: If Courtiers, manners, complements, ceremonies, and entertainments: If Warriors, what belongs unto their charge, but chiefly the managing and conduc t of the achievements or exploits wherein they have been themselves in person: If Ambassadors, the negotiations, intelligences, practices, policies, and manner how to direct, complot, and conduct them. And therefore what in another Writer I should perhaps have cursorie passed over, I have with some advisednesse considered and marked the same in the historie of the Lord of Langley, a man most expert and intelligen t in such matters: which is, that after he had exactly set down and declared those glorious, and far- fetcht remonstrances of the Emperor Charles the fifth made in the consistorie of Rome, in the presence of the Bishop of Mascon, and the Lord of Velly, our Ambassadors; wherein he entermixed many bitter and outrageous words against us; and amongst others, that if his Captains and Soldiers were not of much more faithfulnesse and sufficiencie in the art of war than our Kings, he would forthwith tie a rope about his necke, and go aske him mercy: whereof he seemed to believe something: for afterward while he lived, he chanced twice or thrice to utter the very same words. Moreover, that he had challenged the King to fight with him, man to man in his shirt, with Rapier and dagger in a boat. The said Lord of Langey, following his story addeth that the said Ambassadors making a dispatch of what had passed unto the King, dissembled the chiefest part unto him, indeed concealed the two pr ecedent articles from him. Now me thought it very strange, that it should lie in the power of an Ambassador to dispence with any point, concerning the advertizements he should give unto his Master, namely of such consequence, coming from such a person, and spoken in so great an assembly, whereas me seemed it should have been the office of a trustie servant, truly and exactly to set down thin as they were, and in what manner they had succeeded: to the end the liberty of disposing, judging and ch using, might wholly lie in the master. For to alter and conceal the truth from him, for fear he should conster and take it other than he ought, and lest that might provoke him to some had resolution; and in the meanewhile to suffer him to be ignorant of his own affairs, me thought should rather have appertained to him that gives the law, than to him that receiveth the same; the Master or overseer of the schools, and not to him who should think himself inferior, as well in authority as in wisdom and good counsell. Howsoever it were, I would be loth be so used in my own small and particular business, we do so willingly upon every slight occasion and pretence neglect and forgoe commandement, and are so far from obeying, that we rather usurp a kind of mastery and free power: every man does so naturally aspire unto liberty and authority, that no profit ought to be so dear unto a superior, proceeding from those that serve him as their simple and natural obedience. Whosoever obeyeth by discretion, and not by subjection, corrupteth and abuseth the office of commanding. And P. Crassus he whom the Romans deemed five times happy, when he was Consull in Asia, having sent a Graecian Inginer, to bring the greatest of two ship-masts before him, which he had seen in Athens, therewith to frame an engine of battery: This man under colour of his skill, presumed to do otherwise than he was bidden, and brought the lesser of the two masts which according to his arts reason he deemed the fittest. Crassus having patiently heard his reasons and allegations, caused him to be well whipped; preferring the interest of true discipline, before that of the work. On the other side a man might also consider, that this so strict obedience belongs but to precise and prefixed commandements. Ambassadors have a more scopefull and free charge, which in many points dependeth chiefly of their disposition. They do not meerely execute, but frame and direct by their own advice and counsell, the will of their Master. I have in dayes seen some persons of commandement, checked and found fault withall, because they had rather obeyed the literall sense, and bare words of the Kings letters, than the occasions of the affairs they had in hand. Men of understanding and experience do yet at this daye condemne the custom of the Kings of Persia, which was to mince the instructions given to their Agents, and Lieutenants so small, that in the least accident they might have recourse to their directions and ordinainces: This delay, in so far reaching a scope of domination, having often brought great prejudice, and notable dammage unto their affairs. And Crassus writing unto a man of that profession and advertizing him of the use whereto he purp osed the foresaid mast; seems he not to enter into conference with him concerning his determination, and wish him to interpose his censure or advice of it. Return to CHAPTER XVII: OF FEARE Send comments and corrections to the CHAPTER XVII: OF FEARE Obstupui, steteruntque comæ, et vox faucibus hæsit. -- 1 VIRG. æn. 1. ii. 774. I stood agast, my hair on end, My jaw-tide tongue no speech would lead. AM no good Naturalist (as they say and I know not well by what springs fear does work in us: but well I wot it is a strange passion: and as Physitian s say, there is none does sooner transport our judgement out of his due seat. Verily I have seen diverse become mad and senselesse for fear: indeed in him, who is most settled and best resolved, it is certain that while his fit continueth, it begetteth many strange dazelings, and terrible amazements in him. I omit to speak of the vulgar sort, to whom it sometimes representeth strange apparitions, as their fathers and grandfathers ghosts, risen out of their graves, and in their winding sheets: and to others it sometimes sheweth Larves, Hobgoblins, Robbin-good-fellowes, and such other Bugbeares and Chimeræs. But even amongst Soldiers, with whom it ought to have no credit at all, how often has she changed a flocke of sheep into a troupe of armed men? Bushes and shrubs into men at- arms and officiers? our friends into our enemies? and a red crosse into a white? At what time the Duke of Bourbon took Rome, an Ancient that kept sentinell in the borough Saint Peter, was at the first alarm surprised with such terror, that with his colours in his hand he suddenly threw himself through the hole of a breach out of the City, and just in the midst of hisenemies, supposing the way to go straight in the heart of the City: but in the end he no sooner perceived the Duke of Bourbons troupes advancing to withstand him, imagining it to be some sallie the Citizens made that way, he better bethinking himself, turned head, and the very same way he came out, he went into the town again, which was more than three hundred paces distance towards the fields. The like happened, but not so successfully, unto Captain Iulle his ensigne-bearer at what time Saint Paul was taken from us by the Earle of Bures, and the Lord of Reu, who was so frighted with fear, that going about to cast himself over the town wals, with his Ancient in his hand, or to creepe through a spike-hole, he was cut in peeces by the assailants. At which siege likewise, that horror and fear is very memorable, which so did cboake, seize upon, and freeze the heart of a gentleman, that having received no hurt at all, he fell down stark dead upon the ground before the breach. The like passion rage does sometimes possesse a whole multitude. In one of the encounters that Germanicus had with the Germanes, two mightie troupes were at one instant so frighted with fear, that both betooke themselves to their heels, and ran awa y two contrary ways, the one right to that place whence the other fled. It sometimes addeth wings unto our heels, as unto the first named, and other times it takes the use of feet from us: as we may read of Theophilus the Emperor, who in a battle he lost against the Agarens, was so amazed and agonied, that he could not resolve to scape away by flight: adeo pavor etiam auxilia formidat; ’Fear is so afraid even of that should help;’ Untill such time as Manuel, one of the chief leaders in his army, having rouzed and shaken him, as it were out of a dead sleepe, said unto him, ’Sir, if you will not presently follow me, I will surely kill you, for better were it you should lose your life, than being taken prisoner, lose your Empire and all.’ Then does she show the utmost of her power, when for her own service, she calls us off unto valor, which it has exacted from our duty and honor. In t he first set battle, the Romans lost against Hanibal, under the Consul Sempronius, a troupe of well-nigh ten thousand footmen was so surprised with fear, that seeing no other way to take, nor by what other course to give their basenes free passage, they headlong bent their flight toward the thickest and strongest squadron of their enemies, which with such fury it rowted and slew a great number of the Carthaginians: purchasing a reproachfull and disgraceful flight, at the same rate it might have gained a most glorious victory. It is fear I stand most in fear of. For, in sharpnesse it surmounteth all other accidents. What affecfion can be more violent and just than that of Pompeyes friends, who in his own ship were spectators of that horrible massacre? yet is it, that the fear of the ægyptian sailes, which began to approach them, did in such sort daunt and skare them, that some have noted, they only busied themselves to hasten the marriners to make what speed they could and by main strength of oares to save themselves, until such time, as being arrived at Tyre, and that they were free from fear, they had leisure to bethinke themselves of their late loss, and give their plaints and tears free passage, which this other stronger passion had suspended and hindred. Tum pavor sapientiam omnem mihi ex animo expectorat.-- CIC. Tusc. Qu. 1. iv. ex Enn.; De Orat. 1. iii. Fear then unbreasts all wit, That in my mind did sit. Those who in any skirmish or sudden bickering of warr e have been throughly skared, fore-hurt, wounded, and gored as they be, are many times the next day after brought to charge again. But such as have conceived a true fear of their enemies, it is hard for you to make them looke them in the face again. Such as are in continuall fear to lose their goods, to be banished, or to be subdued, live in incessant agonie and languor; and thereby often lo se both their drinking, their eating, and their rest. Whereas the poore, the banished, and seely servants, live often as carelesly and as pleasantly as the other. And so many men, who by the impatience and urging of fear, have hanged, drowned, and headlong tumbled down from some rocke, have plainly taught us, that fear is more importunate and intolerable than death. The Græcians acknowledge another kind of it, which is beyond the error of our discourse: proceeding, as they say without any ap parent cause, and from an heavenly impulsion. Whole Nations and Armies are often seen surprised with it. Such was that which brought so wonderful a desolation to Carthage, where nothing was heard but lamentable outcries and frightfull exclamations: the inhabitants were seen desperately to run out of their houses, as to a sudden alarm, and furiously to charge, hurt, and enter-kill one another, as if they had been enemies come to usurpe and possesse their City. All things were there in a disordered confusion, and in a confused fury, until such time as by praiers and sacrifices they had appeased the wrath of their Gods. They call it to this day, the Panike terror. Return to CHAPTER XVIII: THAT WE SHOULD NOT JUDGE OF OUR HAPPINESSE UNTILL AFTER OUR DEATH CHAPTER XVIII: THAT WE SHOULD NOT JUDGE OF OUR HAPPINESSE UNTILL AFTER OUR DEATH -- scilicet ultima semper Expectanda dies homini est, dicique beatus Ante obitum nemo, supremaquefun era debet. --OVID. Met. 1. iii. 135. We must expect of man the latest day Nor ere he die, he’s happie, can we say. HE very children are acquainted with the story of Croesus to this purpose: who being taken by Cyrus, and by him condemned to die, upon the point of his execution, cried out aloud: ’Oh Solon, Solon!’ which words of his, being reported to Cyrus; who inquirug what be meant by them, told him, he now at his own cost verified the advertisement Solon had before times given him; which was, that no man, what cbeerefull and blandishing countenance soever fortune showed them may rightly deem himself happie, till such time as he have passed the last day of his life, by reason of the uncertaintie and vicissitude of humane things, which by a very light motive, and slight occasion, are often changed from one to another cleane contrary state and degree. And therefore Agesilaus answered one that counted the King of Persia happy, because being very young the garland of so mightie and great a dominion: ’indeed but said he, Priam at the same age was not unhappy.’ Of the Kings of Macedon that succeeded Alexander the Great, some were afterward seen to become Joyners and Scriveners at Rome: and of Tyrants of Sicilie, School-masters at Corinth. One that had conquered halfe the world, and been Emperor over so many Armies, became an humble and miserable suter to the raskally officers of a king of ægypte: At so high a rate did that great Pompey purchase the irkesome prolonging of his life but for five or six moneths. And in our fathers days, Lodowicke Sforze, tenth Duke of Milan under whom the State of Italie had so long been turmoiled and shaken, was seen to die a wretched prisoner at Loches in France, but not till he had lived and lingered ten years in thraldom, which was the worst of his bargaine. The fairest Queene, wife to the greatest King of Christendome, was she not lately mene to die by the hands of an executioner? Oh unworthie and barbarous crueltie! And a thousand such examples. For, it seems that as the sea-billowes and surging waves, rage and storme against the Burly pride and stubborne height of our buildings, so are there above, certain spirits that envie the rising prosperities and greatneme here below. Vsque adeo res humanas vis abdita quædam Obterit, et pulchros fasces sævasque secures Proculcare, ac ludibrio sibi habere videtur. -- 1 LUCRET. 1. v. 1243. A hidden power so mens states has out-worne Faire swords, fierce scepters, signes of honors borne, It seems to trample and deride in scorne. And it seems Fortune does sometimes narrowly watch the last day of our life, thereby to show her power, and in one moment to overthrow what for many years together she had been erecting, and makes us cry after Laberius, Nimirum hac die undi plus vixi, mihi quam vivendum fuit Thus it is, ’I have lived longer by this one day than I should.’ So may that good advice of Solon be taken with reason. But forasmuch as he is a Philosopher, with whom the favors or disfavours of fortune, and good or in lucke have no place, and are not regarded by him; and puissances and greatnesses, and accidents of quality, are well- nigh indifferent: I deem it very likely he had a further reach, and meant that the same good fortune of our life, which dependeth of the tranquillitie and contentment of a welborne mind, and of the resolution and assurance of a well ordered soul, should never be ascribed unto man, until he have been seen play the last act of his comedie and without doubt the hardest. In all the rest there may be some maske: either these sophisticall discourses of Philosophie are not in us bat by countenance, or accidents that never touch us to the quick, give us alwaies leisure to keep our countenance setled. But when that last part, of death, and of ourselves comes to be acted, when no dissembling will avail, then is it high time to speak plaine_English, and put off all vizards: then whatsoever the pot containeth must be shewne, be it good or had, foul or cleane, wine or water. Nam veræ voces tum demum pectore ab imo Ejiciuntur, et eripitur persona, manet res. -- 1 LUCRET. 1. iii 57. For then are sent true speeches from the heart, We are oursel ves, we leave to play a part. See here, why at this last cast, all our lives other actions must be tride and touched. It is the masterday, the day that judgeth all others: it is the day, says an auncient Writer, that must judge of all my forepassed years, To death do I refer the essay of my studies fruit. There shall we see whether my discourse proceed from my heart, or from my mouth. I have seen diverse, by their death, either in good or evil, give reputation to all their forepass ed life. Scipio, father-in-law to Pompey, in well dying, repaired the ill opinion which until that hour men had ever held of him. Epaminondas being demanded which of the three he esteemed most, either Chabrias, or Iphicrates, or himself: ’It is necessary,’ said he, ’that we be seen to die, before your question may well be resolved.’ Verily, we should steale much from him, if he should be weighed without the honor and greatness of his end. God has willed it, as he pleased: but in my time three of the most execrable persons that ever I knew in all abomination of life, and the most infamous have been seen to die very orderly and quietly, and in every circumstance composed even unto perfection. There are some brave and fortunate deaths. I have seen her cut the twine of some man’s life, with a progresse of wonderful advancement, and with so worthie an end, even in the flowre of his growth and spring of h is youth, that in mine opinion, his ambitious and haughty couragious designes, thought nothing so high as might interrupt them: who without going to the place where he pretended , arived there more gloriously and worthily than either his desire or hope aimed at, and by his fall forewent the power and name whither by his course he aspired. When I judge of other men’s lives, I ever respect how they have behaved themselves in their end; and my chiefest study is, I may well demeane myself at my last gasp, that is to say, quietly and constantly. Return to CHAPTER XIX: THAT TO PHILOSOPHIZE IS TO LEARNE HOW TO DIE CHAPTER XIX: THAT TO PHILOSOPHIZE IS TO LEARNE HOW TO DIE ICERO says, that to Philosophise is no other thing than for a man to prepare himself to death: which is the reason that studie and contemplation does in some sort withdraw our soul from us and severally employ it from the body, which is a kind of apprentisage and resemblance of death; or else it is, that all the wisdom and discourse of the world, does in the end resolve upon this point, to teach us not to fear to die. Truly either reason mockes us, or it only aimeth at our contentment, and in fine, bends all her travell to make us live well, and as the holy Scripture, says, ’at our ease.’ All the opinions of the world conclude, that pleasure is our end, howbeit they take diverse means unto and for it, else would men reject them at their first coming. For, who would give eare unto him, that for it’s end would establish our pain and disturbance? The dissentions of philosophicall sects in this case are verbal: Transcurramus solertissimas nugas;1 ’Let us run over such over-fine fooleries and subtill trifles.’ There is more wilfulnesse and wrangling among them, than pains to a sacred profession. But what person a man undertakes to act, he does ever therewithal personate his own. Allthough they say, that in virtue itself, the last scope of our aime is voluptuousnes. It pleaseth me to importune their ears still with this word, which so much offends their bearing. And if it imply any chief pleasure or exceeding contentment, it is rather due to the assistance of virtue, than to any 1. SEN. Epist. 117.other supply, voluptuousnes being more strong, sinnowie, sturdie. and manly, is but more seriously voluptuous. And we should give it the name of pleasure, more favorable, sweeter, and more natural; and not terme it vigor, from which it has his denomination. Should this baser sen suality deserve this fair name, it should be by competencie and not by privilege. I find it less void of incommodities and crosses than virtue. And besides that, her taste is more fleeting,. momentarie, and fading, she has her fasts, her eves and her travels, and both sweat and blood. Furthermore she has particularly so many wounding passions, and of so severall sorts, and so filthie and loathsome a societie waiting upon her, that she is equivalent to penitencie. We are in the wrong, to think her incommodities serve her as a provocation and seasoning to her sweetues, as in nature one contrary is vivified by another contrary: and to say, when we come to virtue, that like succeses and difficulties overwhelme it, and yield it austere and inaccessible. Whereasmuch more properly then unto voluptuousness they ennobled sharpen, animate, and raise that divine and perfecte pleasure which it meditates and procureth us. Truly he is very unworthie her acquaintance, that counter-ballancet h her cost to his friut, and knowes neither the graces nor use of it. Those who go about to instruct us, how her pursuit is very hard and laborious, and her iovisance well-pleasing and delightfull: what else tell they us, but that she is ever unpleasant and irksome? For, what humane meane did ever attaine unto an absolute enjoying of it? The perfectest have been content but to aspire and approach her, without ever possessing her. But they are deceived; seeing that of all the pleasures we know, the pursute of them is pleasant. The enterprise is perceived by the quality of the thing, which it has regard unto: for it is a good portion of the effect, and consubstantiall. That happines and felicitie which shineth in virtue, replenishet her approaches and appurtenances, even unto the first entrance and utmost barre. Now of all the benefits of virtue, the contempt of the contempt of death is the chiefest, a meane that furnisheth our life with an ease-full tranquillitie and gives us a pure and amiable taste of it: without which every other voluptuousnes is extinguished. See, here the reasons why and all rules encounter and agree with this article. And albeit they all leade us with a common accord to despise grife, povertie, and other accidentall crosses, to which man’s life is subject, it is not with an equall care: as well because accidents are not of such a necessitie for most men pass their whole life without feeling any wan t or povertier and othersome without feeling any grief or sicknes, as Xenophilus the Musitian, who lived an hundred and six years in perfect and continuall health: as also if the worst happen, death may at all times, and whensoever it shall please us, cut off all other inconveniences and crosses. But as for death, it is inevitable. Omnes eodem cogimur, omnium Versatur urna, serius, ocius Sors exitura, et nos in æter- num Exilium impositura cymbæ -- 1 HOR. l. iii. Od. iii. 25. All to one place are driv’n, of all Shak’t is the lot-pot, where-hence shall Sooner or later drawns lots fall, And to deaths boat for aye enthrall. And by consequence, if she makes us affeard, it is a continual subject of torment, and which can no way be eased. There is no starting-hole will hide us from her, she will find us wherever we are, we may as in a suspected countrie start and turn here and there: quæ quasi saxum Tantalo semper impendet (Cic. De Fin. 1) ’Which evermore hangs like the stone over the head of Tantalus:’ Our laws do often condemne and send malefactors to be executed in the same place where the crime was committed: to which while they are going, leade them along the fairest houses, or entertaine them with the best cheere you can, non Siculæ dapes Dulcem elaborabunt saporem: Non avium, citharæque cantus Somnum reducent -- 1 HOR. 1. iii. Od. i. 18. Not all King Denys daintie fare, Can pleasing taste for them prepare No song of birds, no musikes sound Can lullabie to sleepe profound. Doe you think they can take any pleasure in it? or be any thing delighted? and that the finall intent of their voiage being still before their eyes, has not altered and altogether distracted their taste from all these commodities and allurements? Audit iter, numeratgue dies, spatioque viarum Metitur vitam, torquetur peste futura. -- CLAUD. in Ruff. 1. ii. i. 137. 2 He heares his journey, counts his days, so measures he His life by his waies length, vext with the ill shall be. The end of our cariere is death, it is the necessarie object of our aime: if it affright us, how is it possible we should step one foot forther without an ague? The remedie of the vulgar sort is, not to think on it. But from what brutal stupidity may so grosse a blindnesse come upon him? he must be made to bridle his Asse by the tail, Qui capite ipse suo instituit vestigia retro. -- 3 LUCRET. 1. iv. 474. Who does a course contrary run With his head to his course begunne. It is no marvell if he be so often taken tripping some do no sooner hear the name of death spoken of, but they are afraid, indeed the most part will crosse themselves, as if they heard the Devill named. And because mention is made of it in mens wills and testaments, I warrant you there is none will set his hand to them, til the physician has given his last doom, and utterly forsaken him. And God knowes, being then betweene such pain and fear, with what sound judgment they endure him. For so much as this syllable sounded so unpleasantly in their ears, and th is voice seemed so ill-boding and unlucky, the Romans had learned to allay and dilate the name by a Periphasis. In liew of saying, he is dead, or he has ended his days, they would say, he has lived. So it be life, be it past or no, they are comforted: from whom we have borrowed our phrases quondam, alias, or late such a one. It may perhaps be, as the common saying is, the time we live is worth the money we pay for it. I was borne betweene eleven of the clocke and noone, the last of Februarie 1 533, according to our computation, the yeare beginning the first of Januarie. It is but a fortnight since I was 39 years old. I want at least as much more. If in the meane time I should trouble my thoughts with a matter so far from me, it were but folly. But what? we see both young and old to leave their life after one self-same condition. No man departs otherwise from it, than if he but now came to it, seeing there is no man so crazed, bedrell, or decrepit, so long as he remembers Methusalem, but thinkes he may yet live twentie years. Moreover, seely creature as you are, who has limited the end of your days? Happily you presumest upon physicians reports. Rather consider the effect and experience. By the common course of things long since you livest by extraordinarie favor. Thou hast alreadie over-past the ordinary tearmes of common life: And to prove it, remember but your acquaintances, and tell me how many more of them have died before they came to your age, than have eithe r attained or outgone the same: indeed, and of those that through renoune have ennobled their life, if you but register them, I will lay a wager, I will find more that have died before they came to five and thirty years, than after. It is consonant with reason and pietie, to take example by the humanity of Jesus Christ, who ended his humane life at three and thirty years. The greatest man that ever was being no more than a man, I meane Alexander the Great, ended his dayes, and died also of that age. How many severall means and waies has death to surprise us! Quid quisque vitet, nunquam homini satis Cautum est in horas. -- 1 HOR. 1. ii. Od. xiii. 13. A man can never take good heed, Hourely what he may shun and speed. I omit to speak of agues and pleurisies; who would ever have imagined that a Duke of Brittanie should have been stifled to death in a throng of people, as whilome was a neighbour of mine at Lyons, when Pope Clement made his entrance there? Hast you not seen one of our late Kings slain in the middest of his sports? and one of his ancestors die miserably by the chocke of an hog? Eschilus fore- threatned by the fall of an house, when he stood most upon his guard, strucken dead by the fall of a tortoise shell, which fell out of the tallants of a eagle flying in the air? and another choked with the kernel of a grape? And an Emperor die by the scratch of a combe, while he was combing his head? And Aemylius Lepidus with hitting his foot against a doore-seele? Add Aufidius with stumbling against the Consull-chamber doore as he was going in thereat? And Cornelius Gallus, the Prætor, Tigillinus, Captain of the Roman watch, Lodowike, son of Guido Gonzaga, Marquis of Mantua, end their days betweens womens thighs? And of a far worse example Speusippus, the Platonian philosopher, and one of our Popes? Poore Bebius a judge, while he demurreth the sute of a plaintife but for eight days, behold his last expired: And Caius Iulius a Physitian, while he was aniointing the eyes of one of his patients, to have his own sight closed for ever by death. And if amongst these examples, I may adde one of a brother of mine, called Captam Saint Martin, a man of three and twentie years of age, who had alreadie given good testimony of his worth and forward valor, playing at tennis, received a blow with a ball, that hit him a little above the right eare, without appearance of any contusion, bruse, or hurt, and never sitting or resting upon it, died within six hours after of an apoplexie, which the blow of the ball caused in him. These so frequent and ordinary examples, hapning, and being still before our eyes, how is it possible for man to forgo or forget the remembrance of death? and why should it not continually seem unto us, that she is still ready at hand to take us by tth throat? What matter is it, will you say unto me, how and in what manner it is, so long as a man do not trouble and vex himself therewith? I am of this opinion, that however a man may shrowd or hide himself from her dart, indeed, were it under an oxe-hide, I am not the man would shrinke backe: it sufficeth me to live at my ease; and the best recreation I can have, that do I ever take; in other matters, as little vain glorious, and exemplare as you list. -- prætulerim delirus inersque v ideri, Dum mea delectent mala me, vel dinique fallant, Quam sapere et ringi. -- 1 HOR. 1. ii. Epist. ii. 126. A dotard I had rather seem, and dull, Sooner my faults may please make me a gull, Than to be wise, and beat my vexed scull. But it is folly to think that way to come unto it. They come, they go, they trot, they daunce: but no speech of death. All that is good sport. But if she be once come, and on a sudden openly surprise, either them, their wives, their children, or their friends’, what torments, what outcries, what rage, and what despaire does then overwhelme them? saw you ever anything so drooping, so changed, and so distracted? A man must looke to it, and in better times fore-see it. And might that brutish carelessenesse lodge in the mind of a man of understanding (which I find altogether impossible) she sels us her ware at an overdeere rate: were she an enemy by mans wit to be avoided, I would advise men to borrow the weapons of cowardlinesse: but since it may not be, and that be you either a coward or a runaway, an honest or valiant man, she overtakes you, Nempe et fugacem persequitur virum, Nec parcit imbellis juventæ Poplitibus, timidoque tergo. -- HOR. 1. iii.Od. ii. 14. Shee persecutes the man that flies, Shee spares not weake youth to surprise, But on their hammes and backe turn’d plies. And that no temper of curace may shield or defend you, Ille licet ferro cautus se condat et ære, Mors tamen inclusum protrahet inde caput. -- PROPERT. 1. iii. et xvii. 25. 2 Though he with yron and brasse his head empale, Yet death his head enclosed thence with hale. Let us learne to stand, and combat her with a resolute mind. And being to take the greatest advantage she has upon us from her, let us take a cleane contrary way from the common, let us remove her strangenesse from her, let us conve rse, frequent, and acquaint ourselves with her, let us have nothing so much in mind as death, let us at all times and seasons, and in the ugliest manner that may be, indeed with all faces shapen and represent the same unto our imagination. At the stumbling of a horse, at the fall of a stone, at the least prick with a pinne, let us presently ruminate and say with ourselves, what if it were death itself? and thereupon let us take heart of grace, and call our wits together to confront her. Amiddest our bankets, feasts, and pleasures, let us ever have this restraint or object before us, that is, the remembrance of our condition and let not pleasure so much mislead or transport us, that we altogether neglect or forget, how many ways, our joyes, or our feastings, be subject unto death, and by how many hold-fasts she threatens.us and them. So did the ægyptians, who in the middest of their banquetings, and in the full of their greatest cheere, caused the anatomie of a dead man to be brought before them, as a memorandum and warning to their guests. Omnem crede diem ubi diluxisse supremum, Grata superveniet, quo non sperabitur hora. -- HOR. 1. i. Epist. iv. 13. Thinke every day shines on you as your last Welcome it will come, whereof hope was past. It is uncertaine where death looks for us; let us expect her everie where: the premeditation of death, is a fore-thinking of liberty. - He who has learned to die, has unlearned to serve. There is no evil in life, for him that has well conceived, how the privation of life is no evil. To know how to die, does free us from all subjection and constraint. Pualus Emilius answered one, whom that miserable king of Macedon his prisoner sent to entreat him he would not lead him in triumph, ’Let him make that request unto himself.’ Verily, if Nature afford not some help e in all things, it is very hard that art and industrie should go far before. Of my self, I am not much given to melancholy, but rather to dreaming and sluggishness. There is nothing wherewith I have ever more entertained my self, than with the imaginations of death, indeed in the most licentious times of my age, Iucundum, cum ætas florida ver aqeret. -- CATUL. Eleg. iv. 16 When my age flourishing Did spend its pleasant spring. Being amongst fair Ladies, and in earnest play, some have thought me busied, or musing with my self, how to digest some jealousie, or meditating on the uncertaintie of some conceived hope, when God he knowes, I was entertaining my self with the remembrance of some one or other, that but few days before was taken with a burning fever, and of his sodaine end, coming from such a feast or meeting where I was my self, and with his head full of idle conceits, of love, and merry glee; supposing the same, either sickness or end, to be as neare me as him. Iam fuerit nec post, unquam revocare licebit. -- LUCR. 1. iii. 947. Now time would be, no more You can this time restore. I did no more trouble my self or frowne at such conceit, than at any other. It is impossible we should not apprehend or feel some motions or startings at such imaginations at the first, and cmomming sodainely upon us: but doubtlesse, he that shall manage and meditate upon them with an impartiall eye, they will assuredly, in tract of time, become familiar to him: Otherwise, for my part, I should he in continuall fear and agonie; for no man did ever more distrust his life, nor make less account of his continuance: Neither can health, which hitherto I have so long enjoied, and which so seldom has been crazed, lengthen my hopes, nor any sicknesse shorten them of it. At every minute me thinkes I make an escape. And I uncessantly record unto my self, that whatsoever may be done another day, may be effected this day. Truly hazards and danger do little or nothing approach us at our end: And if we consider, how many more there remaine, besides this accident, which in number more than millions seem to threaten us, and hang over us; we shall find, that be we sound or sicke, lustie or weake, at sea or at land, abroad or at home, fighting or at rest, in the middest of a battle or in our beds, she is ever likewise n eere unto us. Nemo altero fragilior est, nemo in crastinum sui certior: ’No man is weaker then other; none surer of himself (to live) till to morrow.Whatsoever I have to do before death, all leisure to end the same seems short unto me, indeed were it but of one hour. Some body not long since turning over my writing tables’, found by chance a memoriall of something I would have done after my death: I told him (and indeed it was true), that being but a mile from my house, and in perfect health and lustie, I had made haste to write it, because I could not assure my self I should ever come home in safety: As one that am ever hatching of my own thoughts, and place them in my self: I am ever prepared about that which I may be: nor can death come when she please) put me in mind of any new thing. A man should ever, as much as in him lieth, be ready booted to take his journey, and above all things , looke he have then nothing to do but with himself. Quid brevi fortes jaculamur ævo Multa? -- HOR. 1. ii. Od. xiv. To aime why are we ever bold, At many things in so short hold? For then we shall have work sufficient, without any more accrease. Some man complaineth more that death does hinder him from the assured course of an hoped for victory, than of death itself; another cries out, he should give place to her, before he have married his daughter, or directe d the course of his childrens bringing up; another bewaileth he must forgo his wives company; another moaneth the loss of his children, the chiefest commodities of his being. I am now by means of the mercy of God in such a taking, that without regret or grieving at any worldly matter, I am prepared to dislodge, whensoever he shall please to call me: I am every where free: my farewell is soone taken of all my friend, except of my self. No man did ever prepare himself to quit the world more simply and fully, or more generally spake of all thoughts of it, than I am fully assured I shall do. The deadest deaths are the best. -- miser, o miser (aiunt) omnia ademit. Una dies infesta mihi, tot præmia vitæ. -- LUCR. 1. iii. 942. O wretch, O wretch (friends cry), one day, All joyes of life has tane away: And the builder, maneant (says he) opera interrupta, minæqe Murorum ingentes. -- VIRG. Aen. 1. iv. 88. The workes unfinisht lie, And walls that threatned hie. A man should designe nothing so long afore hand, or at least with such an intent, as to passionate himself to see the end of it; we are all borne to be doing. Cum moriar, medium solvar et inter opus. -- OVID. Am. 1. ii. El. x. 36. When dying I my self shall spend, Ere halfe my business come to end. I would have a man to be doing, and to prolong his lives offices as much as lieth in him, and let death seize upon me while I am setting my cabiges, care-less of her dart, but more of my unperfect garden. I saw one die, who being at his last gasp, uncessantly complained against his destinie, and that death should so unkindly cut him off in the middest of an historie which he had in hand, and was now come to the fifteenth or sixteenth of our Kings. Illud in his rebus non addunt, nec tibi earum, Iam desiderium rerum super insidet una. -- 2 Lucr. 1. iii. 944. Friends adde not that in this case, now no more Shalt you desire, or want things wisht before. A man should rid himself of these vulgar and hurtful humors. Even as Churchyards were first placed adjoyning unto churches, and in the most frequented places of the City, to enure (as Lycurgus said) the common people, women and children, not to be skared at the sight of a dead man, and to the end that continuall spectacle of bones, sculs, tombs, graves and burials should forewarn us of our condition, and fatall end. Quin etiam exhilarare viris convivia cæde Mos olim, et misercere epulis spectacula dira Certantum ferro, sæpe et super ipsa cadentum Pocula, respersis non parco sanguine mensis. -- SYL. Ital. 1. xi. 51. Nay more, the manner was to welcome guests, And with dire shewes of slaughter to mix feasts. Of them that fought at sharpe, and with bords tainted Of them with much blood, who o’er full cups fainted. And even as the ægyptians after their feastings and carousings caused a great image of death to be brought in and showed to the guests and by-standers, by one that cried aloud, ’Drinke and be merry, for such shall you be when you are dead:’ So have I learned this custom or lesson, to have alwaies death, not only in my imagination, but continually in my mouth. And there is nothing I desire more to be informed of than of the death of men; that is to say what words, what countenance, and what face they show at their death; and in reading of histories, which I so attentively observe. It appeareth by the shuffling and hudling up of my examples, I affect no subject so particularly as this. Were I a composer of books, I would keep a register, commented of the diverse deaths, which in teaching men to die, should after teach them to live. Dicearcus made one of that title, but of another and less profitable end. Some man will say to me, the effect exceeds the thought so far, that there is no fence so sure, or cunning so certain, but a man shall either lose or forget if he come once to that point; let them say what they list: to premeditate on it, gives no doubt a great advantage: and it is nothing, at the least, to go so far re without dismay or alteration, or without an ague? There belongs more to it: Nature herself lends her hand, and gives us courage. If it be a short and violent death, we have no leisure to fear it; if otherwise, I perceive that according as I engage my self in Sicknesse, I do naturally fall into some disdaine and contempt of life. I find that I have more adoe to digest this resolution, that I shall die when I am in health, than I have when I am troubled with a fever: forasmuch as I have no more such fast hold on the commodities of life, whereof I begin to lose the use and pleasure, and view death in the face with a less undanted looke, which makes me hope, that the further I go from that, and the nearer I approch to this, so much more easily do I enter in composition for their exchange. Even as I have tried in many other occurrences, which Cæsar affirmed, that often some things seem greater, being far from us, than if they be near at hand: I have found that being in perfect health, I have much more been frighted with sicknesse, than when I have felt it. The jollitie wherein I live, the pleasure and the strength make the other seem so disproportionable from that, that by imagination I amplifie these commodities by one moitie, and apprehended them much more heavy and burthensome, than I feel them when I have them upon my shoulders. The same I hope will happen to me of death. Consider we by the ordinary mutations and daily declinations which we suffer, how Nature deprives us of the sight of our loss and impairing: what has an aged man left him of his youths vigor; and of his forepast life? Heu senibus vitæ portio quanta manet -- COR. Gal. 1. i. 16. Alas to men in years how small A part of life is left in all? Cæsar to a tired and crazed Souldier of his guard, who in the open street came to him, to beg leave he might cause himself to be put to death; viewing his decrepit behaviour, answered plesantly: ’Doest you think to be alive then?’ Were man all at once to fall into it, I do not think we should be able to bear such a change, but being fair and gently led on by her hand, in a slow, and as it were unperceived desease; by little and little, and step by step, she roules us into that miserable state, and day by day seekes to acquaint us with it. So that when youth failes in us, we feel, nay we perceive no shaking or transcharge at all in ourselves: which in essence and veritie is a harder death, than that of a languishing and irkesome life, or that of age. Forasmuch as the leape from an ill being unto a not being, is not so dangerous or steepie; as it is from a delightfull and flourishing being unto a painfull and sorrowfull condition. A-weake bending, and faint stopping body has less strength to bear and under go a heavy burden: So has our soul. She must be rouzed and raised against the violence and force of this adversarie. For as it is impossible she should take any rest while she feareth: whereof if she be assured (which is a thing exceeding humane condition) she may boast that it is impossible unquietnesse, torment, and fear, much less the least displeasure should lodge in her. Non vultus instantis tyranni Mente qualit solida, neque Auster, Dux inquieti turbidus Adriæ. Nec fulminantis magna Jovis manus. -- HOR. iii. Od. iii. No urging tyrants threatning face, Where mind is found can it displace, No troublous wind the rough seas Master, Nor Joves great hand the thunder-caster. She is made Mistris of her passions and concupiscence, Lady of indulgence, of shame of povertie, and of all fortunes injuries. Let him that can, attaine to this advantage. Herein consists the true and sovereign liberty, that affords us means wherewith to jeast and make a scorne of force and injust ice, and to deride imprisonment, gives, or fetters. -- in manicis, et Compedibus, sævo te sub custode tenebo. Ipse Deus simul atque volam, me solvet opinor, Hoc sentit, moriar. Mors ultima linea rerum est. -- HOR. 1. i. Ep. xvi. 76. In gyves and fetters I will hamper you, Under a Jayler that shall cruel be: Yet, when I will, God me deliver shall, He thinkes, I shall die: death is end of all. Our religion has had no surer humane foundation than the contempt of life. Discourse of reason does not only call and summon us unto it. For why should we fear to lose a thing, which being lost, cannot be moaned? but also, since we are threatened by so many kinds of death, there is no more inconvenience to fear them all, than to endure one: what matter is it when it commeth, since it is unavoidable? Socrates answered one that told him, ’The thirty tyrants have condemned you to death.’ ’And Nature them,’ said he. What fondnesse is it to carke and care so much, at that instant and passage from all exemption of pain and care? As our birth brought us the birth of all things, so shall our death the end of all things. Therefore is it as great folly to weepe, we shall not live a hundred yeeres hence, as to waile we lived not a hundred yeeres agoe. ’Death is the beginning of an other life.’ So wept we, and so much did it cost us to enter into this life; and so did we spoil us of our ancient veil in entring into it. Nothing can be grievous that is but once. Is it reason so long to fear a thing of so short time? Long life or short life is made all one by death. For long or short is not ill things that are no more. Aristotle says, there are certain little beasts alongst the river Hyspanis, that live but one day; she whieh dies at 8 o’clocke in the morning, dies in her youth, and she that dies at 5 in the afternoon, dies in her decrepitude, who of us does not laugh, when we shall see ihis short moment of continuance to be had in consideration of good or ill fortune? The most and the least is ours, if we compare it with eternitie, or equall it to the lasting of mountains, rivers, stars, and trees, or any other living creature, is not less ridiculous. But nature compels us to it. Depart (says she) out of this world, even as you came into it. The same way you came from death to life, return without passion or amazement, from life to death: your death is but a peece of the worlds order, and but a parcell of the worlds life. -- inter se mortales mutua vivunt, Et quasi cursores vitæ lampada tradunt. -- LUCRET, ii. 74, 77. 1 Mortall men live by mutual entercourse: And yield their life-torch, as men in a course. Shal I not change the goodly contexture of things, for you? It is the condition of your creation: death is a part of ourselves: you flie from yourselves. The being you enjoy is equally shared betweene life and death. The first day of your birth does as well addresse you to die, as to live. Prima quæ vitam dedit, hora, carpsit. -- SEN. Her. Sur. chor. iii. The first hour, that to me Gave life, strait, cropt it then. Nascentes morimur, fluisque ab origine pendet. -MANIL. Ast. 1. iv. 2 As we are borne we die; the end Does of the originall depend. All the time you live, you steale it from death: it is at her charge. The continuall work of your life, is to contrive death: you are in death, during the time you continue in life: for, you are after death, when you are no longer living. Or if you had rather have it so, you are dead after life: but during life, you are still dying: and death does more rudely touch the dying than the dead, and more lively and essentially. If you have profited by life, you have also been fed thereby, depart then satisfied. Cur non ut plenus vitæ conviva recedis -- LUCRET. 1. iii. 982. Why like a full-fed guest, Depart you not to rest? If you have not known how to make use of it: if it were unprofitable to you, what need you care to have, lost it? to what end would you enjoy it longer? -- cur amplius addere quæris Rursum quod percat male, et ingratum occidat omne? -- LUCRET. 1. iii. 985. Why seek you more to gain, what must again, All perish ill, and pass with grief or pain? Life in itself is neither good nor evil; it is the place of good or evil, according as you prepare it for them. And if you have lived one day, you have seen all: one day is equal to all other days. There is no other light, there is no other night. This Sunne, this Moone, these Starres, and this disposition, is the very same which your forefathers enjoved. and which shall also entertaine your posterity. Non alium videre patres, aliumve nepotes Aspicient. -- MANIL. i. 522. No other saw our Sires of old, No other shall their sons behold. And if the worst happen, the distribution and varietie of all the acts of my comedie, is performed in one yeare. If you have observed the course of my foure seasons; they containe the infancie the youth, the viriltie, and the old age of the world. He has plaied his part: he knowes no other witness belonging to it, but to begin again, it will ever be the same, and no other. -- Versamur ibidem, atque insumus usque, -- LUCRET. 1. iii. 123. We still in one place turn about, Still there we are, now in, now out. Atque in se sua per vestigia volvitur annus. -- VIRG. Georg. 1. ii. 402. The yeare into itself is cast By those same steps, that it has past. I am not purposed to devise you other new sports. Nam tibi præterea quod machiner, inveniamque Quod placeat, nihil est; eadem sunt omnia semper. -- Id. 1. ii. 978. Else nothing, that I can devise or frame, Can please you, for all things are still the same. Make roome for others, as others have done for you. Equalitie is the chief ground-work of equitie, who can comp laine to be comprehended where all are contained? So may you live long enough, you shall never diminish anything from the time you have to die: it is bootlesse: so long shall you continue in that state which you fear, as if you had died being in your swathing-clothes, and when you were sucking. -- licet, quot vis, vivendo vincere secla, Mors æterna tamen, nihilominus illa manebit. -- LUCRET. 1. iii. 1126. Though yeeres you live, as many as you will, Death is eternall, death remaineth still. And I will so please you, that you shall have no discontent. In vera nescis nullum fore morte alium te, Qui possit vivus tibi te lugere peremptum, Stansque jacentem. -- 911. Thou know’st not there shall be not other you, When you are dead indeed, that can tell how Alive to waile you dying, Standing to waile you lying. Nor shall you wish for life, which you so much desire. Nec sibi enim quisquam tum se vitamque requirit, -- 963. Nec desiderium nostri nos afficit ullum. -- 966. For then none for himself himself or life requires: Nor are we of ourselves affected with desires. Death is less to be feared than nothing, if there were anything less than nothing. -- multo mortem minus ad nos esse putandum, Si minus esse potest quam quod nihil esse videmus. -- 970. Death is much less to us, we ought esteeme, If less may be, than what does nothing seem. Nor alive, nor dead, it does concern you nothing. Alive because you are: Dead, because you are no more. Moreover, no man dies before his hour. The time you leave behinde was no more yours than that which was before your birth, and conc erneth you no more. Respice enim quam nil ad nos anteacta vetustas Temporis æterni fuent. -- 1016. For marke, how all antiquitie foregone Of all time ere we were, to us was none. Wheresoever your life ended, there is it all. The profit of life consists not in the space, but rather in the use. Some man has lived long, that has a short life, Follow it whilst you have time. It consists not in number of yeeres, but in your will, that you have lived long enough. Did you think you should never come to the place, where you were still going? There is no way but has an end. And if company may solace you, does not the whole world walke the same path? -- Omnia te, vita perfuncta, sequentur. -- 1012. Life past, all things at last Shall follow you as you hast past. Doe not all things move as you do, or keep your course? Is there any thing grows not old together with yourselfe? A thousand men, a thousand beasts, and a thousand other creatures die in the very instant that you die. Nam nox nulla diem, neque noctem aurora sequuta est, Que non audierit mistus vagitibus ægris Ploratus, mortis comites et funeris atri. -- ii, 587. No night ensued day light; no morning followed night, Which heard not moaning mixt with sick-mens groaning, With deaths and funerals joined was that moaning. To what end recoile you from it, if you cannot go backe. You have seen many who have found good in death, ending thereby many many miseries. But have you seen any that has received hurt thereby? Therefore it is meere simplicitie to condemne a thing you never approve, neither by yourselfe nor any other. Why doest you complain of me and of destinie? Doe we offer you any wrong? is it for you to direct us, or for us to governe you? Although your age be not come to her period, your life is. A little man is a whole man as well as a great man. Neither men nor their lives are measured by the Ell. Chiron refused immortalitie, being informed of the conditions thereof, even by the God of time and of continuance, Saturne his father. Imagine truly how much an ever-during life would be less tolerable and more painfull to a man, than is the life which I have given him. Had you not death you would then uncessantly curse, and cry out against me, that I had deprived you of it. I have of purpose and unwittingly blended some bitternesse amongst it, that so seeing the cornmoditie of its use, I might hinder you from over-greedily embracing, or indiscreetly calling for it. To continne in this moderation, that is, neither to fly from life nor to run to death (which I require of you) I have tempered both the one and other betweene sweetnes and sowrenes. I first taught Thales, the chiefest of your Sages and Wisemen, that to live and die were indifferent, which made him answer one very wisely, who asked him why he died not: ’Because,’ said he, ’it is indifferent. The water, the earth, the aire, the fire, and other members of this my universe, are no more the instruments of your life than of your death. Why fearest you your last day? he is no more guiltie, and conferreth no more to your deith, than any of the others. It is not the last step that causeth weariness: it only declares it. All days march towards death, only the last comes to it.’ Behold here the good precepts of our universall mother Nature. I have oftentimes bethought my self whence it proceedeth, that in times of war, the visage of death (whether we see it in us or in others) seems without all comparison much less dreadful and terrible unto us, than in our houses, or in our beds, otherwise it should be an army of Physitians and whiners, and she ever being one, there must needs be much more assurance amongst countrie-people and of base condition, than in others. I verily believe, these fearefull looks, and astonishing countenances wherewith we encompass it, are those that more amaze and terrifie us than death: a new form of life; the out cries of mothers; the wailing of women and children; th e visitation of dismaid and swouning friends; the assistance of a number of pale-looliing, distracted, and whining servants; a darke chamber: tapers burning round about; our couch beset round with Physitians and Preachers; and to conclude, nothing but horror and astonishment on every side of us: are we not already dead and buried? The very children are afraid of their friends, when they see them masked; and so are we. The maske must as well be taken from things as from men, which being removed, we shall find nothing hid under it, but the very same death, that a seely varlet, or a simple maid-servant, did latterly suffer without amazement or fear. Happie is that death which takes all leisure from the preparations of such an equipage. Return to CHAPTER XX: OF THE FORCE OF IMAGINATION CHAPTER XX: OF THE FORCE OF IMAGINATION ORTIS imaginatio generat casum: ’A strong imagination begetteth chance,’ say learned clearks. I am one of those that feel a very great conflict and power of imagination. All men are shockt therewith, and some overthrowne by it. One impression of it pierceth me, and for want of strength to resist her, my endeavor to avoid it. I could live with the only assistance of holy and merry-hearted men. The sight of others anguishes does sensibly drive me into anguish; and my sense has often usurped the sense of a third man. If one cough continually, he provokes my lungs and throat. I am more unwilling to visit the sicke dutie does engage me unto, than those to whom I am little beholding, and regard least. I apprehend the evil which I studie, and place it in me. I deem it not strange that she brings both agues and death to such as give her scope to work her will and applaud her. Simon Thomas was a great Physitian in his days. I remember upon a time coming by chance to visit a rich old man that dwelt in Tholouse, and who was troubled with the cough of the lungs, who discoursing with the said Simon Thomas of the means of his recoverie, he told him, that one of the best was, to give me occasion to be delighted in his companie, and that fixing his eyes upon the liveliness and freshness of my face and setting his thoughts upon the jolitie and vigor, wherewith my youthful age did then flourish, and filling all his senses with my flourishing estate, his habitude might thereby be amended, and his health recovered. But he forgot to say, that mine might also be empaired and infected. Gallus Vibius did so well enurehis mind to comprehend the essence and motions of folly, that he so transported his judgement from out his seat, as he could never afterwards bring it to his right place again; and might rightly boast to have become a foole through wisdom. Some there are, that through fear anticipate the hang-mans hand; as he did, whose friends having obtained his pardon, and putting away the cloth wherewith he was hoodwinkt, that he might hear it read, was found stark dead upon the scaffold, wounded only by the stroke of imagination. We sweat, we shake, we grow pale, and we blush at the motions of our imaginations; and wallowing in our beds we feel our bodies agitated and turmoiled at their apprehensions, indeed in such manner as sometimes we are ready to yield up the spirit. And burning youth (although asleepe) is often therewith so possessed and enfolded, that dreaming it does satisfy and enjoy her amorous desires. Ut quasi transactis sæpe omnibu’ rebu’ profundant Fluminis ingentes fluctus, vestemnque cruentent. -- LUCRET. 1. iv. 1027. And if all things were done, they powre foorth streames, And bloody their night-garment in their dreames. And although it be not strange to see some men have hornes growing upon their head in one night, that had none when they went to bed: notwithstanding the fortune or success of Cyppus King of Italie is memorable, who because the day before he had with earnest affection assisted and been attentive at a bul-baiting, and having all night long dreamed of hornes in his head, by the very force of imagination brought them forth the next morning in his forehead. An earnest passion gave the son of Croesus his voice, which Nature denied him. And Antiochus got an ague, by the excellent beautie of Stratonice so deeply imprinted in his mind. Plinie reporteth to have seen Lucius Cossitius upon his marriage day to have been transformed from a woman to a man. Pontanus and others recount the like metamorphosies to have hapned in Italie these ages past: And through a vehement desire of him and his mother. Vota puer solvit, que femina voverat Iphis. -- OVID . Met. 1. ix. 794. Iphis a boy, the vows then paid, Which he vow’d when he was a maid. My self traveling on a time by Vitry in France, hapned to see a man, whom the Bishop of Soissons has in confirmation, named Germane, and all the inhabitants thereabout have both known and seen to be a woman-child, until she was two and twentie years of age, called by the name of Marie. He was, when I saw him, of good years, and had a long beard, and was yet unmarried. He says, that upon a time, leaping, and straining himself to overleape another, he wot not how, but where before he was a woman, he suddenly felt the instrument of a man to come out of him: and to this day the maidens of that town and countrie have a song in use, by which they warne one another, when they are leaping, not to strain themselves overmuch, or open thir legs too wide, for fear they should be turned to boies, as Marie Germane was. It is no great wonder, that such accidents do often happen, for if imagination have power in such things, it is so continually annexed, and so forcibly fastened to this subject, that lest she should so often fall into the relaps of the same thought, and sharpnesse of desire, it is better one time for all to incorporate this virile part unto wenches. Some will not sticke to ascribe the scarres of King Dagobert, or the cicatrices of Saint Francis unto the power of Imagination. Othersome will say, that by the force of it, bodies are sometimes removed from their places. And Celsus reports of a Priest, whose soul was ravished into such an extasie, that for a long time the body remained void of all respiration and sense. Saint Augustine speaks of another, who if he but heard any lamentable and wailful cries, would suddenly fall into a swone, and be so forcibly carried from himself, that did any chide and braule never so loud, pinch and thumpe him never so much, be could not be made to stir, until he came to himself again. Then would he say, he had heard sundry strange voyces, coming as it were from a far, and perceiving his pinches and bruses, wondered at them. And that it was not an obstinate conceit, or wilfull humor in him, or against his f eeling sense, it plainly appeared by this, because during his extasie, he seemed to have neither pulse nor breath. It is very likely that the principal credit of visions, of enchantments, and such extraordinary effects, proceedeth from the power of imaginations, working especially in the mindes of the vulgar sort, as the weakest and seeliest, whose conceit and beleefe is so seized upon, that they imagine to see what they see not. I am yet in doubt, these pleasant bonds, wherewith our world is so fettered, and France so pestered, that nothing else is spoken of, are perhaps but the impressions of apprehension, and effects of fear. For I know by experience, that some one, for whom I may as well answer as for my self, and in whom no manner of suspition either of weaknesse or enchantment might fall, hearing a companion of his make report of an extraordinary faint sowning, wherein he was fallen, at such a time as he least looked for it and wrought him no small shame, whereupon the horrour of his report did so strongly strike his imagination, as he ranne the same fortune, and fell into a like drooping. And was thenceforward subject to fall into like fits: So did the passionate remembrance of his inconvenience possesse and tyrannize him; but his fond doting was in time remedied by another kind of raving. For himself avowing and publishing aforehand the infirmitie he was subject unto, the contention of his soul was solaced upon this, that bearing his evil as expected, his dutie thereby diminished, and he grieved less thereat. And when at his choice, he has had law and power (his thought being cleered and unmasked, his body finding itself in his right due place) to make the same to be felt, seized upon, and apprehended by others knowledge: he has fully and perfectly recovered himself. If a man have once been capable, he cannot afterward be incapable, except by a just and absolute weaknesse. Such a mischief is not to be feared, but in the enterprises where our mind is beyond all measure bent with desire and respect; and chiefly where opportunity comes unexpected, and requires a sudden dispatch. There is no means for a man to recover himself from his trouble; I know some, who have found to come unto it with their bodies as it were halfe glutted elsewhere, thereby to stupifie or allay the heat of that fury, and who through age, find themselves less unable, by how much more they be less able: And another, w ho has also found good, in that a friend of his assured him to be provided with a counter-battery of forcible enchantments, to preserve him in any such conflict: It is not amisse I relate how it was. An Earle of very good place, with whom I was familiarly acquainted, being married to a very fair Lady, who had long been solicited for love by one assisting at the wedding, did greatly trouble his friends; but most of all an old Lady his kins-woman, who was chief at the marriage, and in whose hous e it was solemnized, as she that much feared such sorceries and witchcrafts: which she gave me to understand, I comforted her as well as I could, and desired her to rely upon me. I had by chance a peece of golden plate in my trunke, wherein were ingraven certain celestiall figures good against the Sunne-beames, and for the head-ach, being fitly laid upon the suture of the head: and that it might the better he kept there, it was sewed to a riband, to be fasteded under the chin. A fond doting c onceit, and cosin-germane to that we now speak of. James Peletier had while he lived in my house bestowed that singular gift upon me; I advised my self to put it to some use, and told the Earle, he might perhaps be in danger, and come to some misfortune as others had done, the rather because some were present, that would not sticke to procure him some ill lucke, and which was worse, some spitefull shame; but nevertheless I willed him boldly to go to be d: For I would show him the part of a true friend, and in his need, spare not for his good to employ a miracle, which was in my power; alwaies provided, that on his honor he would promise me faithfully to keep it very secret; which was only, that when about mid-night he should have his candle brought hime if he had had no good success in his business, he should make such and such a signe to me. It fel out his mind was so quailed, and his ears so dulled, that by reason of the bond wherewith the trouble of his imagination had tied him, he could not run on poste: and at the hour appointed, made the signe agreed upon betweene us, I came and whispered him in the eare, that under pretence to put us all out of his chaluber, he should rise out of his bed, and in jesting manner take my night-gowne which I had on, and put it upon himself (which he might well do, because we were much of one stature) and keep it on till he had performed my Appointment, which was, that when we should he gone o ut of the chamber, he should withdraw himself to make water, and using certain jestures I had showed him, speak such words thrice over. And every time he spake them he should girt the ribband, which I put into his hands, and very carefully place the plate thereto fastened, just upon his kidneyes, and the whole figure, in such a posture. All which when he had accordingly done, and the last time so fastened the ribband, that it might neither be untide nor stirred from his place, he should then bo ldly and confidently return to his charge, and not forget to spread my night-gowne upon his bed, but so as it might cover them both. These fopperies are the chief of the effect. Our thought being unable so to free itself, but some strange means will proceed from some abstruse learning: There inanitie gives them weight and credit. To conclude, it is most certain, my Characters proved more venerian than solare, more in action than in prohibition. It was a ready and curious humor drew me to this effect, far from my nature. I am an enemy to craftie and feigned actions, and hate all suttletie in my hands, not only recreative, but also profitable. If the action be not vicious, the course to it is faultie. Amasis King of Egypt took to wife Laodice, a very beauteous young virgin of Greece, and he that before had in every other place found and showed himself a lustie gallant, found himself so short, when he came to grapple with her , that he threatned to kill her, supposing it had been some charme or sorcerie. As in all things that consist in the fantasia, she addrest him to devotion. And having made his vows and promises to Venus, he found himself divinely freed, even from the first night, of his oblations and sacrifices. Now they wrong us to receive and admit us with their wanton, squeamish, quarrelous countenances, which setting us afire, extinguish us. Pythagoras his neece was wont to say, that a woman which lies with a man ought, together with her petiecoate, leave off all bashfulness, and with her petiecoate, take the same again. The mind of the assailant molested with sundry different alarums, is easily dismaid. And he whom imagination has once made to suffer this shame (and she has caused the same to be felt but in the first acquaintances; because they are then burning and violent, and in the first acquaintance and coming together, or trial a man gives of himself, he is much more afraid and qu aint to misse the marke he shoots at) having begun ill he fals into an ague or spite of this accident, which afterward continueth in succeeding occasions. Married men because time is at their command, and they may go to it when they list, ought never to press or importune their enterprise, unless they be readie. And it is better undecently to faile in hanseling the nuptiall bed, full of agitation and fits, by waiting for some or other fitter occasion, and more private opportunity, less sudden an d alarmed, than to fall into a perpetual misery, by apprehending an astonishment and desperation of the first refusall. Before possession taken, a patient ought by sallies, and diverse times, lightly assay and offer himself without vexing or opiniating himself, definitively to convince himself. Such as know their members docile and tractable by nature, let them only endeavor to countercosin their fantasia. Men have reason to checke the indocile libe rtie of this member, for so importunately insinuating himself when we have no need of him, and so importunately, or as I may say impertinently failing, at what time we have most need of him; and so imperiously contesting by his authority with our will, refusing with such fiercenes and obstinacy our solicitations both mentall and manuall. Nevertheless if a man inasmuch as he does gormandize and devour his rebellion, and draws a trial by his condemnation, would pay me for to plead his cause, I w ould perhaps make other of our members to be suspected to have (in envy of his importance, and sweetness of his use) devised this imposture, and framed this set quarrell against him. and by some malicious complot armed the world against him, enviously charging him alone with a fault common to them all. For I refer to your thought, whether there be any one particular part of our body that does not sometimes refuse her particular operation to our will and wish, and that does not often exercise and practise against our will. All of them have their proper passions, which without any leave of ours do either awaken or lull them asleepe. How often do the forced motions and changes of our faces witness the secretest and most lurking thoughts we have, and bewray them to by-standers? The same cause that does animate this member, does also, unwitting to us, embolden our heart, our lungs, and our pulses. The sight of a pleasing object, reflecting imperceptibly on us, the flame of a contagiou s or aguish emotion. Is there nought besides these muscles and veines, that rise and fall without the consent, not only of our will, but also of our thought? We cannot command our hair to stand on end, nor our skinne to startle for desire or fear. Our hands are often carried where we direct them not. Our tongue and voice are sometimes to seek of their faculties, the one loses her speech, the other her nimblenesse. Even when we have nothin g to feed upon, we would willingly forbid it: the appetites to eat, or list to drinke, do not leave to move the parts subject to them, even as this other appetite, and so, though it be out of season, forsaketh us, when he thinks good. Those instruments that serve to discharge the belly, have their proper compressions and dilatations, besides our intent, and against our meaning, as those are destined to discharge the kidneys. And that which, the better to authorize our wills power, Saint Augustin alleageth, to have seen one, who could at all times command his posterior, to let as many scapes as he would, and which Vives endeareth by the example of an other in his days, who could let tunable and organized ones, following the tune of any voice propounded into his ears, inferreth the pure obedience of that member: than which none is commonly more indiscreet anid tumultuous. Seeing my self know one so skittish and mutinous, that these fortie years keepes his master in such awe, that, will he or nill be, he will with a continuall breath, constant and unintermitted custom breake winde at his pleasure, and so brings him to his grave. And would to God I knew it but by histories how that many times our belly being restrained thereof, bring us even to the gates of a pining and languishijig heath: And that the Emperor, who gave us free leave to vent at all times, and every where, had also given us the power to do it. But our will, by whose privilege we advance this reproch, how much more likely, and consonant to trueth may we tax it of rebellion, and accuse it of sedition, by reason of its unruliness and disobedience. Will she at all times do that which we would have her willingly to do? Is she not often willing to effect that which we forbid her to desire? and that to our manifest prejudice and dammage? Does she suffer herself to be directed by the conclusions of our reason? To conclude, I would urge in defense of my client, that it would please the judges to consider , that concerning this matter, his cause being inseparably conjoyned to a comfort, and indistinctly; yet will not a man addresse himself but to him, both by the arguments and charges, which call no way appertaine to his said consort. For, his effect is indeed sometime importunately to invite, but to refuse never: and also to invite silently and quietly. Therefore is the sawcinesse and illegalitie of the accusers seen. Howsoever it be, protesting that advocates and judges may wrangle, contend, and give sentence, what and how they please, Nature will in the meane time follow her course; who, had she endowed this member with any particular privilege, yet had she done but right, and showed but reason. Author of the only immortall work of mortal man. Divine work according to Socrates; and love, desire of immortalitie, and immortall Damon himself. Some man perhaps, by the effects of imagination leaveth the pox or kings evil here, which hi s companion carrieth into Spain again: lo here why in such cases men are accustomed to require a prepared mind, why do physicians labor and practise before hand the conceit and credence of their patients, with so many false promises of their recovery and health, unless it be that the effect of imagination may supple and prepare the imposture of one of their decoction? They knew that one of their trades-masters has left written, how some men have been found, in whom the only sight of a potion has wrought his due operation: all which humor or caprice is now come into my mind, upon the report which an apothecarie, whilome a servant in my fathers house, was wont to tell me, a man by knowledge simple, and by birth a Switzer; a nation little vain-glorious, and not much given to lying, which was, that for a long time he had known a merchant in Tholouse, sickish, and much troubled with the stone, and who often had need of glisters, who according to the fits and occurrences of his evil, caused them diversly to be prescribed by physicians. Which being brought him, no accustomed form to them belonging was omitted, and would often taste whether they were too hot, and view them well. and lying along upon his bed, on his bellie, and all complements performed, only injection excepted, which ceremony ended, the apothecarie gone, and the patient lying in his bed, even as if he had received a glister indeed, he found and felt the very same effect which they do that have effectually taken them. And if the physician saw it had not wrought sufficiently, he would accordingly give him two or three more in the same manner. My witness protesteth, that the sicke mans wife, to save charges (for he paid for them as if he had received them) having sometimes assaid to make them only with luke warme water, the effect discovered the craft, and being found not to work at all, they were forced to return to the former, and use the apothecarie. A woman supposing to have swallowed a pinne with her bread, cried and vexed her-self, even as if she had felt an intolerable pain in her throat, where she imagined the same to sticke; but because there appeared neither swelling or alteration, a skilfull man deeming it to be but a fantasie conceived, or opinion, apprehended by eating of some gretty peece of bread, which perhaps might pricke her in the swallow, made her to vomit, and unknonne to her, cast a pin in that which she had vomi ted. Which the woman perceiving and imagining she had cast the same, was presently eased of her pain. I have known a gentleman, who having feasted a company of very honest gentlemen and gentlewomen, in his own house, by way of sport, and in jest, boasted two or three days after (for there was no such thing) that he had made them eat of a baked cat; where the gentlewoman of the companie apprehended such horror, that falling into a violent ague and distemper of her stomacke, she could by no meane s he recovered. Even brute beasts, as well as we, are seen to be subject to the power of imagination; witness some dogs, who for sorrow of their masters death are seen to die, and whom we ordinarily see to startle and harke in their sleep, and horses to neigh and struggle. But all this may be referred to the narrow future of the spirit and the body, entercommunicating their fortunes one unto another. It is another thing that imagination does sometime s work, not only against her own body, but also against that of others. And even as one body ejecteth a disease to his neighhour, as does evidently appeare by the plague, pox, or sore eyes, that go from one to another: Dum spectant oculi læsos, læduntur et ipsi: Multaque corporibus transitione nocent.-- OVID. Am. 1. ii. 219. Eies become sore, while they looke on sore eyes: By passage many ills our limbs surprise. Likewise the imagination moved and tossed by some vehemence, does cast some darts, that may offend a strange object. Antiquitie has held, that certain women of Scithia, being provoked and vexed against some men, had the power to kill them only with their looke. The tortoises and the estriges hatch their egges with their looks only, a signe that they have some ejaculative virtue. And concerning witches they are said to have offensive and harme-working eyes. Nescia quis teneros oculus mihi fascinat agnos. -- VIRG. Buc. Ecl. iii. 103. My tender Lambs I cannot see, By what bad eye, bewitched be. Magitians are but ill respondents for me. So it is, that by experience we see women to transferre diverse markes of their fantasies, unto children they bear in their wombes: witnes she that brought forth a blacke-a-more. There was also presented unto Charles, King of Bohemia, an Emperor, a young girle, borne about Pisa, all shagd and hairy over and over, which her mother said, to have been conceived so, by reason of an image of Saint John Baptist, that was so painted, and hung over her bed. That the like is in beasts, is witnessed by Jacob’s sheep, and also by partridges and hares, that grow white by the snow upon mountaines. There was lately seen a cat about my own house, so earnestly eyeing a bird, sitting upon a tree, that heseeing the cat, they both so wistly fixed th eir looks one upon another, so long, that at last the bird fell down as dead in the cat’s pawes, either drunken by his own strong imagination, or drawne by some attractive power of the cat. Those that love hawking, have perhaps heard the Falkner tale, who earnestly fixing his sight upon a kite in the aire, laid a wager that with the only force of his looke, he would make it come stooping down to the ground, and as some report did it many times. The histories I borrow, I refer to the consciences of those I take them from. The discourses are mine, and hold together by the proofe of reason, not of experiences: each man may adde his example to them: and who has none, considering the number and varietie of accidentes let him not leave to think, there are store of them. If I come not well for my self, let another come for me. So in the studie wherein I treat of our manners and motions, the fabulous testimonies, alwaies provided they be likely and possible, may serve to the purpose, as well as the true, whether it hapned or no, be it at Rome or at Paris, to John or Peter, it is alwaies a tricke of humane capacitie, of which I am profitably advised by this report. I see it and reape profit by it, as well in shadow as in body. And in diverse lessons that often histories afford, I commonly make use of that which is most rare and memorable. Some writers there are whose end is but to relate the events. Mine, if I could attaine to it, should be to declare what may come to pass, tou ching the same. It is justly allowed in schooles, to suppose similitudes, when they have none. Yet do not I so, and concerning that point, in superstitious religion, I exceed all historicall credit. To the examples I here set down, of what I have read, heard done, or seen, I have forbid my self so much as to dare to change the least, or alter the idlest circumstances. My conscience does not falsifie the least jot. I wot not whether my insight does. Concerning this subject I do sometimes ent er into conceit, that it may well become a divine, a philosopher, or rather men of exquisite conscience, and exact wisdom, to write histories. How can they otherwise engage their credit on a popular reputation? How can they answer for the thoughts of unknown persons? And make their bare conjectures pass for current paiment? Of the actions of diverse members, acted in their presence, they would refuse to bear witness of them, if by a judge they were put to their corporall oath. And there is no man so familiarly known to them, of whose inward intention they would undertake to answer at full. I hold it less hazardous to write of things past than present; forasmuch as the writer is not bound to give account but of a borrowed trueth. Some persuade me to write the affairs of my time, imagining I can see them with a sight less blinded with passion, than other men, and perhaps nearer, by reason of the accesse which fortune has given me to the chiefest of diverse factions. But they will not say, how for the glory of Salust, I would not take the paines; as one that am a vowed enemy of observance, to assiduitie, and to constancy, and that there is nothing so contrary to my style as a continued narration. I do so often for want of breath breake off and interrupt my self. I have neither composition nor explication of any worth. I am as ignorant as a child of the phrases and vowels belonging to common things. And therefore have I atte mpted to say what I can, accommodating the matter to my power. Should I take any man for a guide, measure might differ from his. For, my liberty being so far, I might perhaps publish judgements, agreeing with me, and consonant to reason, yet unlawfull and punishable. Plutarke would perhaps tell us of that which he had written, that it is the workes of others, that his examples are in all and everie where true, that they are profitable to posterity, and presented with a lustre, that lights and directs us unto virtue, and that is his work. It is not dangerous, as in a medicinable drug, whether an old tale or report, be it thus or thus, so or so. Return to CHAPTER XXI: THE PROFIT OF ONE MAN IS THE DAMMAGE OF ANOTHER CHAPTER XXI: THE PROFIT OF ONE MAN IS THE DAMMAGE OF ANOTHER EMADES the Athenian condemned a man of the City, whose trade was to sell such necessaries as belonged to burials, under colour, he asked too much profit for them: and that such profit could not come unto him without the death of many people. This judgement seems to be i ll taken, because no man profiteth but by the loss of others: by which reason a man should condemne all manner of gain. The Merchant thrives not but by the licentiousnesse of youth; the Hushandman by dearth of some; the Architect but by the ruine of houses; the Lawyer by suits and controversies betweene men: Honour itself, and practice of religious ministers, is drawne from our death and vices. ’No physician delighteth in the health of his own friend,’ says the ancient Greeke Comike: ’nor no Souldier is pleased with the peace of his citie, and so of the rest.’ And which is worse, let every man sound his own conscience, he shall find that our inward desires are for the most part nourished and bred in us by the loss and hurt of others; which when I considered, I began to think how Nature does not gainesay herself in this, concerning her general policy: for Physitians hold that the birth, increase, and augmentation of everything, is the alteration and corruption of another. Nam quodcunque suis mutatum finibus exit, Continuo hoc mors est illius, quod fuit ante. -- LUCRET. 1. i. 687, 813; 1. ii. 162; 1. iii. 536. Whatever from it’s bounds does changed pass, That strait is death of that which erst it was. Return to CHAPTER XXII: OF CUSTOME, AND HOW A RECEIVED LAW SHOULD NOT EASILY BE CHANGED CHAPTER XXII: OF CUSTOME, AND HOW A RECEIVED LAW SHOULD NOT EASILY BE CHANGED Y opinion is that he conceived aright of the force of custom that first invented this tale; how a country woman having enured herself to cherish and bear a young calfe in her arms, which continuing, she got such a custom, that when he grew to be a great oxe, she carried him still in her arms. For truly Custome is a violent and deceiving schoole-mistris. She by little and little, and as it were by stealth, establisheth the foot of her authority in us; by which mild and gentle beginning, if once by the aid of time it have setled and planted the same in us, it will soone discover a furious and tyrannical countenance unto us; against which we have no more the liberty to lift so much as our eyes; we may plainly see her upon every occasion to force the rules of Nature: Vsus efficacissimus rerum omnium magister: (PLIN. Epist. xx) Use is the most effectuall master of all things. I believe Platoes den mentioned in his common-wealth, and the Physitians that so often quit their arts reason by authority; and the same King who by means of her, ranged his stomacke to be nourished with poyson; and the mayden that Albe rt mentioneth to have accustomed her-self to live upon spiders: and now in the new-found world of the Indians, there were found diverse populous nations, in far differing climates, that lived upon them; made provision of then, and carefully fed them; as also of grass-hoppers, pissemires, lizards, and nightbats; and a toad was sold for six crownes in a time that all such meats were scarce amongst them, which t hey boyle, rost, bake, and dresse with diverse kinds of sawces. Others have been found to whom our usual flesh and other meats were mortal and venomous. Consuetudinis magna est vis; Pernoctant venatores in nive, in montibus uri se patiuntur: Pugiles clæstibus contusi, ne ingemiseunt quidem. (CIC. Tusc. Qu. ii.) ’Great is the force of custom: Huntsmen wil watch all night in snow, and endure to be scorched on the hils: Fencers brused with sand- bags or cudgels, do not so much as groan.’ These forrein examples are not strange, if we but consider what we ordinarily find by travell, and how custom quaileth and weakeneth our customary senses. We need not go seek what our neighbors report of the Cataracts of Nile; and what Philosophers deem of the celestiall music, which is, that the bodies of it’s circles, being solid smooth, and in their rowling motion, touching and rubbing one against another, must of necessitie produce a wonderful harmonie: by the changes and entercaprings of which, the revolutions, motions, cadences, and carols of the asters and planets, are caused and transported. But that universally the hearing senses of these low world’s creatures, dizzied and lulled asleepe, as those of the ægyptians are, by the continuation of that sound, how loud and great soever it be, cannot sensibly perceive or distinguish the same. Smiths, Millers, Forgers, Armorers, and such other, could not possibly endure the noise that commonly rings in their ears, if it did pierce them as it does us. My perfumed Jerkin serveth for my nose to smell unto, but after I have worne it three or foure days together, not I, but others have the benefit of it. This is more strange, that notwithstanding long intermissions, custom may join and establish the effect of her impression upon our senses; as they prove that dwell near to bells or steeples. I have my longing near unto a tower, where both evening and morning a very great bell does chime Ave Marie and Coverfew, which jangling does even marke the tower to shake; at first it troubled me much, but I was soone acquainted with it, so that now I am nothing offended with it, and many times it cannot waken me out of my sleeps. Plato did once chide a child for playing with nuts, who answered him, ’Thou chidest me for a small matter.’ ’Custome,’ replied Plato, ’is no small matter.’ I find that our greatest vices make their first habit in us from our infancie, and that our chief government and education lieth in our nurses hands. Some mothers think it good sport to see a child wring off a chickens necke, and strive to beat a dog or cat. And some fathers are so fond-foolish, that they will conster as a good Augur or fore-boding of a martiall mind to see their sons misuse a poore peasant, or tug a lackey, that does not defend himself; and impute it to a ready wit, when by some wily disloyaltie, or crafty deceit, they see them cousin and over-reach thei r fellowes: yet are they the true seeds or roots of cruelty, of tyranny, and of treason. In youth they bud, and afterward grow to strength, and come to perfection by means of custom. And it is a very dangerous institution, to excuse so base and vile inclinations, with the weaknesse of age, and lightness of the subject. First, it is nature that speaks, whose voice is then shriller, purer, and more native, when it is tender, newer, and youngest. Secondly, the deformity of the crime consisteth not in the difference betweene crownes and pins; it depends of itself. I find it more just to conclude thus: why should not he as well deceive one of a crowne as he does of a pinne? than as commonly some do, saying, alas, it is but a pinne; I warrant you, he will not do so with crownes. A man would carefully teach children to hate vices of their own genuity, and so distinguish the deformity of them, that they may not only eschew them in their actions, but above all I hate them in their hearts: and what colour soever they bear, the very conceit may seem odious unto them, I know well, that because in my youth I have ever accustomed my self to tread a plaine-beaten path, and have ever hated to entermeddle any manner of deceipt of cousoning-craft, even in my childish sports (for truly it is to be noted, that Childrens playes are not sports, and should be deemed as their most serious actions); there is no pastime so slight, that inwardlie I have not a natural propension and serious care, indeed extreme contradiction, not to use any deceipt. I shuffle and handle the cards as earnestly for counters, and keep as strict an accompt, as if they were double duckets, when playing with my wife or children, it is indifferent to me whether I win or lose, as I do when I play in good earnest. How and wherever it be, my own eyes will suffice to keep me in office; none else do watch me so narrowly; not that I respect more . It is not long since in my own house, I saw a little man, who at Nantes was borne without arms, and has so well fashioned his feet to those services his hands should have done him, that in truth they have almost forgotten their natural office. In all his discourses he nameth them his hands: he carveth any meat, he chargeth and shoots off a pistole, be threads a needle, he soweth, he writeth, puts off his cap, combeth his head, plaieth at cards and dice; shuffleth and handleth them with as great dexteritie as any other man that has perfect use of his hands: the monie I have sometimes given him he has carried away with his feet, as well as any other could do with his hands. I saw another, being a Child, that with the bending of his feet (because he had no hands) would brandish a two-hand-sword and manage a Hol-bard, as nimbly as any man could do with his hands: he would cast them in the aire, then receive them again, he would throw a Dagger, and make a whip to yarke and lash, as cunningly as any Carter in France. But her effects are much better discovered in the strange impressions which it worketh in our mindes where it meetes not so much resistance. What cannot she bring to pass in our judgements and in our conceits? Is there any opinion so fantastical, or conceit so extravagant (I omit to speak of the grosse imposture of religions, wherewith so many great nations and so many worthy and sufficient men have been besotted, and drunken: For, being a thing beyond the compasse of our humane reason, it is more excusable if a man that is not extraordinarily illuminated thereunto by divine favor, do lose and miscarrie himself therein), or of other opinions, is there any so strange, that custom has not planted and established by laws in what regions soever it has thought good? And this ancient exclamation is most just: Non pudet physiumc, id est speculatorem venatoremque naturæ, ab animis consuetudine imbutis quæ rere testimonium veritatis?(CIC. Nat. Deor. 1. i.) ’Is it not a shame for a natural Philosopher, that is the watchman and hunts-man of nature, to seek the testimony of truth from mindes endowed and double dide with custom?’ I am of opinion, that no fantasie so mad can fall into humane imagination, that meetes not with the example of some public custom, and by consequence that our reason does not ground and bring to a stay. There are certain people that turn their backs towards those they salute, and never looke him in the face whom they would honor or worship. ’There are others, who when the King spitteth, the most favoured Lady in his court stretcheth forth her hand; and in another countrey, where the noblest about him, stoop to the ground to gather his ordure in some fine linnen cloth. Let us here by the way insert a tale. A French Gentleman was ever wont to blow his nose in his hand (a thing much against our fashion), maintaining his so doing; and who in wittie jesting was very famous. He asked m e on a time, what privilege this filthie excrement had, that we should have a daintie linnen cloth or handkercher to receive the same; and which is worse, so carefully fold it up, and keep the same about us, which should be more loathsome to ones stomacke than to see it cast away, as we do all our other excrements and filth. Mee thought he spake not altogether without reason: and custom had taken from me the discerning of this strangenesse, which being reported of another countrie we deem so hideous. Miracles are according to the ignorance wherein we are by nature, and not according to natures essence; use brings the sight of our judgement asleepe. The barbarous heathen are nothing more strange to us than we are to them: nor with more occasion, as every man would avow, if after he had travelled through these far-fetcht examples, he could stay himself upon the discourses and soundly conferre them. Humane reason is a tincture in like weight and measure, infused into all our opinions and customs what form soever they be of: infinite in matter: infinite in diversitie. But I will return to my theme. There are certain people, where, except his wife and children, no man speaks to the King but through a trunke. Another nation, where virgins show their secret parts openly, and married women diligently hide and cover them. To which custom, this fashion, used in other places, has some relation: where chastitie is nothing regarded but for marriage sake; and maidens may at their pleasure lie with whom they list; and being with child, they may without fear of accusation, spoyle and cast their chitdren with certain medicaments, which they have only for that purpose. And in another country, if a Merchant chance to marrie, all other Merchants that are bidden to the wedding are bound to lie with the bride before her husband, and the more they are in number, the more honor and commendation is hers for constancy and capacitie; the like if a gentleman or an officer marrie; and so of all orders: except it be a day-labourer, or some other of base condition for then must the Lord or Prince lie with the bride amongst whom (notwithstanding this abusive custom) loyaltie in married women is highly regarded, and held in speciall account during the time they are married. Others there are where public brothel-houses of men are kept, and where open mart of marriages are ever to be had: where women go to the wars with their hushands, and have place, not only in fight, but also in command, where they do not only weare jewels at their noses, in their lip and cheekes, and in their toes, but also big wedges of gold through their paps and buttocks, where when they eat they wipe their fingers on their thighs, on the bladder of their genitories, and the soles of their feet; where not children, but brethren and nephewes inherit; and in some places, the nephewes only, except in the succession of the Prince. Where to order the communitie of goods, which amongst them is religiously observed, certain Soveraigne Magistrats have the general charge of husbandry and tilling of the lands, and of the distribution of the fruits, according to every mans need: where they howle and weepe at their childrens deaths, and joy and feast at their old mens decease. Where ten or twelve men be all in one bed with all their wives; where such women as lose their hushands , by any violent death, may marrie again, others not: where the condition of women is so detested that they kill all the maiden children as soon as they are borne, and to supply their natural need, they buy women of their neighbors. Where men may at their pleasure, without alleging any cause, put away their wives, but they (what just reason soever they have) may never put away their husbands. Where husbands may lawfully sell their wives, if they be barren. Where they cause dead bodies first to be boiled, and then to be brayed in a morter, so long till it come to a kind of pap, which afterward they mingle with their wine, and so drinke it. Where the most desired sepulcher that some wish for, is to be devoured of dogges, and in some places of birds. Where some think that blessed soules live in all liberty, in certain pleasant fields stored with al commodities, and that from them proceeds that Eccho which we hear. Where they fight in the water, and shoot execeeding true with their bowes as they are swimming. Where in signe of subjection men must raise their shoulders and stoop with their heads, and put off their shoes when they enter their Kings houses. Where Eunuchs that have religious women in keeping, because they shall not be loved, have also their noses and lips cut off. And Priests that that they may the better acquaint themselves with their Demons, and take their Oracles, put out their eyes. Where every man makes himself a God of what be pleaseth: the hunter of a Lion or a Fox; the fisher, of a certain kind of Fish; and frame themselves Idols of every humane action or passion: the Sunne, the Moone, and the earth are their chiefest Gods: the form of swearing is, to touch the ground, looking upon the Sunne, and where they eat both flesh and fish raw. Where the greatest oath is to sweare by the name of some deceased man that has lived in good reputation in the countrie, touching his grave with the hand. Where the new-years gifts that Kings send unto Princes their vassals every yeare, is some fire, which when it is brought, all the old fire is cleane put out: of which new fire all the neighbouring people are bound upon pain, læse majestatis, to fetch for their uses. When the King (which often cometh to pass) wholly to give himself unto devotion, gives over his charge, his next successor is bound to do like, and convayeth the right of the Kingdome unto the third heir. Where they diversifie the form of policy according as their affairs seem to require; and where they depose their Kings when they think good, and appoint them certain ancicnt grave men to undertake and weald the Kingdoms government, which sometimes is also committed to the communaltie. Where both men and women are equally circumcised, and likewise baptised. Where the souldier, that in one or diverse combats has presented his King with seven enemies heads, is made noble. Where some live under that so rare and unsociable opinion of the mortalitie of soules. Where women are brought abed without pain or grief. Where women on both their legs weare greaves of Copper: and if a louse bite them, they are bound by duty of magnanimity to bite it again: and no maid dare marrie, except she have first made offer of her Virginitie to the King. Where they salute one another laying the forefinger on the ground, and then lifting it up toward heaven: where all men bear burthens upon their head, and women on their shoulders. Where women pisse standing, and men cowring. Where in signe of true friendship they send one another some of their own blood, and offer incense to men which they intend to honor, as they do to their Gods: where not only kindred and consanguinitie in the fourth degree, but in any furthest off, can by no means be tolerated in marriages: where children sucke till they be four, and sometimes twelve years old, in which place they deem it a dismal thing to give a child sucke the first day of his birth. Where fathers have the charge to punish their male children, and mothers only maidchildren, and whose punishment is to hang them up by the feet and so to smoke them. Where women are circumcised: where they eat all manner of herbes, without other distinction but to refuse those that have ill savour: where all things are open, and how fair and rich soever their houses be, they have neither doors nor windowes, nor any chests to locke: yet are all theeves much more severely punished there than anywhere else; where, as monkies do, they kill lice with their teeth, and think it a horrible matter to see them crusht between their nailes; where men as long as they live never cut their hair nor pair their nailes: another place where they only pair the nailes of their right hand, and those of the left are never cut, but very curiously maintained: where they endeavour to cherish all the hair growing on the right side, as long as it will grow, and very often shave away that of the left side: where in some Provinces near unto us some women cherish their hair before, and other some that behinde, and shave the contrary: where fathers lend their children, and husbands their wives to their guests, so that they pay ready money: where men may lawfully get their mothers with child: where fathers may he with their daughters and with their sons: where in solemn assemblies and banquets, without any distinction of blood or alliance, men will lend one another their children. In some places men feed upon humane flesh, and in others, where it is deemed an office of pietie in children to kill their fathers at a certain age: in other places fathers appoint what children shall live and be preserved, and which die and be cast out, while they are yet in their mothers wombe: where old husbands lend their wives to young men, for what use soever they please: In other places, where al women are common without sinne or offence: indeed in some places, where for a badge of honor they weare as many frienged tassels, fastened to the skirt of their garment, as they have laine with severall men. Hath not custom also made a severall common-wealth of women? has it not taught them to manage Armies? to levie Armies, to marshall men, and to deliver battles? And that which strict-searching Philosophie could never persuade the wisest, does she not of her own natural instinct teach it to the grosest headed vulgar? For we know all nations, where death is not only condemned, but cherished: where children of seven years of age, without changing of countenance, or showing any signe of dismay, endured to be whipped to death; where riches and worldly pelfe was so despised and holden so contemptible, that the miserablest and neediest wretch of a City would have scorned to stoop for a purse full of gold. Havo we not heard of diverse most fertile regions, plenteously yielding al manner of necessary victuals, where nevertheless the most ordinary cates and daintiest dishes were but bread, water-cresses, and water? Did not custom work this wonder in Chios, that during the space of seven hundred yeres it was never found or heard of that any woman or maiden had her honor or honestie called in question? And to conclude, there is nothing in mine opinion, that either she does not, or cannot: and with reason does Pindarus, as I have heard say, call her the Queen and Empresse of all the world. He that was met beating of his father answered, ’It was the custom of his house; that his father had so beaten his grandfather, and he his great- grandfather;’ and pointing to his son, said, ’This child shall also beat me when he shall come to my age.’ And the father, whom the son hauled and dragged through thicke and thinne in the street, commanded him to stay at a certain doore: for himself had dragged his father no further: which were the bounds of the hereditarie and injurious demeanours the children of that family were wont to show their fathers. ’By custom,’ says Aristotle, ’as often by sicknesse, do we see women tug and teare their haires, bite their nailes, and eat cole and earth and more by custom than by nature do men meddle and abuse themselves with men.’ The laws of conscience, which we say to proceed from nature, rise and proceed of custom; every man holding in special regard and inward veneration the opinions approved, and custo mes received about him, cannot without remorse leave them, nor without applause applie himself unto them: when those of Creet would in former ages curse any man, they besought the Gods to engage him in some bad custom. But the chiefest effect of her power is to seize upon us, and so to entangle us, that it shall hardly lie in us to free ourselves from her hold-fast, and come into our wits again, to discourse and reason of her ordinances; verily, because we sucke them with the milke of our birth , and forasmuch as the worlds visage presents itself in that estate unto our first view, it seems we are borne with a condition to follow that course. And the common imaginations we find in credit about us, and by our fathers seed infused in our soul, seem to be the general and natural. Whereupon it followeth, that whatsoever is beyond the compasse of custom, we deem likewise to be beyond the compasse of reason, God knowes how for the most part, unreasonably. If as we, who study ourselves, have learned to do, every man that heareth a just sentence, would presently consider, how it may in any sort belonging unto his private state, each man should find that this is not so much a good word as a good blow to the ordinary sottishnesse of his judgment. But men receive the admonitions of truth and her precepts, as directed to the vulgar, and never to themselves; and in liew of applying them to their maners, most men most foolish ly and unprofitably apply them to their memory. But let us return to customs soveraignty: such as are brought up to liberty, and to command themselves, esteeme all other form of policy as monstrous and against nature. Those that are enured to, Monarchie do the like. And what facilitie soever fortune affoordeth them to change, even when with great difficultie they have shaken off the importunitie of a tutor, they run to plant a new one with semblable difficulties because they cannot resolve themselves to hate tutorship. It is by the meditation of custom that every man is contented with the place where nature has setled him; and the savage people of Scotland have nought to do with Touraine; nor the Scithians with Thessalie. Darius demanded of certain Græcians, ’For what they would take upon them the Indians custom, to eat their deceased fathers.’ (For such was their manner, thinking they could not possibly give them a more noble and favourable tomb than in their own bowels.) They answered him, ’That nothing in the world should ever bring them to embrace so inhumane a custom.’ But having also attempted to persuade the Indians to leave their fashion and take the Græcians, which was to burne their corpes, they were much more astonished thereat. Every man does so, forasmuch as custom does so bleare us that we cannot distinguish the true visage of things. Nil adeo magnum, nec tam mirabile quicquam Principio, quod non minuant mirarier omnes Paulatim . -- (LUCRET. 1. ii, 1037) Nothing at first so wondrous is, so great, But all, t’admire, by little slake their heat. Having other times gone about to endeare and make some one of our observations to be of force, and which was with resolute auctoritie received in most parts about us, and not desiring, as most men do, only to establish the same by the force of laws and examples, but having ever bin from her beginning, I found the foundation of it so weake that myself, who was to confirme it in others, had much adoe to keep my countenance. This is the receipt by which Plato undertaketh to banish the unnaturall and preposterous loves of his time, and which he esteemeth sovereign and principal: To wit, that public opinion may condemne them; that Poets, and all men else may tell horrible tales of them. A receit by means whereof the fairest daughters winne no more the love of their fathers, nor brethren most excellent in beautie the love of their sisters. The very fables of Thyestes, of Oedipus, and of Macareus, having with the pleasures of their songs infused this profitable opinion in the tender conceit of children. Certes, chastitie is an excellent virtue, the commoditie whereof is very well known; but to use it, and according to nature to prevaile with it, is as hard as it is easy, to endeare it and to prevaile with it according to custom, to laws and precepts. The first and universall reasons are of a hard perscrutation. And our Masters pass them over in gleaning, or in not daring so much as to taste them, at first sight cast themselves headlong into the liberty or sanctuarie of custom. Those that will not suffer themselves to be drawne out of his original source, do also commit a greater error, and submit themselves to savage opinions: witness Chrysippus; who in so many severall places of his compositions, inserted the small accompt he made of conjunctions, how incestuous soever they were. He that will free himself from this violent prejudice of custom, shall find diverse things received with an undoubted resolution, that have no other anker but the hoarie head and frowning wimples of custom, which ever attends them: which maske being pulled off, and referring all matters to truth and reason, he shall perceive his judgment, as it were overturned, and placed in a much surer state. As for example, I will then aske him, what thing can be more strange than to see a people bound to follow laws he never understood? Being in all his domesticall affairs, as marriages, donations, testaments, purchases, and sales, necessarily bound to customary rules, which forasmuch as they were never written nor published in his own tongue, he cannot understand, and whereof he must of necessity purchase the interpretation and use. Not according to the ingenious opinion of Isocrates, who counselled his King ’to make the Trafikes and negotiations of his subjects free, enfranchize and gameful, and their debates, controversies, and quarrels burthensome, and charged with great subsidies and impositions.’ But according to a prodigious opinion, to make open sale, and trafficke of reason itself, and to give laws a course of merchandize, is very strange. I commend fortune for that (as our historians report) it was a Gentleman of Gaskonie, and my Countriman, that first opposed himself against Charles the great, at what time he went about to establish the Latine and Imperiall laws amongst us. What is more barbarous than to see a nation, where by lawful custom the charge of judging is sold, and judgments are paid for with readie monie; and whore justice is lawfully denied him that has not wherewithall to pay for it; and that this merchandize has so great credit, that in a politicall government there should be set up a fourth estate of Lawyers, breath- sellers, and pettifoggers, and joined to the three ancient states, to wit, the Clergy, the Nobility, and the Communaltie; which fourth state having the charge of laws, and sometimes auctoritie of goods and lives, should make a body, apart and severall from that of Nobilitie, whence double laws must follow, those of honor and those of justice; in many things very contrary do those as rigorously condemne a lie pocketed up, as these a lie revenged: by the law and light of arms he that putteth up an injurie shall be degraded of honor and nobility; and he that revengeth himself of it, shall by the civill Law incur a capital punishment. He that shall addresse himself to the laws to have reason for some offence done unto his honor, dishonoureth himself. And who does not so, is by the Lawes punished and chastised. And of these. so different parts, both nevertheless having reference to one head; those having peace, these war committed to their charge; those having the gain, these the honor; these knowledge, these virtue ; those reason, these strength; those the word, these action; those justice, these valor; those reason, these force; those a long gowne, and these a short coat, in partage and share. Touching indifferent things, as clothes and garments, whosoever will reduce them to their true end, which is the service and commodity of the body, whence dependeth their originall grace and comlines, for the most fantastic to my humor that may be imagined, amongst others I will give them our square caps; that long hood of plaited velvet, that hangs over our womens head, with his parti-coloured traile, and that vain and unprofitable modell of a member which we may not so much as name with modesty, whereof notwithstanding we make public show and open demonstration. Those considerations do nevertheless never distract a man of understanding from following the common guise. Rather, on the contrary, me seems that all severall, strange, and particular fashions proceed rather of folly or ambitious affectation than of true reason: and that a wise man ought inwardly to retire his mind from the common press, and hold the same liberty and power to judge freely of all things, but for outward matters he ought absolutely to follow the fashions and form customarily received. Publike society has nought to do with our thoughts; but for other things, as our actions, our travel, our fortune, and our life, that must be accomodated and left to its service and common opinions: as that good and great Socrates, who refused to save his life by disobeying the magistrate, indeed a magistrate most wicked and unjust. For that is the rule of rules, and general law of laws, for every man to observe those of the place wherein he liveth. -- Gnom. Graec. vii. Lawes of the native place, To follow, is a grace. See here some of another kind. There riseth a great doubt whether any so evident profit may be found in the change of a received law, of what nature soever, as there is hurt in removing the same; forasmuch as a well-setled policy may be compared to a frame or building of diverse parts joined together with such a ligament as it is impossible to stir or displace one, but the whole body must needs be shaken, and show a feeling of it. The Thurians Law-giver instituted that ’whosoever would go about, either to abolish any one of the old Lawes, or attempt to establish a new, should present himself before the people with a rope about his necke, to the end, that if his invention were not approved of all men, he should presently be strangled.’ And he of Lacedemon laboured all his life to get an assured promise of his citizens, that they would never infringe any one of his ordinances. That Ephore or Tribune, who so rudely cut off the two strings that Phrinis had added unto music, respecteth not whether music be better or no with them, or whether the accords of it be better filled, he has sufficient reason to condemne them, because it is an alteration of the old form. It is that which the old rustie sword of justice of Marseille did signify. I am distasted with noveltie, what countenance soever it show; and I have reason so to be, for I have seen very hurtful effects follow the same. That which so many years since does so press us, has not yet exploited all. But some alleage, with apparance, that by accident it has produced and engendered all, indeed, both the mischiefes and ruines that since are committed without against it; it is that a man should blame and find faulte with. Heu patior telis vulnera facta meis. -- OVID. Epist, Phyl. 48. Alas I suffer smart Procured by my own dart. Those which attempt to shake an estate, are commonly the first overthrowne by the fall of it: he that is first mover of the same, reapeth not alwayes the fruit of such troubles; he beats and troubleth the water for others to fish in. The contexture and combining of this monarchie and great building, having bin dismist and disolved by it, namely in her old years, gives as much overture and entrance as a man will to like injuries. Royall Majestie does more hardly fall from the top to the middle, than it tumbleth down from the middle to the bottom. But if the inventors are more damageable, the imitators are more vicious, to cast themselves into examples, of which they have both felt and punished the horror and mischief. And if there be any degree of hon our, even in ill doing, these are indebted to others for the glory of the invention and courage of the first attempt. All sorts of new licentiousnesse do perhaps draw out of this originall and fruitfull source, the images and patterns to trouble our commonwealth. We may read in our very laws, made for the remedie of the first evil, the apprentisage and excuse of all sorts of wicked enterprise: And in favor of public vices, they are named with new and more pleasing words for their excuses, bastardizing and allaying their true titles: yet it is to reforme our consciences and our conceits, Honesta oratio est (TEREN. Andria Act. i. sc. i.) - ’It is an honest speech and well said.’ But the best pretence of innovation or noveltie is most dangerous: Adeo nihil motum ex antiquo probabile est. (TIT. LIV. xxxiv. 54.) So nothing moved out of the first place is allowable.’ Yet, me seems (if I may speak boldly) that it argueth a great self-love and presumption for a man to esteeme his opinions so far, that for to establish them a man must be faine to subvert a public peace, and introduce so many inevitable mischiefes, and so horrible a corruption of manners, as civill wars and alterations of a state bring with them, in matters of such consequence, and to bring them into his own countrie. Is it not ill husbanded to advance so many certain and known vices, for to combate contested and debatable errors? Is ther e any worse kind of vices than those which shocke a man’s own conscience and natural knowledge? The Senate durst give this defeate in payment about the controversies betweene it and the people for the mysterie of their religion: Ad deos id magis quam ad se pertinere: ipsos visuros, ne sacra sua polluantur: (TIT. LIV. x. 6.) ’That that did rather belong to the Gods than to them, and the Gods should looke to it, that their due rites were not polluted.’ Agreeing with that, which the Oracle answered those of Delphos, in the Median war, fearing the invasions of the Persians. They demanded of that God what they should do with the treasures consecrated to his temple, whether hide or cary them away: who answered them, that they should remove nothing, but take care of themselves, for he was able to provide for all things that were fit for him. Christian religion has all the markes of extreme justice and profit, but none more apparent than the exact commendation of obedience due unto magistrate, and manute ntion of policies: what wonderful example has divine wisdom left us, which to establish the: well-fare of humane kind, and to conduct this glorious victory of hers against death and sinne, would not do it but at the mercy of our politik order, and has submitted the progresse of it, and the conduct of so high and worthie effect, to the blindnesse and injustice of our observations and customs, suffering the innocent blood of so many her favored elect to run, and allowing a long loss of years for the ripening of this inestimable fruit? There is much difference betweene the cause of him that followeth the formes and laws of his countrie, and him that undertaketh to governe and change them. The first alleageth for his excuse, simplicitie, obedicnce, and example; whatsoever he does cannot be malice, at the most it is but ill lucke. Quis est enim, que non moveat clarissimis monumentis testata consignataque antiquitas? (CIC. Div. 1. i.) ’For who is he whom antiquitie will not move, being witnessed and si gned with former monuments?’ Besides that which Isocrates says that defect has more part in moderation, than has excess. The other is in much worse case. For he that meddles with causing and changing, usurpeth the authority of judging: and must resolve himself to see the fault of what he hunteth for, and the good of what he bringeth in. This so vulgar consideration has confirmed me in my state, and restrained my youth, that was more rash, from burthening my shoulders with so filthie a burden, as to make my self respondent of so important a science. And in this to dare, what in sound judgement I durst not in the easiest of those wherein I had been instructed, and wherein the rashnesse of judging is of no prejudice. Seeming most impious to me, to go about to subject public constitutions and unmoveable observances, to the instabilitie of a private fantasie (private reason is but a private jurisdiction) and to undertake that on divine laws, which no policy would tolerate in civill law. Wherein although man’s reason have much more commerce, yet are they soveraignly judges of their judges: and their extreme sufficiencie serveth to expound custom and extend the use that of them is received, and not to divert and innovate the same. If at any time divine providence has gone beyond the rules to which it has necessary constrained us, it is not to give us a dispensation from them. They are blowes of her divine hand, which we ought not imitate, but admire: as extraordinarie examples, markes of an express and particular avowing of the severall kinds of wonders, which for a testimony of her ominpotencie it offereth us, beyond our orders and forces, which it is folly and impiety to go abont to represent, and which we onght not follow but contemplate with admiration, and meditate with astonishment. Acts of her personage, and not of ours. Cotta protesteth very opportunely; Quum de religione agitur, T. Coruncanium, P. Scipionem, P. Scævolam, Pontifices maximos, non Zenonem, aut Cleanthem, aut Chrysippum sequor: (1 CIC. De. Nat. 1. iii. c. 2.) ’When we talk of religion, I follow Titus Coruncanium, Publius Scipio, P. Scævola, and the professors of religion, not Zeno, Cleanthes, or Chrysippus.’ May God know it in our present quarrel, wherein are a hundred articles, indeed, great and deepe articles, to be removed and alterd, although many there are who may boast to have exactly survaid the reasons and foundations of one and another faction. It is a number, if it be a number, that should have no great meane to trouble us. But whither goeth all this other throng? Under what colours does it quarter itself? It followeth of theirs, as of other weake and ill applied medicines, the humors that it would have purged in us, it has enflamed, exasperated, and sharpned, by her conflict, and still do remaine in our bodies. It could not by reason of her weaknesse purge us, but has rather weakned us; so that we cannot now void it, and by her operation we reap nothing but long, continuall, and intestine griefes and aches, yet is it, that fortune, ever reserving her authority above our discourses, does sometimes present us the urgent necessitie, that laws must need yield her some place: And when a man resisteth the increase of an innovation, brought in by v iolence, to keep himself each-where and altogether in rule and bridle against those that have the keyes of fields, to whom all things are lawfull, that may in any sort advance their design, that have not law, nor order, but to follow their advantage, it is a dangerous obligation and prejudiciall inequalitie. Aditum nocendi perfido prostat fides. -- SEN. Oed. act. iii. sc. 1. Trust in the untrustee, may To hurt make open way . For so much as the ordinary discipline of an estate, th at has his perfect health, does not provide for these extraordinarie accidents, it presupposeth a body holding itself in his principal members and offices, and a common consent to observe and obey it. Lawfull proceeding is a cold, dull, heavy, and forced proceeding: and is not like to hold out against a licentious and unbridled proceeding. It is yet, as all men know, a reproach to those two great personages, Octavius and Cato, in their civill wars: the one of Scilla, the other of Cæsar, because they rather suffered their countrie to incur all extremities, than by her laws to aid her, or to innovate anything. For truly in these last necessities, where nothing is left to take hold by, it were. Peradventure better to shrug the shoulders, stoop the head, and somewhat yield to the stroke, than beyond possibilitie to make head and resist, and be nothing the better, and give violence occasion to trample all underfoot: and better were it to force the laws to desire but what they may, since they may not what they would. So did he that ordained them to sleepe foure and twentie hours: And he who for a time removed one day from the Calendar: And another who of the moneth of June made a second May. The Lacedemonians themselves, so strict observers of their countries ordinances, being urged by their Lawes, which precisely forbid and inhibited to chuse one man twice to be their Admiral, and on the other side their affairs necessarily requiring that Lysander should once more take that charge upon him, they created one Aracus Admiral, but instituted Lysander superintendent of all maritime causes. And with the same sutteltie, one of their Ambassadors being sent to the Athenians for to obtaine the change of some ordinance, Pericles alleging that it was expresly forbid to remove the table wherein a law had once been set down, persuaded him but to turn, for that was not forbidden. It is that whereof Plutarke commendeth Philopæmen, who being borne to command, could not only command according to the laws, but the laws themselves, whensoever public necessitie required it. Return to CHAPTER XXIII: DIVERS EVENTS FROM ONE SELFSAME COUNSELL nonpfit and educational purposes only. CHAPTER XXIII: DIVERS EVENTS FROM ONE SELFSAME COUNSELL AMES AMIOT, great Almoner of France, did once tell me this story, to the honor of one of our Princes (and so he was indeed by very good tokens, albeit by offspring he were a stranger), that during our first troubles, at the siege of Roane, the said Prince being advertised by the Queene-mother of a conspiracie and enterprise that should be attempted against his life, and by letters particularly informed him of the partie that should performe it, who was a gentleman of Anjow, or Manse, and who to that purpose did ordinarily frequent the said Princes court; he never imparted that secret or communicated that warning to any man, but the next morrow walking upon Saint Catherins hill, whence our battery played against the town (for it was, at what time we laid siege to Roane) with the said Lord great Almoner and another Bishop by his side, he chanced to descrie the said gentleman, whom the Queene-mother had described unto him, and caused him to be called, who being come before his presence, said thus unto him, perceiving him alreadie to wax pale and tremble at the alarums of his conscience: Master, such a one, I am fully persuaded you fore-imagine what I will charge you with, and your countenance does plainly show it, you can conceal nothing from me: for I am so well instructed of your business that would you go about to hide it, you should but marre all, you have perfect knowledge of this and this thing (which were the chiefest props and devices of the secretest drifts of his complot and conspiracie) faile not therefore, as you tender your life, to confesse the truth of all your purpose.’ When the silly man saw himself so surprised and convicted (for the whole matter had been discovered unto Queene by one of the complices) he had no other way but to lift up his hands and beg for grace and mercy at the Princes hands, at whose feete he would have prostrated himself, but that he would not let him: thus following his discourse: ’Come hither my friend,’ said he, ’Did I ever do you any displeasure? Have I ever through any particular hatred wronged or offended any friends of yours? It is not yet three weekes since I knew you, what reason might move you to conspire and enterprise my death?’ The gentleman with a faint trembling voice, and self-accusing looke, answered him, that no particular occasion had ever moved him to that, but the interest of the general cause of his faction, and that some of them had persuaded him, that to root out, and in what manner soever, to make away so great an enemy of their religion, would be an execution full of pietie, and a work of supererogation. Then said the Prince, ’I show you how much the religion which I profess is more mild than that whereof you make profession: yours has persuaded you to kill me, without hearing me, having never been offended by me: and mine commands me to pardon you, convicted as you are, that you would so treacherously and without cause have killed me. Goe your way, withdraw your self, let me never see you here again, and if you be wise, henceforward in your enterprises take honester men for your counsellers than those of your religion.’ The Emperor Augustus being in Gaule, received certain advertisement of a conspiracie, that L. Cinna complotted against him, whereof he purposed to be avenged, and for that purpose sent to all his friends against the next morrow for advice and counsell, but passed the fore-going night with great anxietie and unrest, considering that following his intent, be should bring a yong Gentleman, well borne, of a noble house, and great Pompeyes nephew, to his death: which perplexitie produced diverse stran ge discourses and consideration in him. ’What,’ says he unto himself, ’shall it ever be reported, that I do live in fear, and suffer mine enemy to walke at his pleasure and liberty? Shall he then go free, that has attempted and resolved to deprive me of my life, which both by sea and land I have saved from so many civill wars, and from so many battles? And now that I have stablished an universall peace in the world, shall he be absolved and go unpunished, that has not only determined to murther, but sacrifice me?’ (For, the complot of the conspiracie was to murther him when he should be at sacrifice.) After that, having taken some rest with himself, he with a lowder voice began to exclaime and cry out against himself, saying, ’Why livest you, if the lives of so many depend on your death? Shall your vengeance and cruelties never have an end? Is your life of that worth, as it may countervaile the sundry mischiefes that arelike to ensue, if it be preserved?’ Livia his wife being in bed with him, perceiving his agonie and hearing his speeches, says thus unto him: ’And may not womens counsells be admitted? Doe as Physitians are wont, who when their ordinairie receipts will not work, have recourse to the contrary. Hitherto you couldest never do any good with severitie: Lepidus has followed Savidienus Murena Lepidus, Coepio Murena, Egnatius Scoepio; begin now to prove what a good lenitie and clemencie will do you: Cinna is convicted, pardon him: To annoy or hurt you now he is not able, and you shall thereby increase your glory.’ Augustus seemed very glad to have found an Advocate of his humor, and having thanked his wife, and countermanded his friends whom he had summoned to the Counsell, commanded Cinna to be brought before him alone. Then sending all men out of his chamber, and a chaire prepared for Cinna to sit in, he thus bespoke him: ’First, Cinna, I require to have a gentle audience, and that you wilt not interrupt my speech, which ended, I will give you time and leisure to answer me: Thou knowest (oh Cinna) that when I had taken you prisoner in mine enemies campe, who were not only become, but borne my foe; I saved you, then put you in quiet possession of your goods, and at last, have so enriched you, and placed you in so high a degree, that even the conquerours are become envious over the conquered. The Priests office, which you beggedst at my hands, I freely bestowed on you, having first refused the same to others, whose fathers and friends had in many battles shed their blood for me: After all which benefits, and that I had in dutie tied you so fast unto me, you hast notwithstanding undertaken to kill me.’ To whom Cinna replied, crying alowd, ’That he had never so much as conceived so wicked a thought, much less entertained the same.’ ’Oh Cinna, this is not according to your promise,’ answered then Augustus, ’which was that you would not interrupt me: What I say is true, you hast undertaken to murther me in such a place on such a day, in such a company. and in such manner:’ and seeing him so amazed in heart, and by his evidence strucken dumbe, moved thereunto, not by the condition of his promise, but by the guilt of his self-accusing conscience; ’why would you do it,’ replied he, ’is it because you would be Emperor? Truly the commonwealth is but in hard condition, if none but myself hinder you from the Empire. Thou canst not so much as defend thine own hous and didst but lately lose a processe only by the favor of a seely libertine. What, hast you no meane of power in any other matter, but to attempt Cæsars life? I quit it, if there be no man but my self to impeach your hopes. Supposest you that Paulus, that Fabius, that the Cossenians, or the Servillianes will ever permit you? And so great a troupe of noble men, noble not only in name, but such as by their virtues honor their nobility, will ever suffer it?’ After many other such like discourses (for he talked with him more than two hours) he said unto him: ’Away, oh Cinna, that life which once I gave you, as to an enemy, I now give you again, as to a traitour and a patricide: let a true friendship from this day forward begin betweene us, let us strive together which of us two with a better faith shall out-go the other, and whether I have given your life, or you hast received the same with great confidence:’ and so left him. Shortly after he gave him the Consulship, blaming him that he durst not aske it of him. And ever after held him as his dear friend, and made him alone heir and executor of his goods. Now after this accident, which hapned to Augustus in the xl yeare of his age, there was never any conspiracie or enterprise attempted against him; and he received a just reward for his so great clemency. But the like succeeded not to one Prince, for his mildness and lenitie could not so warrant him, but that afterward he fell into the snares of the like treason: so vain and frivolous a thing is humane wisdom: and contrary to all projects, devices, counsels and precautions, fortune does ever keep a full sway and possession of all events. We count those Physitians happy and successful, that successfully end a desperate cure, or come to a good issue: as if there were no other art but theirs, that could not subsist of itself, and whose foundations were too feeble to stand and rely upon h er own strength: and as if there were none but it, that stands in need of fortunes helpe-affoording hand, for the effecting of her operations. My conceit of it is, both the worst and the best a man may imagine: for, thankes be to God, there is no commerce betweene us: I am contrary to others: for I ever despise it, and when I am sick, instead of entring into league or composition with it, I then beginne to hate and fear it most: and answer such as urge me to take Physicke, that at least they will tarie till such time as I have recovered my health and strength again; that then I may the better be enabled to endure the violence and hazard of their potions. I let nature work, and presuppose unto my self that she has provided herself, both of teeth and clawes, to defend herself from such assaults as shall beset her, and to maintaine this contexture or frame, whose dissolution it so much hateth. In liew of bringing helpe unto her when she most striveth, and is combated by sicknesse I greatly fear lest I bring succor unto her adversarie, and surcharge her with new enemies. Now I conclude, that not only in Physicke, but likewise in sundry more certain arts, fortune, has great share in them. The Poeticall furies, which ravish and transport their Author beyond himself, why shall we not ascribe them to his good fortune, since himself confesseth that they exceed his strength and sufficiencie, and acknowledgeth to proceed from elsewhere than from himself, and that they are not in his power, no more than Orators say to have those strange motions and extraordinary agitations, that in their art transport them beyond their purpose? The like we see to be in painting, for sometimes the Painters hand shall draw certain lines or draughts, so far exceeding his conception or skill, that himself is forced to enter into admiration and amazement. But fortune yet does much more evidently show the share she has in all their workes, by the graces and beauties that often are found in them, not only beyond the intent, but besides the very knowledge of the workman. A heedy Reader shall often discover in other mens compositions, perfections far differing from the Authors meaning, and such as perhaps he never dreamed of, and illustrateth them with richer senses and more excellent constructions. As for military enterprises, no man is so blinde but seeth what share fortune has in them : even in our counsels and deliberations, some chance or good lucke must needs be joined to them, for whatsoever our wisdom can affect is no great matter. The sharper and quicker it is, more weaknesse findes it in itself, and so much the more does it distrust itself. I am of Sillæs opinion: and when I nearest consider the most glorious exploits of war, me thinkes I see, that those who have the conduct of them, employ neither counsell nor deliberation about them, but for fashion-sake, and leave the best part of the enterprise to fortune, and on the confidence they have in her ayd, they still go beyond the limits of all discourse. Casuall rejoycings, and strange furies ensue among their deliberations, which for the most induce them to take the counsell least grounded upon apparance or reason, and which quaile their courage beyond reason; whence it has succeeded unto diverse great Captains, by giving credit to such rash counsels; and alleging to their soldiers, that by some divine inspiration, and other signes and prognostications, they were encouraged to such and such enterprises. See here why in this uncertaintie and perplexitie, which the impuissances and inabilitie does bring us to see and chuse what is most commodious for the difficulties which the diverse accidents and circumstances of everie thing draw with them: the surest way, if other considerations did not invite us thereto, is, in my conceit, to follow the partie, wherein is most honestie and justice; a nd since a man doubteth of the nearest way, ever to keep the right. As in these two examples I have lately mentioned, there is no doubt but that it was more commendable and generous in him who had received the offence, to remit and pardon the same, than to have done otherwise. If the first had but ill-success, his good intent is not to be blamed; and no man knows, had be taken the contrary way, whether he should have escaped the end, to which destinie called him; and then had he lost the glory and commendations of so seld-seen humanitie. Sundrie men possessed with this fear, are read-of in ancient Histories; the greatest part of which have followed the way of fore- running the conspiracies which were complotted against them, by revenge or tortures, but I see very few, that by this remedy have received any good; witness so many Roman Emperours. He that perceiveth himself to be in this danger ought not much to rely upon his power, or hope in his vigilancie. For, how hard a matter is it for a man to warrant and safeguard himself from an enemy, that masks under the visage of the most officious and heartie-seeming friend we have? And to know the inward thoughts and mind-concealed meanings of such as daily attend, and are continually with us? It will little avail him to have foraine nations to his guard, and ever to be encircled about with troupes of Armed men? whosoever he be that resolveth to condemne his own life, may at any time become Master of other mens lives. Moreover, that continual suspicion which makes the Prince to mistrust every body, should be a wonderful vexation to his mind. And therefore when Dion was advertised that Calippus watched to kill him, could never find in his heart to informe himself of it: affirming: ’He had rather die once, than ever live in fear and misery, and to guard himself not only from his enemies, but from his very friends.’ Which thing Alexander presented more lively and undantedly by effect, who by a letter of Parmenio having received advertisement that Philip, his neerest and best regarded Physitian, had with money been suborned and corrupted by Darius to poison him, who at the very instant that he gave Philip the letter to read, swallowed down a potion he had given him: was it not to express his resolution, that if his friends would kill him he would not shun them, but consent to their treachery? This Prince is the Soveraigne patterne of hazardous attempt s: yet know I not whether in all his life he showed an act of more resolute constancy than this, nor an ornament so many ways famous. Those which daily preach and buzze in Princes ears, under colour of their safetie, a heedy diffidence and everwarie distrustfulnesse, do nought but tell them of their ruine, and further their shame and downefall. No noble act is atchieved without danger. I know one by his own complexion, of a right martial courage and ready for any resolution, whose good and hopefull fortune is dayly corrupted by such verball persuasion; as first to keep close with his friends; never to listen to any reconciliation with his old enemies: to stand upon his own guard; never to commit himself to any stronger than himself, what fair promise soever they make him, or whatsoever apparant profit they seem to containe. I also know another, who because he did ever follow the contrary counsell, and would never listen to such schoole- reasons, has beyond all hope raised his fortune above the common reach. That boldness wherewith they so greedily gape after glory, is alwayes at hand, when ever need shall be, as gloriously in a doublet as in an armour; in a cabinet as in a campe; the arm held down, as lifted up. A wisdom so tenderly precise, and so precisely circumspect, is a mortal enemy to haughty executions. Scipio, to sound the depth of Siphax intent, and to discover his mind; leaving his army, and abandoning the yet unsetled country of Spain, which under his new conquest of it was likely to be suspected, he, I say, could pass into Affrike only with two simple ships or small barkes, to commit himself in a strange and foe countrie, to engage his person, under the power of a barbarous King, under an unknown faith, without either hostage or letters of credence, indeed, without any body, but only upon the assurance of the greatness of his courage, of his successeful good fortune, and of the promise of his high-raised hopes. Habita fides ipsam plerumque fidem obligat: ’Most commonly trusting obligeth trustinesse.’ To an ambitious and fame aspiring mind, contrariwise, a man must yield little, and cary a hard hand against suspicions: Fear and distrust draw on offences and allure them. The most mistrustful of our Kings established his affairs, and setled his estate, especially because he had voluntarily given over, abandoned and committed his life and liberty, to the hands and mercy of his enemies: Seeming to put his whole confidence in them, that so they might likewise conceive an,undoubted affiance in him. Cæsar did only confront his mutinous legions, and oppose his hardly-ruled Armies, with the mind-quelling authority of his countenance, and awe-moving fiercenesse of his words: and did so much trust himself and his fortune, that he no whit feared to abandon and commit himself to a seditious and rebellious Armie. -- stetit aggere fulti Caespitis, intrepidus vultu, meritque timeri Nil metuens. -- 1 LUCAN. 1. iii. 296. He on a rampart stood of turfe upreard, Fearlesse and following none, was to be fear’d. True it is, that this undaunted assurance cannot so fully and lively be represented, but by those in whom the imagination or apprehension of death, and of the worst that may happen, can strike no amazement at all: for, to represent it fearfully-trembling, doubtful and uncertaine, for the service of an important reconciliation, is to effect no great matter: It is an excellent motive to gain the heart and good will of others, for a man to go and submit himself to them, provided it be done freely, and without constraint of any necessitie, and in such sort that a man bring a pure and unspotted confidence with him, and at least his countenance void of all scruple. Being yet a child, I saw a gentleman who had the command of a great City, and by a commotion. of a seditiously furious people greatly put to his plunges, who to suppresse the rising fire of his tumult, resolved to sally out from a strongly assured place, where he was safe, and yield himself to that many- headed monster mutinous rowt; thrived so ill by it that he was miserably slain amongst them: yet deem I not this oversight to have beent so great in issuing out, his memory being of most men condemned, as because he took away his submission and remissenesse, and attempted to exunguish that rage and hurly-bur ly rather by way of following than of guiding, and by requiring sute than by demonstrative resolution; and I deem, a gratiously mild severetie, with a militaire commandement, full of confidence and securitie, beseeming his rank and the dignitie of his charge, had better availed him, had become more successfull, at least with more honor, and well-seeming comlinesse. There is nothing less to be expected or hoped for at the hands of this monstrous faced multitude, thus agitated by fury, than humanitie and gentlenesse; it will much sooner receive reverence and admit fear. I might also blame him, that having undertaken a resolution (in my judgment, rather brave than rash) to caste himself inconsiderately, weake and unarmed, amidst a tempestuous ocean of senselesse and mad men, he should have gone through stitch with it, and not leave the person he represented in the briers, whereas after he had perceived the danger at hand, he chanced to bleed at the nose; and then to change that demiss and flattering countenance he had undertaken into a dismaid and drooping looke, filling both voice and eyes with astonishment and repentance: and seeking. to squat himself, he the more enflamed and called them upon him. It was determined there should be a general muster made of diverse troupes of armed men (a place fittest for secret revenges, and where they may safest be achieved) there were most apparent reasons, that the place was very unsure, or at least, to be suspected, by such as were to have the principal and necessary charge to survey them. Divers counsels were proposed, sundry opinions heard, as in a subject of great difficultie, and on which depended so many weightie consequences. My advice was, they should carefully avoid to give any testimony of suspition or show of doubt, and that our troupes should be as full as might be, and the Fyles orderly ranked, and every Souldier show an undaunted carriage and undismayed countenance, and instead of keeping some of our forces backe (which thing most opinions aimed at) all Captains should he put in mind to admonish their Soldiers to make their sallies as orderly and as strong as might be, in honor of the assistance; and spare no powder, which would serve as a gratification toward these suspectfull troupes, which afterward caused a mutual and profitable confidence. I find the course that Julius Cæsar held to be the best a man may take: First he assayed by clemencie to purchase the love of his very enemies, contenting himself in the conspiracies that were discovered unto him, simply to show they were not unknown to him, but, had perfect notice of them. That done, he took a most noble resolution, which was, without dread or dismay, or any care-taking, to attend whatsoever might betide him, wholy abandoning and remitting himself into the hands of the Gods and of fortune. For certainely, it is the state wherein he was, when he was murthered in the Senate. A stranger having published ere that he could teach Dionysius the tyrant of Siracusa a way to understand and discover the very certaintie of all the practices his subjects or any else should practise against him, if he could bestowe a good summe of money upon him: Dionysius being thereof advertised, sent for him, to discover the secret, and understand the truth of so necessarie an art for this preservation: the stranger told him, there was no other skill in his art, but that he should deliver him a talent, and then boast he had learned the use of so unvaluable a secret of him. Dionysius allowed of his invention, and forthwith caused six hundred crownes to be delivered him. It is not likely that ever he would have given so great a summe of mony to an unknown man, but in reward of a most profitable instruction; for by way of this reputation he kept his enemies still in awe. And therefore do Princes wisely publish such advertisements as they receive of the plots conspired, and treasons practised against their lives and states, thereby to make men believe, that nothing can be attempted against them, but they shall have knowledge of it. The Duke of Athens committed many foolish oversights in the establishing of his late tyrannie upon the Florentines, but this the chiefest, that having received the first advertisement of the Monopolies and Complots the Florentines contrived against him, by Mathew, surnamed Morozo, one of the complices, thinking to suppresse this warning, and conceal that any in the City were offended at him, or grudged at his rule, caused him immediately to be put to death. I remember to have heretofore read the story of a Roman (a man of speciall dignitie) who flying the tyrannie of the Triumvirate, had many times by the sutteltie of his invention, escaped those who pursued him. It fortuned upon a day, that a troupe of horse- men, who had the charge to apprehend him, passing alongst a hedge under which he lay lurking, had well-nigh discovered him; which he perceiving, and considering the dangers and difficulties he had so long endured, thinking to save himself from the continuall and daily searches that every where were made after him, and calling to mind the small pleasure he might hope of such a life, and how much better it were for him to die at once than live in such continuall fear and agonie, himself called them, and voluntarily discovered his lurking hole, and that he might rid them and himself from further pursuit and care, did willingly yield unto their crueltie. For a man to call his enemies to aid him, is a counsell somewhat rash, yet think I it were better to embrace it, then remaine still in the continuall fit of such a fever that has no remedie. But since the provisions of man may apply unto it, are full of unquietnesse and uncertaintie, much better is it with a full assurance to prepare himself patiently to end ure whatsoever may happen, and draw some comfort from that which a man is never sure shall come to pass. Return to CHAPTER XXIV. OF PEDANTISME. CHAPTER XXIV OF PEDANTISME I HAVE in my youth oftentimes been vexed to see a Pedant brought in, in most of Italian comedies, for a vice or sport-maker, and the nicke- name of Magister to be of no better signification amongst us. For, my self being committed to their tuition, how could I chuse but he somewhat jealous of their reputation? In deed I sought to excuse them by reason of the natural disproportion that is betweene the vulgar sort, and rare and excellent men, both in judgment and knowledge: forasmuch as they take a cleane contrary course one from another. But when I considered the choysest men were they that most contemned them, I was far to seek, and as it were lost my self: witness our good Bellay: Mais je hay par sur tout un scavoir pedantesque. A pedant knowledge, I Detest out of all cry. Yet is this custom very ancient; for Plutarke says, that Greeke and Scholer were amongst the Romans words of reproach and reputation. And coming afterwards to years of more discretion, I have found they had great reason, and that magis magnos clericos, non sunt magis magnas sapientes: ’The most great Clerkes are not the most wisest men. But whence it may proceed, that a mind rich in knowledge, and of so many things, becomes thereby never livelier nor more quickesighted; and a grose-headed and vulgar spirit may without amendment containe the discourse and judgement of the most excellent wits the world ever produced, I still remaine doubtfull. To receive so many, so strange, indeed so great wits, it must needs follow (said once a Lady unto me, indeed one of our chiefest Princesses, speaking of some body) that a man’s own wit, force, droops, and as it were diminishes itself, to make roome for others. I might say, that as plants are choked by over-much moisture, and lampe dammed with too much oyle, so are the actions of the mind over-whelmed by over-abundance of matter and studie: which occupied and intangled with so great a diversitie of things, loses the meane to spread and clear itself and that surcharge keepeth it low-drooping, and faint. But it is otherwise, for our mind stretch the more by how much more it is replenished. And in examples of former times, the contrary is seen, of sufficient men in the managin g of public affairs, of great Captains, and notable Counsellers in matters of estate, to have been therewithall excellently wise. And concerning Philosophers, retired from all public negotiations, they have indeed sometimes been vilified by the comike liberty of their times, their opinions and demeanors yielding them ridiculous. Will you make them Judges of the right of a processe, or of the actions of a man? They are readie for it. They enquire whether there be any life yet remaining, wheth er any motion. Whether man be any thing but an Oxe, what working or suffering is; what strange beasts law and justice are. Speake they of the Magistrate, or speak they unto him; they do it with an unreverent and uncivill liberty. Heare they a Prince or a King commended? He is but a shepherd to them, as idle as a Swaine busied about milking of his cattell, or shearing of his sheepe: but more rudely. Esteeme you any man for possessing two hundred acres of land? They scoffe at him, as men accustomed to embrace all the world as their possession. Do you boast of your Nobilitie, because you can blazon your descent of seven or eight rich Grandafthers? They will but little regard you, as men that conceive not the universall image of nature, and how many predecessors every one of us has had, both rich and poore, Kings and groomes, Greekes and Barbarians. And were you lineally descended in the fiftieth degree from Hercules, they deem it a vanity to vaunt or allege this gift of fortune. So did the vulgar sort disdaine them as ignorant of the first and common things, and as presumptuous and insolent. But this Platonicall lustre is far from that which our men stand in need of. They were envied as being beyond the common sort, as despising public actions, as having proposed unto themselves a particular and inimitable life, aiming and directed at certam high discourses, and from the common use; these are disdained as men beyond the ordinary fashion, as incapable of public charges, as leading an unsociable life, and professing base and abject customs, after the vulgar kind. Odi homines ignavos opere, Philosophos sententia: (Pacuvius, Lips. i. 10) I hate men that are fooles in working, and Philosophers in speaking. As for those Philosophers, I say, that as they were great in knowledge, so were they greater in all action. And even as they report of that Syracusan Geometrician, who being taken from his bookish contemplation to show some practice of his sk ill, for the defense of his countrie reared sodainly certain terror-moving engines, and showed effects far exceeding all mens conceit, himself notwithstanding disdaining all this his handieworke, supposing he had thereby corrupted the dignitie of his art; his engines and manuall works being but the apprentiships, and trials of his skill in sport: So they, if at any time they have been put to the trial of any action, they have been seen to flie so high a pitch, and with so lofty a flight, that men might apparently see their minds and spirits were through the intelligence of things become wonderfully rich and great. But some perceiving the seat of politike government possessed by unworthy and incapable men, have withdrawne themselves from it. And he who demanded of Crates, how long men should Philosophize, received this answer, Untill such time as they who have the conduct of our Armies be no longer blockish asses. Heraclitus resigned the royalty unto his brother. And to the Ephesians, who reproved him for spending his time in playing with children before the temple: he answered And is it not better to do so, than to governe the public affairs in your companie? Others having their imagination placed yond fortune and the world, found the seat of justice, and the thrones of Kings, to be but base and vile. And Empedocles refused the royalty which the Agrigentines offered him. Thales sometimes accusing the carke and care men took about good busbandry, and how to grow rich; some replied unto him, that he did as the Fox, because he could not attaine unto it himself; which hearing, by way of sport he would show by experience how he could at his pleasure become both thriftie and rich; and bending his wits to gain and profit, erected a traffike, which within one yeare brought him such riches as the skilfullest in trade of thriving could hardly in all their life devise how to get the like. That which Aristotle reporteth of some who called both him and Anaxagoras, and such like men, wise and not prudent, because they cared not for things more profitable: besides, I do not very well digest this nice difference of words that serveth my find-fault people for no excuse: and to see the base and needie fortune wherewith they are content, we might rather have just cause to pronounce them neither wise nor prudent. I quit this first reason, and think it better to say, that this evil proceedeth from the bad course they take to follow sciences; and that respecting the manner we are instructed in them, it is no wonder if neither Schollers nor Masters, howbeit they may prove more learned become no whit more sufficient. Verily the daily care and continuall charges of our fathers aymeth at nothing so much as to store our heads with knowledge and-learning; as for judgement and virtue, that is never spoken of. If a man pass by, crie out to our people: Oh what a wise man goeth yonder! And of another: Oh what a good man is yonder! he will not faile to cast his eyes and respect toward the former. A third crier were needfull, to say, Oh what blocke-heads are those! We are ever readie to aske, Hath he any skill in the Greeke and Latine tongue? can he write well? does he write in prose or verse? But whether he be grown better or wiser, which should be the chiefest of his drift, that is never spoken of. We should rather enquire who is better wise than who is more wise. We labor, and toyle, and plod to fill the memory, and leave both understanding and conscience empty. Even as birds flutter and skip from field to field to pecke up corne, or any graine, and without tasting the same, carrie it in their bils, therewith to feed their little ones; so do our pedants gleane and picke learning from bookes, and never lodge it further than their lips, only to degorge and cast it to the wind. It is strange how fitly sottishnesse takes bold of mine example. Is not that which I do in the greatest part of this composition, all one and self same thing? I am ever here and there picking and culling, from this and that book, the sentences that please me, not to keep them (for I have no store-house to reserve them in) but to transport them into this: where, to say truth, they are no more mine than in their first place: we are (in mine opinion) never wise, but by present learning, not by that which is past, and as little by that which is to come. But which is worse, their Schollers and their little ones are never a whit the more fed or better nourished: but passeth from hand to hand, to this end only, thereby to make a glorious show, therewith to entertaine others, and with its help to frame some quaint stories, or prettie tales, as of a light and counterfeit coyne unprofitable for any use or employment, but to reckon and cast accompts. Apud alios loqui didicerunt, non ipsi secum. Non est loq uendum, sed gubernandum: (SEN. Epist. cviii.) They have learned to speak with others, not with themselves: speaking is not so requisite as government. Nature, to show that nothing is savage in whatsoever she produces, causeth oftentimes, even in rudest and most unarted nations, productions of spirits to arise, that confront and wrestle with the most artist productions. As concerning my discourse, is not the Gaskonie proverbe, drawne from a bagpipe, prettie and quaint? Bouha prou houha, mas a remuda lous dits qu’em: You may blow long enough, but if once you stir your fingers, you may go seek We can talk and prate, Cicero says thus, These are Platoes customs, These are the very words of Aristotle; but what say we our selves? what do we? what judge we? A Peroquet would say as much. This fashion puts me in mind of that rich Roman, who to his exceeding great charge had been very industrious to find out the most sufficient men in all sciences, which he continually kept about him, that if at any time occasion should be moved amongst his friends to speak of any matter pertaining to Schollership, they might supplie his place, and be readie to assist him: some with discourse, some with a verse of Homer, othersome with a sentence, each one according to his skill or profession; who persuaded himself that all such learning was his own, because it was contained in his servants minds. As they do whose sufficiencie is placed in their sumptuous libraries. I know some, whom if I aske what he knows, he will require a book to demonstrate the same, and durst not dare to tell me that his posteriors are scabious, except he turn over his Lexicon to see what posteriors and scabious is. We take the opinions and knowledge of others into our protection, and that is all; I tell you they must be enfeoffed in us, and made our own. We may very well be compared unto him, who having need of fire, should go fetch some at his neighbors chimney, where finding a good fire, should there stay to warme himself, forgetting to carrie some home. What availes it us to have our bellies full of meat, if it be not digested? If it be not transchanged in us? except it nourish, augment, and strengthen us. We may imagine that Lucullus, whom learning made and framed so great a captaine without experience, would have taken it after our manner? We rely so much upon other mens arms, that we disanull our own strength. Will I arm my self against the fear of death? it is at Seneca’s cost: will I draw comfort either for my self, or any other? I borrow the same of Cicero. I would have taken it in my self, had I been exercised unto it: I love not this relative and begd-for sufficiencie. Suppose we may be learned by other mens learning. Sure I am we can never be wise but by our own wisdom. Μισω σοφιστην, οστις ουχ αυτω σοφος. --Proverb. Iamb. That wise man I cannot abide, That for himself cannot provide. Ex quo Ennius: Nequidquam sapere sapientem, qui ipso ibi prodesse non quiret. Whereupon says Ennius: That wise man is vainly wise, who could not profit himself. ----- si cupidus, si Vanus, et Euganea quantumvis vilior agna. Juven. Sat. viii. 14. If covetous, if vain (not wise) Than any lambe more base, more nice. Non enim paranda nobis solum, sed fruenda sapientia est: (Cic. Finib. i.p.). For we must not only purchase wisdom, but enjoy and employ the same. Dionysius scoffeth at those Gramarians, who ploddingly labor to know the miseries of Ulysses, and are ignorant of their own; mocketh those musitians that so attentively tune their instruments, and never accord their manners; derideth those orators that study to speak of justice, and never put it in execution. Except our mind be the better, unless our judgement be the sounder, I had rather my scholler had employed his time in playing at tennis; I am sure his body would be the nimbler. See but one of these our universitie men or bookish schollers return from schole, after he has there spent ten or twelve years under a pedants charge: who is so inapt for any matter? who so unfit for any companie? who so to seek if he come into the world? all the advantage you discover in him is that his Latine and Greeke have made him more sottish, more stupid, and more presumptuous, than before he went from home. Whereas he should return with a mind full-fraught, he returnes with a wind- puft conceit: instead of plum-feeding the same, he has only spunged it up with vanity. These masters, as Plato speaks of sophisters (their cosin Germanes) of all men, are those that promise to be most profitable unto men, and alone, amongst all, that not only amend not what is committed to their charge as does a carpenter or a mason, but empaire and destroy the same, and yet they must full dearely be paied. If the law which Protagoras proposed to his disciples, were followed, which was, that either they should a pay him according to his word, or sweare in the temple how much they esteemed the profit they had received by his discipline, and accordingly satisfy him for his paines, my pedagogues would be aground, especially if they would stand to the oath of my experience. My vulgar Perigordian-speech, does very pleasantly terme such self-conceited wizards, letter ferits, as if they would say letter-strucked men, to whom (as the common saying is) letters have given a blow with a mallet. Verily for the most part they seem to be distracted even from common sense. Note but the plaine husbandman, or the unwilie shoemaker, and you see them simply and naturally plod on their course, speaking only of what they know, and no further; whereas these letter-puft pedants, because they would faine raise themselves aloft, and with their litterall doctrine which floteth up and down the superficies of their braine, arm themselves beyond other men, they uncessantly intricate and entangle themselves: they utter loftie words, and speak golden sentences, but so that another man does place, fit, and applie them. They are acquainted with Galen, but know not the disease. They will stuffe your head with laws, when God wot they have not yet conceived the ground of the case. They knowe the theorike of all things, but you must seek who shall put it in practice. I have seen a friend of mine, in my own house, who by way of sport talking with one of these pedanticall gulls, counterfeited a kind of fustian tongue, and spake a certain gibrish, without rime or reason, sans head or foot, a hotch-potch of diverse things, but that he did often enterlace it with inke-pot termes, incident to their disputations, to ammuse the bookish sot for a whole day long with debating and contending; ever thinking he answered the objections made unto him; yet was he a man of letters and reputation, a graduate, and wore a goodly formall long gowne. Vos o patritius sanguis quos vivere par est Ooccipiti cæco, posticæ occurrite sannæ Pers. Sat. 1. 61. You noble blouds, who with a noddle blind Should live, meet with the mocke that’s made behind. Whosoever shall narrowly looke into this kind of people, which far and wide has spred itself, he shall find (as I have done) that for the most part they neither understand themselves nor others, and that their memory is many times sufficiently full fraught, but their judgment ever hollow and empty: except their natural inclination have of itself otherwise fashioned them. As I have seen Adrianus Turnebus who having never professed any thing but studie and letters, wherein he was, in mine opinion, the worthiest man that lived these thousand years, and who notwithstanding had no pedanticall thing about him but the wearing of his gowne, and some externall fashions that could not well be reduced, and incivilized to the courtiers cut; things of no consequence. And I naturally hate our people, that will more hardly endure a long robe uncuriously worne, than a crosse skittish mind: and that observe what leg, or reverence he makes, note his garbe or demeanor, view his boots or his hat, and marke what manner of man he is. For his inward parts, I deem him to have been one of the most unspotted and truly honest minds that ever was. I have sundry times of purpose urged him to speak of matters furthest from his study, wherein he was so clear-sighted, and could with so quick an apprehension conceive, and with so sound a judgment distjnguish them, that he seemed never to have professed or studied other facultie than war and matters of state. Such spirits, such natures may be termed worthy, goodly, and solid. ----- queis arte benigna Et meliore luto finxit præcordia Titan. Juven. Sat. xiv. 34. Whose bowels heavens-bright-Sunne composed Of better mold, art well disposed. That maintaine themselves against any bad institution. Now it sufficeth not that our institution marre us not, it must change us to the better. There are some of our parliaments and courts, who when they are to admit of any officers , do only examine them of their learning; others, that by presenting them the judgment of some law cases, endeavor to sound their understanding. Me thinks the latter keep the better style: And albeit these two parts are necessarie, and both ought to concur in one, yet truly should that of learning be less prized than judgement, this may well be without the other, and not the other without this. For as the Greeke verse says. Ως ουδεν η αθησις, ην η νους παρη. Gnom. Græc. χ. et φ. ult. Learning nought worth does lie, Be not discretion by. Whereto serveth learning, if understanding be not joined to it? Oh would to God, that for the good of our justice, the societies of lawyers were as well stored with judgement, discretion and conscience, as they are with learning and wit. Non vitæ, sed scholæ discimus: (SEN. Epist. cvi. f.) We learne not for our life, but for the schoole. It is not enough to join learning and knowledge to the mind, it should be incorporated into it: it must not be inckled, but dyed with it; and if it change not and better her estate (which is imperfect) it were much better to leave it. It is a dangerous sword, and which hindreth and offendeth her master, if it be in a weake hand, and which has not the skill to manage the same: Vt fuerit melius non didicisse: So as it were better that we had not learned. It is perhaps the cause that neither we nor divinitie require much learning in women; and that Francis Duke of Britannie, son to John the fifth, when be was spoken unto for a marriage betweene him and Isabel a daughter of Scotland; and some told him she was but meanly brought up and without any instruction of learning, answered, he loved her the better for it, and that a woman was wise enough if she could but make a difference betweene the shirt and dublet of her husbands. It is also no such wonder (as some say) that our auncesters did never make any great accompt of letters, and that even at this day (except it be by chaunce) they are not often found in our kings and princes chiefest councels and consultations: And if the end to grow rich by them which now adaies is altogether proposed unto us by the studie of law, of Phisicke, of Pedantisme, and of Divinitie, did not keep them in credit, without doubt you should see them as beggarly and needy, and as much vilified as ever they were. And what hurt I pray you since they neither teach us to think well nor-do well? Postquam docti prodierunt, boni desunt.(Sen. Epist. xcv.) Since men became learned, good men failed Each other science is prejudiciall unto him that has not the science of goodnesse. But may not the reason I whilom sought for, also proceed thence? That our studie in France, having as it were no other aime but profit, but those less whom nature has produced to more generous offices, than lucrative, giving themselves unto learning, or so briefly (before they have apprehended any liking of them, retired unto a profession that has no communitie with bookes) there are then none left, altogether to engage themselves to studie and Bookes, but the meaner kind of people, and such as are borne to base fortune, and who by learning and letters seek some meane to live and enrich themselves.The minds of which people being both by natural inclination, by example, and familiar institution, of the basest stampe do falsly reap the fruit of learning. For it is not in her power to give light unto the mind, that has none, nor to make a blind man to see. The mysterie of it is not to affoord him sight, but to direct it for him, to addresse his goings, alwaies provided he have feet of his own, and good, strait, and capable legs. Knowledge is an excellent drug, but no drug is sufficiently strong to preserve itself without alteration or corruption, according to the fault of the vessell that contained it. Some man has a clear sight, that is not right-sighted, and by consequence seeth what good is, and does not follow it; and seeketh knowledge, but makes no use of it. The chiefest ordinance of Plato in his Commonwealth is to give unto his Citizens their charge according to their nature. Nature can do all, and does all. The crookt backt, or deformed, are unfit for any exercise of the body, and crooked and mis-shapen minds unproper for exercises of the mind. The bastard and vulgar sort are unworthy of Philosophie. When we see a man ill shod, if he chance to be a Shoomaker, we say it is no wonder, for commonly none goes worse shod than they. Even so it seems that experience does often show us, a Physitian less healthy, a Divine less reformed, and most commonly a Wiseman less sufficient than another. Aristo Chius had heretofore reason to say that Philosophers did much hurt their auditors, forasmuch as the greatest number of minds are not apt to profit by such instructions which, if they take not a good, they will follow a bad course: ασωτους ex Aristippi, acerbos ex Zenonis Schola exire (Cic. Deor. iii.). They proceed licentious out of the School of Aristippus, but bitter out of the School of Zeno. In that excellent institution which Zenophon gives the Persians, we find, that as other nations teach their children Letters, so they taught theirs virtue. Plato said the eldest borne son, in their royall succession, was thus taught. "As soone as he was borne, he was delivered, not to women, but to such Eunuchs as by reason of their virtue were in chiefest authority about the King. Their speciall charge was first to shapen his limbs and body, goodly and healthy; and at seven years of age they instructed and inured him to sit on horsebacke, and to ride a hunting: when he came to the age of fourteene, they delivered him into the ha nds of foure men, that is to say, the wisest, the justest, the most temperate and the most valiant of all the nation. The first taught him religion; the second, to be ever upright and true; the third, to become Master of his own desires; and fourth, to fear nothing." It is a thing worthy great consideration, that in that excellent, and as I may terme it, matchlesse policy of Lycurgus, and in truth, by reason of her perfection, monstrous, yet notwithstanding, so careful for the education of children, as of her principal charge, and even in the Muses bosome and resting-place, there is so little mention made of learning: as if that generous youth disdaining all other yokes but of virtue, ought only to be furnished, in liew of tutors of learning, with masters of valor, of justice, of wisdom, and of temperance. An example which Plato has imitated in his Lawes. The manner of their discipline was, to propound questions unto them, teaching the judgement of men and of their actions: and if by way of reason or discourse they condemned or praised either this man or that deed, they must be told the truth and best: by which means at once they sharpened their wits, and learned the right. Astiages in Zenophon calleth Cyrus to an accompt of his last lesson. It is (says he) that a great lad in our Schools, having a little coat, gave it to one of his fellowes, that was of lesser stature than himself, and took his coat from him, which was too big for him: our Master having made me judge of that difference, I judged that things must be left in the state they were in, and that both seemed to be better fitted as they were; whereupon he showed me I had done ill; because I had only considered the comelinesse where I should chiefly have respected justice, which required that none should be forced in any thing which properly belonged to him, and said he was whipt for it, as we are in our countrie-townes, when we have forgotten the first preterperfect tense or Aoriste of greekzzz. My Regent might long enough make me a prolixe and cunning Oration in genere demonstrativo, in the oratorie kind of praise or dispraise, before ever he should persuade me his School is worth that. They have gone about to make the way shorter: and since Sciences (even when they are right taken) can teach us nothing but wisdom, honestie, integritie, and resolution; they have at first sight attempted to put their children to the proper of effects, and instruct them, not by hear-say, but by assay of action, lively modelling and framing them not only by precepts and words, but principally by examples and works, that it might not be a Science in their mind, but rather his complexion and habitude; not to purchase, but a natural inheritance. To this purpose, when Agesilaus was demanded what his opinion was, children should learne: he answered, What they should do being men. It is no marvell, if such an institution have produced so admirable effects. Some say, that in other Cities of Greece they went to seek for Rhetoricians, for Painters, and for Musicians; whereas in Lacedemon, they sought for Law-givers, for Magistrates, and Generals of armies: In Athens men learn’d to say well, but here, to do well: there to resolve a sophisticall argument, and to confound the imposture and amphibologie of words, captiously enterlaced together; here to shake off the allurements of voluptuousness, and with an undaunted courage to contemne the threats of fortune, and reject the menaces of death: those busied and laboured themselves about idle words, these after martiall things: there the tongue was ever in continuall exercise of speaking, here the mind is an incessant practice of well-doing. And therefore was it not Strange, if Antipater requiring fiftie of their children for hostages, they answered cleane contrary to that we would do, that they would rather deliver him twice so many men; so much did they value and esteeme the loss of their countries education. When Agesilaus inviteth Xenophon to send his children to Sparta, there to be brought up; it is not because they should learne Rhetorike or Logike, but, as himself says, to the end they may learne the worthiest and best science that may be, to wit the knowledge how to obey and the skill how to commmand. It is a sport to see Socrates, after his blunt manner, to mocke Hippias, who reporteth unto him what great summes of money he had gained, especially in certain little Cities and small townes of Sicily, by keeping schoole, and teaching letters, and that at Sparta he could not get a shilling. That they were but idiots and foolish people, who can neither measure nor esteeme nor make no accompt of Grammer, or of Rythmes and who only ammuse themselves to know the succession of Kings, the establishing and declination of estates, and such like trash of flim-flam tales. Which done, Socrates forcing him particularly to allow the excellencie of their form of public government, the happinesse and virtue of their private life, remits unto him to guesse the conclusion of the unprofitablenesse of his arts.. Examples teach us both in this martiall policy, and in all such like, that the studie of sciences donth more weaken and effeminate mens minds than corroborate and adapt them to war. The mightiest, indeed the best setled estate, that is now in the world, is that of the Turkes, a nation equally instructed to the esteem e of arms, and disesteeme of letters. I find Rome to have been most valiant when it was least learned. The most warlike nations of our days are the rudest and most ignorant. The Scithians, the Parthians and Tamburlane, serve to verifie my saying. When the Gothes over-ran and ravaged Greece; that which saved all their Libraries from the fire was, that one among them scattered this opinion, that such trash of bookes and papers must be untoucht and whole for their enemies, as the only meane and proper instrument to divert them from all militarie exercises, and ammuse them to idle, secure, and sedentarie occupations. When our King Charles the eight, in a manner without unsheathing his sword, saw himself absolute Lord of the whole Kingdome of Naples, and of a great part of Thuscanie, the Princes and Lords of his traine ascribed this sodaine and unhoped for victory, and facilitie of so noble and prodigious a conquest, only to this, that most of the Princes and nobility of Italie amused themselves rather to become ingenious and wise by learning, than vigorous and warriers by militarie exercises. Return to CHAPTER XXV: OF THE INSTITUTION AND EDUCATION OF CHILDREN; TO THE LADIE DIANA OF FOIX, COUNTESSE OF GURSON CHAPTER XXV: OF THE INSTITUTION AND EDUCATION OF CHILDREN; TO THE LADIE DIANA OF FOIX, COUNTESSE OF GURSON NEVER knew father, how crooked and deformed soever his son were, that would either altogether cast him off, or not acknowledge him for his own: and yet (unlease he be meerely besotted or blinded in his affection) it may not be said, but he plainly perceiveth his defects, and has a feeling of his imperfections. But so it is, he is his own. So it is in myself. I see better than any man else, that what I have set down is nought but the foolish imaginations of him who in his youth has tasted nothing but the paring, and seen but superficies of true learning: whereof he has retained but a general and shapelesse form: a smacke of every thing in general, but nothing to the purpose in particular: After the French manner. To be short, I know there is an art of Phisicke; a course of laws; foure parts of the Mathematikes; and I am not altogether ignorant what they tend unto. And perhaps I also know the scope and drift of Sciences in general to be for the service of our life. But to wade further, or that ever I tired my self with plodding upon Aristotle (the Monarch of our modern doctrine) or obstinately continued in search of any one science: I confesse I never did it. Nor is there any one art whereof I am able so much as to draw the first lineaments. And there is no scholler (be he of the lowest form) that may not repute himself wiser than I, who am not able to oppose him in his first lesson: and if I be forced to it, I am constrained very impertinently to draw in matter from some general discourse, whereby I examine, and give a guesse at his natural judgement: a lesson as much unknown to them as theirs is to me. I have not dealt or had commerce with any excellent book, except Plutarke or Seneca, from whom (as the Danaides) I draw my water, uncessantly filling, and as fast emptying: some thing whereof I fasten to this paper, but to my self nothing at all. And touching Bookes: Historie is my chief studie, Poesie my only delight, to which I am particularly affected: for as Cleanthes said, that as the voice being forciblie pent in the narrow gullet of a trumpet, at last issueth forth more strong and shriller , so me seems, that a sentence cunningly and closely couched in measure-keeping Posie, darts itself forth more furiously, and wounds me even to the quick. And concerning the natural faculties that are in me (whereof behold here an essay). I perceive them to faint under their own burden; my conceits, and my judgement march but uncertaine, and as it were groping, staggering, and stumbling at every rush: And when I have gone as far as I can, I have no whit pleased my self: for the further I saile the more land I descrie, and that so dimmed with fogges, and overcast with clouds, that my sight is so weakned, I cannot distinguish the same. And then undertaking to speak indifferently of all that presents itself unto my fantasie, and having nothing put my own natural means to employ therein, if it be my hap (as commonly it is) among good Authors, to light upon those very places which I have undertaken to treat off, as even now I did in Plutarke, reading his discourse of the power of imagination, wherein in regard of those wise men, I acknowledge my self so weake and so poore, so dull and grose-headed, as I am forced both to pittie and disdaine my self, yet am I pleased with this; that my opinions have often the grace to jump with theirs, and that I follow them a loofe-off, and thereby possesse at least, that which all other men have not; which is, that I know the utmost difference between them and my self: all which notwithstanding, I suffer my inventions to run abroad, as weake and faint as I have produced them, without bungling and botching the faults which this comparison has discovered to me in them. A man had need have a stronge backe, to undertake to march foot to foot with these kind of men. The indiscreet writers of our age, amidst their triviall compositions, intermingle and wrest in whole sentences taken from ancient Authors, supposing by such filching-theft to purchase honor and reputation to themselves, do cleane contrary. For, this infinite varietie and dissemblance of lustres, makes a face so wan, so ill-favored, and so uglie, in respect of theirs, that they lose much more than gain thereby. These were two contrary humors: The Philosopher Chrisippus was wont to foist-in amongst his bookes, not only whole sentences and other long-long discourses, but whole bookes of other Authors, as in one, he brought in Euripides his Medea. And Apollodorus was wont to say of him, that if one should draw from out his bookes what he had stolne from others, his paper would remaine blanke. Whereas Epicurus cleane contrary to him in three hundred volumes he left behind him, had not made use of one allegation. It was my fortune not long since to light upon such a place: I had languishingly traced after some French words, so naked and hollow, and so void either of sense or matter, that at last I found them to be nought but meere French words; and after a tedious and wearisome travell, I chanced to stumble upon an highe riche and even to the clouds-raised piece, the descent whereof had it been somewhat more pleasant or easy, or the ascent reaching a little further, it had been excusablee and to be borne with-all; but it was such a steepie down-fall, and by meere strength hewen out of the main rocke, that by reading of the first six words, me thought I was carried into another world: whereby I perceive the bottome whence I came to be so low and deep, as I durst never more adventure to go through i ; for, if I did stuffe any one of my discourses with those rich spoiles, it would manifestly cause the sottishnesse of others to appeare. To reprove my own faults in others, seems to me no more insufferable than to reprehend (as I do often) those of others in my self: They ought to be accused every where, and have all places of Sanctuarie taken from them; yet do I know how over boldly, at all times I adventure to equall my self unto my filchings, and so march hand in hand with them, not without a fond hardie hope, that I may perhaps be able to bleare the eyes of the Judges from discerning them. But it is as much for the benefit of my application, as for the good of my invention and force. And I do not furiously front, and body to body wrestle with those old champions: it is but by flights, advantages, and false offers I seek to come within them, and if I can, to give them a fall. I do not rashly take them about the necke, I do but touch them, nor do I go so far as by my bargains I would seem to do; could I but keep even with them, I should then be an honest man; for I seek not to venture on them, but where they are strongest. To do as I have seen some, that is, to shroud themselves under other arms, not daring so much as to show their fingers ends unarmed and to botch up all their works (as it is an easy matter in a common subject, namely for the wiser sort) with ancient inventions, here and there hudled up together. And in those who endeavoured to hide what they have filched from others, and make it their own, it is first a manifest note of injustice, then a plaine argument of cowardlinesse; who having nothing of any worth in themselves to make show of, will yet under the countenance of others sufficiencie go about to make a fair offer: Moreover (oh great foolishnesse) to seek by such cosening tricks to forestall the ignorant approbation of the common sort, nothing fearing to discover their ignorance to men of understanding (whose praise only is of value) who will soon trace out such borrowed ware. As for me, there is nothing I will do less. I never speak of others, but that I may the more speak of my self. This concerneth not those mingle-mangles of many kinds of stuffe, or as the Greeks call them Rapsodies, that for such are published, of which kind I have (since I came to years of discretion seen diverse most ingenious and wittie; amongst others, one under the name of Capilupus; besides many of the ancient stampe. These are wits of such excellence, as both here and elsewhere they will soone be perceived, as our late famous writer Lipsius, in his learned and laborious work of the Politikes: yet whatsoever come of it, for so much as they are but follies, my intent is not to smother them no more than a bald and hoarie picture of mine, where a Painter has drawne not a perfect visage, but my own. For, however, these are but my humors and opinions, and I deliver them but to show what my conceit is, and not what ought to be beleeved. Wherein I ayme at nothing but to display my self, who perhaps (if a new prentiship change me) shall be another to morrow. I have no authority to purchase beliefe, neither do I desire it; knowing well that I am not sufficiently taught to instruct others. Some having read my precedent Chapter, told me not long since in my own house, I should somewhat more have extended my self in the discourse concerning the institution of children. Now (Madam) if there were any sufficiencie in me touching that subject, I could not better employ the same than to bestow it as a present upon that little lad, which ere long threatneth to make a happie issue from out your honorable woombe: for (Madame) you are too generous to begin with other than a man child. And having had so great a part in the conduct of your successeful marriage, I may challenge some right and interest in the greatness and prosperitie of all that shall proceed from it: moreover, the ancient and rightful possession, which you from time to time have ever had, and still have over my service, urgeth me with more than ordinary respects, to wish all honor, wellfare and advantage to whatsoever may in any sort concerne you and Tours. And truly, my meaning is but to show that the greatest difficultie, and importing all humane knowledge, seems to be in this point, where the nurture and institution of young children is in question. For as in matters of husbandrie, the labor that must be used before sowing, setting; and planting, indeed in planting itself, is most certain and easy. But when that which was sowen, set and planted, commeth to take life; before it come to ripenesse, much adoe, and great varietie of proceeding belongeth to it. So in men, it is no great matter to get them, but being borne, what continuall cares, what diligent attendance, what doubts and feares, do daily wait to their parents and tutors, before they can be nurtured and brought to any good? The fore-show of their inclination while they are young is so uncertaine, their humors so variable, their promises so changing, their hopes so false, and their proceedings so doubtful, that it is very hard (indeed for the wisest) to ground any certain judgment, or assured success upon them. Behold Cymon, view Themistocles, and a thousand others, how they have differed, and fallen to better from themselves, and deceive the expectation of such as knew them. The young whelps both of Dogges and Beares at first sight show their natural dispositions but men headIong embracing this custom or fashion, following that humor or opinion, admitting this or that passion, allowing of that or this law, are easily changed, and soone disguised; yet it is hard to force the natural propension or readinesse of the mind, whereby it followeth, that for want of heedie fore- sight in those that could not guide their course well, they often employ much time in vain, to addresse young children in those matters whereunto they are not naturally addicted. All which difficulties notwithstanding in mine opinion is, to bring them up in the best and profltablest studies, and that a man should slightly pass over those fond presages, and deceiving prognostikes, which we over precisely gather in their infancie. And (without offence be it said) me thinks that Plato in his Commonwealth allowed them too-too much authority. Madame, Learning joined with true knowledge is an especiall and gracefull ornament, and an implement of wonderful use and consequence, namely, in persons raised to that degree of fortune wherein you are. And in good truth, learning has not her own true form, nor can she make show of her beauteous lineaments, if she fall into the hands of base and vile persons. {For, as famous Torquato Tasso says: ’Philosophie being a rich and noble Queene, and knowing her own worth, graciously smileth upon and lovingly embraceth Princes and noble men, if they become suiters to her, admitting them as the minions, and gently affoording them all the favors she can; whereas upon the contrary, if she be wooed, and sued unto by clownes, mechanicall fellowes, and such base kind of people, she holds herself disparaged and disgraced, as holding no proportion with them. And therefore see we by experience, that if a true Gentleman or nobleman follow her with any attention, and wooed her with importunitie, he shall learne and know more of her, and prove a better scholler in one yeare, than an ungentle or base fellow shall in seven, though he pursue her never so attentively.’] She is much more readie and fierce to lend her furtherance and direction in the conduct of a war, to attempt honorable actions, to command a people, to treat a peace with a prince of forraine nation, than she is to form an argument in Logick, to devise a Syllogisme, to canvass a case at the barre or to prescribe a receit of pills. So (noble Lady) forasmuch as I cannot persuade myself, that you will either forget or neglect this point, concerning the institution of yours, especially having tasted the sweetness thereof, and being descended of so noble and learned a race. For we yet possesse the learned compositions of the ancient and noble Earles of Foix, from out whose heroicke loynes your husband and you take your ofspring. And Francis Lord of Candale, your worthie uncle, does daily bring forth such fruits thereof, as the knowledge of the matchlesse quality of your house shall hereafter extend itself to, many ages will therefore make you acquainted with one conceit of mine, which contrary to the common use I hold, and that is all I am able to affoord you concerning that matter. The charge of the Tutor, which you shall appoint your son, in the choice of whom consisteth the whole substance of his education and bringing up; on which are many branches depending, which (forasmuch as I can adde nothing of any moment to it) I will not touch at all. And for that point, wherein I presume to advise him, he may so far forth give credit unto it, as he shall see just cause. To a gentleman borne of noble parentage, and heir of a house that aymeth at true learning, and in it would be disciplined, not so much for gain or commoditie to himself (because so abject an end is far unworthie the grace and favor of the Muses, and besides, has a regard or dependencie of others) nor for externall show and ornament, but to adorn and enrich his inward mind, desiring rather to shape and institute an able and sufficient man, than a bare learned man; my desire is therefore, that the parents or overseers of such a gentleman he very circumspect, and careful in chusing his director, whom I would rather commend for having a well composed and temperate braine, than a full stuft head, yet both will do well. And I would rather prefer wisdom, judgement, civill customs, and modest behaviour, than bare and meerly literall learning; and that in his charge he hold a new course. Some never cease brawling in their schollers ears (as if they were still pouring in a tonell) to follow their book, yet is their charge nothing else but to repeat what has been told them before. I would have a tutor to correct this part, and that at first entrance, according to the capacitie of the wit he has in hand, he should begin to make show of it, making him to have a smacke of all things, and how to choose and distinguish them, without helpe of others, sometimes opening him the way, other times leaving him to open it by himself. I would not have him to invent and speak alone, but suffer his disciple to speak when his turn commeth. Socrates, and after him Arcesilaus, made their schollers to speak first and then would speak themselves. Obest plerumq ue iis qui discere vol unt, auctoritas eorum qui docent (Cic. De Nat. i.). ’Most commonly the authority of them that teach, hinders them that would learne.’ It is therefore meet that he make him first trot-on before him, whereby he may the better judge of his pace, and so guesse how long he will hold out, that accordingly he may fit his strength: for want of which proportion we often marre all. And to know how to make a good choice, and how far forth one may proceed (still keeping a due measure), is one of the hardest labours I know. It is a signe of a noble, and effect of an undanted spirit, to know how to second, and how far forth he shall condescend to his childish proceedings, and how to guide them. As for myself, I can better and with more strength walke up than down a hill. Those which, according to our common fashion, undertake with one self- same lesson, and like manner of education, to direct many spirits of diverse formes and different humors, it is no marvell if among a mulutude of children, they scarce meet with two or three that reap any good fruit by their discipline, or that come to any perfection. I would not only have him to demand an accompt of the words contained in his lesson, but of the sense and substance thereof, and judge of the profit he has made of it, not by the testimony of his memory, but by the witness of his life. That what he lately learned, he cause him to set forth and portray the same into sundrie shapes, and then to accommodate it to as many different and severall subjects, whereby he shal perceive, whether he have yet apprehended the same, and therein enfeoffed himself, at due times taking his instruction from the institution given by Plato. It is a signe of cruditie and indigestion for a man to yield up his meat, even as he swallowed the same: the stomacke has not wrought his full operation, unless it have changed form, and altered fashion of that which was given him to boyle and concoct. [We see men gape after no reputation but learning, and when they say, such a one is a learned man, they think they have said enough;] Our mind does move at others pleasure, and tyed and forced to serve the fantasies of others, being brought under by authority, and forced to stoop to the lure of their bare lesson; we have been so subjected to harpe upon one string, that we have no way left us to descant upon voluntarie; our vigor and liberty is cleane extinct. Nunquam tutelæ suæ fiunt: ’They never come to their own tuition.’ It was my hap to be familiarlie acquainted with an honest man at Pisa, but such an Aristotelian, as he held this infallible position; that a comformitie to Aristotles doctrine was the true touchstone and squire of all solid imaginations and perfect veritie; for, whatsoever had no coherencie with it, was but foolish Chimeræs and idle humors; inasmuch as he had known all, seen all, and said all. This proposition of his being somewhat over amply and injuriously interpreted by some, made him a long time after to be troubled in the inquisition of Rome. I would have him make his scholler narrowly to sift all things with discretion, and harbour nothing in his head by mere authority or upon trust. Aristotles principles shall he no more axiomes unto him, than the Stoics or Epicurians. Let this diversitie of judgements he proposed unto him, if he can, he shall be able to distinginsh the truth from falsehood, if not, he will remaine doubtful. Che non men che saper dubbiar m’aggrada. DANTE, Inferno, cant. xii. 48. No less it pleaseth me, To doubt, than wise to be. For if by his own discourse he embrace the opinions of Xenophon or of Plato, they shall be no longer theirs, but his. He that meerely followeth another, traceth nothing, and seeketh nothing: Non sumus sub Rege, sibi quisque se vindicet (SEN. Epist. xxxiii). ’We are not under a Kings command, every one may challenge himself, for let him at least know that he knows.’ It is requisite he endeavor as much to feed himself with their conceits as labor to learne their precepts; which, so he know how to applie, let him hardily forget, where or whence he had them. Truth and reason are common to all, and are no more proper unto him that spake them heretofore, than unto him that shall speak them hereafter. And it is no more according to Platoes opinion than to mine, since both he and I understand and see likewise. The Bees do here and there sticke this and cull that flower, but afterward they produce the hony, which is peculiarly their own, then is it no more Thyme or Majoram. So of peeces borrowed of others, he may lawfully alter, transforme, and confound them, to shape out of them a perfect peece of work, altogether his own; alwaies provided his judgement, his travell, studie, and institution tend to nothing, but to frame the same perfect. Let him hardily conceal where or whence he has had any helpe, and make no show of anything, but of that which he has made himself. Pirates, pilchers, and borrowers, make a show of their purchases and buildings, but not of that which they have taken from others: you see not the secret fees or bribes Lawyers take of their Clients, but you shall manifestly discover the alliances they make, the honors they get for their children, and the goodly houses they build. No man makes open show of his receits, but every one of his gettings. The good that comes of studie (or at least should come) is to prove better, wiser and honester. It is the understanding power (said Epicharmus) that seeth and heareth, it is it that profiteth all and disposeth all, that moveth, swayeth, and ruleth all: all things else are but blind, senselesse, and without spirit. And truly in barring him of liberty to do any thing of himself, we make him thereby more servile and more coward. Who would ever enquire of his scholler what he thinketh of Rhetorike, of Grammar of this or of that sentence of Cicero? Which things thoroughly fethered (as if they were oracles) are let flie into our memory; in which both letters and syllables are substantiall parts of the subject. To know by roat is no perfect knowledge, but to keep what one has committed to his memories charge, is commendable: what a man directly knows, that will he dispose-of, without turning still to his book or looking to his pattern. A meere bookish sufficiencie is unpleasant. All I expect of it is an imbellishing of my actions, and not a foundation of them, according to Platoes mind, who says, constancy, faith, and sinceritie are true Philosophie; as for other Sciences, and tending elsewhere, they are but garish paintings. I would faine have Paluel or Pompey, these two excellent dauncers of our time, with all their nimblenesse, teach any man to do their loftie tricks and high capers, only with seeing them done, and without stirring out of his place, as some Pedanticall fellowes would instruct our minds without moving or putting it in practice. And glad would I be to find one that would teach us how to manage a horse, to tosse a pike, to shoot-off a peece, to play upon the lute, or to warble with the voice, without any exercise, as these kind of men would teach us to judge, and how to speak well, without any exercise of speaking or judging. In which kind of life, or as I may terme it, Prentiship, what action or object soever presents it-self into our eyes, may serve us in stead of a sufficient book. A prettie pranke of a boy, a knavish tricke of a page, a foolish part of a lackey, an idle tale or any discourse else, spoken either in jest or earnest, at the table or in companie, are even as new subjects for us to work upon: for furtherance whereof commerce or common societie among men, visiting of forraine countries, and observing of strange fashions, are very necessary, not only to be able (after the manner of our yong gallants of France) to report how many the Church of Santa Rotonda is in length or breadth, or what rich garments the curtezan Signora Livia weareth and the worth of her hosen: or as some do, nicely to dispute how much longer or broader the face of Nero is, which they have seen in some old ruines of Italie, than that which is made for him in other old monuments else-where. But they should principally observe , and be able to make certain relation of the humors and fashions of those countries they have seen, that they may the better know how to correct and prepare their wits by those of others. I would therefore have him begin even from his infancie to travell abroad; and first, that at one shoot he may hit two markes, he should see neighbour-countries, namely where languages are most different from ours; for, unless a mans tongue be fashioned unto them in his youth, he shall never attaine to the true pronunciation of them if he once grow in years. Moreover, we see it received as a common opinion of the wiser sort, that it agrees not with reason, that a child he alwaies nuzzled, cockered, dandled, and brought up in his pairents lap or sight; forasmuch as their natural kindness, or (as I may call it) tender fondnesse, causeth often, even the wisest to prove so idle, so overnice, and so base- minded. For parents are not capable, neither can they find in their hearts to see them checkt, corrected, or chastised, nor endure to see them brought up so meanly, and so far from daintinesse, and many times so dangerously, as they must needs be. And it would grieve them to see their children come home from those exercises, that a Gentleman must necessarily acquaint himself with, sometimes all wet and bemyred, other times sweatie and full of dust, and to drinke being either extreme hot or exceeding cold; and it would trouble them to see him ride a rough, untamed horse, or with his weapon furiously incounter a skilful Fencer, or to handle or shoot-off a musket; against which there is no remedy, if he will make him prove a sufficient, compleat, or honest man: he must not he spared in his youth; and it will come to pass, that he shall many times have occasion and be forced to shocke the rules of Physicke. Vitamque sub dio et trepidis agat In rebus. -- HOR. 1. i. Od. ii. 4. Leade he his life in open aire. And in affairs full of despaire. It is not sufficient to make his mind strong, his muskles must also be strengthened: the mind is overborne if it be not seconded: and it is too much for her alone to discharge two offices. I have a feeling how mine panteth, being joined to so tender and sensible a body, and that lieth so heavy upon it. And in my lecture, I often perceive how my Authors in their writings sometimes commend examples for magnanimity and force, that rather proceed from a thicke skin and hardnes of the bones. I have known men, women and children borne of so hard a constitution, that a blow with a cudgell would less hurt them, than a filip would doo me, and so dull and blockish, that they will neither stir tongue nor eyebrowes, beat them never so much. When wrestlers go about to counterfeit the Philosophers patience, they rather show the vigor of their sinnewes than of their heart. For the custom to bear travell, is to tolerate grief: Labor callum obducit dolori (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ii.). ’Labour worketh a hardnesse upon sorrow.’ He must be enured to suffer the pain and hardnesse of exercises, that so he may be enduced to endure the pain of the colicke, of cauterie, of fals, of sprains, and other diseases incident to mans body: indeed, if need require, patiently to bear imprisonment and other tortures, by which sufferance he shall come to be had in more esteeme and accompt: for according to time and place, the good as well as the bad man may perhaps fall into them; we have seen it by experience. Who-soever striveth against the laws, threats good men with mischief and extortion. Moreover, the authority of the Tutor (who should be sovereign over him) is by the cockering and presence of the parents, hindred and interrupted: besides the awe and respect which the houshold bears him, and the knowledge of the meane, possibilities, and greatness of his house, are in my judgement no small lets in a young Gentleman. In this schoole of commerce, and societie among men, I have often noted this vice, that in lieu of taking acquaintance of others, we only endeavor to make ourselves known to them: and we are more ready to utter such merchandize as we have, than to ingrosse and purchase new commodities. Silence and modesty are qualities very convenient to civil conversation. It is also necessary that a young man be rather taught to be discreetly- sparing and closehanded, than prodigally-wastfull and lavish in his expences, and moderate in husbanding his wealth when he shall come to possesse it. And not to take pepper in the nose for every foolish tale that shall be spoken in his presence, because it is an uncivil importunity to contradict whatsoever is not agreeing to our humor: let him be pleased to correct himself. And let him not seem to blame that in others which he refuseth to do himself, nor go about to withstand common fashions. Licet sapere sine pompa, sine invidia (Sen. Epist. ciii. f.). ’A man may be wise without ostentation, without envie.’ Let him avoid those imperious images of the world, those uncivil behaviours and childish ambition wherewith, God wot, too-too many are possest: that is, to make a fair show of that which is not in him: endeavoring to be reputed other than indeed he is; and as if reprehension and new devices were hard to come by, he could by that meane acquire into himself the name of some peculiar virtue. As it pertaineth but to great Poets to use the liberty of arts; so is it tolerable but in noble minds and great spirits to have a preheminence above ordinary fashions. Si quid Socrates et Aristippus contra morem et consuetudinem fecerunt, idem sibi ne abitretur licere; Magis enim illi et divinis honis hanc licentiam assequebantur (Cic. Off. i.). ’If Socrates and Aristuppus have done ought against customs or good manner, let not a man think he may do the same: for they obtained this license by their great and excellent good parts:’ He shall be taught not to enter rashly into discourse or contesting, but when he shall encounter with a Champion worthie his strength; And then would I not have him employ all the tricks that may fit his turn, but only such as may stand him in most stead. That he be taught to be curious in making choice of his reasons, loving pertinency, and by consequence brevity. That above all, he be instructed to yield, indeed to quit his weapons unto truth, as soone as he shall discern the same, whether it proceed from his adversarie, or upon better advice from himself; for he shall not be preferred to any place of eminencie above others, for repeating of a prescript part; and he is not engaged to defend any cause, further than he may approove it; nor shall he be of that trade where the liberty for a man to repent and re-advise himself is sold for readie money. Neque, ut omnia, que præscripta et imperata sint, defendat, necessitate ulla cogitur (Cic. Acad. Qu. iv.). ’Nor is he inforced by any necessitie to defend and make good all that is prescribed and commanded him.’ If his tutor agree with my humor, he shall frame his affection to be most loyall and true subject to his Prince, and a most affectionate and couragious Gentleman in al that may concerne the honor of his Soveraigne or the good of his countrie, and endeavor to suppresse in him all manner of affection to undertake any action otherwise than for a public good and dutie. Besides many inconveniences, which greatly prejudice our liberty by reason of these particular bonds, the judgment of a man that is waged and bought, either it is less free and honest, or else it is blemisht with oversight and ingratitude. A meere and precise Courtier can neither have law nor will to speak or think otherwise than favourable of his Master, who among so many thousands of his subjects has made choice of him alone, to institute and bring him up with his own hand. These favors, with the commodities that follow minion Courtiers, corrupt (not without some colour of reason) his liberty, and dazle his judgement. It is therefore commonly seen that the Courtiers-language differs from other mens, in the same state, and to be of no great credit in such matters. Let therefore his conscience and virtue shine in his speech, and reason be his chi efe direction. Let him be taught to confesse such faults as he shall discover in his own discourses, albeit none other perceive them but himself; for it is an evident show of judgement, and effect of sinceritie, which are the chiefest qualities he aymeth at. That wilfully to strive, and obstinately to contest in words, are common qualities, most apparent in basest mindes: That to readvise and correct himself, and when one is most earnest, to leave an ill opinion, are rare, noble, and Philosophicall conditions. Being in companies he shall be put in mind, to cast his eyes round about, and every where: For I note, that the chief places are usually seezed upon by the most unworthie and less capable; and that height of fortune is seldom ioyned with sufficiencie. I have seen that whilst they at the upper end of a board were busie entertaining themselves with talking of the beautie of the hangings about a chamber, or of the taste of some good cup of wine, many good discourses at the lower end have utterly been lost. He shall weigh the carriage of every man in his calling, a Heardsman, a Mason, a Stranger, or a Traveller; all must be employed; every one according to his worth; for all helps to make up a houshold; indeed, the folly and the simplicitie of others shall be as instructions to him. By controlling the graces and manners of others, he shall acquire unto himself envie of the good and contempt of the bad. Let him hardly be possest with an honest curiosity to search out the nature and causes of all things: let him survey whatsoever is rare and singular about him; a building, a fountain, a man, a place where any battle has been fought, or the passages of Cæsar or Charlemaine. Quæ tellus sit lenta gelu, quæ putris ab æstu, Ventus in Italiam quis bene vela ferat. -- Prop. iv. El. iii. 39. What land is parcht with heat, what clog’d with frost. What wind drives kindly to the Italian coast. He shall endeavor to be familiarly acquainted with the customs, with the means, with the state, with the dependances and alliances of all Princes; they are things soone and pleasant to be learned, and most profliable to be known. In this acquaintance of men, my intending is, that he chiefely comprehend them, that live but by the memory of bookes. He shall, by the help of Histories, informe himself of the worthiest minds that were in the best ages. It is a frivolous studie, if a man list, but of unvaluable worth to such as can make use of it, and as Plato says, the only studie the Lacedemonians reserved for themselves. What profit shall he not reap, touching this point, reading the lives of our Plutarke? Alwayes conditioned, the master bethinke himself whereto his charge tendeth, and that he imprint not so much in his schollers mind the date of the ruine of Carthage, as the manners of Hanniball and Scipio, nor so much where Marcellus died, as because he was unworthy of his devoire he died there: that he teach him not somuch to know Histories as to judge of them. It is amongst things that best agree with my humor, the subject to which our spirits do most diversly applie themselves. I have read in Titus Livius a number of things, which perhaps others never read, in whom Plutarke perhaps read a hundred more than ever I could read, which perhaps the author himself did never intend to set down. To some kind of men it is a meere gramaticall studie but to others a perfect anatomie of Philosophy; by means whereof the secretest part of our nature is searched into. There are in Plutarke many ample discourses most worthy to be known: for in my judgement, he is the chief work-master of such works, whereof there are a thousand, whereat he has but slightly glanced; for with his finger he does but point us out a way to walke in, if we list; and is sometimes pleased to give but a touch at the quickest and main point of a discourse, from whence they are by diligent studie to be drawne, and so brought into open market. As that saying of his, That the inhabitants of AsiaNon, gave perhaps both subject and occasion to my friend Boetie to compose his book of voluntarie servitude. If it were no more but to see Plutarke wrest a slight action to mans life, or a word that seems to bear no such sence, it will serve for a whole discourse. It is pittie men of understanding should so much love brevitie; without doubt their reputation is thereby better, but we the worse. Plutarke had rather we should commend him for his judgement than for his knowledge, he loves better to leave a kind of longing-desire in us of him, than a satietie. He knew very well that even in good things too much may be said: and that Alexandridas did justly reprove him who spake very good sentences to the Ephores, but they were over tedious. Oh stranger, quoth he, you speakest what you oughtest, otherwise then you should. Those that have leane and thin bodies stuffe them up with bumbasting. And such as have but poore matter, will puff it up with loftie words. There is a marvelous cleerenesse, or as I may terme it an enlightning of mans judgement drawne from the commerce of men, and by frequenting abroad in the world; we are all so contrived and compast in ourselves, that our sight is made shorter by the length of our nose. When Socrates was demaunded whence he was, he answered, not of Athens, but of the world; for he, who had his imagination more full and farther stretching, embraced all the world for his native City, and extended his acquaintance, his societie, and affections to all man-kind: and not as we do, that looke no further than our feet. If the frost chance to nip the vines about my village, my Priest does presently argue that the wrath of God hangs over our head, and threatneth all mankind: and judgeth that the Pippe is alreadie falne upon the Canibals. In viewing these intestine and civill broiles of ours, who does not exclaime, that this worlds vast frame is near unto a dissolution, and that the day of judgement is readie to fall on us? never remembering that many worse revolutions have been seen, and that while we are plunged in grief, and overwhelmed in sorrow, a thousand other parts of the world besides are blessed with happinesse, and wallow in pleasures, and never think on us? whereas, when I behold our lives, our license, and impunitie, I wonder to see them so mild and easy. He on whose head it haileth, thinks all the Hemispheare besides to be in a storme and tempest. And as that dull-pated Savoyard said, that if the seelie King of France could cunningly have managed his fortune, he might very well have made himself chief Steward of his Lords household, whose imagination conceived no other greatness than his Masters; we are all insensible of this kind of error: an error of great consequence and prejudice. But whosoever shall present into his inward eyes, as it were in a Table, the Idea of the great image of our universall mother Nature, attired in her richest robes, sitting in the throne of her Majestie, and in her visage shall read so general and so constant a varietie; he that therein shall view himself, not himself alone, but a whole Kingdome, to be in respect of a great circle but the smallest point that can be imagined, he only can value things according to their essentiall greatness and proportion. This great universe (which some multiplie as Species under one Genus) is the true looking-glasse wherein we must looke, if we will know whether we be of a good stamp or in the right byase. To conclude, I would have this worlds-frame to be my Schollers choise-book: So many strange humors, sundrie sects, varying judgements, diverse opinions, different laws, and fantastic customs teaches us to judge rightly of ours, and instruct our judgement to acknowledge his imperfections and natural weaknesse, which is no easy an apprentiship: So many innovations of estates, so many fals of Princes, and changes of public fortune, may and ought to teach us, not to make so great accompt of ours: So many names, so many victories, and so many conquests buried in darke oblivion, makes the hope to perpetuate our names but ridiculous, by the surprising of ten Argo-lettiers, or of a small cottage, which is known but by his fall. The pride and fiercenesse of so many strange and gorgeous shewes: the pride-puft majestie of so many courts, and of their greatness, ought to confirme and assure our sight, undauntedly to bear the affronts and thunder-claps of ours, without feeling our eyes: So many thousande of men, low-laide in their graves afore us, may encourage us not to fear, or be dismaied to go meet so good companie in the other world; and so of all things else. Our life (said Pithagoras) draws neare unto the great and populous assemblies of the Olympike games wherein some, to get the glory and to win the goale of the games, exercise their bodies with all industrie; others, for greedinesse of gain, bring thither marchandise to sell: others there are (and those be not the worst) that seek after no other good, but to marke how why, and to what end, all things are done: and to be spectators or observers of other mens lives and actions, that so they may the better judge and direct their own. Unto examples may all the most profitable Discourses of Philosophie be sorted, which ought to be the touch-stone of human actions, and a rule to square them by, to whom may be said, served but one alone, because they could not pronounce one only syllable, which is -----quid fas optare, asper Vtile nummus habet, patriæ charisque propinquis Quantum elargiri deceat, quem te Deus esse Jussist, et humana qua parte locatus es in re, Quid sum us, aut quidnam victuri gignimur. -- Pers. Sat. iii. 69, 67. What you mayest wish, what profit may come clear, From new-stampt coyne, to friends and countrie dear What you ought’st give: whom God would have you be, And in what part mongst men he placed you. What we are, and why, To live heer we were bore. What it is to know, and not to know (which ought to be the scope of studie), what valor, what temperance, and what justice is: what difference there is betweene ambition and avarice, bondage and freedome, subjection and liberty, by which markes a man may distinguish true and perfect contentment, and how far-forth one ought to fear or apprehend death, grief, or shame. Et quo quemque modo fugiatque fertaque laborem. -- Virg. Æn. viii.853. Now ev’ry labor he may plie. And bear, or ev’ry labor flie. What wards or springs move us, and the causes of so many motions in us: For me seems, that the first discourses wherewith his conceit should be sprinkled, ought to be those that rule his manners and direct his sense; which will both teach him to know himself, and how to live and how to die well. Among the liberall Sciences, let us begin with that which makes us free; Indeed, they may all, in some sort stead us, as an instruction to our life, and use of it, as all other things else serve the same to some purpose or other. But let us make especiall choice of that which may directly and pertinently serve the same. If we could restraine and adapt the appurtenances of our life to their right byase, and natural limits, we should find the best part of the Sciences that now are in use, cleane out of fashion with us: indeed, and in those that are most in use, there are certain by-ways and deep-flows most profitable, which we should do well to leave, and to the institution of Socrates, limit the course of our studies in those where profit is wanting. ---- sapere aude, Incipe: vivendi qui recte prorogat horam Rusticus expectat dum defluayt amnis at ille Labitur, et labetur in omne volubis ævum. -- Hor. i. Epist. ii. 40. Be bold to be wise: to begin, be strong He that to live well does the time prolong, Clowne-like expects, till down the streame be run, That runs, and will run, till the world be done. It is mere simplicitie to teach our children, Quid moveant Pisces, animosaque siqna Leonis, Lotus et Hesperia quid Capricornus aqua. -- Prop. iv. El. i. 85. What Pisces move, or hot breath’d Leos beames. Or Capricornus bath’d in western streames. The knowledge of the starres, and the motion of the eighth spheare, before their own; Τι Πλειαδεσσι καοι τι δ’ ηστρασι Βοωτεω What longs it to the seaven stars, and me, Or those about Bootes be. Anaximenes writing to Pythagoras, says, ’With what sense can I amuse my self in the secrets of the Starres, having continually death or bondage before mine eyes!? For at that time the Kings of Persia were making preparations to war against his Countrie. All men ought to say so. Being beaten with ambition, with avarice, with rashnesse, and with superstition, and having, such other enemies unto life within him. Wherefore shall I study and take care about the mobility and variation of the world? When he is once taught what is fit to make him better and wiser, he shall be entertained with Logicke, natural Philosophy. Geometry, and Rhetoricke, then having setled his judgement, looke what science he does most addict him self unto, he shall in short time attaine to the perfection of it. His lecture shall be somtimes by way of talk and somtimes by book: his tutor may now and then supply him with the same Author, as an end and motive of his institution: sometimes giving him the pith and substance of it ready chewed. And if of himself he be not so throughly acquainted with bookes, that he may readily find so many notable discourses as are in them to effect his purpose, it shall not be amisse that some learned man be appointed to keep him company, who at any time of need may furnish him with such munit ion as he shall stand in need of; that he may afterward distribute and dispense them to his best use. And that this kind of lesson be more easy and natural than that of Gaza, who will make question? Those are but harsh, thornie, and unpleasant precepts; vain, idle and immaterial words, on which small hold may be taken; wherein is nothing to quicken the mind. In this the spirit findeth substance to hide and feed upon. A fruit without all comparison much better, and that will soone be ripe. It is a thing worthy consideration, to see what state things are brought unto in this our age; and how Philosophie, even to the wisest, and men of best understanding, is but an idle, vain and fantastic name, of small use and less worth, both in opinion and effect. I think these Sophistries are the cause of it, which have forestalled the ways to come unto it: They do very ill that go about to make it seem as it were inaccessible for children to come unto, setting it foorth with a wrimpled, gastlie, and frowning visage; who has masked her with so counterfet, pale, and hideous a countenance? There is nothing more beauteous, nothing more delightfull, nothing more gainesome; and as I may say, nothing more fondly wanton: for she presenteth nothing to our eyes, and preacheth nothing to our ears. but sport and pastime. A sad and lowring-looke plainly declareth that that is not her haunt. Demetrius the Gramarian, finding a companie of Philosophers sitting close together in the Temple of Delphos, said unto them, ’Either I am deceived, or by your plausible and pleasant looks, you are not in any serious and earnest discourse amongst yourselves;’ to whom one of them, named Heracleon the Megarian, answered, ’That belongeth to them, who busie themselves in seeking whether the future tense of the verbe βαλλω has a double k, or that labor to find the derivation of the comparatives, χειρων βελτιων, and of the superlatives χειριστον βελτιστον, it is that they must chafe in intertaining themselves with their science: as for discourses of Philosophie they are wont to glad, rejoice, and not to vex and molest those that use them. Deprendas animi tormenta latentis in agro Corpore, deprendas et gaudia; sumit utrumque Inde habitum facies. ----- 1 JUVEN. Sat. ix. 18. You may perceive the torments of the mind. Hid in sicke body, you the joyes may find; The face such habit takes in either kind. That mind which harboureth Philosophie, ought by reason of her sound health, make that body also sound and healthie: it ought to make her contentment to through-shine in all exteriour parts: it ought to shapen and modell all outward demeanours to the modell of it: and by consequence arm him that does possesse it, with a gracious stoutness and lively audacite, with an active and pleasing gesture, and with a setled and cheereful countenance. The most evident token and apparant signe of true wisdom is a constant and unconstrained rejoycing, whose estate is like unto all things above the Moone, that is ever clear, alwaies bright. It is Baroco and Baralipton, that makes their followers prove so base and idle, and not Philosophie; they know her not but by hear-say; what? Is it not she that cleereth all stormes of the mind? And teacheth misery, famine and sicknesse to laugh? Not by reason of some imaginarie Epicicles, but by natural and palpable reasons. Shee aymeth at nothing but virtue; it is virtue she seekes after; which as the schoole says, is not pitcht on the top of an high, steepie, or inaccessible; hill; for they that have come unto her, affirme that cleane-contrary she keeps her stand, and holds her mansion in a fair, flourishing, and pleasant plaine, whence as from an high watch tower, she survaieth all things, to be subject unto her, to whom any man may with great facilitie come, if he but know the way or entrance to her palace: for, the pathes that lead unto her are certain fresh and shadie greene allies, sweet and flowrie waies, whose ascent is even, easy, and nothing wearisome, like unto that of heavens vaults. Forasmuch as they have not frequented this virtue, who gloriously, as in a throne of Majestie, sits sovereign, goodly, triumphant, lovely, equally delicious, and couragious, protesting herself to be a professed and irreconcileable enemy to all sharpnesse, austerite, fear, and compulsion; having nature for her guide, fortune and voluptuousness for her companions; they according to their weaknesse have imaginarily feigned her, to have a foolish, sad, grim, quarelous, spitefull, threatning, and disdainfull visage, with an horride and unpleasant looke; and have placed her upon a craggie, sharpe, and unfrequented rocke, amidst desert climes and uncouth crags, as a scar-crow, or bug-bear, to affright the common people with. Now the tutour, which ought to know that he should rather seek to fill the mind and store the will of his disciple, as much, or rather more, with love and affection, than with awe, and reverence unto virtue, may show and tell him, that Poets follow common humors, making him plainly to perceive and as it were palpably to feel, that the Gods have rather placed labor and sweat at the entrances which lead to Venus chambers, than at the doores that direct to Pallas cabinets. And when he shall perceive his scholler to have a sensible feeling of himself presenting Bradamant or Angelica before him, as a Mistresse to enjoy, embelished with a natural, active, generous, and unspotted beautie not uglie or Giant-like, but blithe, livelie, in respect of a wanton, soft, affected, and artificiall-flaring beautie; the one attired like unto a young man, coyfed with a bright-shining helmet, the other disguised and drest about the head like unto an impudent harlot, with embroyderies, frizelings, and carcanets of pearles: he will ho doubt deem his own love to be a man and no woman, if in his choice he differ from that effeminate shepheard of Phrygia. In this new kind of lesson be shall declare unto him, that the prize, the glory, and height of true virtue, consisted in the facilitie, profit, and pleasure of his exercises: so far from difficultie and incumbrances, that children as well as men, the simple as soone as the wise, may come unto her Discretion and temperance, not force or waywardnesse are the instruments to bring him unto her. Socrates (vertues chief favorite) that he might the better walke in the pleasant, natural, and open path of her progresses, does voluntarily and in good earnest, quit all compulsion. Shee is the nurse and foster-mother of all humane pleasures, who in making them just and upright, she also makes them sure and sincere. By moderating them, she keepeth them in ure and breath. In limiting and cutting them off, whom she refuseth; she whets us on toward those she leaveth unto us; and plenteously leaves us them, which Nature pleaseth, and like a kind mother gives us over unto satietie, if not unto wearisomnesse, unless we will perhaps say that the rule and bridle, which stayeth the drunkard before drunkennesse, the glutton before surfetting, and the letcher before the losing of his hair, be the enemies of our pleasures. If common fortune faile her, it cleerely scaped her; or she cares not for her, or she frames another unto herself, altogether her own, not so fleeting nor so rowling. She knows the way how to be rich, mightie and wise, and how to lie in sweet-perfumed beds. She loves life; she delights in beautie, in glory, and in health. But her proper and particular office is, first to know how to use such goods temperately, and how to lose them constantly. An office much more noble than severe, without which all course of life is unnaturall, turbulent, and deformed, to which one may lawfully join those rocks, those incumbrances, and those hideous monsters. If so it happen, that his Disciple prove of so different a condition, that he rather love to give eare to an idle fable than to the report of some noble voiage, or other notable and wise discourse, when he shall hear it; that at the sound of a Drum or clang of a Trumpet, which are wont to rowse and arm the youthly heat of his companions, turneth to another that calleth him to see a play, tumbling, jugling tricks, or other idle lose-time sports; and who for pleasures sake does not deem it more delightsome to return all sweatie and wearie from a victorious combat, from wrestling, or riding of a horse, than from a tennis-court or dancing schoole, with the prize or honor of such exercises; The best remedy I know for such a one is, to put him prentice to some base occupation, in some good town or other, indeed, were he the son of a Duke; according to Platoes rule, who says ’That ohildren must be placed, not according to their fathers conditions, but the faculties of their mind.’ Since it is Philosophie that teacheth us to live, and that infancie as well as other ages, may plainly read her lessons in the same, why should it not be imparted unto young Schollers? Udum et molle lutum est, nunc nunc propetandus, et acri Fingendus sine fine rota. -- Pers. Sat. iii.23. He’s moist and soft mould, and must by and by Be cast, made up, while wheele whirl’s readily. We are taught to live when our life is well-nigh spent. Many schollers have been infected with that loathsome and marrow-wasting disease before ever they came to read Aristotles treatise of Temperance. Cicero was wont to say, ’That could he out-live the lives of two men, he should never find leisure to study the ’Lyrike Poets.’ And I find these Sophisters both worse and more unprofitable. Our child is engaged in greater matters; And but the first fifteene or sixteene years of his life are due unto Pedantisme, the rest unto action: let us therefore employ so short time as we have to live in more necessarie instructions. It is an abuse; remove these thornie quiddities of Logike, whereby our life can no whit be amended, and betake ourselves to the simple discourses of Philosophy; know how to chuse and fitly to make use of them: they are much more easy to be conceived than one of Bocace his tales. A child coming from nurse is more capable of them, than he is to learne to read or write. Philosophy has discourses, whereof infancie as well as decaying old-age may make good use. I am of Plutarkes mind, which is, that Aristotle did not so much ammuse his great Disciple about the arts how to frame Syllogismes, or the principles of Geometric, as he endevoured to instruct him with good precepts concerning valor, prowess, magnanimity, and temperance, and an undanted assurance not to fear any thing; and with such munition he sent him, being yet very young, to subdue the Empire of the world, only with 30000. footmen, 4000. horsemen, and 42000. Crownes in monie. As for other arts amd sciences; he says Alexander honoured them, and commended their excellencie and comlinesse; but for any pleasure he took in them, his affection could not easily be drawne to exercise them. ----- petite hinc juvenesque senesque Finem animo certum, miserisque viatica canis.-- Sat. v. 64. Young men and old, draw hence (in your affairs) Your minds set marke, provision for gray haires. It is that which Epicurus said in the beginning of his letter to Meniceus: ’Neither let the youngest shun nor the oldest wearie himself in philosophying for who does otherwise seems to say, that either season to live happily is not yet come, or is already past.’ Yet would I not have this young gentleman pent-up, nor carelesly cast-off to the heedlesse choler or melancholy humor of the hasty School-master. I would not have his budding spirit corrupted with keeping him fast-tied, and as it were labounng fourteene or fifteene hours a day poaring on his book, as some do, as if he were a day-labouring man; neither do I think it fit, if at any time, by reason of some solitairie or melancholy complexion, he should be seen with an over-indiscreet application given to his book, it should be cherished in him; for, that does often make him both unapt for civill conversation and distracts him from better employments: How many have I seen in my days, by an over-greedy desire of knowledge, become as as it were foolish? Carneades was so deeply plunged, and as I may say besotted in it, that he could never have leisure to cut his hair, or pare his nailes: nor would I have his noble manners obscured by the incivilitie and barbarisms of others. The French wisdom has long since proverbially been spoken of as very apt to conceive study in her youth, but most unapt to keep it long. In good truth, we see at this day that there is nothing lovelier to behold than the young children of France; but for the most part, they deceive the hope which was fore- apprehended of them: for when they once become men, there is no excellencie at all in them. I have heard men of understanding hold this opinion, that the Colleges to which they are sent (of which there are store) do thus besot them: whereas to our schollers a cabinet, a gardin, the table, the bed, a solitarinesse, a companie, morning and evening, and all hours shall be likewise unto him, all places shall be a study for him: for Philosophy (as a former of judgemente, and modeler of customs) shall be his principal lesson, having the privilege to entermeddle herself with all things, and in all places. Isocrates the Orator, being once requested in a great banket to speak of his art, when all thought he had reason to answer, said, ’It is not now time to do what I can, and what should now be done, I cannot do it;’ For, to present orations, or to enter into disputation of Rhetorike, before a companie assembled together to be merrie, and make good cheere, would be but a medley of harsh and jarring music. The like may be said of all others Sciences. But touching Philosophy, namely, in that point where it treateth of man, and of his duties and offices, it has been the common judgement of the wisest, that in regard of the pleasantnesse of her conversations, she ought not to be rejected, neither at banquets nor at sports. And Plato having invited her to his solemn feast, we see how kindly she entertaineth the companie with a mild behaviour, fitly stuting herself to time and place, notwithstanding it be one of his learned’st and profitable discourses. Æque pauperibus prodest, locupletibus æque, Et neglecta æque pueris senibusque nocebit. ----- HOR. i. Epist. i. 25. Poore men likewise, likewise rich men it easeth. Alike it, scorned, old and young displeaseth. So doubtlesse he shall less be idle than others; for even as the paces we bestow walking in a gallerie, althouch they be twice as many more, wearie us not so much as those we spend in going a set journey: So our lesson being past over, as it were, by chance, or way of encounter, without strict observance of time or place, being applied to all our actions, shall be digested, and never felt. All sports and exercises shall be a part of his study; running, wrestling, music, dancing, hunting, and managing of arms and horses. I would have the exterior demeanor or decencie, and the disposition of his person to be fashioned together with his mind: for, it is not a mind, it is not a body that we erect, but it is a man, and we must not make two parts of him. And as Plato says, They must not be erected one without another, but equally be directed, no otherwise than a couple of horses matched to draw in one self-same teeme. And to hear him, does he not seem to employ more time and care in the exercises of his body: and to think that the mind is together with the same exercised, and not the contrary? As for other matters, this institution ought to be directed by a sweet-severe mildness; Not as some do, who in liew of gently-bidding children to the banquet of letters, present them with nothing but horror and crueltie. Let me have this violence and compulsion removed, there is nothing that in my seeming, does more bastardise and dizzie a well-borne and gentle nature: If you would have him stand in awe of shame and punishment, do not so much enure him to it: accustome him patiently to endure sweat and cold, the sharpnesse of the wind, the heat of the sunne, and how to despise all hazards. Remove from him all nicenesse and quaintness in clothing, in lying , in eating, and in drinking: fashion him to all things, that he prove not a fair and wanton- puling boy, but a lustie and vigorous boy: When I was a child, being a man, and now am old, I have ever judged and believed the same. But amongst other things, I could never away with this kind of discipline used in most of our Colleges. It had perhaps been less hurtful, if they had somewhat inclined to mildness, or gentle intreatie. It is a very prison of captivated youth, and proves dissolute in punishing it before it be so. Come upon them when they are going to their lesson, and you hear nothing but whipping and brawling, both of children tormented, and masters besotted with anger and chafing. How wide are they, which go about to allure a child’s mind to go to its book, being yet but tender and fearefull, with a stearne-frowning countenance, and with hands full of rods? Oh wicked and pernicious manner of teaching! which Quintillian has very well noted, that this imperious kind of authority, namely, this way of punishing of children, draws many dangerous inconveniences within. How much more decent were it to see their school- houses and formes strewed with green boughs and flowers, than with bloudy burchentwigs? If it lay in me, I would do as the Philosopher Speusippus did, who caused the pictures of Gladness and Joy, of FloraPlato sheweth him self in framing of his laws about the recreation and pastime of the youth of his City, and how far he extends him self about their exercises, sports, songs, leaping, and dancing, whereof he says, that severe antiquitie gave the conduct and patronage unto the Gods themselves, namely, to Apollo, to the Muses, and to Minerva. Marke but how far-forth he endevoreth to give a thousand precepts to be kept in his places of exercises both of body and mind. As for learned Sciences, he stands not much upon them, and seems in particular to commend Poesie, but for Musickes sake. All strangenesse and self-particularitie in our manners and conditions, is to be shunned, as an enemy to societie and civill conversation. Who would not be astonished at Demophons complexion, chief steward of Alexanders household, who was wont to sweat in the shadow, and quiver for cold in the sunne? I have seen some to startle at the smell of an apple more than at the shot of a peece; some to be frighted with a mouse, some readie to cast their gorge at the sight of a messe of creame, and others to be scared with seeing a fether bed shaken: as Germanicus, who could abide to see a cock, or hear his crowing. There may perhaps be some hidden propertie of nature, which in my judgement might easilie be removed, if it were taken in time. Institution has gotten this upon me (I must confesse with much adoe) for, except here, all things else that are mans food agree indifferently with my taste. The body being yet souple, ought to be accommodated to all fashions and customs; and (alwaies provided, his appetites and desires be kept under) let a yong man boldly be made fit for al Nations and companies; indeed, if need be, for al disorders and surfetings; let him acquaint himself with al fashions; That he may be able to do al things, and love to do none but those that are commendable. Some strict Philosophers commend not, but rather blame Calisthenes, for losing the good favor of his Master Alexander, only because he would not pledge him as much as he had drunke to him. He shall laugh, jest, dally, and debauch himself with his Prince. And in his debauching, I would have him out-go al his fellowes in vigor or and constancy, and that he omit not to do evil neither for want of strength or knowledge, but for lacke of will. Multum interest utrum peccare quis nolit, aut nesciat. ’There is a great difference, whether one have no will, or no wit to go amisse.’ I thought to have honoured a gentleman (as great a stranger, and as far from such riotous disorders as any is in France) by enquiring of him in very good companie, how many times in all his life he had bin drunke in Germany, during the time of his abode there, about the necessarie affairs of our King; who took it even as I meant it, and answered three times, telling the time and manner how. I know some, who for want of that quality, have been much perplexed when they have had occasion to converse with that nation. I have often noted with great admiration, that wonderful nature of Alcibiades, to see how easilie he could sute himself to so diverse fashions and different humors, without prejudice unto his health; sometimes exceeding the sumptuousnesse and pompe of the Persians, and now and then surpassing the austeritie and frugality of the Lacedemonians; as reformed in Sparta, as voluptuous in Ionia. and of the Graces, to be set up roundabout his school-house. Where their profit lieth, there should also be their recreation. Those meats ought to be sugred over, that are healthful for childrens stomakes, and those made bitter that are hurtful for them. It is strange to see how careful Omnis Aristippum decuit color, et status, et res. -- Hor. Epist. xvii. 23. All colours, states, and things are fit For courtly Aristippus wit. Such a one would I frame my Disciple, ----- quem duplici panno patientia velat, Mirabor, vitæ via si conversa decebit. --25. Whom patience clothes with sutes of double kind, I muse, if he another way will find. Personamque feret non inconcinnus utramque. -- 29. He not unfitly may Both parts and persons play. See here my lessons, wherein he that acteth them, profiteth more than he that but knows them, whom if you see, you hear, and if you hear him, you see him. God forbid, says some body in Plato, that to Philosophize, be to learne many things, and to exercise the arts. Hanc amplissimam omnium artium bene vivendi disciplinam, vita magis quam litteris persequenti sunt. (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ’This discipline of living well, which is the amplest of all other arts, they followed rather in their lives than in their learning or writing.’ Leo Prince of the Phliasians, enquiring of Heraclides Ponticus what art he professed, he answered, ’Sir, I professe neither art nor science; but I am a Philosopher.’ Some reproved Diogenes, that being an ignorant man, he did nevertheless nmeddle with Philosophie, to whom he replied, ’So much the more reason have I and to greater purpose do I meddle with it.’ Hegesias praid him upon a time to read some book unto him: ’You are a merry man,’ said he; ’As you chuse natural and not painted right and not counterfeit figges to eat, why do you not likewise chuse, not the paint ed and written, but the true and natural exercises?’ He shall not so much repeat, as act his lesson. In his actions shall he make repetition of the same. We must observe, whether there be wisdom in his enterprises, integritie in his demeanor, modesty in his jestures, justice in his actions, judgement and grace in his speech, courage in his sicknesse, moderation in his sports, temperance in his pleasures, order in the government of his house, and indifference in his taste, whether it be flesh, fish, wine, or water, or whatsoever he feedeth upon. Qui disciplinam suam non ostentationem scientiæ sed legem vitæ putet: quique obtemperet ipse sibi et decretis pareat (Cic. ibid. ii.). ’Who thinks his learning not an ostentation of knowledge, but a law of life, and himself obayes himself and does what is decreed.’ The true mirror of our discourses is the course of our lives. Zeuxidamus answered one that demanded of him, why the Lacedemonians did not draw into a book, the ordinances of prowess, th t so their yong men might read them; ’it is,’ says he, ’because they would rather accustome them to deeds and actions, than to bookes and writings.’ Compare at the end of fifteene or sixteens years one of those collegiall Latinizers, who has employed all that while only in learning how to speak, to such a one as I meane. The world is nothing but babling and words, and I never saw man that does not rather speak more than he ought, than less. Notwithstanding halfe our age is consumed that way. We are kept foure or five years learning to understand bare words, and to joine them into clauses, then as long in proportioning a great body extended into foure or five parts; and five more at least ere we can succinctly know how to mingle, joine, and interlace them handsomly into a subtil fashion, and into one coherent orbe. Let us leave it to those whose profession is to do nothing else. Being once on my journey to Orleans, it was my chance to meet upon that plaine that lieth on this side Clery, with two Masters of Arts, traveling toward Bordeaux, about fiftie paces one from another; far off behind them, I descride a troupe of horsemen, their Master riding formost, who was the Earle of Rochefocault; one of my servants enquiring of the first of those Masters of Arts, what Gentleman he was that followed him; suposing my servant had meant his fellow-scholler, for he had not yet seen the Earles traine, answered pleasantly, ’He is no gentleman. Sir, but a Gramarian, and I am a Logitian.’ Now, we that contrariwise seek not to frame a Gramiarian, nor a Logitian, but a compleat gentleman, let us give them leave to mispend their time; we have else- where, and somewhat else of more import to do. So that our Disciple be well and sufficiently stored with matter; words will follow and if they will not follow gently, he shall hale on perforce. I hear some excuse themselves, that they cannot express th eir meaning, and make a semblance that their heads are so full stuft with many goodly things, but for want of eloquence they can neither utter nor make show of them. It is a meere fopperie. And will you know what, in my seeming, the cause is? They are shadows and Chimeræs, proceeding of some formelesse conceptions, which they cannot distinguish or resolve within, and by conseguence are not able to produce them inasmuch as they understand not themselves: And if you but marke their earnestnesse, and how they stammer and labor at the point of their deliverie, you would deem that what they go withall, is but a conceiving, and therefore nothing near down-lying; and that they do but licke that imperfect and shapelesse lump of matter, As for me, I am of opinion, and Socrates would have it so, that he who had a clear and lively imagination in his mind, may easilie produce and utter the same, although it be in Bergamask or Welsh, and if he be dumbe, by signes and tokens. iv.). Verbaque prævisam rem non invita sequentur. --Hor. Ars. Poet. 311. When matter we fore-know, Words voluntarie flow. As one said, as poetically in his prose, Cum res animum occupavere, verba ambiunt; (Sen. Controv. vii. Proæ). ’When matter has possest their minds, they hunt after words:’ and another: Ipsee res verba rapiunt. ’Things themselves will catch and carry words:’ He knowes neither Ablative, Conjunctive, Substantive, nor Gramar, no more does his Lackeye nor any Oyster-wife about the streets, and yet if you have a mind to it he will intertaine you, your fill, and perhaps stumble as little and as seldom against the rules of his tongue, as the best Master of arts in France. He has no skill in Rhetoricke, nor can he with a preface fore-stall and captivate the Gentle Readers good will: nor careth he greatly to know it. In good sooth, all this garish painting is easilie defaced, by the lustre of an in-bred and simple truth; for these dainties and quaint devices serve but to ammuse the vulgar sort; unapt and incapable to taste the most solid and firme meat: as Afer very plainly declareth in Cornelius Tacitus. The Ambassadours of SamosCleomenes King of Sparta, prepared with a long prolix Oration, to stir him up to war against the tyrant Policrates, after he had listned a good while unto them, his answer was: ’Touching your Exordium or beginning I have forgotten it; the middle I remember not; and for your conclusion I will do nothing in it.’ A fit, and (to my thinking) a very good answer; and the Orators were put to such a shift, as they knew not what to replie. And what said another? the Athenians from out two of their cunning Architects, were to chuse one to erect a notable great frame; the one of them more affected and self presuming, presented himself before them with a smooth fore-premeditated discourse, about the subject of that piece of work, and thereby drew the judgements of the common people unto his liking; but the other in few words spake thus: ’Lords of Athens, what this man has said I will performe.’ In the greatest earnestnesse of Ciceroes eloquence many were drawn into a kind of admiration; But Cato jesting at it, said, ’Have we not a pleasant Consull?’ A quick cunning Argument, and a wittie saying, whether it go before or come after, it is never out of season. If it have no coherence with that which gooth before, nor with what commeth after; it is good and commendable in itself. I am none of those that think a good Ryme, to make a good Poeme; let him hardly (if so he please) make a short syllable long, it is no great matter: if the inventition be rare and good, and his wit and judgement have cunningly played their part. I will say to such a one; he is a good Poet, but an ill Versifier. being come to Emunctæ naris durus componere versus. Hor. i. Sat. iv. 8. Lucil. A man whose sense could finely pierce. But harsh and hard to make a verse. Let a man (says Horace) make his work loose all seames, measures, and joints. Tempora certa modosque et quod prius ordine verbum est, Posterius facias, præponens ultima primis: Invenias etiam disjecti membra Poetæ. -- 58, 62. Set times and moods, make you the first word last The last word first, as if they were new cast: Yet find the unjoynted Poets joints stand fast. He shall for all that, nothing gain-say himself, every piece will make a good show. To this purpose answered Menander those that chid him, the day being at hand, in which he had promised a Comedy, and had not begun the same, ’Tut-tut,’ said he, It is alreadie finished, there wanteth nothing but to adde the verse unto it;’ for, having ranged and cast the plot in his mind, he made small accompt of feet, of measures, or cadences of verses, which indeed are but of small import in regard of the rest. Since great Ronzarde and learned Bellay have raised our French Poesie unto that height of honor where it now is: I see not one of these petty ballad-makers, or prentise dogrell rymers, that does not bombast his labours with high-swelling and heaven-disimbowelling words, and that does not marshall his cadences very near as they do. Plus sonat quam valet (Sen. Epist. xl.). ’The sound is more than the weight or worth.’ And for the vulgar sort, there were never so many Poets, and so few good: but as it has been easy for them to represent their rymes, so come they far short in imitating the rich descriptions of the one, and rare inventions of the other. But what shall he do, if he be urged with sophisticall subtilties about a Sillogisme? A gammon of Bacon makes a man drink, drinking quencheth a mans thirst; Ergo, a gammon of bacon quencheth a mans thirst. Let him mock at it, it is more wittie to be mockt at than to be answered. Let him borrow this pleasant counter-craft of Aristippus: ’Why shall I unbind that, which being bound does so much trouble me?’ Someone proposed certain Logicall quiddities against Cleanthes, to whom Chrisippus said; use such jugling tricks to play with children, and divert not the serious thoughts of an aged man to such idle matters. If such foolish wiles, Contorta et aculeata sophismata (Cic. Acad. Qu. iv.). ’Intricate and stinged sophismes,’ must persuade a lie, it is dangerous: but if they proove void of any effect, and move him but to laughter, I see not why he shall beware of them. Some there are so foolish that will go a quarter of a mile out of the way to hunt after a quaint new word, if they once get in chace; Aut qui non verba rebus aptant, sed res extstrinsecus arcessunt, quibus verba conveniant: ’Or such as fit not words to matter, but fetch matter from abroad, whereto words be fitted.’ And another, Qui ancicujus verbi decore placentis vocentur ad id quod non proposuerant scribere (Sen. Epist. lix.). ’Who are allured by the grace of some pleasing word, to write what they intended not to write.’ I do more willingly winde up a wittie notable sentence, that so I may sew it upon me, than unwinde my thread to go fetch it. Contrariwise, it is for words to serve and wait upon the matter, and not for matter to attend upon words, and if the French tongue cannot reach unto it, let the Gaskonie, or any other. I would have the matters to surmount, and so fill the imagination of him that harkeneth, that he have no remembrance at all of the words. It is a natural, simple, and unaffected speech that I love, so written as it is spoken, and such upon the paper, as it is in the mouth, a pithie, sinnowie, full, strong, compendious and materiall speech, not so delicate and affected as vehement and piercing. Hæc demum sapiet dictio, quæ feriet.-- Epitaph. Lucan. 6. In fine, that word is wisely fit, Which strikes the fence, the marke does hit. Rather difficult than tedious, void of affection, free, loose and bold, that every member of it seem to make a body; not Pedanticall, nor Frier-like, nor Lawyer-like, but rather down right, Souldier-like. As Suetonius calleth that of Julius Cæsar, which I see no reason why he calleth it. I have sometimes pleased myself in imitating that licenciousnesse or wanton humor of our youths, in wearing of their garments; as carelessly to let their cloaks hang down over one shoulder; to weare their cloakes scarfe or bawdrikewise, and their stockings loose hanging about their legs. It represents a kind of disdainful fiercenesse of these forraine embellishings, and neglect carelesnesse of art: But I commend it more being employed in the course and form of speech. All manner of affectation, namely in the livelinesse and liberty of France, is unseemely in a Courtier. And in a Monarchie every Gentleman ought to addresse himself unto a Courtiers carriage. Therefore do we well somewhat to incline to a native and carelesse behaviour. I like not a contexture, where the seames and pieces may be seen: As in a well compact body, what need a man distinguish and number all the bones and veines severally? Quæ veritati operam dat oratio, incomposita sit et simplex.1 Quis accuratete loquitur nisi qui vult putide loqui (Se. Epist. xl. m. lxxv. p.). ’The speach that intendeth truth must be plaine and unpollisht: Who speaks elaborately, but he that means to speak unsavouredly?’ That eloquence offereth injurie unto things, which altogether draws us to observe it. As in apparell, it as a signe of pusillanimitie for one to marke himself, in some particular and unusuall fashion: so likewise in common speech, for one to hunt after new phrases, and unaccustomed quaint words, proceedeth of a scholasticall and childish ambition. Let me use none other than are spoken in the hals of Paris. Aristophanes the Gramarian was somewhat out of the way, when he reproved Epicurus, for the simplicitie of his words, and the end of his art oratorie, which was only perspicuitie in speeche. The imitation of speech, by reason of the facilitie of it, followeth presently a whole nation. The imitation of judging and inventing, comes more slow. The greater number of Readers, because they have found one self-same kind of gowne, suppose most falsely to holde one like body. Outward garments and clokes may be borrowed, but never the sinews and strength of the body. Most of those that converse with me, speak like unto these Essayes; but I know not whether they think likewise. The Athenians (as Plato averreth) have for their part great care to be fluent and eloquent in their speech; The Lacedemonians endeavor to be short and compendious; and those of Creet labor more to be plentifull in conceits than in language. And these are the best. Zeno was wont to say, ’That he had two sorts of disciples; the one he called φιλολογους, curious to learne things, and those were his darlings, the other he termed λογοφιλους, who respected nothing more than the language. Yet can no man say, but that to speak well, is most gracious and commendable, but not so excellent as some make it: and I am grieved to see how we employ most part of our time about that only. I would frst know my own tongue perfectly, then my neighbors with whom I have most commerce. I must needs acknowledge, that the Greeke and Latine tongues are great ornaments in a gentleman, but they are pnrchased at over-high a rate. Use it who list, I will tell you how they may be gotten better, cheaper, and much sooner than is ordinarily used, which was tried in myself. My late father, having, by all the means and industrie that is possible for a man, sought amongst the wisest, and men of best understanding, to find a most exquisite and readie way of teaching, being advised of the inconveniences then in use; was given to understand that the lingring while, and best part of our youth, that we employ in learning the tongues, which cost them nothing, is the only cause we can never attaine to that absolute perfection of skill and knowledge of the Greekes and Romanes. I do not believe that to be the only cause. But so it is, the expedient my father found out was this; that being yet at nurse, and before the first loosing of my tongue, I was delivered to a Germane (who died since, a most excellent Physitian in France) he being then altogether ignorant of the French tongue, but exquisitely readie and skilfull in the Latine. This man, whom my father had sent for of purpose, and to whom he gave very great entertainment, had me continually in his arms, and was mine only overseer. There were also joined unto him two of his countrymen, but not so learned; whose charge was to attend, and now and then to play with me; and all these together did never entertaine me with other than the Latine tongue. As for others of his household, it was an inviolable rule, that neither himself, nor my mother, nor man, nor maid-servant, were suffered to speak one word in my companie, except such Latine words as every one had learned to chat and prattle with me. It were strange to tell how every one in the house profited therein. My Father and my Mother learned so much Latine, that for a need they could understand it, when they heard it spoken, even so did all the household servants, namely such as were neerest and most about me. To be short, we were all so Latinized, that the townes round about us had their share of it; insomuch as even at this day, many Latine names both of workmen and of their tooles are yet in use amongst them. And as for myself, I was about six years old, and could understand no more French or Perigordine than Arabike; and that without art, without bookes, rules, or grammar, without whipping or whining, I had gotten as pure a Latin tongue as my Master could speak; the rather because I could neither mingle or confound the same with other tongues. If for an Essay they would give me a Theme, whereas the fashion in CoIleges is, to give it in French, I had it in bad Latine, to reduce the same into good. And Nicholas Grucci, who has written De comitiis Romanorum, William Guerenti, who has commented Aristotele: George Buchanan, that famous Scottish Poet, and Marke-Antonie Muret, whom (while he lived) both FranceItalie to this day, acknowledge to have been the best orator: all which have been my familiar tutors, have often told me, that in mine infancie I had the Latine tongue so readie and so perfect, that themselves feared to take me in hand. And Buchanan, who afterward I saw attending on the Marshall of Brissacke, told me, he was about to write a treatise of the institution of children, and that he took the model and patterne from mine: for at that time he had the charge and bringing up of the young Earle of Brissack, whom since we have seen prove so worthy and so valiant a Captain. As for the Greeke, wherein I have but small understanding, my father purposed to make me learne it by art; But by new and uncustomed means, that is, by way of recreation and exercise. We did tosse our declinations and conjugations to and fro, as they do, who by way of a certain game at tables learne both Arithmetic and Geometrie. For, amongst other things he had especially been persuaded to make me taste and apprehend the fruits of dutie and science by an unforced kind of will, and of my own choice; and without any compulsion or rigor to bring me up in all mildness and liberty: indeed with such kind of superstition, that, whereas some are of opinion that suddenly to awaken young children, and as it were by violence to startle and fright them out of their dead sleepe in a morning (wherein they are more heavy and deeper plunged than we) does greatly trouble and distemper their braines, he would every morning cause me to be awakened by the sound of some instrument; and I was never without a servant who to that purpose attended upon me. This example may serve to judge of the rest; as also to commend the judgement and tender affection of so careful and loving a father: who is not to be blamed, though he reaped not the fruits answerable to his exquisite toyle and painefull manuring. Two things hindered the same; first the barrennesse and unfit soyle: for howbeit I were of a sound and strong constitution, and of a tractable and yielding condition, yet was I so heavy, so sluggish, and so dull, that I could not be rouzed (indeed were it to go to play) from out mine idle drowzinesse. What I saw, I saw it perfectly; and under this heavy, and as it were Lethe-complexion did I breed hardie imaginations, and opinions far above my years. My spirit was very slow, and would go no further, than it was fed by others; my apprehension blockish, my invention poore; and besides, I had a marvelous defect in my weake memory; it is therefore no wonder, if my father could never bring me to any perfection. Secondly, as those that in some dangerous sicknesse, moved with a kind of hope-full and greedie desire of perfect health again, give eare to every Leach of Emperike, and follow all counsels, the good man being exceedingly fearefull to commit any oversight, in a matter he took so to heart, suffered himself at last to be led away by the common opinion, which like unto the Cranes, followeth over those that go before, and yielded to custom: having those no longer about him, that had given him his first directions, and which they had brought out of Italie. Being but six years old I was sent to the College of Guyenne, then most flourishing and reputed the best in France, where it is impossible to adde any thing to the great care he had, both to chuse the best and most sufficient masters that could be found, to read unto me, as also for all other circumstances partaining to my education; wherein contrary to usual customs of Colleges, he observed many particular rules. But so it is, it was ever a College. My Latin tongue was forthwith corrupted, whereof by reason of discontinuance, I afterward lost all manner of use: which new kind of institution stood me in no other stead, but that at my first admittance it made me to over-skip some of the lower formes, and to be placed in the highest. For at thirteene years of age that I left the College, I had read over the whole course of Philosophie (as they call it) but with so small profit, that I can now make no account of it. The first taste or feeling I had of bookes, was of the pleasure I took in reading the fables of Ovids Metamorphosies; for, being but seven or eight years old, I would steale and sequester my self from all other delights, only to read them: Forasmuch as the tongue wherein they were written was to me natural; and it was the easiest book I knew, and by reason of the matter therein contained most agreeing with my young age. For of King Arthur, of Lancelot du Lake, of Amadis, of Huon of Burdeaux, and such idle time consuming and wit-besotting trash of bookes wherein youth does commonly ammuse itself, I was not so much as acquainted with their names, and to this day know not their bodies, nor what they containe: So exact was my discipline. Whereby I became more carelesse to studie my other prescript lessons. And well did it fall out fall out for my purpose, that I had to deale with a very discreet master, who out of his judgement could with such dexterite winke at and second my untowardlinesse, and such other faults that were in me. For by that means I read over Virgils Æneados, Terence, Plautus, and other Italian Comedies, allured thereunto by the pleasantnesse of their severall subjects: Had he been so foolishly-severe, or so severely froward as to crosse this course of mine, I think verily I had never brought any thing from the College, but the hate and contempt of Bookes, as does the greatest part of our Nobilitie. Such was his discretion, and so warily did he behave himself, that he saw and would not see: he would foster and increase my longing: suffering me but by stealth and by snatches to glut my self with those Bookes, holding ever a gentle hand over me, concerning other regular studies. For, the chiefest thing my father required at their hands (unto whose charge he had committed me) was a kind of well conditioned mildness and facilitie of complexion. And, to say truth, mine had no other fault, but a certain dull languishing and heavy slothfullnesse. The danger was not, I should do ill, but that I should do nothing. No man did ever suspect I would prove a bad, but an uuprofitable man: foreseeing in me rather a kind of idlenesse than a voluntary craftinesse. I am not so self-conceited but I perceive what has followed. The complaints that are daily buzzed in mine ears are these; that I am idle, cold, and negligent in offices of friendship, and dutie to my parents and kinsfolk; and touching public offices, that I am over singular and disdainfull. And those that are most injurious cannot aske, why I have taken, and why I have not paied? but may rather demand, why I do not quit, and why I do not give? I would take it as a favor, they should wish such effects of supererogation in me. But they are unjust and over partiall, that will go about to exact that from me wh ich I owe not, with more rigour than they will exact from themselves that which they owe; wherein if they condemne me, they utterly cancell both the gratifying of the action, and the gratitude, which thereby would be due to me. Whereas the active well doing should be of more consequence, proceeding from my hand, in regard I have no passive at all. Wherefore I may so much the more feetly dispose of my fortune, by how much more it is mine, and of my self that am most my own. Notwithstanding, if I were a great blazoner of my own actions, I might perhaps barre such reproches, and justly upbraid some, that they are not so much offended, because I do not enough, as for that I may, and it lies in my power to do much more than I do. Yet my mind ceased not at the same time to have peculiar unto itself well setled motions, true and open judgements concerning the objects which it knew; which alone, and without any helpe or communication it would digest. And amongst other things, I ver ily believe it would have proved altogether incapable and unfit to yield unto forces or stoop unto violence. Shall I account or relate this quality of my infancie, which was, a kind of boldness in my looks, and gentle softnesse in my voice, and affabilitie in my gestures, and a dexterite in conforming my self to the parts I undertook? for before the age of the and Alter ab undecimo tum me vix ceperat annus. Virg. Buc. Ecl. viii. 39. Yeares had I (to make even) Scarce two above eleven. I have under-gone and represented the chiefest parts in the Latin Tragedies of Buchanan, Guerenti, and of Muret; which in great state were acted and plaid in our College of Guyenne: wherein Andreas Goveanus our Rector principal; who as in all other parts belonging to his charge, was without comparison the chiefest Rector of France, and my self (without ostentation be it spoken) was reputed, if not a chief master yet a principal Actor in them. It is an exercise I rather commend than disalow in young Gentlemen: and have seen some of our Princes (in imitation of some of former ages) both commendably and honestly, in their proper persons act and play some parts in Tragedies. It has heretofore been esteemed a lawfull exercise, and a tolerable profession in men of honor, namely in Greece. Aristoni tragico actori rem aperit: huic et genus et fortuna honesta erant: nec ars, quia nihil tale apud Græcos pudori est, ea deformabat ((Liv. dec. iii. 4). ’He imparts the matter to Ariston a Player of tragedies, whose progenie and fortune were both honest; nor did his profession disgrace them, because no such matter is a disparagement amongst the Greeks.’ And I have ever accused them of impertinencie, that condemne and disalow such kindes of recreations, and blame those of injustice that refuse good and honest Comedians, or (as we call them) Players, to enter our good townes, and grudge the common people such public sports. Politike and well ordered commonwealths endeavor rather carefully to unite and assemble their Citizens together; as in serious offices of devotion, so in honest exercises of recreation. Common societie and loving friendship is thereby cherished and increased. And besides, they cannot have more formal and regular pastimes allowed them, than such as are acted and represented in open view of all, and in the presence of the magistrates themselves: And if I might bear sway I would think it reasonable, that Princes should sometimes, at their proper charges, gratifie the common people with them as an argument of a fatherly affection, and loving goodness towards them: and that in populous and frequented cities, there should be Theatres and places appointed for such spectacles; as a diverting of worse inconveniences, and secret actions. But to come to my intended purpose, there is no better way to allure the affection, and to entice the appetite: otherwise a man shall breed but asses laden with Bookes. With jerkes of rods they have their satchels full of learning given them to keep. Which to do well, one must not only harbor in himself, but wed and marry the same with his mind. Renascence Editions Return to CHAPTER XXVI: IT IS FOLLIE TO REFERRE TRUTH OR FALSEHOOD TO OUR SUFFICIENCIE CHAPTER XXVI: IT IS FOLLIE TO REFERRE TRUTH OR FALSEHOOD TO OUR SUFFICIENCIE T is not perhaps without reason, that we ascribe the facilitie of beleeving and easines of persuasion us to simplicitie and ignorance: For me seems to have learnt heretofore, that beliefe was, as it were an impression conceived in our mind, and according as the same was found either more soft, or of less resistance, it was easier to imprint anything therein. Ut necesse est lancem in libra ponderibus impositis deprimi: sic animum perspicuis cedereAcad. Qu. iv.). ’As it is necessarie a scale must go down the balance when weights are put into it, so must a mind yield to things that are manifest.’ (Cic. Forasmuch, therefore, as the mind being most empty and without counterpoize, so much the more easily does it yield under the burden of the first persuasion. And that’s the reason why children, those of the common sort, women, and sickefolks, are so subject to be mis-led, and so easy to swallow gudgeons. On the other side it is a sottish presumption to disdaine and condemne that for false, which unto us seems to bear no show of likelihood or truth which is an ordinary fault in those who persuade themselves to be of more sufficiency than the vulgar sort. So was I sometimes wont to do, and if I heard any body speak, either of ghosts walking, of foretelling future things, of enchantments, of witchcrafts, or any other thing reported, which I could not well conceive, or that was beyond my reach. Somnia, terrores magicos, miracula, sagas, Nocturnos lemures, portentaque Thessali -- Hor. ii. Ep. ii. 208. Dreames, magic terrors, witches, uncouth-wonders. Night-walking sprites, Thessalian conjur’d-thunders. I could not but feel a kind of compassion to see the poore and seely people abused with such follies. And now I perceive that I was as much to be moaned myself: Not that experience has since made me to discerne any thing beyond my former opinions: yet was not my curiosity the cause of it, but reason has taught me, that so resolutely to condemne a thing for false and impossible, is to assume unto himself the advantage, to have the bounds and limits of Gods will, and of the power of our common mother Nature tied to his sleeve: And that there is no greater folly in the world than to reduce them to the measure of our capacitie and bounds of our sufficiencie. If we terme those things monsters or miracles to which our reason cannot attaine, how many such do daily present themselves unto our sight? Let us consider through what clouds, and how blinde-fold we are led to the knowledge of most things that pass our hands: verily we shall find, it is rather custom than science that removeth the strangenesse of them from us: ----- jam nemo fessus saturusque videndi, Suspicere in coeli dignatur lucida templa.-- Lucr. ii. Now no man tir’d with glut of contemplation, Deignes to have heav’ns bright Church in admiration. And that those things, were they newly presented unto us, we should doubtlesse deem them as much or more unlikely and incredible than any other. ------ si nunc primum mortalibus adsint Ex improviso, ceu sint objecta repente, Nil magis his rebus paterat mirabile dici, Aut minus ante quod auderent fore credere gentes. -- 1042. If now first on a sudden they were here Mongst mortal men, object to eye or eare, Nothing than these things would more wondrous be, Or that, men durst less think, ever to see. He who had never seen a river before, the first he saw be thought it to be the Ocean: and things that are the greatest in our knowledge, we judge them to be the extremest that nature worketh in that kind. Scilicet et fluvius qui non est maximum, ei est Qui non ante aliquem majorem vidit, ei ingens Arbor homoque videtur, et omnia de qenere omni Maxima quæ vi dit quisque, hæc ingentia fingit. -- vi. 671. A streame none of the greatest, may so seem To him, that never saw a greater streame. Trees, men, seem huge, and all things of all sorts, The greatest one has seen, he huge reports. Consuetudine oculorum assuescunt animi neque admirantur, neque requirunt rationes earum rerum, quas semper vident (Cic. Nat. De. ii.). ’Mindes are acquainted by custom of their eyes, nor do they admire or enquire the reason of those things which they continually behold.’ The novelty of things does more incite us to search out the causes, than their greatness: we must judge of this infinite power of nature, with more reverence, and with more acknowledgement of our own ignorance and weaknesse. How many things of small likelihood are there, witnessed by men, worthie of credit, whereof if we cannot be persuaded, we should at least leave them in suspence? For to deem them impossible, is by rash presumption to presume and know how far possibilitie reacheth. If a man did well understand, what difference there is betweene impossibilitie, and that which is unwonted, and betweene that which is against the course of nature and the common opinion of men, in not beleeving rashly, and in not dis-beleeving easily; the rule of Nothing too-much, commanded by Chilon, should be observed. When we find in Froisard, that the Earle of Foix (being in Bearne) had knowledge of the defeature at Inberoth of King John of Castile, the morrow next it hapned, and the means he alleageth for it, a man may well laugh at it: And of that which our Annales report, that Pope Honorius, the very same day that King Philip AugustusMantes, caused his public funerals to be solemnized, and commanded them to be celebrated throughout all Italie. For, the authority of the witnesses has perhaps no sufficient warrant to restraine us. But what if Plutarke, besides diverse examples which he alleageth of antiquitie, says to have certainly known, that in Domitians time the news of the battle lost by Antonius in Germany many days journeies thence, was published in Rome, and divulged through the world the very same day it succeeded: And if Cæsar holds that it has many time happened, that report has foregone the accident: Shall we not say that those simple people have suffered themselves to be cousened and seduced by the vulgar sort, because they were not as clear-sighted as he? Is there any thing more daintie, more unspotted, and more lively than Plinies judgement, whensoever it pleaseth him to make show of it? Is there any farther from vanity? I omit the excellencie of his learning and knowledge, whereof I make but small reckoning: in which of those two parts do we exceed him? Yet there is no scholler so meanely learned but will convince him of lying, and read a lecture of contradiction against him upon the progresse of natures works. And when we read in Bouchet the myracles wrought by the reliques of Saint Hillarie, his credit is not sufficient to barre us the liberty of contradicting him: yet at random to condemne all such like histories, seems to me a notable impudencie. That famous man, Saint Augustine, witnesseth to have seen a blinde child to recover his sight, over the reliques of Saint Gervase and Protaise, at Milan: and a woman at Carthage to have become cured of a canker by the sign of the holy Crosse, which a woman newly baptized made unto her: and Hesperius a familiar friend of his, to have expelled certain spirits that molested his house, with a little of the earth of our Saviours sepulcher; which earth being afterwards transported into a Church, a Paralitike man was immediately therewith cured: and a woman going in procession, having as she past by with a nose-gaie touched the case wherein Saint Stevens bones were, and with the same afterward rubbed her eyes, she r ecovered her sight, which long before she had utterly lost: and diverse other examples, where he affirmeth to have been an assistant himself. What shal we accuse him of, and two other holy Bishops, Aurelius and Maximmus, whom he calleth for his witnesses? Shal it be of ignorance, of simplicity, of malice, of facility, or of imposture? Is any man living so impudent, that thinks he may be compared to them, whether it be in virtue or piety, in knowledge or judgement, in wisdom or sufficiency? Qui ut rationem nulllam afferent, ipsa auctoritate me frangerent (Cic. Div. i.). ’Who though they alleged no reason, yet might subdue me with their very authority.’ It is a dangerous foolish hardinesse, and of consequence, besides the absurd temerity it draws with it, to despise what we conceive not. For, after that according to your best understanding, you have established the limits of truth and bounds of falsehood, and that it is found you must necessarily believe things wherein is more strangenesse, than in those you deny; you have alreadie bound your self to abandon them. Now that which me thinkes brings as much disorder in our consciences, namely in these troubles of religion wherein we are, is the dispensation Catholikes make of their beliefe. They suppose to show themselves very moderate and skilfull, when they yield their adversaries any of those articles now in question. But besides that, they perceive not what an advantage it is for him that chargeth you, if you but once begin to yield and give them ground; and how much that encorageth him to pursue his point: those articles which they chuse for the lightest, are often times most important. Either a man must wholy submit himself to the authority of our Ecelesiasticall policy, or altogether dispence himself from it: It is not for us to determine what part of obedience we owe unto it. And moreover, I may say it, because I have made trial of it, having sometimes used this liberty of my choice, and particular election, not regarding certain points of the observance of our Church, which seem to bear a face either more vain or more strange; coming to communicate them with wise men, I have found that those things have a most solid and steadie foundation, and that it is but foolishnesse and ignorance, makes us receive them with less respect and reverence than the rest. Why remember we not, what, and how many, contradictions we find and feel even in our own judgement? How many things served us but yesterday as articles of faith, which to day we deem but fables? Glory and curiosity are the scourges of our soules. The latter induceth us to have an oar in every ship, and the former forbids us to leave anything unresolved or undecided. died at Renascence Editions Return to CHAPTER XXVII: OF FRIENDSHIP CHAPTER XXVII: OF FRIENDSHIP ONSIDERING the proceeding of a Painters work I have, a desire has possessed me to imitate him: He maketh choice of the most convenient place and middle of everie wall, there to place a picture, laboured with all his skill and sufficiencie; and all void places about it he filleth up with antike Boscage or Crotesko works; which are fantastic pictures, having no grace, bnt in the variety and strangenesse of them. And what are these my compositions in truth, other than antike works and monstrous bodies, patched and hudled up together of diverse members without any certain or well ordered figure, having neither order, dependencie, or proportion, but casual and framed by chance? Definit in piscem mulier formosa superne. -- HOR. Art. Poet. 4. A woman fair for parts superior, Ends in a fish for parts inferior. Touching this second point I go as far as my Painter, but for the other and better part I am far behinde: for my sufficiency reacheth not so far as that I dare undertake a rich, a polished, and, according to true skill, an art-like table. I have advised myself to borr ow one of Steven de la Boetic, who with this kind of work shall honor all the world. It is a discourse he entitled Voluntary_Servitude, but those who have not known him, have since very properly baptized the same, The Against-one. In his first youth he wrote, by way of Essaie, in honor of libertie_against_Tyrants. It has long since been dispersed amongst men of understanding, not without great and well deserved commendations: for it is full of wit and containeth as much learning as may be: yet does it differ much from the best he can do. And if in the age I knew him in, he would have undergone my dessigne to set his fantasies down in writing, we should doubtlesse see many rare things, and which would very meerely approch the honor of antiquity: for especially touching that part of natures gifts, I know none may be compared to him. But it was not long of him, that ever this Treatise came to mans view, and I believe he never saw it since it first escaped his hands: with certain other notes concerning the edict of Januarie, famous by reason of our intestine war, which perhaps in other places find their deserved praise. It is all I could ever recover of his reliques (whom when death seized, he by his last will and testament, left with so kind remembrance, heir and executor of his librarie and writings) besides the little book, I since caused to be published: To which his pamphlet I am particularly most bounden, for so much as it was the instrumentall meane of our first acquaintance. For it was showed me long time before I saw him; and gave me the first knowledge of his name, addressing, and thus nourishing that unspotted friendship which we (so long as it has pleased God) have so sincerely, so entire and inviolably maintained between us, that truly a man shall not commonly hear of the like; and amongst our modern men no signe of any such is seen. So many parts are re quired to the erecting of such a one, that it may be counted a wonder if fortune once in three ages contract the like. There is nothing to which Nature has more addressed us than to societie. And Aristotle says that perfect Law- givers have had more regardful care of friendship than of justice. And the utmost drift of its perfection is this. For generally, all those amities nourished by voluptuousness or profit, public or private need, are thereby so much the less fair and and so much the less true amities, in that they intermeddle other causes, scope, and fruit with friendship, than itself alone: Nor do those foure ancient kindes of friendships, Naturall, social, hospitable, and venerian, either particularly or conjointly beseeme the same. That from children to parents may rather be termed respect: Friendship is nourished by communication, which by reason of the over-great disparitie cannot be found in them, and would happly offend the duties of nature: for neither all the secret thoughts of parents can be communicated unto children, lest it might engender an unbeseeming familiaritie betweene them, nor the admonitions and corrections (which are the chiefest offices of friendship) could be exercised from children to parents. There have nations been found, where, by custom, children killed their parents, and others where parents slew their children, thereby to avoid the hindrance of enterbearing one another in after times: for naturally one dependeth from the ruine of another. There have Philosophers been found disdaining this natural conjunction: witness Aristippus, who being urged with the affection he ought his children, as proceeding from his loyns, began to spit, saying, That also that excrement proceeded from him, and that also we engendred wormes and lice. And that other man, whom Plutarke would have persuaded to agree with his brother, answered, ’I care not a straw the more for him, though he came out of the same wombe I did.’ Verily the name of Brother is a glorious name, and full of loving kindness, and therefore did he and I terme one another sworne brother: but this commixture, dividence, and sharing of goods, this joyning wealth to wealth, and that the riches of one shall be the povertie of another, does exceedingly distemper and distract all brotherly alliance, and lovely conjunction: If brothers should conduct the progresse of their advancement and thrift in one same path and course, they must necessarily oftentimes hinder and crosse one another. Moreover, the correspondencie and relation that begetteth these true and mutually perfect amities, why shall it be found in these? The father and the son may very well be of a far differing complexion, and so many brothers. He is my son, he is my kinsman; but he may be foole, a bad, or a peevish-minded man. And then according as they are friendships which the law and dutie of nature does command us, so much the less of our own voluntarie choice and liberty is there required unto it: And our genuine liberty has no production more properly her own, than that of affection and amitie. Sure I am, that concerning the same I have assaied all that might be, having had the best and most indulgent father that ever was, even to his extremest age, and who from father to son was descended of famous house, and touching this rare-seen virtue of brotherly concord very exemplare: ------ et ipse Notus in fratres ommi paterni. -- Hor ii. Od. ii 6. To his brothers known so kind, As to bear a fathers mind. To compare the affection toward women unto it although it proceed from our own free choice, a man cannot, nor may it be placed in this rank: Her fire, I confesse it (----- neque enim est dea nescia nostri Quæ dulcem curis miscat amaritiem.) (Nor is that Goddesse ignorant of me, Whose bitter-sweets with my cares mixed be.) to be more active, more fervent, and more sharpe. But it is a rash and wavering fire, waving and diverse: the fire of an ague subject to fits and stints, and that has but slender hold-fast of us. In true friendship, it is a general and universall heat, and equally tempered, a constant and setled heat, all pleasure and smoothnes, that has no pricking or stinging in it, which the more it is in lustfull love, the more is it but a raging and mad desire in following that which flies us, Come seque la lepre il cacciatore Al fredo, al caldo, alla montagna, al lito, Ne piu l’estima poi che presa vede, E sol dietro a chi fugge afretta il piede.--Arios. can. x. st. 7. Ev’n as the huntsman does the hare pursue, I n cold, in heat, on mountaines, on the shore, But cares no more, when he her ta’en espies, Speeding his pace only at that which flies. As soone as it creepeth into the termes of friendship, that is to say, in the agreement of wits, it languisheth and vanisheth away: enjoying does lose it, as having a corporall end, and subject to satietie. On the other side, friendship is enioyed according as it is desired, it is neither bred, nor nourished, nor increaseth but in jovissance, as being spirituall, and the mind being refined by use custom. Under this chief amitie, these fading affections have cometimes found place in me, lest I should speak of him, who in his verses speaks but too much of it. So are these two passions entered into me in knowledge one of another; but in comparison never: the first flying a high, and keeping a proud pitch, disdainfully beholding the other to pass her points far under it. Concerning marriage besides that it is a covenant which has nothing free but the entrance, the continuance being forced and constrained depending else-where than from our will, and a match ordinarily concluded to other ends: A thousand strange knots are therein commonly to be unknit, able to break the web, and trouble the whole course of a lively affection; whereas in friendship there is no commerce or busines depending on the same, but itself. Seeing (to speak truly) that the ordinary sufficiency of women cannot answer this conference and communication the nurse of this sacred bond: nor seem their mindes strong enough to endure the pulling of a knot so hard so fast, and durable. And truly, if without that, such a genuine and voluntarie acquaintance might be contracted, where not only mindes had this entire jovissance, but also bodies, a share of the alliance, and where a man might wholly be engaged: It is certain, that friendship would thereby be more compleat and full: But this sex could never yet by any example attaine unto it, and is by ancient schooles rejected thence. And this other Greeke licence is justly abhorred by our customs, which notwithstandnlg, because according to use it had so necessarie a disparitie of ages, and diference of offices betweene lovers, did no more sufficiently answer the perfect union and agreement, which here we require: Quis est enim iste amor amicitiiæ? cur neque deformem adolescentem quisquam amat, neque formosum senem? (Cic. Tusq. Que. iv.) ’For, what love is this of friendship? why does no man love either a deformed young man, or a beautifull old man?’ For even the picture the Academie makes of it, will not (as I suppose) disavowe me, to say thus in her behalfe: That the first fury, enspired by the son of Venus in the lovers hart, upon the object of tender youths-flower, to which they allow all insolent and passionate violences, an immoderate heat may produce, was simply grounded upon an externall beauty; a false image of corporall generation: for in the spirit it had no power, the sight whereof was yet concealed, which was but in his infancie, and before the age of budding. For, if this fury did seize upon a base minded courage, the means of its pursuit were riches, gifts, favor to the advancement of dignities, and such like vile merchandice, which they reprove. If it fell into a more generous mind, the interpositions were likewise generous: Philosophicall instructions, documents to reverence religion, to obey the laws, to die for the good of his countrie: examples of valor, wisdom and justice; the lover endevoring and studying to make himself acceptable by the good grace and beauty of his mind (that of his body being long since decayed) hoping by this mentatll societie to establish a more firme and permanent bargaine. When this pursuit attained the effect in due season (for by not requiring in a lover, he should bring leisure and discretion in his enterprise, they require it exactly in the beloved; forasmuch as he was to judge of an internall beauty, of a difficile knowledge, and abstruse discovery) then by the interposition of a spiritual beauty was the desire of a spiritual conception engendred in the beloved. The latter was here chiefest; the corporall, accidentall and second, altogether contrary to the lover. And therefore do they prefer the beloved, and verifie that the gods likewise prefer the same: and greatly blame the Poet Æschylus, who in the love betweene Achilles and Patroclus ascribeth the lovers part unto Achilles, who was in the first and beardlesse youth of his adolescency and the fairest of the Græcians. After this general communitie, the mistris and worthiest part of it, predominant and exercising her offices (they say the most availefull commodity did thereby redound both to the private and public). That it was the force of countries received the use of it, and the principal defense of equitie and liberty: witness the comfortable loves of Hermodius and Aristogiton. Therefore name they it sacred and divine, and it concerns not them whether the violence of tyrants, or the demisnesse of the people be against them: To conclude, all that can be alleged in favor of the Academy, is to say, that it was friendship, a thing which has no bad reference unto the Stoical definition of love: Amorem conatunt esse amicitiæ faciendæ ex pulchritudinis specie. (CIC. Tusc. Qu. ii,. c. 84. 2) ’That love is an endeavor of making friendship, by the show of beautie.’ I return to my description in a more equitable and equall manner. Omnino amicitiæ, corroboratis jam confirmatisque, ingeniis et ætatibus, judicandæ sunt (Cic. Amic.): ’Clearely friendships are to be judged by wits, and ages already strengthened and confirmed.’ As for the rest, those we ordinarily call friendes and amities, are but æquaintances and familiarities, tied together by some occasion or commodities, by means whereof our mindes are entertained. In the amitie I speak of, they entermixe and confound themselves one in the other, with so universall a commixture, that they weare out and can no more find the seame that has conjoined them together. If a man urge me to tell wherfore I loved him, I feel it cannot be expressed, but by answering; Because it was he, because it was myself. There is beyond all my discourse, and besides what I can particularly report of it I know not what inexplicable and fatall power a meane and a mediatrix of this indissoluble union. We sought one another before we had seen one another, and by the reports we heard one of another; which wrought greater violence in us, than the reason of reports may well bear; I think by some secret ordinance of the heavens, we embraced one another by our names. And at our first meeting which was by chance at a great feast, and solemn meeting of a whole towneship, we found ourselves so surprised, so known, so acquainted, and so combinedly bound together, that from thenceforward, nothing was so neer unto us as one unto anothers. He wrote an excellent Latyne Satyre since published; by which he excuseth and expoundeth the precipitation of our acquaintance, so suddenly come to her perfection; Sithence it must continue so short a time, and begun so late (for we were both grown men, and he some years older than my self) there was no time to be lost. And it was not to be modelled or directed by the paterne of regular and remisse friendship, wherein so many precautions of a long and preallable conversation are required. This has no other Idea than of itself, and can have no reference but to itself. It is not one especiall consideration, nor two, nor three, nor foure, nor a thousand: It is I wot not what kind of quintessence, of all this commixture, which having seized all my will, induced the same to plunge and lose itself in his, which likewise having seized all his will, brought it to lose and plunge itself in mine, with a mutual greedinesse, and with a semblable concurrance. I may truly say, lose, reserving nothing unto us, that might properly be called our own, nor that was either his or mine. When Lelius in the presence of the Roman Consuls, who after the condemnation of Tiberius Gracchus, pursued all those that had been of his acquaintance, came to enquire of Caius Blosius (Who was one of his chiefest friends) what he would have done for him, and that he answered, ’All things.’ ’What, all things?’ replied he. ’And what if he had willed you to burne our temples?’ Blosius answered, ’He would never have commanded such a thing.’ ’But what if he had done it?’ replied Lelius. The other answered, ’I would have obeyed him.’ If he were so perfect a friend to Gracchus as histories report, he needed not offend the Consuls with this last and bold confession, and should not have departed from the assurance he had of Gracchus his mind. But yet those who accuse this answer as seditious, understand not well this mysterie: and do not presuppose in what termes he stood, and that he held Gracchus his will in his sleeve, both by power and knowledge. They were rather friends than Citizens, rather friends than enemies of their countrey, or friends of ambition and trouble. Having absolutely committed themselves one to another, they perfectly held the reines of one anothers inclination: and let this yoke be guided by virtue and conduct of reason (because without them it is altogether, impossible to combine and proportion the same). The answer of Blosius was such as it should be. If their affections miscarried, according to my meaning, they were neither friends one to other, nor friends to themselves. As for the rest, this answer sounds no more than mine would do, to him that would in such sort enquire of me; if your will should command you to kill your daughter, would you do it? and that I should consent unto it: for, that heareth no witness of consent to do it: because I am not in doubt of my will, and as little of such a friends will. It is not in the power of the worlds discourse to remove me from the certaintie I have of his intentions and judgments of mine: no one of its actions might be presented unto me, under what shape soever, but I would presently linde the spring and motion of it. Our mindes have jumped so unitedly together, they have with so fervent an affection consideredof each other, and with like affection so discovered and sounded, even to the very bottome of each others heart and entrails, that I did not only know his, as well as my own, but would (verily) rather have trusted him concerning any matter of mine than my self. Let no man compare any of the other common friendships to this. I have as much knowledge of them as another, indeed of the perfectest of their kind; yet wil I not persuade any man to confound their rules, for so a man might be deceived. In these other strict friendships a man must march with the bridle of wisdom and precaution in his hand: the bond is not so strictly tied but a man may in some sort distrust the same. Love him (said Chilon) as if you should one day hate him again. Hate him as if you should love him again. This precept, so abhominable in this sovereign and mistris Amitie, is necessarie and wholesome in the use of vulgar and customarie friendships: toward which a man must employ the saying Aristotle was wont so often repeat, ’Oh ye friends, there is no perfect friend.’ In this noble commerce, offices and benefits (nurses of other amities) deserve not so much as to be accounted of: this confusion so full of our wills is cause of it: for even as the friendship I bear unto my self, admits no accrease, by any succour I give my self in any time of need, whatsoever the Stoices allege; and as I acknowledge no thanks unto my self for any service I do unto myself so the union of such friends, being truly of perfect, makes them lose the feeling of such duties, and hate, and expell from one another these words of division and difference: benefit, good deed, dutie, obligation, acknowledgement, prayer, thanks, and such their like. All things being by effect common betweene them. Wils, thoughts, judgements, goods, wives, children, honor, and life; and their mutual agreement, being no other than one soul in two bodies, according to the fit definition of Aristotle, they can neither lend or give ought to each other. See here the reason why Lawmakers, to honor marriage with some imaginary resenmblance of this divine bond, inhibite donations between husband and wife; meaning thereby to inferre, that all things should peculiarly be proper to each of them, and that they have nothing to divide and share together. If in the friendship whereof I speak, one might give unto another, the receiver of the benefit should binde his fellow. Fore each seeking more than any other thing to do each other good, he who yields both matter and occasion, is the man sheweth himself liberall, giving his friend that contentment, to effect towards him what he desires most. When the Philosopher Diogenes wanted money, he wvas wont to say that he redemanded the same of his friends, and not that he demanded it: And to show how that is practised by effect, I will relate an ancient singular example. Eudamidas the Corinthian had two friends: Charixenus a Sycionian, and Aretheus a Corinthian; being upon his death-bed, and very poore, and his two friends very rich, thus made his last will and testament: ’To Aretheus, I bequeath the keeping of my mother, and to maintaine her when she shall be old: To Charixenus the marrying of my daughter, and to give her as great a dowry as he may: and in case one of them shall chance to die before, I appoint the survivor to substitute his charge, and supply his place.’ Those that first saw this testament laughed and mocked at the same; but his heirs being advertised thereof, were very well pleased, and received it with singular contentment. And Charixenus, one of them, dying five dayes after Eudamidas, the substitution being declared in favor of Aretheus, he carefully and very kindly kept and maintained his mother, and of the five talents that he was worth he gave two and a halfe in marriage to one only daughter he had, and the other two and a halfe to the daughter of Eudamidas, whom he married both in one day. This example is very ample, if one thing were not, which is the multitude of friends: For, this perfect amity I speak of, is indivisible: each man does so wholly give himself unto his friend, that he has nothing left him to divide else-where: moreover he is grieved that he is [not] double, triple, or quadruple, and has not many soules or sundry wils, that he might conferre them all upon this subject. Common friend-ships may be divided; a man may love beauty in one, facility of behaviour in another and wisdom in another, paternity in this, fraternitie in that man, and so forth: but this amitie that possesseth the soul, and swaies it in all soveraigntie, it is impossible it should be double. If two at one instant should require helpe, to which would you run? Should they crave contrary offices of you, what order would you follow? Should one commit a matter to your silence, which if the other knew would greatly profit him, what course would you take? Or how would you discharge yourselfe? A singular and principal friendship disolveth all other duties, and freeth all othet obligations. The secret I have sworne not to reveale to another, I may without perjurie impart it unto him, who is no other but my self. It is a great and strange wonder for a man to double himself; and those that talk of tripling know not, nor cannot reach into the height of it. ’Nothing is extreme that has his like.’ And he who shal presuppose that of two I love the one as well as the other, and that they enter-love one another, and love me as much as I love them: he multiplieth in brother-hood, a thing most singular, and a lonely one, and than which one alone is also the rarest to be found in the world. The remainder of this history agrees very well with what I said; for, Eudamidas gives us a grace and favor to his friends to employ them in his need: he leaveth them as his heirs of his liberality, which consisteth in putting the means into their hands to do him good. And doubtlesse the force of friendship is much more nobly shewen in his deed than in Aretheus. To conclude, they are imaginable effects to him that has not tasted them; and which makes me wonderfully to honor the answer of that young Souldier to Cyrus, who enquiring of him what he would take for a horse with which he had lately gained the prize of a race, and whether he would change him for a Kingdome? ’No surely, my Liege (said he), yet would I willingly forgoe him to gain a true friend, could I but find a man worthy of so precious an alliance.’ He said not ill, in saying ’could I but find.’ For, a man shall easily find men fit for a superficial acquaintance; but in this, wherein men negotiate from the very centre of their harts, and make no spare of any thing, it is moste requisite all the wards and springs be sincerely wrought and perfectly true. In confederacies, which hold but by one end, men have nothing to provide for, but for the imperfections, which particularly do interest and concerne that end and respect. It is no great matter what religion my Physician or Lawyer is of: this consideration has nothing in common with the offices of that friendship they owe me. So do I in the familiar acquaintances that those who serve me contract with me. I am nothing inquisitive whether a Lackey be chaste or no, but whether he be diligent: I fear not a gaming Muletier, so much as if he be weake; nor a hot swearing Cooke, as one that is ignorant and unskilfull; I never meddle with saying what a man should do in the world; there are over man others that do it; but what my self do in the world. Mihi sic usus est: Tibi, ut opus est facto, face. -- Ter. Heau. act. i. sc. 1, 28. So is it requisite for me; Doe you as needfull is for you. Concerning familiar table-talk, I rather acquaint my self with and follow a merry conceited humor, than a wise man: And in bed I rather prefer beauty than goodnesse; and in society or conversation of familiar discourse, I respect rather sufficiencye though without Preud’hommie, and so of all things else. Even as he that was found riding on an hobby-horse, playing with his children besought him who thus surprised him not to speak of it until he were were a father himself, supposing the tender fondnesse and fatherly passion which then would posesse his mind should make him an impartiall judge of such an action; so would I wish to speak to such as had tried what I speak of: but knowing how far such an amitie is from the common use, and how seld seen and rarely found, I looke not to find a competent judge. For, even the discourses, which stern antiquitie has left us concermng this subject, seem to me but faint and forcelesse in respect of the feeling I have of it: And in that point the effects exceed the very precepts of philosophie. Nil ego contulerim jucundo sanus antico.-- Hor. i. Sat. v 44. For me, be I well in my wit. Nought, as a merry friend, so fit. Ancient Menander accounted him happy that had but met the shadow of a true friend: verily he had reason to say so, especially if he had tasted of any: for truly, if I compare all the rest of my forepassed life, which although I have, by the meere mercy of God, past at rest and ease, and except the loss of so dear a friend, free from all grievous affliction, with an ever-quietnesse of mind, as one that have taken my natural and originall commodities in good payment, without searching any others: if, as I say, I compare it all unto the foure years I so happily enjoyed the dear society of that worthy man, it is nought but a vapour, nought but a darke and yrksome light. Since the time I lost him, quem semper acerbum, Semper honoratum (sic Dii voluistis) habebo. Virg. Æn. iii. 49. Which I shall ever hold a bitter day, Yet ever honor’d (so my God t’obey). I do but languish, I do but sorrow: and even those pleasures, all things present me with, in stead of yielding me comfort, do but redouble the grief of his loss. We were copartners in all things. All things were with us at halfe; me thinkes I have stolne his part from him. ---- Nec fas esse ulla me voluptate hic frui Decrevi, tantisper dum ille abest meus particeps. -- Ter. Heau. act. 1. sc. i, 97. I have set down, no joy enjoy I may. As long as he my partner is away. I was so accustomed to be ever two, and so enured to be never single, that me thinks I am but halfe my self. Illam mea si partem animæ tulit, Maturior vis, quid moror altera, Nec charus æque nec superestes, Integer? Ille dies utramque Duxit ruinam. -- Hor. ii. Od. xvii. 5. Since that part of my soul riper fate reft me, Why stay I here the other part he left me? Not so dear, nor entire, while here I rest: That day has in one ruine both opprest. There is no action can betide me, or imagination possesse me, but I hear him saying, as indeed he would have done to me; for even as he did excel me by an infinite distance in all other sufficiencies and vertues, so did he in all offices and duties of friendship. Quis desiderio sit pudor aut modus, Tam chari capitis? -- i. Od. xxiv. 1. What modesty or measure may I bear, In want and wish of him that was so dear? O misero frater adempte mihi! Omnia tecum una perierunt gaudia nostra. Quæ tuus in vita dulcis alebat amor. Tu mea, tu moriens fregisti commoda frater. Tecum una tota est nostra sepulta anima, Cujus ego interitu tota demente fugavi Hæc studia, atque omnes delicias animi. Alloquar? audiero nunquam tua verba loquentem Numquam eqo te vita frater amabilior, Aspiciam posthac? at certe semper amabo. -- Catul. Eleg. iv. 20, 92, 23, 95, 21, 94, 25; El. i. 9. O brother rest from miserable me, All our delights are perished with you, Which your sweet love did nourish in my breath. With you my soul is all and whole inshrinde, At whose death I have cast out of my mind All my mindes sweet-meats, studies of this kind Never shall I, hear you speak, sapeake with you? Thee brother, than life dearer, ne ver see? Yet shall you ever be belov’d of me, but let us a little hear this yong man speak, being but sixteene years of age. Because I have found this work to have since been published (and to an ill end) by such as seek to trouble and subvert the state of our common-wealth, nor caring whether they shall reforme it or no; which they have fondly inserted among other writings of their invention, I have revoked my intent, which was to place it here. And lest the Authors memory should any way be interassed with those that could not throughly know his opinions and actions, they shall understand that this subject was by him treated of in his infancie, only by way of exercise, as a subject, common, bare-worne, and wyer-drawne in a thousand bookes. I will never doubt but he beleeved what he wrote, and wrote as be thought: for he was so conscientious that no lie did ever pass his lips, indeed were it but in matters of sport or play: and I know, that had it been in his choyce , he would rather have been borne at Venice than at Sarlac; and good reason why: But he had another maxime deepely imprinted in his mind, which was, carefully to obey, and religiously to submit himself to the laws, under which he was borne. There was never a better citizen, nor more affected to the welfare and quietnesse of his countrie, nor a sharper enemy of the changes, innovations, newfangles, and hurly-burlies of his time: He would more willingly have employed the utmost of his endevours to extinguish and suppresse, than to favor or further them: His mind was modelled to the patterne of other best ages. But yet in exchange of his serious treatise, I will here set you down another, more pithie, materiall, and of more consequence, by him likewise produced at that tender age. Return to CHAPTER XXVIII. NINE AND TWENTIE SONNETS OF STEVEN DE LA BOETIE, TO THE LADY OF GRAMMONT, COUNTESSE OF GUISSEN. CHAPTER XXVIII. NINE AND TWENTIE SONNETS OF STEVEN DE LA BOETIE, TO THE LADY OF GRAMMONT, COUNTESSE OF GUISSEN ADAME, I present you with nothing that is mine, either because it is already yours, or because I find nothing therein worthy of you. But wherever these verses shall be seen, for the honor which thereby shall redound to them, by having this glorious Corisanda of Andoins for their guide, I thought it good to adorn them with your worthy name. I have deemed this present fit for your Ladiship, forasmuch as there are few Ladies in France, that either can better judge of Poesie, or fitter apply the use of it, than your worthy self: and since in these her drooping days, none can give it more life, or vigorous spirit, than you, by those rich and high-tuned accords, wherewith amongst a million of other rare beauties Nature has richly graced you. Madame, these verses deserve to be cherished by you: and I am persuaded you will be of mine opinion; which is that none have come out of Gaskonie, that either had more wit or better invention and that witness to have proceeded from a richer veine. And let no jealousie possesse you, inasmuch as you have but the remainder of that which whilome I caused to be printed under the name of my Lord of Foix, your worthy, noble and dear kinsman: For truly, these have a kind of livelinesse, and more piercing Emphasis than any other, and which I cannot well express: as he that made them in his Aprile youth, and when he was enflamed with a noble glorious flame, as I will one day tell your honor in your eare. The other were afterward made by him in favor of his wife, at what time he wooed and solicited her for marriage, and began to feel I wot not what martiall chilnesse and husbands coldnesse. And I am one of those whose opinion is, that divine Poesie does no where fadge so well, and so effectually applaudeth, as in a youthfull, wanton, and unbridled subject. The above mentioned nine and twentie Sonnets of Boetie, and that in the former impressions of this book were here set down, have since been printed with his other works. Return to CHAPTER XXIX: OF MODERATION. CHAPTER XXIX: OF MODERATION. S if our sense of feeling were infected, we corrupt by our touching, things that in themselves are fair and good. We may so seize on virtue, that if we embrace it with an over greedy and violent desire, it may become vitious. Those who say, ’There is never excess in virtue, because it is no longer virtue if any excess be in it,’ do but jest at words. Insani sapiens nomen ferat, æquus iniqui, Vltra quam satis est, virtutem si petat ipsam. -- Hor. i. Epi. vi. 15. A wise man mad, just unjust, may I name, More than is meet, een virtue if he claime. Philosophy is a subtile consideration. A man may love virtue too much, and excessively demeane himself in a good action. Gods holy worde does apply itself to this byase: Be not wiser than you should, and be soberly wise. I have seen some great men, blemish the reputation of their religion, by shewing themselves religious beyond the example of men of their quality. I love temperate and indifferent natures. Immoderation towards good, if it offend me not, it amazeth, and troubleth me how I should call it. Neither Pausanias his mother, who gave the first instruction, and for her sons death brought the first stone: Not Posthumius the Dictator, that brought his own son to his end, whom the heat and forwardnesse of youth, had perhaps before his rank, made to charge his enemies, seem so just as strange unto me. And I neathe r love to persuade or follow so savage and so dear a virtue. The Archer that overshoots his marke, does no otherwise than he that shooteth short. Mine eics trouble me as much in climbing up toward a great light, as to go down into the darke. Callicles in Plato says, the extremity of Philosophy to be hurtful: and perswades no man to wade further into it than the bounds of profit: And that taken with moderation, it is pleasant and commodious, but in the end it makes a man wild and vicious, disdainfull of religion and of common laws: an enemy of civill conversation; a foe to humane sensualitie and worldly pleasures: incapable of all politike administration; and unfit to assist others or to helpe himself: apt to be without revenge buffeted, and baffled. He says true: for in her excess, she enthralleth our natural liberties, and by an importunate wile, diverts us from the fair and plaine path, which nature traceth out for us. The love we bear to women is very lawful; yet does Divinitie bridle and restraine the same. I remember to have read in Saint Thomas, in a place where he condemneth marriages of kinsfolk in forbidden degrees, this one reason amongst others: that the love a man beareth to such a woman may be immoderate; for, if the wedlocke, or husbandlike affection be sound and perfect, as it ought to be, and also surcharged with that a man oweth to alliance and kindred; there is no doubt but that surcease may easily transport a husband beyond the bounds of reason. Those Sciences that direct the manners of men, as Divinitie and Philosophy, meddles with all things. There is no action so private and secret may be concealed from their knowledge and jurisdiction. Well do they learne that search and censure their liberty. It is women who communicate their parts as much as a man list to wantonize with them: but to phisicke them bashfulness forbids them. I will then in their behalfe teach husbands this, if there be any too much flesht upon them: which is, that the very pleasures they have by the familiaritie of their wives, except moderately, used, they are reproved: and not only is that, but in any other unlawfull subjects, a man may trespasse in licentiousnesse, and offend in excess. Those shamelesse endearings, which the first heat suggests unto us in that sportfull delight, are not only undecently, but hurtfully employed towards our wives. Let them at least learne impudence from another hand. They are ever broad-waking when we need them. I have used no means but natural and simple instruction. Marriage is a religious and devout bond: and that is the reason the pleasure a man has of it should be a moderate, staied and serious pleasure, and mixed with severitie, it ought to be a voluptuousness somewhat circumspect and conscientious. And because it is the chiefest of generation, there are that make a question, whether it be lawfull to require them of copulation, as well when we have no hope of children, as when they are over-aged, or big with child. It is an homicide, according to Plato. Certain Nations (and amongst others, the Mahometane) abhorre Conjunction with women great with child. Many also with those that have their monethly disease. Zenobia received her husband but for one charge which done, all the time of her conception she let him go at random, and that past, she gave him leave to begin again: a notable and generous example of marriage. Plato borroweth the narration of some needy and hunger-starven Poet of this sport. That Jupiter one day gave his wife so hot a charge, impatient to stay till she came to bed, he laid her along upon the floors; and by the vehemence of his pleasure forgot the urgent and weighty resolutions lately concluded upon with the other gods of his celestiall court; boasting he found it as sweet at that time as he had done when first he spoiled her of her virginitie by stealthe and unknown to their parents. The Kings of Persia, called for their wives when they went to any solemn feast, but when much drinking and wine began to beat them in good earnest, they sent them to their chambers, seeing they could no longer refrain, but must needs yield to sensualitie lest they should be partakers of their immoderate lust, and in their stead sent for other women, whom this duty of respect might not concern. All pleasures and gratifications are not well placed in all sorts of people. Epaminondas had caused a dissolute young man to be imprisoned: Pelopidas intreated him, that for his sake he would set him at liberty, but he refused him, and yielded to free him at the request of an harlot of his, which likewise sued for his enlargement; saying, it was a gratification due unto a Courtizan, and not to a Captain. Sophocles being partner with Pericles in the Pretorship, seeing by chance a fair boy to pass by: ’Oh what a beauteous boy goeth yonder!’ says he to Pericles: ’That speech were more fitting another than a Pretor,’ answered Pericles, ’who ought not only to have chaste hands, but also unpolluted eyes.’ Ælius Verus the Emperor, his wife complaining that he followed the love of other women, answered, he did it for conscience sake, for so much as marriage was a name of honor and dignity, and not of foolish and lascivious lust. And our Ecclesiasticall Historie has with honor preserved the memory of that wife which sued to be devorced from her husband, because she would not second and consent to his over- insolent and lewde embracements. To conclude, there is no voluptuousuesse so just, wherein excess and intemperance is not reproachfull unto us. But to speak in good sooth, is not a man a miserable creature? He is scarce come to his own strength by his natural condition, to taste one only compleate, entire and pure pleasure, but he laboreth by discourse to cut it off: he is not wretched enough, except by art and study he augment his misery. Fortunæ miseras auximus arte vias. --Propert. iii. El. vi. 32. Fortunes unhappie ill, We amplifie by skill. Humane wisdom does foolishly seek to be ingenious in exercising herself to abate the number and diminish the pleasure of sensualities that pertaine to us: as it does favorably and industriously in employing her devises, to paint and set a luster on evils, before our eyes, and therewith to recreate our sense. Had I been chief of a faction, I would have followed a more natural course, which to say true, is both commodious and sacred, and should perhaps have made my self strong enough to limite the same. Although our spirituall and corporall Physitians: as by covenant agreed upon betweene them, find no way of recoverie, nor remedies for diseases of body and mind, but by torment, grief and pain, watching, fasting, hair-shirts, far and solitarie exile, perpetuall prison, roddes and other afflictions, have therefore been invented: But so, that they be truly afflictions, and that there be some stinging sharpnesse in them: And that the success be not as Gallios was, who having been confined to the ile of Lesbos, news came to Rome, that there he lived a merry life; and what the Senate had laid upon him for a punishment, redounded to h s commodity: whereupon they agreed to revoke him home to his own house and wife, strictly enjoyning him to keep the same, thereby to accommodate their punishment to his sense and feeling. For he to whom fasting should procure health and a merrie heart, or he to whom a posion should be more healthy than meat, it would be no longer a wholesome receipt, no more than drugs in other medicines, are of no effect to him that takes them with appetite and pleasure. Bitternesse and difficultie are circumstances fitting their operation. That nature which should take Reubarbe as familiar, should no doubt corrupt the use of it; it must be a thing that hurts the stomacke, if it shal cure it: and here the common rule failes, that infirmities are cured by their contraries: for one ill cureth another. This impression has some reference to this other so ancient, where some think they gratifie both heaven and earth by killing and massaging themselves, which was universally embraced in all religions. Even in our fathers age; Amurath at the taking of Isthmus, sacrificed six hundred young Greecians to his fathers soul; to the end their blood might serve as a propitiation to expiate the sinnes of the deceased. And in the new countries discovered in our days yet uncorrupted, and virgins, in regard of ours, it is a custom well nigh received everie where. All their idolles are sprinkled with humane blood, not without diverse examples of horrible crueltie. Some are burnt alive, and half roasted drawne from the fire, that so they may pull out their hearts and entrails; othersome, indeed women, are fleade quick, and with their yet-bleeaing skins, they invest and cover others. And no less of examples of constant resolution. For these wretched sacrifiable people, old men, women and children, some days before, go themselves begging their almes, for the offering of their sacrifice, and all of full glee, singing, and dancing with the rest, they present themselves to the slaughter. The Ambassadours of the Kings of Mexico, in declaring and magnifying the greatness of their Master to Fernando Cortez, after they had told him that he had thirty vassals, whereof each one was able to levie a hundred thousand combatants, and that he had his residence in the fairest and strongest City under heaven, added, moreover, that he had fiftie thousand to sacrifice every yeare: verily some affirme that they maintaine contiuall wars with certain mightie neighbouring Nations, not so much for the exercise and training of their youth, as that they may have store of prisoners taken in war to supply their sacrifices. In another province, to welcome the said Cortez, they sacrificed fiftie men at one clap. I will tell this one story more: Some of those people having been beaten by him, sent to know him, and to intreat him of friendship. The messengers presented him with three kinds of presents, in this manner: Lord, if you be a fierce God, that lovest to feed on flesh and blood, here are five slaves, eat them, and we will bring you more: if you be a gently mild God, here is incense and feathers; but if you be a man, take these birds and fruits, that here we present and offer unto you. Return to CHAPTER XXX: OF THE CANIBALLES CHAPTER XXX: OF THE CANIBALLES T WHAT time King Pirrhus came into Italie, after he had survaid the marshalling of the Armie, which the Romans sent against him: ’I wot not,’ said he, ’what barbarous men these are (for so were the Greeks wont to call all strange nations) ’but the disposition of this Armie, which I see, is nothing barbarous.’ So said the Greeks of that which Flaminius sent into their countrie: And Philip viewing from a Tower the order and distribution of the Romaine camp, in his kingdome under Publius Sulpitius Galba. See how a man ought to take heed, lest he over-weeningly follow vulgar opinions, which should be measured by the rule of reason, and not by the common report. I have had long time dwelling with me a man, who for the space of ten or twelve years had dwelt in that other worlde which in our age was lately discovered in those parts where Villegaignon first landed, and surnamed AntartikeFrance. This discoverie of so infinit and vast a countrie, seems worthy great consideration. I wot not whether I can warrant my self, that some other be not discovered hereafter, sithence so many worthy men, and better learned than we are, have so many ages been deceived in this. I fear me our eyes be greater than our bellies, and that we have more curiosity than capacitie. We embrace all, but we fasten nothing but wind. Plato maketh Solon to report (Plat. Tim.) that he had learn’t of the Priests of the City of Says in Egypt, that whilom, and before the general Deluge, there was a great land called Atlantis, situated at the mouth of the strait of Gibraltar, which contained more firme land than Affrike and Asia together. And that the kings of that countrie did not only possesse that Iland, but had so far entered into the main land, that of the bredth of Affrike, they held as far as Egypt; and of Europes length, as far as Tuscanie: and that they undertook to invade Asia, and to subdue all the nations that compasse the Mediterranean Sea, to the gulfe of Mare-Maggiore [the Black Sea], and to that end they traversed all Spain, France and Italie, so far as Greece, where the Athenians made head against them; but that a while after, both the Athenians themselves, and that great Iland, were swallowed up by the Deluge. It is very likely this extreme ruine of waters wrought strange alterations in the habitations of the earth; as some hold that the Sea has divided Sicilie from Italie, Hæc loca vi quandam, et vasta convulsa ruina Dissiluisse ferunt, cum protinus utraque tellus Vna foret. -- Virg Æn. iii 414, 416. Then say, sometimes this land by that forsaken, And that by this, we re split, and ruine-shaken, Whereas till then both lands as one were taken. Cypres from Suria, the Iland of Negroponto from the main land of Beotia, and in other places joined lands that were sundred by the Sea, filling with mud and sand the chanels betweene them. ------ sterilisque diu palus aptaque remis Vicinas urbes alit, et grave sentit aratrum. Hor. Art. Poet. 65. The fenne long barren, to be row’d in, now Both feeds the neighbour townes, and feeles the plow. But there is no great apparence the said Iland should be the new world world we have lately discovered; for it wellnigh touched Spain, and it were an incredible effect of inundation to have removed the same more than twelve hundred leagues, as we see it is. Besides, our modern Navigations have now almost discovered that it is not an Iland, but rather firme land, and a continent, with the East Indias on one side, and the countries lying under the two Poles on the other; from which if it be divided, it is with so narrow a strait and intervall, that it no way deserveth to be named an Iland: For, it seems there are certain motions in these vast bodies, some natural, and other some febricitant, as well as in ours. When I consider the impression my river of Dordoigne worketh in my time, toward the right shoare of her descent, and how much it has gained in twentie years, and how many foundations of diverse houses it has overwhelmed and violently carried away; I confesse it to be an extraordinarie agitation: for, should it alwaies keep one course, or had it ever kept the same, the figure of the world had ere this been overthrowne: But they are subject to changes and alterations. Sometimes they overflow and spread themselves on one side, sometimes on another; and other times they containe themselves in their natural beds or chanels: I speak not of sudden inundations, whereof we now treat the causes. In Medoc alongst the Sea-coast, my brother the Lord of Arsacke, may see a town of his buried under the sands, which the sea casteth up before it: The tops of some buildings are yet to be discerned. His Rents and Demaines have been changed into barren pastures. The inhabitants thereabouts affirme, that some years since, the Sea encrocheth so much upon them, that they have lost foure leagues of firme land: These sands are her fore- runners. And we see great hillocks of gravell moving, which march halfe a league before it, and usurpe on the firme land. The other testimony of antiquitie, to which some will refer this discoverie, is in Aristotle (if at least that little book of unheard of wonders be his) where he reporteth that cortaine Carthaginians having sailed athwart the Atlantike Sea, without the strait of Gibraltar, after long time, they at last discovered a great fertill Iland, all replenished with goodly woods, and watred with great and deepe rivers, far distant from al land, and that both they and others, allured by the goodnes and fertility of the same, went thither with their wives, children, and household, and there began to inhabit and settle themselves. The Lords of Carthage seeing their countrie by little and little to be dispeopled, made a law and express inhibition, that upon pain of death no more men should go thither, and banished all that were gone thither to dwell, fearing (as they said) that in success of time, they would so multiply as they might one day supplant them, and overthrow their own estate. This narration of Aristotle has no reference unto our new found countries. This servant I had, was a simple and rough-hewen fellow: a condition fit to yield a true testimony. For, subtile people may indeed marke more curiously, and observe things more exactly, but they amplifie and glose them: and the better to persuade, and make their interpretations of more validitie, they cannot chuse but somewhat alter the story. They never represent things truly, but fashion and maske them according to the visage they saw them in; and to purchase credit to their judgement, and draw you on to believe them, they commonly adorn, enlarge, indeed, and hyperbolize the matter. Wherein is required either a most sincere reporter, or a man so simple, that he may, have no invention to build upon, and to give a true likelihood unto false devices, and be not wedded to his own will. Such a one was my man; who besides his own report, has many times showed me diverse Mariners and Merchants, whom he had known in that voyage. So am I pleased with his information, that I never enquire what Cosmographers say of it. We had need of Topographers to make us particular narrations of the places they have been in. For some of them, if they have the advantage of us, that they have seen Palestine, will challenge a privilege, to tell us news of all the world besides. I would have every man write what he knowes, and no more: not only in that, but in all other subjects. For one may have particular knowledge of the nature of one river, and experience of the quality of one fountain, that in other things knowes no more than another man: who nevertheless to publish this little scantling, will undertake to write of all the Physickes. From which vice proceed diverse great inconveniences. Now to return to my purpose I find (as far as I have been informed) there is nothing in that nation that is either barbarous or savage, unless men call that barbarisme which is not common to them. As indeed, we have no other ayme of truth and reason, than the example and Idea of the opinions and customs of the countrie we live in. There is ever perfect religion, perfect policy, perfect and compleat use of all things. They are even savage, as we call those fruits wild which nature of herself a nd of her ordinary progresse has produced: whereas indeed, they are those which ourselves have altered by our artificiall devices, and diverted from their common order, we should rather terme savage. In those are the true and most profitable vertues, and natural properties most lively and vigorous, which in these we have bastardized, apphing them to the pleasure of our corrupted taste. And if notwithstanding, in diverse fruits of those countries that were never tilled, we shall find that in respect of ours they are most excellent, and as delicate unto our taste; there is no reason, art should gain the point of honor of our great and puissant mother Nature. We have so much by our inventions surcharged the beauties and riches of her workes, that we have altogether overchoaked her: yet where ever her puritie shineth, she makes our vain and frivolous enterprises wonderfully ashamed. Et veniunt haderæ sponte sua melius, Surgit et in solis formsior arbutus antris. Et volucres nulla dulcius arte canunt.-- Propert. i El. ii. 10. Ivies spring better of their own accord, Unhaunted spots much fairer trees afford. Birds by no art much sweeter notes record. All our endeavour or wit cannot so much as reach to represent the nest of the least birdlet, its contexture, beautie, profit and use, no nor the web of a seely spider. All things (says Plato) are produced either by nature, by fortune, or by art. The greatest and fairest by one or other of the two first, the least and imperfect by the last. Those nations seem therefore so barbarous unto me, because they have received very little fashion from humane wit, and are yet near their originall naturalitie. The laws of nature do yet command them which are but little bastardized by ours, and that with such puritie, as I am sometimes grieved the knowledge of it came no sooner to light, at what time there were men that better than we could have judged of it. I am sorie Lycurgus and Plato had it not: for me seems that what in those nations we see by experience, does not only exceed all the pictures wherewith licentious Poesie has proudly imbellished the golden age, and all her quaint inventions to faine a happy condition of man, but also the conception and desire of Philosophy. They could not imagine a genuitie so pure and simple as we see it by experience; nor ever believe our societie might be maintained with so little art and humane combination. It is a nation, would I answer Plato, that has no kind of traffike, no knowledge of Letters, no intelligence of numbers, no name of magistrate, nor of politike superioritie; no use of service, of riches or of povertie; no contracts, no successions, no partitions, no occupation but idle; no respect of kindred, but common, no apparell but natural, no manuring of lands, no use of wine, corne, or mettle. The very words that import lying, falshood, treason, dissimulations, covetousnes, envie, detraction, and pardon, were never heard of amongst them. How dissonant would he find his imaginarie common-wealth from this perfection? Hos natura modos primum dedit. Nature at first uprise, These manners did devise. Furtherrnore, they live in a country of so exceeding pleasant and temperate situation, that as my testimonies have told me, it is very rare to see a sicke body amongst them; and they have further assured me, they never saw any man there either shaking with the palsie, tooth less, with eyes dropping, or crooked and stooping through age. They are seated along the sea-coast, encompassed toward the land with huge and steepie mountaines, having betweene both, a hundred leagues or thereabout of open and champaine ground. They have great abundance of fish and flesh, that have no resemblance at all with ours, and eat them without any sawces or skill of Cookerie, but plaine boiled or broiled. The first man that brought a horse thither, althongh he had in many other voyages conversed with them, bred so great a horror in the land, that before they could take notice of him, they slew him with arrows. Their buildings are very long, and able to containe two or three hundred soules, covered with barkes of great trees, fastned in the ground at one end, enterlaced and joined close together by the tops, after the manner of some of our Granges; the covering whereof hangs down to the ground, and steadeth them as a flancke. They have a kind of wood so hard, that ryving and cleaving the same, they make blades, swords, and gridirons to broile their meat with. Their beds are of a kind of cotten cloth, fastened to the house roofe, as our ship-cabbanes: everie one has his severall couch for the women lie from their husbands. They rise with the Sunne, and feed for all day, as soone as they are up: and make no more meales atter that. They drinke not at meat, as Suidas reporteth, of some other people of the East, which dranke after meales but drinke many times a day, and are much given to pledge carowses. Their drinke is made of a certain root, and of the colour of our Claret wines, which lasteth but two or three days; they drinke it warme: It has somewhat a sharpe taste, wholesome for the stomack, nothing heady, but laxative for such as are not used unto it, yet very pleasing to such as are accustomed unto it. In stead of bread, they use a certain white composition, like unto Corianders confected. I have eaten some, the taste whereof is somewhat sweet and wallowish. They spend the whole day in dancing. Their young men go a hunting after wild beasts with bowes and arroes. Their women busie themselves therewhil’st with warming of their drinke, which is their chiefest office. Some of their old men, in the morning before they go to eating, preach in common to all the household, walking from one end of the house to the other, repeating one self-same sentence many times, till he have ended his turn (for their buildings are a hundred paces in length) he commends but two things unto his auditorie. First valor against their enemies, then lovingnesse unto their wives. They never misse (for their restrainte) to put men in mind of this dutie, that it is their wives whiche keep their drinke luke-warme and well-seasoned. The form of their beds, cords, swords blades, and woodden bracelets, wherewith they cover their hand wrists, when they fight, and great Canes open at one end, by the sound of which they keep time and cadence in their dancing, are in many places to be seen, and namely in my own house. They are shaven all over, much more close and cleaner than we are, with no other Razors than of wood or stone. They believe their soules to be eternall, and those that have deserved well of their Gods to be placed in that part of heaven where the Sunne riseth, and the cursed toward the West in opposition. They have certain Prophets and Priests which commonly abide in the mountaines, and very seldom show themselves unto the people; but when they come down there is a great feast prepared, and a solemn assembly of manie towneshipes together (each grange as I have described maketh a village, and they are about a French league one from another.) The Prophet speaks to the people in public, exhorting them to embrace virtue, and follow their dutie. All their moral discipline containeth but these two articles; first an undismaied resolution to war, then an inviolable affection to their wives. He does also Prognosticate of things to come, and what success they shall hope for in their enterprises he neither swadeth or disswadeth them from war but if he chance to misse of his divination, and that it succeed otherwise than he foretold them, if he be taken, he is hewen in a thousand peeces, and condemned for a false Prophet. And therefore he that has once misreckoned himself is never seen again. Divination is the gift of God; the abusing whereof should be a punishable imposture. When the Divines amongst the Scythians had foretold an untruth, they were couched along upon hurdles full of heath or brushwood, drawne by oxen, and so manicled hand and foot, burned to death. Those which manage matters subject to the conduct of man’s sufficiencie are excusable, although they show the utmost of their skill. But those that gull and conicatch us with the assurance of an extraordinarie facultie, and which is beyond our knowledge, ought to be double punished; first because they performe not the effect of their promise, then for the rashnesse of their imposture and unadvisednesse of their fraud. They war against the nations that lie beyond their mountaines, to which they go naked, having no other weapons than bowes or woodden swords, sharpe at one end as our broaches are. It is an admirable thing to see the constant resolution of their combats, which never end but by effusion of blood and murther: for they know not what fear or rowts are. Every Victor brings home the head of the enemy he has slain as a Trophey of his victory, and fasteneth the same at the entrance of his dwelling place. After they have long time used and entreated their prisoners well, and with all commodities they can devise, he that is the Master of them; sommining a great assembly of his acquaintance; tieth a corde to one of the prisoners arms, by the end whereof he holds him fast, with some distance from him, for fear he might offend him, and gives the other arm, bound in like manner, to the dearest friend he has, and both in the presence of all the assembly kill him with swords: which done, they roast and then eat him in common, and send some slices of him to such of their friends as are absent. It is not, as some imagine, to nourish themselves with it (as anciently the Scithians wont to do), but to represent an extreme and inexpiable revenge. Which we prove thus; some of them perceiving the Portugales, who had confederated themselves with their adversaries, to use another kind of death when they took them prisoners; which was, to burie them up to the middle, and against the upper part of the body to shoot arrows, and then being almost dead, to hang them up; they supposed, that the people of the other world (as they who had sowed the knowledge of many vices amongst their neighbors, and were much more cunning in all kindes of evils and mischief than they) under-took not this manner of revenge without cause, and that consequently it was more smartfull and cruel than theirs, and thereupon began to leave their old fashion to follow this. I am not sorie we note the barbarous horror of such an action, but grieved, that prying so narrowly into their faults we are so blinded in ours. I think there is more barbarisme in eating men alive, than to feed upon them being dead; to mangle by tortures and torments a body full of lively sense, to roast him in peeces, and to make dogs and swine to gnaw and teare him in mammocks (as we have not only read, but seen very lately, indeed in our own memory, not amongst ancient enemies, but our neighbors and fellow-citizens; and which is worse, under pretence of pietie and religion) than to roast and eat him after he is dead. Chrysippus and Zeno, arch-pillars of the Stoice sect, have supposed that it was no hurt at all in time of need, and to what end soever, to make use of our carrion bodies, and to feed upon them, as did our forefathers, who being besieged by Cæsar in the City of Alexia, resolved to sustain the famine of the siege, with the bodies of old men, women, and other persons unserviceable and unfit to fight. Vascones (fama est) alimentis talibus usi Produxere ammas .-- Juven. Sat. xv. 93. Gascoynes (as fame reports) Liv’d with meats of such sortes. And Physitians fear not, in all kindes of compositions availefull to our health, to make use of it, be it for outward or inward applications. But there was never any opinion found so unnaturall and immodest, that would excuse treason, treacherie, disloyaltie, tyrannie, crueltie, and such like, which are our ordinary faults. We may then well call them barbarous, in regard to reasons rules, but not in respect of us that exceed them in all kindes of barbarisme. Their wars are noble and generous and have as much excuse and beautie as this humane infirmitie may admit: they ayme at nought so much, and have no other foundation amongst them, but the meere jelousie of virtue. They contend not for the gaining of new lands; for to this day they yet enioy that natural ubertie and fruitfulnesse, which without labouring toyle, does in such plenteous abundance furnish them with all necessary things, that they need not enlarge their limits. They are yet in that happy estate as they desire no more than what their natural necessities direct them: whatsoever is beyond it, is to them superfluous. Those that are much about one age, do generally enter- call one another brethren, and such as are younger they call children, and the aged are esteemed as fathers to all the rest. These leave this full possession of goods in common, and without division to their heirs, without other claim or title but that which nature does plainely impart unto all creatures, even as she brings them into the world. If their neighbors chance to come over the mountaines to assaile or invade them, and that they get the victory over them, the Victors conquest is glory, and the advantage to be and remaine superior in valor and virtue: else have they nothing to do with the goods and spoyles of the vanquished, and so return into their countrie, where they neither want any necessarie thing, nor lacke this great portion, to know how to enjoy their condition happily, and are contented with what nature affoordeth them. So do these when their turn commeth. They require no other ransome of their prisoners, but an acknowledgement and confession that they are vanquished. And in a whole age, a man shall not find one that does not rather embrace death, than either by word or countenance remissely to yield one jot of an invincible courage. There is none seen that would not rather be slain and devoured, than sue for life, or show any fear. They use their prisoners with all liberty, thatl they may so much the more hold their lives dear and precious, and commonly entertaine them with threats of future death, with the torments they shall endure, with the preparations intended for that purpose, with mangling and slicing of their members, and with the feast that shall be kept at their charge. All which is done, to wrest some remisse, and exact some faint yielding speech of submission from them, or to possesse them with a desire to escape or run away; that so they may have the advantage to have danted and made them afraid, and to have forced their constancy. For certainly true victory consisteth in that only point. ------ Victoria nulla est Quam quæ confessos animo quoque subjugat hostes. -- Claud. vi. Cons. Hon. Pan. 245. No conquest such, as to suppresse Foes hearts, the conquest to confesse. The Hungarians, a most war-like nation, were whilome wont to pursue their prey Tio longer than they had forced their enemy to yield unto their mercy. For, having wrested this confession from him, they set him at liberty without offence or ransome, except it were to make him sweare never after to bear arms against them. We get many advantages of our enemies, that are but borrowed and not ours: It is the quality of porterly- rascall, and not of virtue, to have stronger arms and sturdier legs: Disposition is a dead and corporall quality. It is a tricke of fortune to make our enemy stoop, and to bleare his eyes with the Sunnes-light: It is a pranke of skill and knowledge to be cunning in the art of fencing, and which may happen unto a base and worthelesse man. The reputation and worth of a man consisteth in his heart and will: therin consists true honor: Constancie is valor, not of armesand legs but of mind and courage; it consisteth not of the spirit and courage of our horse, nor of our arms, but in ours. He that obstinately faileth in his courage, Si succiderit, de genu pugnat. ’If he slip or fall he fights upon his knee.’ He that in danger of imminent death is no whit danted in his assurednesse; he that in yielding up his ghost beholding his enemy with a scornefull and fierce looke, he is vanquished, not by us, but by fortune: he is slain, but not conquered. The most valiant are often the most unfortunate. So are there triumphant losses in envie of victories. Not those foure sister victories, the fairest that ever the Sunne beheld with his allseeing eye, of Salamis, of Plateæ, of Mycale, and of Sicilia, durst ever dare to oppose all their glory together to the glory of the King Leonidas his discomfiture and of his men, at the passage of Thermopylæ: what man did ever run with so glorious an envie or more ambitious desire to the goale of a combat, than Captain Ischolas to an evident loss and overthrow? who so ingeniously or more politikely did ever assure himself of his welfare than he of his ruine? he was appointed to defend a certain passage of Peloponesus against the Arcadians, which finding himself altogether unable to performe, seeing the nature of the place and inequalitie of the forces, and resolving that whatsoever should present itself unto his enemy, must necessarily be utterly defeated: On the other side, deeming it unworthy both his virtue and magnanimity, and the Lacedemonian name, to faile or faint in his charge, betweene these two extremities he resolved upon a meane and indifferent course, which was this. The youngest and best-disposed of his troupe he reserved for the service and defense of their countrie, to which he sent them backe; and with those whose loss was least, and who might best be spared, he determined to maintaine that passage, and by their death to force the enemy to purchase the entrance of it as dear as possibly he could; as indeed it followed. For being suddenly environed round by the Arcadians, after a great slaughter made of them, both himself and all his were put to the sword. Is any Trophey assigned for conquerours that is not more duly due unto these conquered? A true conquest respecteth rather an undanted resolution, an honorable end, than a fair escape, and the honor of virtue does more consist in combating than in beating. But to return to our historie, these prisoners, however they are dealt withall, are so far from yielding, that contrariwise during two or three moneths that they are kept, they ever carry a cheerfull countenance, and urge their keepers to hasten their trial, they outragiously dote and injure them. They upbraid them with their cowardlinesse, and with the number of battles they have lost again theirs. I have a song made by a prisoner, wher ein is this clause, ’Let them boldly come altogether, and flocks in multitudes, to feed on him; for with him they shall feed upon their fathers and grandfathers, that heretofore have served his body for food and nourishment: These muscles,’ says he, ’this flesh, and these veines, are your own; foolish men as you are, know you not that the substance of your forefathers limbes is yet tied unto ours? Taste them welle for in them shall you find the relish of your own flesh:’ An invention, that has no show of barbarisme. Those that paint them dying, and that represent this action, when they are put to execution, delineate the prisoners spitting in their executioners faces, and making mowes at them. Verily, so long as breath is in their body they never cease to brave and defie them, both in speech and countenance. Surely in respect of us these are very savage men: for either they must be so in good sooth, or we must be so indeed; There is a wondrous difference betweene their form and ours. Their men have many wives, and by how much more they are reputed valiant so much the greater is their number. The manner and beautie of their marriages is wondrous strange and remarkable: For, the same jealousie our wives have to keep us from the love and affection of other women, the same have theirs to procure it. Being more careful for their husbands honor and content than of any thing else, they endeavor and apply all their industrie to have as many rivals as possibly they can, forasmuch as it is a testimony of their husbands virtue. Our women would count it a wonder, but it is not so: It is virtue properly Matrimoniall, but of the highest kind. And in the Bible, Lea, Rachell, Sara, and Iacobs wives brought their fairest maiden servants into their husbands beds. And Livia seconded the lustfull appetites of Augustus to her great prejudice. And Stratonica, the wife of King Dejotarus did not only bring the most beauteous chamber-maide that served her to her husbands bed, but very carefully brought up the children he begot on her, and by all possible means aided and furthered them to succeed in their fathers royalty. And least a man should think that all this is done by a simple and servile or awefull dutie unto their custom, and by the impression of their ancient customs authority, without discourse or judgement, and because they are so blockish and dull- spirited, that they can take no other resolution, it is not amisse we alleage some evidence of their sufficiencie. Besides what I have said of one of their warlike songs, I have another amorous canzonet, which beginneth in this sense: ’Adder stay, stay good adder, that my sister may by the patterne of your partie-coloured coat drawe the fashion and work of a rich lace, for me to give unto my love; so may your beautie, your nimblenesse or disposition be ever preferred before all other serpents.’ The first couplet is the burden of the song. I am so conversant with Poesie that I may judge this invention has no barbarisme at all in it, but is altogether Anacreontike. Their language is a kind of pleasant speech, and has a pleasing sound, and some affinitie with the Greeke terminations. Three of that nation, ignorant how dear the knowledge of our corruptions will one day cost their repose, securitie, and happinesse, and how their ruine shall proceed from this commerce, which I imagine is already well advanced (miserable as they are to have suffered themselves to be so cosened by a desire of new-fangled novelties, and to have quit the calmnesse of their climate to come and see ours), were at Roane in the time of our late King Charles the ninth, who talked with them a great while. They were showed our fashions, our pompe, and the form of a fair citie; afterward some demanded their advice, and would needs know of them what things of note and admirable they had observed amongst us: they answered three things, the last of which I have forgotten, and am very sorie for it, the other two I yet remember. They said, ’First they found it very strange that so many tall men with long beards, strong and well armed, as it were about the Kings person [it is very likely they meant the Switzers of his guard] would submit themselves to obey a beardlesse child, and that we did not rather chuse one amongst them to command the rest.’ Secondly (they have a manner of phrase whereby they call men but a moytie one of another.) ’They had perceived there were men amongst us full gorged with all sorts of commodities, and others which, hunger- starved and bare with need and povertie, begged at their gates: and found it strange these moyties so needy could endure such an injustice, and that they took not the others by the throate, or set fire on their houses.’ I talked a good while with one of them, but I had so bad an interpreter, who did so ill apprehend my meaning, and who through his foolishnesse was so troubled to conceive my imaginations, that I could draw no great matter from him. Touching that point, wherein I demanded of him what good he received by the superioritie he had amongst his countriemen (for he was a Captain and our Mariners called him King), he told me it was to march foremost in any charge of war: further, I asked him how many men did follow him, he showed me a distance of place, to signifie they were as many as might be contained in so much round, which I guessed to be about 4 or 5 thousand men: moreover, demanded if when wars were ended, all his authority expired; he answered, that he had only this left him, which was, that when he went on progresse, and visited the villages depending of him, the inhabitants prepared paths and high-waies athwart the hedges of their woods, for him to pass through at ease. All this is not very ill; but what of that? They weare no kind of breeches nor hosen. Return to CHAPTER XXXI: THAT A MAN OUGHT SOBERLY TO MEDDLE WITH JUDGING OF DIVINE LAWES. CHAPTER XXXI: THAT A MAN OUGHT SOBERLY TO MEDDLE WITH JUDGING OF DIVINE LAWES. HINGS unknown are the true scope of imposture and subject of Legerdemaine: forasmuch as strangenesse itself does first give credit unto matters, and not being subject to our ordinary discourses, they deprive us of means to withstand them. To this purpose, said Plato, ’it is an easier matter to please, speaking of the nature of the Gods than of men: For the Auditors ignorance lends a fair and large cariere and free liberty, to the handling of secret hidden Matters. Whence it followeth that nothing is so firmly beleeved as that which a man knows least; nor are there people more assured in their reports than such as tell us fables, as Alchumists, Prognosticators, Fortune-tellers, Palmesters, Physitians, id genus omne, ’and such like.’ To which, if I durst, I would join a rable of men that are ordinary interpreters and controulers of Gods secret desseignes, presuming to find out the causes of every accident, and to prie into the secrets of Gods divine will, the incomprehensible motives of his works. And howbeit the continuall varietie and discordance of events drive them from one corner to another, and from East to West, they will not leave to follow their bowle, and with one small pensill drawe both white and blacke. There is this commendable observance in a certain Indian nation, who if they chance to be discomfited in any skirmish or battle, they publikely beg pardon of the Sunne, who is their God, as for an unjust action, referring their good or ill fortune to divine reason, submitting their judgement and discourses unto it. It suffiseth a Christian to believe that all things come from God, to receive them from his divine and inscrutable wisdom with thanksgiving, and in what manner soever they are sent him, to take them in good part. But I utterly disalow a common custom amongst us, which is to ground and establish our religion upon the prosperitie of our interprises. Our beleefe has other sufficient foundations, and need not be authorized by events. For the people accustomed to these plausible arguments, and agreeing with his taste, when events sort contrary and disadvantageous to their expectation, they are in hazard to waver in their faith. As in the civil wars, wherein we are now for religions sake. those which got the advantage at the conflict of Rochelabeille, making great joy and bone-fires for that accident, and using that fortune as an assured approbation of their faction: when afterward they come to excuse their disaster of Mont-contour and Jarnac, which are scourges and fatherly chastisements: if they have not a people wholy at their mercy, they will easily make him perceive what it is to take two kinds of corne out of one sacke: and from one and the same mouth to blow both hot and cold. It were better to entertaine it with the true foundations of veritie. It was a notable Sea battle which was lately gained against the Turkes under the conduct of Don John of Austria. But it has pleased God to make us at other times both see and feel other such, to our no small loss and detriment. To conclude, it is no easy matter to reduce divine things unto our balance, so they suffer no impeachment: And he that would yield a reason why Arrius and Leo his Pope, chief Principals and main supporters of this heresie, died both at several times of so semblable and so strange deaths (for being forced through a violent belly-ache to go from their disputations to their close-stoole, both suddenly yielded up their ghosts on them), and exaggerate that divine vengeance by the circumstance of the place, might also adde the death of Heliogabalus unto it, who likewise was slain upon a privie. But what? Ireneus is found to be engaged in like fortune: Gods intent being to teach us that the good have some thing else to hope for, and the wicked somewhat else to fear, than the good or bad fortune of this world: He manageth and applieth them according to his secret disposition: and depriveth us of the means thereby foolishly to make our profit. And those that according to humane reason will thereby prevaile do but mocke themselves. They never give one touch of it, that they receive not two for it. S. Augustine gives a notable trial of it upon his adversaries. It is a conflict no more decided by the arms of memory than by the weapons of reason. A man should be satisfied with the light which it pleaseth the Sunne to communicate unto us by virtue of his beames; and he that shall lift up his eyes to take a greater within his body, let him not think it strange if for a reward of his over-weening and arrogancie he loses his sight. Quis hominum potesi scire consiliun Dei? aut quis poterit cogitare, quid velit dominus?(1 Wisd. ix. 13. ) Who amongst men can know Gods counsell, or who can think that God will do? Return to CHAPTER XXXII: TO AVOID VOLUPTUOUSNESSE IN REGARD OF LIFE CHAPTER XXXII: TO AVOID VOLUPTUOUSNESSE IN REGARD OF LIFE HAVE noted the greatest part of ancient opinions to agree in this: That when our life affords more evil than good, it is then time to die: and to preserve our life to our torment and incommoditie, is to spurre and shocke the very rules of nature: as say the old rules. Ν ζην η θαηνειν ευδαιοως -- Gnom. Græc. Or live without distresse, Or die with happinesse. Καλον το θνησκειν οις υβριν το ζην φερει --Ibid. Tis good for them to die, Whom life brings infamie. Κρεισσν το η ζην εοτιν, η ζην αθλιως -- Soph. Stob. Ser. 118. ’Tis better not to live, Than wretchedly not thrive. But to drive off the contempt of death to such a degree as to employ it to distract and remove himself from honors, riches, greatness, and other goods and favors, which we call the goods of fortune: as if reason had not enough to do to persuade us to forgoe and leave them, without adding this new surcharge unto it, I had neither seen the same commanded nor practised until such time as one place of Seneca came to my hands, wherein counselling Lucilius (a man mightie and in great authority about the Emperor) to change this voluptuous and pompous life, and to withdraw himself from this ambition of the world, to some solitarie, quiet, and philosophicall life: about which Lucilius alleged some difficulties: ’My advice is’ (says he) ’that either you leave and quit that life, or your life altogether: But I persuade you to follow the gentler way, and rather to- untie than breake what you hast so ill knit: alwaies provided you breake it, if you canst not otherwise untie the same.’ Ihere is no man so base minded that loves not rather to fall once than ever to remaine in fear of falling. I should have deemed this counsell agreeing with the Stoices rudenes; But it is more strange it should be borrowed of Epicurus, who to that purpose writeth consonant to this unto Idomeneus. Yet think I to have noted some such like thing amongst our own people, but with Christian moderation. Saint Hilarie, Bishop of Poitiers, a famous enemy of the Arrian heresie, being in Syria, was advertised that Abra, his only daughter, whom he had left at home with her mother, was by the greatest Lords of the countrie solicited and sued unto for marriage, as a damosell very well brought up, fair, rich, and in the prime of her age: he wrote unto her (as we see) that she should remove her affections from all the pleasures and advantages might be presented her; for in his voyage he had found a greater and worthier match or husband of far higher power and magnificence, who should present and endow her with roabes and jewels of unvaluable price. His purpose was to make her lose the appetite and use of daily pleasures, and wholly to wed her unto God. Also which, deeming his daughters death, the shortest and most assured way, he never ceased by vows, prayers and orisons, humbly to beseech God to take her out of this world, and to call her to his mercy, as it came to pass; for she deceased soone after his return, whereof he showed manifest tokens of singular gladnesse. This man seems to endeere himself above others, in that at first sight he addresseth himself to this meane, which they never embrace but subsidiarily, and sithence it is towards his only daughter. But I will not omit the success of this story, although it be not to my purpose. Saint Hilaries wife, having understood by him how her daughters death succeeded with his intent and will, and how much more happy it was for her to be dislodged from out this world than still to abide therein, conceived so lively an apprehension of the eternall and heavenly blessednesse, that with importunate instancie she solicited her husband to do as much for her. And God, at their earnest entreaty and joint-common prayers, having soone after taken her unto himself, it was a death embraced with singular and mutual contentment to both. Renascence Editions Return to CHAPTER XXXIII: THAT FORTUNE IS OFTENTIMES MET WITHALL IN PURSUIT OF REASON CHAPTER XXXIII: THAT FORTUNE IS OFTENTIMES MET WITHALL IN PURSUIT OF REASON HE INCONSTANCIE of Fortunes diverse wavering is the cause she should present us with all sorts of visages. Is there any action of justice more manifest than this? Cesar Borgia, Duke of Valentinois, having resolved to Adrian, Cardinall of Cornetto, with whom Pope Alexander the sixth, his father, and he were to sup that night in Vaticane, sent certain bottles of empoysoned wine before, and gave his butler great charge to have a speciall care of it. The Pope coming thither before his son, and calling for some drinke, the butler supposing the wine had been so carefully commended unto him for the goodnesse of it, immediately presented some unto the Pope, who while he was drinking his son came in, and never imagining his bottles had been touched, took the cup and pledged his father, so that the Pope died presently; and the son, after he had long time been tormented with sicknesse, recovered to another worse fortune. It somtimes seems that when we least think on her, she is pleased to sport with us. The Lord of Estree, then guidon to the Lord of Vandosme, and the Lord of Liques, Lieutenant to the Duke of Ascot, both servants to the Lord of Foungueselles sister, albeit of contrary factions (as it happens among neigbouring bordurers) the Lord of Liques got her to wife: But even upon his wedding day, and which is worse, before his going to bed, the bridegroome desiring to breake a staffe in favor of his new Bride and Mistris, went out to skirmish near to Saint Omer where the Lord of Estree being the stronger, took him prisoner, and to endeare his advantage, the Lady herself was faine, Conjugis ante coacta novi dimittere collum, Quam veniens una atque altera rursus heyems. Noctib us in longis avidum saturraset amorem, --Catul. Ele. iv. 81. Her new feeres necke forced was she to forgoe, Ere winters one and two, returning sloe, In long nights had ful-fil’d Her love so eager wil’d, in courtesy, to sue unto him for the deliverie of his prisoner, which he granted; the French Nobilitie never refusing Ladies any kindness. Seemeth she not to be a right artist? Constantine, the son of Helen, founded the Empire of Constantinople, and so, many ages after, Constantine the son of Helen ended the same. She is sometimes pleased to envie our miracles: we hold an opinion, that King Clovis besieging Angoulesme, the wals by a divine favor fell of themselves. And Bouchet borroweth of some author, that King Robert beleagring a City, and leaving secretly stolne away from the siege to Orleans, there to solemnize the feasts of Saint Aignan, as he was in his earnest devotion, upon a certain passage of the Masse, the walles of the town, besieged without any battery, fell flat to the ground. She did altogether contrary in our wars of Milan; for, Captain Rense, beleagring the City of Eronna for us, and having caused a forcible mine to be wrought under a great curtine of the walls, by force whereof, it being violently flowne up from out the ground, did notwithstanding, whole and unbroken, fall so right into his foundation again, that the besieged found no inconvenience at all by it. She sometimes playeth the Physitian. Jason Phereus, being utterly forsaken of all Physitians, by reason of an impostume he had in his breast, and desirous to be rid of it, though it were by death, as one of the forlorn hope, rusht into a battle amongst the thickest throng of his enemies, where he was so rightly wounded acrosse the body, that his impostume broke, and he was cured. Did she not exceed the Painter Protogenes in the skill of his trade? who having perfected the image of a wearie and panting dog, and in all parts over-tired, to his content, but being unable, as he desired, lively to represent the drivel or slaver of his mouth, vexed against his own work, took his spunge, and, moist as it was with diverse colours, threw it at the picture, with purpose to blot and deface all he had done, fortune did so fitly and rightly carrie the same towards the dogs chaps that there it perfectly finished what his art could never attaine unto. Does she not sometimes addres e and correct our counsels? Isabell Queene of England, being to repasse from Zeland into her Kingdome with an army, in favor of her son against her husband, had utterly been cast away had she come unto the port intended, bemg there expected by her enemies; but fortune, against her will, brought her to another place, where she safely landed. And that ancient fellow, who, hurling a stone at a dog, misst him, and there withall hit and slew his step-dame, had [he] not reason to pronounce this verse, Ταυτοατον ηων καλλιω βονλευται Chance of itself, than we, Does better say and see? Fortune has better advice than we. Icetas had practised and suborned two soldiers to kill Timoleon, then residing at Adrane in Sicily. They appointed a time to do, as he should be assisting at some sacrifice; and scattering themselves amongst the multitude, as they were winking one upon another, to show how they had a very fit opportunity to do the deed, lo here a third man, that with a huge blow of a sword striketh one of them over the head, and fels him dead to the ground and so runs away. His fellow, supposing himself discovered and undone, runs to the altar, suing for sanctuarie, with promise to confesse the truth even as he was declaring the conspiracie, behold the third man, who had likewise been taken, whom as a murtherer the people tugged and hauled through the throng toward Timoleon and the chiefest of the assembly, where he humbly calleth for mercy, alleging that he had justly murthered the murtherer of his father, whom his good chance was to find there, averring by good witnesses before them all, that in the City of the Leontines, his father had been proditoriously slain by him on whom he had now revenged himseIfe. In neede whereof, because he had been so fortunate in seeking to right his fathers untimely death, to save the common father of the Sicilians from so imminent a danger, he had ten Attike mines awarded him. Thus Fortune in her directions exceedeth all the rules of humane wisdom. But to conclude: is not an express application of her favor, goodnesse, and singular pietie manifestly discovered in this action? Ignatius, the Father and the Sonne, both banished by proscription by the Triumvirs of Rome, resolved on this generous act, to yield their lives one into anothers hands, and therebi frustrate the tyrants cruelty. They furiously, with their keene rapiers drawne, ran one against another: Fortune so directed their points that each received his mortal stroke; adding to the honor of seld-seen an amity, that they had just so much strength left them to draw their armed and bloudy hands from out their goared wounds, in that plight so fast to embrace and so hard to claspe one another, that the hangmen were forced, at one stroke and together, to cut off both their heads; leaving their bodies for ever tied in so honorable a knot, and their wounds so joined, that they lovingly drew and suckt each others blood, breath, and life. Return to CHAPTER XXXIV: OF A DEFECT IN OUR POLICIES CHAPTER XXXIV: OF A DEFECT IN OUR POLICIES Y whilome father, a man who had no helpe but from experience and his own nature, yet of an unspotted judgement, has heretofore told me, that he much desired to bring in this custom, which is, that in all cities there should be a certain appointed place to which, whosoever should have need of any thing, might come and cause his business to be registered by some officer appointed for that purpose: As, for example, if one have pearls to sell, he should say, I seek to sell some pearls: and another, I seek to buy some pearls. Such a man would faine have companie to travell to Paris; such a one enquireth for a servant of this or that quality; such a one seeketh for a master, another a workman; some this, some that; every man as he needed. And it seems that this means of enter-warning one another would bring no small commoditie into common commerce and societie; for there are ever conditions that enter-seek one another, and because they understand not one another, they leave men in great necessities. I understand, to the infamous reproach of our age, that even in our sight two most excellent men in knowledge having miserably perished for want of food and other necessaries: Lilius Gregorius Giraldus in Italy, and Sebastianus Castalio in Germany. And I verily believe there are many thousands who, had they known or understood their wants, would sither have sent for them, and with large stipends entertained them, or would have convaid them succour, where ever they had been. The world is not so generally corrupted, but I know some that would earnestly wish, and with harty affections desire, the goods which their forefathers have left them, might, so long as it shall please fortune they may enjoy them, be emploied for the reliefe of rare and supply of excellent mens necessitie, and such as for any kind of worth and virtue are remarkable; many of which are daily seen to be pursued by ill fortune even to the utmost extremity, and that would take such order for them, as, had they not their ease and content, it might only be imputed to their want of reason or lacke of discretion. In this economicke or houshold order, my father had this order, which I can commend, but no way follow: which was, that besides the day-book of household affairs, wherein are registred at least expenses, paiments, gifts, bargains and sales, that require not a Notaries hand to them, which book a receiver had the keeping of: he appointed another journall-book to one of his servants, who was his clerke, wherein he should insert and orderly set down all accidents worthy of the noting. and day by day register the memories of the historie of his house: a thing very pleasant to read when time began to weare out the remembrance of them, and fit for us to pass the time withall, and to resolve some doubts: when such a work was begun, when ended, what way or course was taken, what accidents hapned how long it continued; all our voyages, where, and how long we were from home; our marriages, who died, and when; the receiving of good or bad tidings, who came, who went, changing or removing of household officers, taking of new or discharging of old servants, and such like matters. An ancient custom, and which I would have all men use and bring into fashion again in their several homes: and I repent my self I have so foolishly neglected the same. Return to CHAPTER XXXV: OF THE USE OF APPARELL. CHAPTER XXXV: OF THE USE OF APPARELL. HATSOEVER I aime at, I must needs force some of customs contradictions, so carefully has she barred all our entrances. I was devising in this chil-cold season whether the fashion of these late discovered nations to go naked, be a custom forced by the hot temperature of the air, as we say of the Indians and Moores, or whether it be an original manner of mankind. Men of understanding, forasmuch as whatsoever is contained under heaven (as says the Holy Writ) is subject to the same laws, are wont in such like considerations, where natural laws are to be distinguished from those invented by man, to have recourse to the general policy of the world, where nothing that is counterfet can be admitted. Now, all things being exactly furnished else-whence with all necessaries to maintaine this being, it is not to be imagined that we alone should be produced in a defective and indigent estate, indeed, and in such a one as cannot be maintained without forrain helpe. My opinion is, that even as all plants, trees, living creatures, and whatsoever has life, is naturally seen furnished with sufficient furmture to defend itself from the injurie of all wethers: Proptereaque fere res omnes, aut corio sunt, Aut seta, aut conchis, aut cano, aut cortice tectæ. -- LUCR. iv. 932. Therefore all things almost we cover’d marke, With hide, or hair, or shels, or brawne, or barke. Even so were we. But as those who by an artificiall light extinguish the brightnesse of the day, we have quenched our proper means by such as we have borrowed. And we may easily discerne that only custom makes that seem impossible unto us which is not so: For of those nations that have no knowledge of cloaths, some are found situated under the same heaven, and climate or parallel, that we are in, and more cold and sharper than ours. Moreover, the tenderest parts of us are ever bare and naked, as our eyes, face, mouth nose, and ears; and our country swaines (as our fore, fathers wont) most of them at this day go bare-breasted down to the navill. Had we been borne needing petticoats and breeches, there is no doubt but Nature would have armed that which she has left to the batteries of seasons and fury of wethers with some thicker skin or hide, as she has done our fingers ends and the soales of our feet. Why seems this hard to be believed? Betweene my fashion of apparell and that of one of my countrie-clownes, I find much more difference betweene him and me than betweene his fashion and that of a man who is cloathed but with his bare skin. How many men (especially in Turkie) go ever naked for devotions sake? A certain man demanded of one of our loytring rogues whom in the deep of frosty Winter he saw wandering up and down with nothing but his shirt about him, and yet as blithe and lusty as anot her that keepes himself muffled and wrapt in wanne furres up to the ears; how he could have patience to go so. ’And have not you, good Sir’ (answered he) ’your face all bare? Imagine I am all face.’ The Italians report (as far as I remember) of the Duke of Florence his fool, who when his Lord asked him how, being so ill-clad, he could endure the cold, which he hardly was able to do himself; to whom the foole replied: ’Master, use but my receipt and put all the cloaths you have upon you, as I do all mine; you shall feel no more cold than I do.’ King Massinissa, even in his eldest days, were it never so cold, so frosty, so stormie, or sharpe wether, could never be induced to put something on his head, but went alwaies bareheaded. The like is reported of the Emperor Severus. In the battles that past betweene the Egyptians and the Persians, Herodotus says, that both himself and diverse others took speciall notice that of such as lay slain on the ground the Egyptians sculs were without comparison much harder than the Persians: by reason that these go ever with their heads covered with coifs and turbants, and those from their infancie ever shaven and bare-headed. And King Agesilaus, even in his decrepit age, was ever wont to weare his cloaths both Winter and Summer likewise. Suetonius affirmeth that Cæsar did ever march foremost before his troupes, and most commonly bare-headed, and on foot, whether the sunne shone or it rained. The like is reported of Hanniball, ------ tum vertice nudo, Excipere insanos imbres, cælique ruinam. -- Syl. Ital. 250. Bare-headed then he did endure, Heav’ns ruine and mad-raging showre. A Venetian that has long dwelt amongst them, and who is but lately returned thence, writeth, that in the Kingdome of Pegu, both men and women, leaving all other parts clad, go ever bare-footed, indeed, and on horsebacke also. And Plato for the better health and preservation of the body does earnestly persuade that no man should ever give the feet and the head other cover than Nature has allotted them. He whom the Polonians chuse for their King, next to ours who may worthily be esteemed one of the greatest Princes of our age, does never weare gloves, nor what wether soover it be, winter or summer, other bonnet abroad than in the warme house. As I cannot endure to go unbuttoned or untrussed, so the husband-men neighbouring about me would be and feel themselves as fettered or hand-bound with going so. Varro is of opinion, that when we were appointed to stand bare headed before the gods or in presence of the Magistrates, it was rather done for our health, and to enure and arm us against injuries of the wether, than in respect of reverence. And since we are speaking of cold, and are French-men, accustomed so strangely to array ourselves in party-coloured sutes (not I, because I seldom weare any other than blacke or white, in imitation of my father), let us adde this one thing more, which Captain Martyn du Bellay relateth in the voyage of Luxemburg, where he says to have seen so hard frosts, that their munition-wines were faine to be cut and broken with hatchets and wedges, and shared unto the soldiers by weight, which they carried away in baskets; and Ovid, Nudaque consistunt formam servantia testæ Vina, nec hausta meri sed data frusta bibunt. -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. x. 23. Bare wines, still keeping form of caske stand fast. Not gulps, but gobbets of their wine they taste. The frosts are so hard and sharpe in the emboguing of the Meotis fennes, that in the very place where Mithridates Lieutenant had delivered a battle to his enemies, on hard ground and drie-footed, and there defeated them, the next summer he there obtained another sea- battle against them. The Romanes suffered a great disadvantage in the fight they had with the Carthaginians near unto Placentia, for so much as they went to their charge with their blood congealed and limbes benumbed, through extreme cold: whereas Hanniball had caused many fires to be made throughout his campe, to warme his soldiers by, and a quantitie of oile to be distributed amongst them, that therewith annointing themselves, they might make their sinews more supple and nimble, and harden their pores against the bitter blasts of cold wind which then blew, and nipping piercing of the air. The Greeks retreat from Babilon into their countrie is renowned by reason of the many difficulties and encombrances they encountered withall, and were to surmount: whereof this was one, that in the mountaines of Armenia, being surprised and encircled with so horrible and great quantitie of snow, that they lost both the knowledge of the countrie and the ways: wherewith they were so straitly beset that they continued a day and a night without eating or drinking; and most of their horses and cattell died; of their men a great number also deceased; many with the glittering and whiteness of the snow were stricken blinde; diverse through the extremity were lamed, and their limbes shrunken up; many stark stiffe and frozen with colde, although their senses were yet whole. Alexander saw a nation where in winter they burie their fruit-bearing trees under the ground, to defend them from the frost: a thing also used amongst some of our neighbors. Touching the subject of apparell, the King of Mexico, was wont to change and shift his clothes foure times a day, and never wore them again, employing his leavings and cast-sutes for his continuall liberalities and rewards; as also neither pot nor dish, nor any implement of his kitchen or table were twice brought before him. Return to CHAPTER XXXVI: OF CATO THE YOUNGER CHAPTER XXXVI: OF CATO THE YOUNGER AM not possessed with this common error, to judge of others according to what I am my self. I am easy to believe things differing from my self. Though I be engaged to one form, I do not tie the world unto it, as every man does. And I believe and conceive a thousand manners of life, contrary to the common sort: I more easily admit and receive difference than resemblance in us. I discharge as much as a man will, another being of my conditions and principles, and simply consider of it in my self without relation, framing it upon its own modell. Though my self be not continent, yet do I sincerely commend and allow the continencie of the Capuchins and Theatines, and highly praise their course of life. I do by imagination insinuate my self into their place: and by how much more they be other than my self, so much the more do I love and honor him. I would gladly have every man judged apart, and not be drawne my self in consequence of others examples. My weaknesse does no way alter the opinions I should have of the force and vigor of those that deserve it. Sunt, qui nihil suadent, quam quod se imitari posse confidunt (Cic. Orat. ad Brit.). ’There be such as advise to nothing but what they trust themselves can imitate.’ Crawling on the face of the earthe I cease not to marke, even into the clouds, in the imitable height of some heroicke minds. It is much for me to have a formall and prescript judgement, if the effects be not so, and at least to maintaine the chief part exempted from corruption. It is something thing to have a good mind, when my forces faile me. The age we live in (at least our climate) is so dull and leaden, that not only the execution, but the very imagination of virtue is far to seek, and seems to be no other thing than a College supposition and a gibrish word. ------ virtutem verba putant, ut Lucum ligna --Hor. Ep. vi. i. 31. Vertue seems words to these, As trees are wood, or woods are trees. Quam vereri deberent, etia m si percipere non possent. ’Which yet they should reverence, though they could not reach unto.’ It is an eare-ring or pendant to hang in a cabinet, or at the tongues end, as well as at an eare for an ornament. There are no more vertuous actions known; those that bear a show of virtue have no essence of it: for profit, glory, custom, fear, and other like strange causes direct us to produce them. Justice, valor, integritie, which we then exercise, may by others consideration, and by the countenance they publikly bear, be termed so: but with the true workman it is no virtue at all. There is another end proposed; another efficient cause. Vertue alloweth of nothing but what is done by her, and for her alone. In that great battle at Potidæa which the Greeks under Pausanias gained of Mardonius and the Persians, the victors following their custom, coming to share the glory and prise of the victory betweene them, ascribed the pre- excellencie of valor in that conflict to the Spartane nation. The Spartines, impartiall Judges of virtue, when they came to decide to what particular man of their countrie the honor to have done best in that day should of right belong, they found that Aristodemus had most courageously engaged and hazarded himself: Yet gave him not the prise of honor of it, because his virtue had been therunto incited by an earnest desire to purge himself from the reproch and infamie which he had incurred in the action at Thermopyles, and from all daring ambition to die courageously, thereby to warrant his former imputation. Our judgements are yet sicke, and follow the depravations of our customs. I see the greatest part of our spirits to affect wit, and to show themselves ingenious, by obscuring and detracting from the glory of famous and general ancient actions, giving them some base and malicious interpetation, fondly and enviously charging them with vain causes and frivolous occasions. A subtill invention no doubt. Let any man present me with the most excellent and blameless action, and I will oppose it with fiftie vicious and bad intentions, all which shall carrie a face of likelihood. God knowes (to him that will extend them) what diversitie of images our internal will does suffer: They do not so maliciously as grosely and rudely endeavour to be ingenious with all their railing and detraction. The same pain a man taketh to detract from these noble and famous names, and the very same liberty would I as willingly take to lend them my shoulders to extoll and magnifie them. I would endeavor to charge these rare and choise figures, selected by the consent of wise men for the worlds examples as much and as high as my invention would give me leave with honor, in a plausible interpretation and favourable circumstance. And a man must think that the diligent labours of our invention are far beyond their merit. It is the part of honest minded men to portray virtue as fair as possible fair may be. A thing which would no whit be mis- seeming or undecent, if passion should transport us to the favor and pursuit of so sacred formes, what these do contrary, they either do it through malice or knaverie, with purpose to reduce and sute their beleefe to their capacitie whereof I lately spake; or rather, as I think, because their sight is not of sufficient power or clearnes, nor addressed to conceive or apprehend the far-shining brightnes of virtue in natural and genuine puritie: as Plutarke says, that in his time some imputed the cause of Cato the youngers death to the fear he had conceived of Cesar: whereat he has some reason to be moved: by which a man may judge how much more he would have been offended with those that have ascribed the same unto ambition. Oh foolish people! He would no doubt have performed a fair action, so generous and so just, rather with ignominie than for glory. This man was truly a patterne whom nature chose to show how far humane virtue may reach, and mans constancy attaine unto. But my purpose is not here to treat this rich argument: I will only confront together the sayings of five Latin Poets upon Catoes commendations, and for the interest of Cato, and by incidencie for theirs also. Now ought a gentleman, well-bred, in respect of others, find the two former somewhat languish ing; the third more vigorous, but suppressed by the extravagancie of force. He will judge there were yet place for one or two degrees of invention, to reach unto the fourth, in consideration of which he will through admiration join hands for the last (yet first in some degree and space, but which space he will sweare can by no humane spirit be filled up) he will be much amazed, he will be much amated. Lo, here are wonders, we have more Poets than judges and interpreters of poesie. It is an easier matter to frame it than to know it: Being base and humble, it may be judged by the precepts and art of it: But the good and loftie, the supreme and divine, is beyond rules and above reason. Whosoever discerneth her beautie, with a constant, quick- seeing, and setled looke, he can no more see and comprehend the same than the splendor of a lightning flash. It has no communitie with our judgement; but ransacketh and ravisheth the same. The fury which prickes and moves him that can penetrate h er, does also stricke and wound a third man, if he hear it either handled or recited, as the adamant stone draws not only a needle, but infuseth some of her facultie in the same to draw others: And it is more apparently seen in theaters, that the sacred inspiration of the Muses, having first stirred up the Poet with a kind of agitation unto choler, unto grief, unto hatred, indeed beyond himself, whither and however they please, does also by the Poet strike and enter into the Actor, and consequently by the Actor a whole auditorie or multitude. It is the ligament of our senses depending one of another. Even from my infancie Poesie has had the virtue to transpierce and transport me. But that lively and feeling-movino that is naturally in me have diversly been handled, by the diversitie of forms, not so much higher or lower (for they were ever the highest in every kind) as different in colour. First a blithe and ingenious fluiditie, then a quaint-wittie and loftie conceit. To conclude, a ripe and constant force. Ovid, Lucan, and Virgil will better declare it. But here our Gallants are in their full cariere. Sit Cato dum vivit sane vel Cæsare major. -- Mart. Epig. xxxii. 5. Let Cato Junior, while he does live, greater than Cæsar be. Saith one. ------ et invictum devicta morte Catonem: --Manil. Astr. iv. 87. Cato unconquered, death being vanquished. Saith another: And the third, speaking of the civill wars betweene Cæsar and Pompey. Victrix causa Diis placuit, sed victa Catoni. -- Lucan. Bel. Civ. i. 127. The cause that overcame with Gods was greater; But the cause overcome pleased Cato better. And the fourth upon Cæsars commendations: Et cuncta terrarum subacta, Præter atrocem animum Catonis. -- Hor. ii. Od. i. 23. Of all the earth all parts enthralled, Catoes mind only unappalled. And the harps-master, after he has installed the names of the greatest Romans in his picture, ended thus: ----- -his dantem jura Catonem. --Virg. Æn. viii. 670. Chiefe justice Cato do decree Lawes that for righteous soules should be. Return to CHAPTER XXXVII: HOW WE WEEPE AND LAUGH AT ONE SELFE-SAME THING CHAPTER XXXVII: HOW WE WEEPE AND LAUGH AT ONE SELFE-SAME THING HEN we read in Histories (Plut. Vit. Pyrrh. f.), that Antigonus was highly displeased with his son, at what time he presented unto him the head of King Pirrhus his enemy, slain but a little before in fight against him which he no sooner saw but he burst foorth a weeping: And that Renate Duke of Loraine wept for the death of Charles Duke of Burgundie, whom he had eftsoones discomfited, and was as an assistant mourner at his funeralls: And that in the battle of Anroy (which the Earl of Montfort had gained against the faction of Charles de Blois, for the Dutchy of Britanie) the victorious conqueror met with the body of his enemy deceased, mourned very grievously for him; a man must not suddenly exclaime. E cosi avven che l’animo ciascuna Sua passion sotto ’l contrario manto Ricopre, con la vista hor’ chiara, hor’ bruna. So happens it, the mind covers each passion Under a cloake of colours opposite, To sight now clear, now darke, in diverse fashion. When Cæsar was presented with Pompeis head, Histories report that he turned his looks aside, as from a ghastly and unpleasing spectacle. There has been so long a correspondence in societie in the managing of public affairs, mutually betweene them, such a community of fortunes, so many reciprocall offices and bonds of alliance, that a man cannot think his countenance to have been forced, false, and wily, as this other supposeth. -----tutumque putavit Jam bonus esse socer, lacrymas non sponte cadentes Effudit gemitusque expressit pectore læto. Lucan. ix.1040. Now to be kind indeed he did not doubt Father in law, tears, which came hardly out He shed, and grones exprest From inward pleased brest. For certainly, howbeit the greatest number of our actions be but masked and painted over with dissimulation, and that it may sometimes be true, Hæredis fletus sub persona risus est. -- Aul. Gell. Noct. Att. xvii. c. 14. The weeping of an heir is laughing under a visard or disguise. Yet must a man consider, by judging of his accidents, how our mindes are often agitated by diverse passions; For (as they say) there is a certain assembly of diverse humors in our bodies, whereof she is sovereign mistris, who most ordinarily, according to our complexions, does command us: so in our mind, although it containe severall motions that agitate the same, yet must one chiefly be predominant. But it is not with so full an advantage, but for the volubilitie and supplenesse of our mind, the weakest may by occasion reobtaine the place again, and when their turn cometh, make a new charge; whence we see not only children, who simply and naturally follow nature, often to weepe and laugh at one self-same thing, but none of us all can vaunt himself, what wished for or pleasant voyage soever he undertake, but that taking leave of his family and friends, he shall feel a chilling and panting of the heart, and if he shed not tears, at least he puts his foot in the stirrup with a sad and heavy cheere. And what gentle flame soever does warme the heart of young virgins, yet are they hardly drawne to leave and forgoe their mothers, to betake them to their husbands: whatsoever this good fellow say: Est ne novis nuptis odio Venus, anne parentum Frustrantur falsis gaudia lacrymulis, Ubertum thalami quas intra limina fundunt? Non, ita me Divi, vera gemunt, juverint. -- Catul. Eleg. ii.15. Doe young birds hate indeed fresh Venus toyes, Or with false tears delude their parents joyes, Which in their chambers they powre out amaine? So helpe me God they do not true complain. So is it not strange to mourne for him dead, whom a man by no means would have alive again. When I chide my boy, I do it with the best heart I have: They are true and not feigned imprecations: but that fit past over, let him have need of me, I will gladly, do him all the good I can and by and by I turn over another leafe. If I chance to call one knave or asse, my purpose is not for ever to enfeoffe him with those nick-names; nor do I think to say, tong you liest, if immediately after I call him an honest man. No quality does embrace us purely and universally. If it were not the countenance of a foole to speak alone or to him self, there would scarce be day or hour wherein some body should not hear me mutter and grumble to my self, and against my self, A ( ) in the fooles teeth! yet do not I think it to be my definition. He that seeth me sometimes to cast a frowning looke upon my wife, or sometimes a loving countenance, and thinkes that either of them is but feigned, he is a foole. Nero taking leave of his mother, whom he sent to be drowned, felt notwithstanding the emotion of that motherly farewell, and at one instant was strucken with horror and pity. It is said that the Sunnes-light is not of one continued piece, but that it so uncessantly and without intermission does cast so thicke new raies, one in the necke of another, upon us, that we cannot perceive the space betweene them. Largus enim liquidi-fons luminis æthereus sol, Irrigat assidue cælum candore recenti, Suppeditaque novo confestim lumine lumen. -- Lucr. v. 281. Heav’ns Sunne the plenteous spring of liquid light Still heav’n bedewes with splendor fresh and bright, Still light supplies with light of fresher sight. So does our mind cast her points diversly and impercepubly. Artabanus surprised Xerxes his nephew, and chid him for the sudden changing of his countenance. He was to consider the unmeasurable greatness of his forces at the passage of Hellespont, for the enterprise of Greece. First he was suddenly assailed by an excessive joy, to see so many thousands of men at his service, and witnessed the same by the alacritie and cheerefulnes of his countenance: And immediately at that very moment, his thoughts suggesting how so many lives were to be consumed, and should come to nothing (at the furthest, within one age), he gan to frowne his browes, and grew so pensive that he wept. We have with a resolute and inexorable mind pursued the revenge of an injurie, and felt a singular content for the victory; yet upon better advice do we weepe: it is not that we weepe for: the thing is as it was, there is nothing changed: But that our mind beholds the thing with another eye, and under another shape, it presents itself unto us. For every thing has diverse faces, sundry byases, and severall lustres. Aliance, kinred, old acquaintances, and long friendship seize on our imagination, and at that instant passionate the same according to their quality, but the turn or change of it is so violent that it escapes us. Nil adeo fieri celeri ratione videtur, Quam si mens fieri proponit et inchoat ipsa. Ocius ergo animus quam res se perciet ulla, Ante quarum in promptu natura videtur. -- Lucr. iii. 183. Nothing in so quick sort seems to be done, As mind set on a thing, and once begun, The mind that swifter stirres before our eyes, Than any thing, whose form we soone comprize. And therefore, intending to continue one body of all this pursuit, we deceive ourselves. When Timoleon weepeth the murther he has perpetrated with so mature and generous a determmation, he weepeth not for the liberty restored to his countrie, nor the tyrant, but he weepeth for his brother. One part of his dutie is acted, let us permit him to play the other. Return to CHAPTER XXXVIII: OF SOLITARINESSE CHAPTER XXXVIII: OF SOLITARINESSE ET us leave apart this outworne comparison, betweene a solitarie and an active life: And touching that goodly saying under which ambition and avance shroud themselves, that we are not borne for our particular, but for the public good: let us boldly refer ourselves to those that are engaged and let them beat their conscience, if on the contrary the states, the charges, and this trash of the world are not rather sought and sued for to draw a private commoditie from the public. The bad and indirect means whereth rough in our age men canvase and toyle to attaine the same, do manifestly declare the end thereof to be of no great consequence. Let us answer ambition, that herself gives us the taste of solitarinesse. For what does she shun so much as company? What seeketh she more than elbow-roome? There is no place but there are means and waies to do well or ill. Nevertheless if the saying of Bias be true, ’That the worst part is the greatest:’ Or that which Ecclesiastes says, ’That of a thousand there is not one good:’ Rari quippe boni: numero vix sunt totidem, quot Thebarum portæ, vel divitis ostia Nili: -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 26. 1 Good men are rare, so many scarce (I fear) As gates of Thebes, mouths of rich Nilus were. Contagion is very dangerous in a throng. A man must imitate the vicious, or hate them: both are dangerous: for to resemble them is perilous, because they are many , and to hate many is hazardous, because they are dissemblable, and Merchants that travell by sea have reason to take heed that those which go in the same ship be not dissolute, blasphemers, and wicked, judging such company unfortunate. Therefore Bias said pleasantly to those that together with him passt the danger of a great storme, and called to the Gods for helpe: ’Peace, my masters, lest they should hear that you are here with me.’ And of a more militarie example, Albuberque, Viceroy in India for Emanuel King of Portugall, in an extreme danger of a sea-tempest, took a young boy upon his shoulders, for this only end, that in the common perill his innocence might be his warrant and recommending to Gods favor to set him on shore: yet may a wise man live every where contented, indeed alone, in the throng of a Pallace: but if he may chuse, he will (says he) avoid the sight of it. If need require, he will endure the first: but if he may have his choice, he will chuse the latter. He thinks he has not sufficiently rid himself from vices if he must also contest with other mens faults. Charondas punished those for wicked that were convicted to have frequented lewd companies. There is nothing so dis-sociable and sociable as man, the one for his vice, the other for his nature. And I think Antisthenes did not satisfie him that upbraided him with his conversation with the wicked, saying, ’That Physicians live amongst the sicke:’ Who if they stead sicke mens healths, they impaire their own by the infection, continuall visiting, touching, and frequenting of diseases. Now (as I suppose) the end is both one, thereby to live more at leisure and better at ease. But man does not alwaies seek the best way to come unto it, who often supposeth to have quit affairs when he has but changed them. There is not much less vexation in the government of a private family than in the managing of an entire state: wherever the mind is busied, there it is all. And though domesticall occupations be less important, they are as importunate. Moreover, though we have freed ourselves from the court and from the market, we are not free from the principal torments of our life. ----- ratio et prudentia curas, Non locus effusi late maris arbiter aufert. -- Hor. i. Epist. xi. 25. Reason and wisdom may set cares aside. Not place the Arbiter of seas so wide. Shift we or change we places never so often, ambition, avar ice, irresolution, fear, and concupiscences never leave us. Et post equitem sedet atra cura. -- Hor. iii. Od. i. 39. Care, looking grim and blacke, does sit Behind his backe that rides from it. They often follow us, even into immured cloisters. and into schooles of philosophy; nor do hollow rocks, nor wearing of hair-shirts, nor continuall fastings, rid us from them. Hæret lateri lethalis arundo. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 73. The shaft that death implide Sticks by the flying side. It was told Socrates that one was no whit amended by his travell: ’I believe it well (said he) for he carried himself with him.’ Quid terras alio calentes Sole mutamus? patria quis exul Se quoque fugit? -- Hor. ii. Od. xvi. 18. Why change we soyles warm’d with another Sunne? Who from home banisht has himself outrunne? If a man do not first discharge both himself and his mind from the burden that presseth her, removing from place to place will stir and press her the more, I as in a ship, wares well stowed and closely piled take up least roome, you do a sicke-man more hurt than good to make him change place, you settle an evil in removing the same; as stakes or poles, the more they are stirred and shaken, the faster they sticke, and sinke deeper into the ground. Therefore is it not enough for a man to have sequestered himself from the concourse of people: is it not sufficient to shift place, a man must also sever himself from the popular conditions that are in us. A man must sequester and recover himself from himself. -----rupi jam vincula, dicas, Nam luctata canis nodum arripit, attamen illa Cum fugit, a collo trahitur pars longa catenæ. -- Pers. Sat. v. 158. You will say perhaps I my bonds have quit, Why so the striving dog the knot has bit; Yet when he flies, much chaine does follow it. We carry our fetters with us: is it not all absolute liberty; we still cast backe our looks towards that we have left behinde: our mind does still run on it; our fancie is full of it. ----- nisi purgatum est pectus, quæm prælia nobis Atque pericula tunc ingratis insinuandum? Quantæ conscindunt hominem cupidinis actes Solicitum curæ, quantique perinde timores? Quidve superbia, spurcidia ac petulantia, quantas Efficiunt clades, quid luxus, desidiesque? -- Lucr. v. 44. Unless our breast be purg’d, what wars must we What perils then, though much displeased, see? How great tears, how great cares of sharpe desire Doe careful man distract, torment, enfire? Uncleannesse, wantonnesse, sloth, riot, pride, How great calamities have these implide? Our evil is rooted in our mind: and it cannot scape from itself. In culpa est animus, qui se non effugit unquam, -- Hor. i. Epist. xiv. 13. The mind in greatest fault must lie Which from itself can never flie, Therefore must it be reduced and brought into itself: It is the true solitarinesse, and which may be enjoyed even in the frequencie of peopled Cities and Kings courts; but it is more commodiously enjoyed apart. Now sithence we undertake to live solitarie, and without companie, let us cause our contentment to depend of ourselves: Let us shake off all bonds that tie us unto others: Gaine we that victory over us, that in good earnest we may live solitarie, and therein live at our ease. Stilphon having escaped the combustion of his City, wherein he had lost both wife and children, and all his goods; Demetrius Poliorcetes seeing him in so great a ruine of his Countrie with an unaffrighted countenance, demanded of him, whether he had received any loss: He answered, No: and that (thanks given to God) he had lost nothing of his own. It is that which Antisthenes the Philosopher said very pleasantly, ’That man ought to provide himself with munitions that might float upon the water, and by swimming escape the danger of shipwracke with him.’ Verily, ’a man of understanding has lost nothing if he yet have himself.’ When the City of Nola was over-run by the Barbarians, Paulinus, bishop thereof, having lost all he had there, and being their prisoner, prayed thus unto God: ’O Lord, deliver me from feeling of this loss: for you knowest as yet they have touched nothing that is mine.’ The riches that made him rich, and the goods which made him good, were yet absolutely whole. Behold what it is to chuse treasures well, that may be freed from injurie; and to hide them in a place where no man may enter, and which cannot be betraied but by ourselves. A man that is able may have wives, children, goods, and chiefly health, but not so tie himself unto them that his felicitie depend on them. We should reserve a store-house for our selves, what need soever change; altogether ours, and wholly free, wherein we may hoard up and establish our true liberty, and principal retreit and solitarinesse, wherein we must go alone to ourselves, take out ordinary entertainment, and so privateIy that no acquai ntance or communication of any strange thing may therein find place: there to discourse, to meditate and laugh, as, without wife, without children, and goods, without traine or servants; that if by any occasion they be lost, it seem not strange to us to pass it over; we have a mind moving and turning in itself; it may keep itself companie; it has wherewith to offend and defend, wherewith to receive, and wherewith to give. Let us not fear that we shall faint and droop through tedious and mind-trying idlenesse in this solitarinesse. In solis sis tibi turba locis. Be you, when with you is not any, As good unto your self as many. Vertue is contented with itself, without discipline, without words, and without effects. In our accustomed actions, of a thousand there is not one found that regards us: he whom you seest so furiously, and as it were besides himself, to clamber or crawle up the citie wals or breach, as a point-blank to a whole voly of shot, and another all wounded and skarred, crazed and faint, and well-nie hunger-starven, resolved rather to die than to open his enemy the gate and give him entrance; doest you think he is there for himself? No verily. It is perhaps for such a one whom neither he nor so many of his fellowes ever saw, and who perhaps takes no care at all for them; but is therewhilst wallowing up to the ears in sensualitie, slouth, and all manner of carnal delights . This man, whom about mid- night, when others take their rest, you seest come out of his study, meagre looking, with eyes trilling, flegmatick, squalide, and spauling, doest you think that plodding on his books does seek how he shall become an honester man, or more wise, or more content? There is no such matter. He wil either die in his pursuit, or teach posterity the measure of Plautus verses and the true orthography of a Latine word. Who does not willingly chop and counterchange his health, his ease, indeed his life, for glory and for reputation? The most unprofitable, vain, and counterfet coine, that is in use with us. Our death is not sufficient to make us afraid; let us also charge ourselves with that of our wives, of our children, and of our friends and people. Our own affairs do not sufficiently trouble and vexe us: Let us also drudge, toile, vex, and torment ourselves with our neighbors and friends matters. Vah quemquamne hominem in animum instituere, aut Parare, quod sit charius, quam ipse est sibi? -- Ter. Adel. act. i. scen. i. 13. Fie, that a man should cast, that ought, than he Himselfe of himself more belov’d should be. Solitarinesse, me seems, has more apparence and reason in those which have given their most active and flourishing age into the world, in imitation of of Thales. We have lived long enough for others, live we the remainder of our life unto ourselves: let us bring home our cogitations and inventions unto ourselves and unto our ease. It is no easy matter to make a safe retreit: it does over-much trouble us with joyning other enterprises unto it; since God gives us leisure to dispose of our dislodging. Let us prepare ourselves unto it, packe we up our baggage. Let us betimes bid our companie farewell. Shake we off these violent holdfasts which else-where engage us, and estrange us from ourselves. These so strong bonds must be untied, and a man must eft-soones love this or that, but wed nothing but himself; That is to say, let the rest be our own: yet not so combined and glued together that it may not be sundred without fleaing us, and therewithall pull away some peece of our own. The greatest thing of the world is for a man to know how to be his own. It is high time to shake off societie, since we can bring nothing to it. And he that cannot lend, let him take heed of borrowing. Our forces faile us: retire we them, and shut them up into ourselves. He that can suppresse and confound in himself the offices of so many amities, and of the company, let him do it. In this fall which makes us inutile, irkesome, and importunate to others, let him take heed he be not importunate, irkesome, and unprofitable to himself. Let him flatter court, and cherish himself, and above all let him governe him self, respecting his reason and fearing his conscience, so that he may not without shame stumble or trip in their presence. Rarum est enim, ut satis se quisque vereatur: ’For it is a rare matter that every man sufficiently should stand in awe and reverence of himself.’ Socrates says, ’That young men ought to be instructed, and men exercised in well doing; and old men withdraw themselves from all civill and military negotiations, living at their own discretion, without obligation to any certain office.’ There are some complexions more proper for these precepts of retreit than orhers. Those which have a tender and demiss apprehension, a squemish affection, a delicate will, and which cannot easily subject or employ itself (of which both by natural condition and propense discourse I am one) wil better apply themselves unto this counsell than active minds and busie spirits; which imbrace all, ever where engage, and in all things passionate themselves, that offer, that present and yield themselves to all occasions. A man must make use of all these accidentall commodities, and which are without us, so long as they be pleasing to us; but not make them our principal foundation: It is not so; nor reason, nor nature permit it. Why should we against their laws subject our contentment to the power of others? Moreover, to anticipate the accidents of fortune, for a man to deprive himself of the commodities he has in possession, as many have done for devotion, and some Philosophers by discourse; to serve themselves, to lie upon the hard ground, to pull out their own eyes, to cast their riches into the sea, to seek for pain and smart (some by tormenting this life for the happinesse of another; othersome placing themselves on the lowest step, thereby to warrant themselves from a new fall) is the action of an excessive virtue. Let sterner and more vigorous complexions make their lurking glorious and exemplar. ------ tuta et parvula laudo, Cum res deficiunt, satis inter vilia fortis: Verum ubi quid melius contingit et unctius, idem Hos sapere, et solos aio bene vivere, quorum Conspicitur nitidis fundata pecunia villis. -- Hor. i. Epist. xv. 42. When riches faile, I praise the safe estate, Though small; base things do not high thoughts abate. But when tis better, finer with me, I They only live well, and are wise, do crie, Whose corne in fair farmes does well-grounded lie. There is work enough for me to do without going so far. It sufficeth me, under fortunes favor, to prepare my self for her disfavour; and being at ease, as far as imagination may attaine unto, so represent the evil to come unto my self: Even as we enure ourselves to Tilts and Tourneyes, and counterfeit war in time of peace. I esteeme not Arcesilaus the Philosopher less reformed because I know him to have used household implements of gold and silver, according as the condition of his fortune gave him leave. I rather value him the more than if he had not done it, forasmuch as he both moderately and liberally made use of them. I know unto what limits natural necessitie goeth; and I consider a poore almesman begging at my doore to be often more plump-cheekt, in better health and liking, than I am: Then do I enter into his estate, and essay to frame and sute my mind unto his byase. And so over-running other examples, albeit I imagine death, povertie, contempt, and sicknesse to be at my heels, I easily resolve my self not to apprehend any fear of that which one of less worth than my self does tolerate and undergoe with such patience: And I cannot believe that the basenesse or shallownesse of understanding can do more than vigor and far-seeing, or that the effects and reason of discretion cannot reach to the effects of custom and use. And knowing what slender hold- fast these accessorie commodities have, I omit not in full jovyssance of them, humbly to beseech God of his mercy (as a sovereign request) to make me contented with my self, and with the goods proceeding from me. I see some gallantly-disposed young men, who notwithstanding their fair-seeming show, have boxes full of pils in their coffers at home, to take when the rhume shall assaile them; which so much the less the fear, when they think the remedy to be at hand. So must a man do: as also if he feel himself subject to some greater infirmitie, to store himself with medicaments that may assuage, supple, and stupifie the part grieved. The occupation a man should chuse for such a life must neither be painfull nor tedious, otherwise in vain should we accompt to have sought our abiding there, which depends from the particular taste of every man. Mine does no way accommodate itself to husbandrie. Those that love it, must with moderation apply themselves unto it. Conentur sibi res, non se submittere rebus. -- Epist. i. 19. Endevour they things to them to submit, Not them to things (if they have Horace wit) Husbandrie is otherwise a servile office, as Salust termeth it: It has more excusable parts, as the care of gardening, which Xenophon ascribeth to Cyrus: A meane or mediocritie may be found betweene this base and vile carking care, extended and full of toiling labor, which we see in men that wholly plunge themselves therein, and that profound and extreme retchlesnesse to let all things go at six and seven, which is seen in others. ------ Democriti pecus edit agellos Cultague, dum peregre est animus sine corpore velox. -- Epist. xii. 12. Cattle destroyd Democritus his sets, While his mind bodilesse vagaries fets. But let us hear the counsell which Plinie the younger gives to his friend Cornelius Rufus, touching this point of Solitarinesse: ’I persuade you in this full-gorged and fat retreit wherein you are, to remit this base and abject care of husbandrie unto your servants, and give your self to the study of letters, whence you maist gather something that may altogether be thine own.’ He meaneth reputation: like unto Ciceroes humor, who says, That he will employ his solitarinesse and residence from public affairs to purchase unto himself by his writings an immortall life. ------ usque adeone Scire tuum nihil est, nisi te scire hoc sciat alter?-- Pers. Sat. i. 27. Is it then nothing worth that you doest know. Unless what you doest know, you others show? It seemth to be reason, when a man speaks to withdraw himself from the world, that one should looke beyond him. These do it but by halfes. Indeed they set their match against the time they shall be no more; but pretend to reap the fruit of their dessignes, when they shall be absent from the world, by a ridiculous contradiction. The imagination of those who through devotion seek solitarinesse, filling their minds with the certaintie of heavenly promises, in the other life, is much more soundly consorted. They propose God as an object infinit in goodnesse and incomprehensible in power, unto themselves. The soul has therein, in all free liberty, wherewith to glut herself. Afflictions and sorrowes redound to their profit, being imployed for the purchase and attaining of health and eternall gladnesse. Death, according to ones wish, is a passage to so perfect an estate. The sharpnesse of their rules is presently made smooth and easy by custom; and carnall concupiscences rejected, abated, and lulled asleep by refusing them: for nothing entertaineth them but use and exercise. This only end of another life, blessedly immortall, does rightly merit we should abandon the pleasures and commodities of this our life. And he that can enlighten his soul with the flame of a lively faith and hope, really and constantly, in his solitarinesse does build unto himself a voluptuous and delicious life, far surmounting all other lives. Therefore does neither the end nor middle of this counsell please me. We are ever falling into a relaps from an ague to a burning fever. This plodding occupation of bookes is as painfull as any other, and as great an enemy unto health, which ought principally to be considered. And a man should not suffer himself to be inveagled by the pleasure he takes in them: It is the same pleasure that loses the thriving husband-man, the greedy-covetous, the sinning- voluptuous, and the puft-up ambitious. The wisest men teach us sufficiently to beware and shield us from the treasons of our appetites, and to discerne true and perfect pleasures from delights blended and entermingled with more pain. For most pleasures (say they) tickle, fawne upon, and embrace us, with purpose to strangle us, as did the theeves whom the Egyptians termed Philistas: And if the head-ach would seize upon us before drunkennesse, we would then beware of too much drinking: but sensualitie, the better to entrap us, marcheth before, and hideth her tracke from us. Bookes are delightfull, but if by continuall frequenting them, we in the end lose both health and cheerefulnesse (our best parts) let us leave them. I am one of those who think their fruit can no way countervaile this loss. As men that have long time felt themselves enfeebled through some indisposition, do in the end yield to the mercy of Physicke, and by art have certain rules of life prescribed them, which they will not transgresse: So he that withdrawes himself, as digested and over-tired with the common life, ought likewise to frame and prescribe this unto the rules of reason; direct and range the same by premeditation and discourse. He must bid all manner of travell farewell, what show soever it bear; and in general shun all passions that any way empeach the tranquillitie of mind and body, and follow the course best agreeing with his humor. Vnusquisque sua noverit ire via. -- Propert. ii. El. xxv. 38. His own way every man Tread-out directly can. A man must give to thriving husbandrie, to laborious study, to toilesome hunting, and to every other exercise, the utmost bounds of pleasure; and beware he engage himself no further, if once pain begin to intermeddle itself with her; we should reserve business and negotiations only for so much as is behoovefull to keep us in breath, and to warrant us from the inconveniences which the other extremity of a base, faint-harted idlenesse draws after it. There are certain barren and thornie sciences, which for the most part are forged for the multitude: they should be left for those who are for the service of the world. As for my self, I love no books but such as are pleasant and easy, and which tickle me, or such as comfort and counsell me, to direct my life and death. -----tacitum sylvas inter reptare salubres Curantem quidquid dignum sapiente bonoque est. -- Hor. i. Epist. iv. 4. Silently creeping midst the wholesome wood With care what’s for a wise man and a good. The wiser sort of men, having a strong and vigorous mind, may frame unto themselves an altogether spirituall life. But mine being common, I must help to uphold my self by corporall commodities: And age having eftsoones dispoiled me of those that were most mutable to my fantasia, I instruct and sharpen my appetite to those remaining most sortable this other season. We must tooth and naile retaine the use of this lives pleasures, which our years snatch from us one after another: Carpamus dulcia, nostrum est, Quod vivis: cinis et manes et fabula fies. -- Pers. Sat. v. 155. Plucke we sweet pleasures: we your life give you. Thou shall a tale, a ghost, and ashes be. Now concerning the end of glory, which Plinie and Cicero propose unto us, it is far from my discourse: The most opposite humor to solitarie retiring is ambition. ’Glorie and rest are things that cannot squat in one same form:’ as far as I see, these have nought but their arms and legs out of the throng, their mind and intent is further and more engaged in them than ever it was. Tun’, vetule, auriculis alienis colligis escas? -- Pers. Sat. i. 22. Gatherst you dotard at these years, Fresh baits, fine food, for others ears? They have gone backe that they might leap the better, and with a stronger motion make a nimbler offer amidst the multitude. Will you see how they shoot-short by a cornes breadth? let us but counterpoise the advice of two Philosophers, and of two most different sects: The one writing to Idomeneus, the other to Lucilius, their friends, to divert them from the managing of affairs and greatness unto a solitarie kind of life. ’You have,’ say they, ’lived hitherto swimming and floating adrift, come and die in the haven; you have given the past of your life unto light, give the remainder unto darknesse.’ It is impossible to give over occupations if you do not also give over the fruits of them: Therefore clear your self from all care and glory. There is great danger lest the glittering of your forepassed actions should over much dazle you, indeed, and follow you even to your den. Together with other concupiscences, shake off that which commeth from the approbation of others. And touching your knowledge and sufficiencie, take you no care of them, they will lose no whit of their effect; if your self be anything the better for them. Remember but him, who being demanded to what purpose he toyled so much about an art, which could by no means come to the knowledge of many: ’Few are enow for me; one will suffice, indeed, less than one will content me,’ answered he. He said true: you and another are a sufficient theatre one for another; or you to your self alone. Let the people be one unto you, and one be all the people to you: it is a base ambition to go about to draw glory from ones idlenesse and from ones lurking hole. A man must do as some wild beasts, which at the entrance of their caves will have no manner of footing seen. You must no longer seek what the world says of you, but how you must speak unto your self: withdraw your self into your self; but first prepare your self to receive your self: it were folly to trust to your self if you cannot governe your self. A man may as well faile in solitariness as in companie, there are waies for it, until such time as you have framed your self, such that you dare not halt before your self, and that you shall be ashamed of and bear a kind of respect unto your self, Obversentur species honestæ animo: ’Let honest Ideæs still represent themselves before your mind:’2 Ever present Cato, Phocion, and Aristides unto your imagination in whose presence even fooles would hide their faults, and establish them as controulers of all your intentions. If they be disordered and untuned, their reverence will order and tune them again: they will containe you in a way to be contented with your self; to borrow nothing but from your self, to settle and stay your mind in assured and limited cogitations, wherein it may best please itself, and having gotten knowledge of true felicities, which according to the measure a man understands them, he shall accordingly injoy, and with them rest satisfied, without wishing a further continuance either of life or name. See here the counsell of truly-pure and purely-true philosophie not of a vain-glorious, boasting, and prating philosophie, as is that of the two first. Return to CHAPTER XXXIX: A CONSIDERATION UPON CICERO CHAPTER XXXIX: A CONSIDERATION UPON CICERO NE WORD more in comparison of these two: There are gathered out of Ciceroes writings and from Plinies (in mine opinion little agreeing with his unckle) infinite testimonies of a nature beyond measure ambitious. Amongst others, that they openly solicit the Historians of their times not to forget them in their writings: and fortune, as it were in spight, has made the vanity of their request to continue even to our days, and long since the histories were lost. But this exceedeth all hearts- basenesse in persons of that stampe, to have gone about to draw some principal glory from prating and speaking, even to employ their private Epistles written to their friends; in such sort, as some missing the opportunity to be sent, they notwithstanding cause them to be published, with this worthy excuse, that they would not lose their travell and lucubrations. Is it not a seemly thing in two Roman Consuls, chiefs magistrates of the common-wealth, Empresse of the world, to spend their time in wittily devising and closely hudling up of a quaint missive or wittie epistle, thereby to attaine the reputation that they perfectly understand their mother tongue? What could a seely Schoolmaster, who gets his living by such trash, do worse? If the acts of Xenophon, or Cæsar, had not by much exceeded their eloquence, I cannot believe they would ever have written them. They have endevored to recommend unto posterity, not their sayings, but their doings. And if the perfection of well- speaking might bring any glory suitable unto a great personage, Scipio and Lelius would never have resigned the honor of their comedies, and the elegancies and smooth-sportfull conceits of the Latine tongue, unto an African servant: For, to prove this labor to be theirs , the exquisit eloquence and excellent invention thereof does sufficiently declare it: and Terence himself does avouch it: And I could hardly be removed from this opinion. It is a kind of mockerie and injurie to raise a man to worth by qualities mis-seeming his place and unfitting his calling, although for some other respects praise-worthy; and also by qualities that ought not to be his principal object. As he that would commend a King to be a cunning painter, or a skilfull architect, or an excellent Harquibuzier, or a never-missing-missing runner at the Ring. These commendations acquire a man no honor if they be not presented altogether with those that are proper and convenient unto him, that is to say, justice, and the skill to governe, and knowledge to direct his people both in peace and war. In this sort does Agriculture honor Cyrus, and Eloquence Charlemaine, together with his knowledge in good letters. I have in my time seen some who by writing did earnestly get both their titles and living, to disavow their aprentissage, mar their pen, and affect the ignorance of so vulgar a quality; and which our people holds to be seldom found amongst wise men, endeavouring to commend for better qualities. Demosthenes his companions in their ambassage to Philip, praised their Prince to be fair, eloquent, and a good quaffer. Demosthenes said, they were commendations rather fitting a woman, an advocate, and a spunge, than a King. Imperet bellante prior, jacentem Lenis in hostem. -- 1 HOR. Car. Secul. 51. Better he rule, who mercifull will rue His foe subdued, than he that can subdue. It is not his profession to know either how to hunt cunningly or to dance nimbly. Orabunt causas alii, cælique meatus Describent radio, et fulgentia sidera dicent; Hic regere imperio populos sciat. --Virg. Æn. vi. 850. Others shall causes plead, describe the skies’ Motion by instrument, say how stars rise: But let him know to rule (just, valiant, wise). Plutarke says, moreover, That to appear so absolutely excellent in these less-necessarie parts, is to produce a witness against himself, to have ill spent his hours and fondly- bestowed his studye which might better have been employed to more behoovefull and profitable use. So that Philip, King of Macedon, having heard great Alexander, his son, sing at a feast and vie with the best musitians: ’Art you not ashamed (said he unto him) to sing so well?’ And to the same Philip said a musitian, gainst whom he contended about his Art, ’God forbid, my Sovereigne, that ever so much hurt should befall you, that you should understand these things better than my self.’ A King ought to be able to answer, as Iphicrates did the Orator who in his invective urged him in this manner: ’And what art you, you shouldst so brave it? Art you a man at Armes? Art you an Archer? Art you a Pikeman?’ ’I am none of all those, but I am he who command all those.’ And Antisthenes made it as an argument of little value in Ismenias, when some commended him to be an excellent Flutist. Well I wot that when I hear some give themselves to dwell on the phrase of my Essayes, I would rather have them hold their peace: They do not so much raise the words as depresse the sense; so much the more sharply by how much more obliquely. Yet am I deceived if some others take not more hold on the matter; and how well or ill soever, if any writer has scattered the same, either more materiall, or at least thicker on his paper: That I may collect the more, I do but huddle it; the arguments or chief heads. Let me but adde what followes them, I shall daily increase this volume. And how many stories have I glanced at therein, that speak not a word, which whosoever shall unfold may from them draw infinite Essayes? Nor they, nor my allegations do ever serve simply for examples, authority, or ornament. I do not only respect them for the use I draw from them. They often (beyond my purpose) produce the seed of a richer subject and bolder matter, and often, collaterally, a more harmonious tune, both for me, that will express no more in this place, and for them that shall hit upon my tune. But returning to virtue. I find no great choice betweene him that can speak nothing but evil, and one that can talk nothing but to talk well. Non est ornamentum virile concinnitas (Sen. Epist. cxv. p.). ’Finenesse is no great grace for a man.’ Wise men say, that in respect of knowledge, there is nothing but philosophy, and in regard of effects, but Vertue: which is generally fit for all degrees and for all orders. Something there is likewise in these two other philosophers; for they also promise eternitie to the Epistles they write to their friends. But after another fashion, and to a good purpose, accommodating themselves to others vanity: For they send them word, that if care to make themselves knowen unto future ages, and respect of renown, does yet retaine them in the managing of affairs, and makes them fear solitarmesse and a retired life, to which they would call them, that they take no more paines for it: for as much as they have sufficient credit with posterity, by answering them; and were it but by the epistles they write unto them, they will make Their name as famous and as far knowen, as all their public actions might do. Besides this difference, they are not frivolous, idle, and triviall Epistles, and only compact and held together with exquisite choise words, hudled-up and ranged to a just smoothe cadence, but stufft and full of notable sayings and wise sentences; by which a man does not only become more eloquent, but more wise, and that teach us not to say well, but to do well. Fie on that eloquence which leaves us with a desire of it, and not of things; unless a man will say that Ciceroes being so exceedingly perfect does frame itself a body of perfection. I will further alleage a story, which to this purpose we read of him, to make us palpably feel his natural condition. He was to make an Oration in public, and being urged betimes to prepare himself for it, Eros, one of his servants, came to tel him the Auditorie was deferred till the morrow next; he was so glad of it, that for so good news he gave him his liberty. Touching this subject of Epistles, thus much I will say: It is a work wherein my friends are of opinion I can do something; and should more willingly have undertaken to publish my gifts had I had who to speak unto. It had been requisite (as I have had other times) to have had a certain commerce to draw me on, to encourage me, and to uphold me. For, to go about to catch the winde in a net, as others do, I cannot; and it is but a dreame. I am a sworne enemy to all falsifications. I should have been more attentive and more assured, having a friendly and strong direction, than to behold the diverse images of a whole multitude: and I am deceived if it be not better succeeded with me. I have naturally a comical and familiar stile: But after a manner peculiar unto my self, inept to all public Negotiations, answering my speech which is altogether close, broken, and particular: I have no skill in ceremonious letters, which have no other substance but a fair contexture of complemental phrases and curteous words. I have no taste nor faculty of these tedious offers of service or affection. I believe not so much as is said, and am nothing pleased to say more than I believe. It is far from that which is used nowadaies: For, there was never so abject and servile a prostitution of presentations; life, soul, devotion, adoration, servant, slave; all these words are, so generally used, that when they would express a more emphatical intent and respective will, they have no means left them to express it. I deadly hate to hear a flatterer: which is the cause I naturally affect a pithy, sinnowie, drie, round, and harsh kind of speach; which of such as have no further acquaintance with me, is judged to encline to disdeine. I honor them most whom I seem to regard least: And where my mind marcheth most cheerfully, I often forget the steps of gravitie: And I offer my self but faintly and rudely to those whose I am indeed, and present my self least to such as I have most given my self. Me thinkes they should read it in my heart, and that the expression of my words wrongeth my conception. To welcome, to take leave, to bid farewell, to give thanks, to salute, to present my service, and such verball complements of the ceremoniall laws of our civilitie, I know no man so sottishly-barren of speeche as my self. And I was never employed to indite letters of favor or commendatorie, but he for whom they were, judged them drie, barren, and faint. The Italians are great Printers of Epistles, whereof I think I have a hundred severall volumes. I deem those of Hanniball Caro to be the best. If all the paper I have heretofore scribled for ladies were extant, at what time my hand was truly transported by my passion, a man should perhaps find some page worthy to be communicated unto idle and fond-doting youth, embabuinized with this fury. I ever write my letters in post-hast, and so rashly headlong, that howbeit I write intolerably ill, I had rather write with my own hand than employ another: for I find none that can follow me, and I never copy them over again. I have accustomed those great persons that know me to endure blots, blurs, dashes, and botches, in my letters, and a sheete without folding or margine. Those that cost me either most labor or studie are they that are least worth. When I once begin to traile them, it is a signe my mind is not upon them. I commonly begin without project: the first word begets the second. Our modern letters are more fraught with borders and prefaces than with matters, as I had rather write two than fold and make up one, which charge I commonly resigne to others: So likewise when the matter is ended, I would willingly give another the charge to adde these long orations, offers, praiers, and imprecations, which we place at the end of them, and wish hartily some new fashion would discharge us of them. As also to superscribe them with a legend of qualities, titles, and callings, wherein, lest I might have tripped, I have often times omitted writing, especially to men of Justice, Lawyers, and Financiers. So many innovations of offices, so difficult a dispensation and ordinance of diverse names and titles of honor, which being so dearely bought, can neither be exchanged or forgotten without offence. I likewise find it gracelesse and idly-foolish to charge the front and inscription of the many bookes and pamphlets which we daily cause to be imprinted with them. Return to CHAPTER XL: THAT THE TASTE OF GOODS OR EVILS DOTH GREATLY DEPEND ON THE OPINION WE HAVE OF THEM CHAPTER XL: THAT THE TASTE OF GOODS OR EVILS DOTH GREATLY DEPEND ON THE OPINION WE HAVE OF THEM EN (says an ancient Greeke sentence) are tormented by the opinions they have of things, and not by things themselves. It were a great conquest for the ease of our miserable humane condition; if any man could establish every where this true proposition. For if evils have no entrance into us but by our judgement, it seems that it lieth in our power either to contemne or turn them to our good: If things yield themselves unto our mercy, why should we not have the fruition of them or apply them to our advantage? If that which we call evil and torment, be neither torment nor evil, but that our fancie only gives it that quality, it is in us to change it: and having the choice of it, if none compell us, we are very fooles to bandy for that partie which is irkesome unto us: and to give infirmities, indigence, and contempt, a sharpe and ill taste, if we may give them a good: And if fortune simply affoord us the matter, it lieth in us to give it the form. Now that that which we terme evil is not so of itself, or at least such as it is that it depends of us to give it another taste and another countenance (for all comes to one), let us see whether it can be maintained. If the originall being of those things we fear, had the credit of its own authority to judge itself in us, likewise and semblable would it lodge in all: For men be all of one kind, and except the most or least, they are furnished with like means to judge and instruments to conceive. But the diversitie of opinions which we have of those things, does evidently show that but by composition they never enter into us. Some one perhaps does lodge them in himself, as they are in essence, but a thousand others give them a new being, and a contrary. We accompt of death, of povertie, and of sorrow, as of our chiefest parts. Now death, which some of all horrible things all the most horrible, who knowes not how others call it the only leaven of this lives torments? the sovereign good of nature? the only staie of our liberty? and the readie and common receit of our evils? And as some do, fearefully- trembling and senslesly-affrighted, expect her coming, others endure it more easily than life: And one complaineth of her facilitie: Mors utinam pavidos vitæ subducere nolles, Sed virtus te sola daret! -- Lucan. iv. 580. O death! I would you would’st let cowards live, That resolv’d valor might you only give. But let us leave these glorious minds: Theodorus answered Lysimachus, who threatened to kill him: ’Thou shall do a great exploit to come to the strength of a Cantharides.’ The greatest number of Philosophers are found to have either by designe prevented, or hastned and furthered their deaths. How many popular persons are seen brought unto death, and not to a simple death, but entermixt with shame and sometimes with grievous torments, to embrace it with such an undaunted assurance, some throngh stubborne wilfulnesse, other some through a natural simplicitie, in whom is nothing seen changed from their ordinary condition; selling their domesticall affairs, recommending themselves unto their friends preaching, singing, and entertaining the people: indeed, and sometimes uttering words of jesting and laughter, and drinking to their acquaintance, as well as Socrates? One who was led to the gallowes, desired it might not be through such a street, for fear a Merchant should set a Serjant on his backe for an old debt. Another wished the hang-man not to touch his throat, lest he should make him swowne with laughing, because he was so ticklish. Another answered his confessor, who promised him he should stop that night with our Saviour in heaven, ’Go thither yourselfe to supper, for I use to fast a nights.’ Another upon the gibbet calling for drinke, and the hang-man drinking first, said he would not drinke after him for fear he should take the pox of him. Everie man has heard the tale of the Piccard, who being upon the ladder readie to be throwen down, there was a wench presented unto him, with this offer (as in some cases our law does sometimes tolerate) that if he would marrie her, his life should be saved, who after he had a while beheld her, and perceiving that she halted, said hastily, ’Away, away, good hang-man, make an end of your business, she limps.’ The like is reported of a man in Denmarke, who being adjudged to have his head cut off, and being upon the scaffold, had the like condition offered him, but refused it, because the wench offered him was jaw-falne, longcheekt, and sharpe-nosed. A young lad at Tholous being accused of heresie in all points touching his beleefe referred himself wholly to his Masters faith (a young schollar that was in prison with him) and rather chose to die than he would be persuaded that his Master could erre. We read of those of the town of Arras at what time King Lewis the eleventh took it, that amongst the common people many were found who rather than they would say ’God save the King,’ suffered themselves to be hanged. And of those base- minded jesters or buffons, some have been seen, that even at the point of death would never leave their jesting and scoffing. He whom the heads-man threw off from the Gallowes cried out, ’Row the Gally,’ which was his ordinary by-word. Another, who being at his last gasp, his friends had lain him upon a pallet alongst the fire-side, there to breathe his last, the Physitian demanding where his grief pained him? answered, ’Betweene the bench and the fire:’ And the Priest to give the last unction, seeking for his feet, which by reason of his sicknesse were shrunken up, he told him ’My good friend, you shall find them at my legs ends if you look well.’ To another that exhorted him to recommend himself to God, he asked, ’Who is going to him?’ And the fellow answering, ’Yourselfe shortly:’ ’If it be his good pleasure, I would to God it might be to morrow nignt,’ replied he. ’Recommend but your self to him,’ said the other, and you shall quickly be there.’ ’It is best then,’ answered he, ’that my self carry my own commendations to him.’ In the, kingdome of Narsinga, even at this day their Priests wives are buried alive with the bodies of their dead husbands. All other wives are burnt at their husbands funerals, not only constantly, but cheerfully. When their King dieth, his wives, his concubines, his minions, together with all his officers and servants, which make a whole people, present themselves so merrily under the fire wherein his body is burnt, that they manifestly seem to esteeme it as a great honor to accompanie their deceased master to his ashes. During our last wars of Millaine, and so many takings, losses, miseries, and calamities of that City the people, impatient of so many changes of fortune, took such a resolution unto death, that I have heard my father say he kept accompt of five and twentie chief householders, that in one weeke made them-selves away: An accident which has some affinity with that of the Xanthians, who being besieged by Brutus, did pell-mell headlong, men, women, and children, precipitate them-selves into so furious a desire of death, that nothing can be performed to avoid death which these did not accomplish to avoid life: So that Brutus had much adoe to save a very small number of them. Every opinion is of sufficient power to take hold of a man in respect of life. The first article of that courageous oath which the Countrie of Greece did sweare and keep in the Median war, was that every particular man should rather change his life unto death, than the Persian laws for theirs. What a world of people are daily seen in the Turkish wars, and the Græcians, more willing to embrace a sharpe, a bitter, and violent death, than to be uncircumcized and baptized? An example whereof no religion is incapable. The Kings of Castile having banished the Jewes out of their countrie, King John of Portugall, for eight crownes a man, sold them a retreit in his dominion for a certain time, upon condition (the time expired) they should avoid, and he find them ships to transport them into Affrike. The day of their departure come, which past, it was expressed that such as had not obeyed should for ever remain bond-slaves, ships were provided them, but very scarce and sparingly: And those which were embarked were so rudely, churlishly, and villainously used by the passengers and marines, who besides infinite other indignites, loitred so long on the seas, now forward, now backward, that in the end they had consumed all their victuals, and were forced, if they would keep themselves alive, to purchase some of them, at so excessive a rate and so long, that they were never set ashore till they had brought them so bare that they had nothing left them but their shirts. The news of this barbarous inhumanitie being reported to those that were yet on land, most of them resolved to yield and continue bond-slaves: whereof some made a semblance to change their religion. Emanuel that immediately succeeded John, being come to the Crowne, first set them at liberty, then changing his mind, commanded them to depart out of his dominions, and for their passage assigned them three ports. He hoped, as Bishop Osorius reporteth (a Latine historian of our ages, not to be despised), that the favor of the liberty to which he had restored them, having failed to converte them unto Christianitie, the difficultie to commit themselves unto marriners and pyrates robberies, to leave a Countrie where they were settled with great riches; for to go seek unknowen and strange regions, would bring them into Portugall again. But seeing all his hopes frustrate, and that they purposed to pass away, he cut off two of the three ports he had promised them, that so the tedious distance and incommoditie of the passage might retaine some, or rather that he might have the meane to assemble them altogether in one place, for a fitter opportunity of the execution be intended which was this. He appointed that all their children under fourteene years of age, should be taken from out of the hands of their parents, and removed from their sight and conversation, to some place where they might be brought up and instructed in our religion. He says that this effect caused an horrible spectacle: the natural affection betweene the fathers and the children, moreover the zeale unto their ancient faith, striving against this violent ordinance. Divers fathers and mothers were ordinarily seen to kill themselves, and with a more cruel example, through compassion and love, to throw their young children into pitts and wells, thereby to shun the Law. The terme which he had prefixed them being expired, for want of other means they yielded unto thraldome. Some became Christians, from whose faith and race, even at this day (for it is an hundred years since) few Portugalls assure themselves; although custom and length of time be much more forcible counsellors unto such mutations than any other compulsion. In the town of Castelnaw Darry, more than fifty Albigeois, all heretikes, at one time, with a determined courage suffred themselves to be burned alive, all in one same fire, before they would recant and disavow their opinions, Quoties non modo ductores nostri sed universi etiam exercitus ad non dubiam mortem concurrerunt? (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’How often have not only our Leaders (says Tully), but also our whole armies, run roundly together to an undoubted death?’ I have seen one of my familiar friends run furiously on death, with such and so deepely in his heart rooted affection, by diverse visages of discourse, which I could never suppress in him, and to the first that offered itself masked with a lustre of honor, without apprehending any shape or violent end, therein to precipitate himself. We have many examples in our days, indeed in very children, of such as for fear of some slight incommoditie have yielded unto death. And to this purpose, says an ancient Writer, what shall we not fear, if we fear that which cowardice itself has chosen for her retrait? Here to huddle up a long head-rowle of those of all sexes, conditions, sects, in most happy ages, which either have expected death most constantly, or sought for it voluntarily, and not only sought to avoid the evils of this life, but some, only to shun the satietie of living any longer: and some, for the hope of a better condition elsewhere, I should never have done. The number is so infinite, that verily it would be an easier matter for me to reckon up those that have feared the same. Only this more. Pirro the Philosopher, finding himself upon a very tempestuous day in a boat, showed them whom he perceived to be most affrighted through fear, and encouraged them by the example of an hog that was amongst them, and seemed to take no care at all for the storme: Shall we then dare to say that the advantage of reason, whereat we seem so much to rejoice, and for whose respect we account ourselves Lords and Emperours of all other creatures, has been infused into us for our torment? What availeth the knowledge of things, if through them we become more demiss? If thereby we lose the rest and tranquillitie wherein we should be without them? and if it makes us of worse condition than was Pirrhos hog? Shall we employ the intelligence Heaven has bestowed upon us for our greatest good, to our ruine? repugning natures desseign and the universal order and vicissitude of things, which implieth that every man should use his instruments and means for his own commoditie? Wel (will some tell me) let your rule fit you against death, but what will you say of indigence and necessitie? what will you also say of mind- grieving sorrow, which Aristippus, Hieronymus, and most of the wisest have judged-the last evil? and those which denied the same in words confessed the same in effect? Possidonius being extremely tormented with a sharpe and painfull sicknesse, Pompey came to see him, and excused himself he had chosen so unfit an hour to hear him discourse of Philosophy: ’God forbid (answered Possidonius) that ever pain should so far usurpe upon me as to hinder me from discoursing of so worthy a subject. And thereupon began to speak of the contempt of pain. But there whilst she plaied her part, and uncessantly pinched and urged him, gainst whom he exclaimed: ’Paine do what you list, I shall never be drawne to say that you are an evil.’ That saying, which they would make of such consequence, what does it interre against the contempt of pain? it contends but for the word. And if the pangs thereof move him not therewhilst, why breakes he off his discourse for it? Why thinks he to work a great exploit, not to call it an evil? All does not consist in imagination. Here we judge of the rest. It is assured learning that here does play her part, our own senses are judges of it. Qui nisi sunt veri; ratio quogue falsa sit omnis.-- Lucr. iv. 487. Which senses if they be not true, All reason’s false, it must ensue. Shall we make our skin believe the stripes of a whip do tickle it? and persuade our taste that Aloes be wine of Graves? Pirrhos hog is here in our predicament. He is nothing danted at death, but if you beat him he will grunt, crie, and torment himself. Shall we force the general law of nature, which in all living creatures under heaven is seen to tremble at pain? The very trees seem to groan at offences. Death is but felt by discourse, because it is the motion of an instant. Aut fuit, aut veniet, nihil est præsentis in illa. Death has come, or it will not misse; But in it nothing present is. Morsque minus pænæ, quam mora mortis habet. -- Ovid. Epis. Ariad. 82. Deaths pain’s less, roundly acted. Than when death is protracted. A thousand beasts, a thousand men, are sooner dead than threatned. Besides, what we principally call fear in death, it is pain, her customarie fore-runner. Nevertheless if we must give credit to an ancient father, Malam mortem non facit, nisi quod sequitur mortem. ’Nothing but what follows death makes death to be evil.’ And I might more truly say, that neither that which goeth before, nor that which commeth after, is no appurtenance of death, we falsely excuse ourselves. And I find by experience that it is rather the impatience of the imagination of death that makes us impatient of the pain, and that we feel it twofold grievous, forasmuch as it threats us to die. But reason accusing our weaknesse, to fear so sudden a thing, so unavoidable, so insensible; we take this other more excusable pretence. All evills that have no other danger but of the evil, we count them dangerlesse. The tooth-ach, the pain of the gowt, how grievous soever, because they kill not, who reckoneth them in the number of Maladies? Well, suppose that in death we especially regard the pain: As also povertie has nothing to be feared for but what she casteth upon us through famine, thirst, cold, heat, and other miseries, it makes us feel and endure. So have we nothing to do but with pain. I will willingly grant them that it is the worst accident of our being. For I am the man that hate and shun it as much as possibly may be; because hitherto (thanks be unto God) I have no commerce or dealing with her: But it is in our power, if not to dissanull, at least to diminish the same, through patience: and though tne body should be moved thereat, yet to keep the mind and reason in good temper. And if it were not so, who then has brought virtue, valor, force, magnanimity, and resolution into credit? Where shall they play their part if there be no more pain defied? Avida est periculi virtus: ’ Vertue is desirous of danger.’ If a man must not lie on the hard ground, armed at all assaies, to endure the heat of the scorching Sunne, to feed hungerly upon a horse or an asse, to see himself mangled and cut in peeces, to have a bullet pluckt out of his bones, to suffer incisions, his flesh to be stitcht up, cauterized, and searched, all incident to a martiall man; how shall we purchase the advantage and preheminence which we so greedily seek after, over the vulgar sort? It is far from avoiding the evil and paines of it, as wise men say, that of actions equally good, one should most be wished to be done wherein is most pain and grief. Non enim hilaritate nec lascivia, nec risu aut joco comite levitatis, sed sæpe etiam tristes firmitate et constantia sunt beati: (Cic. De Fin. ii.) ’For men are not happy by mirthfulnesse, or wantonnesse, or laughing, or jesting, which is the companion of lightness; but often, even those that are sorrowfull, through their strong heart and constancy.’ And therefore was it impossible to persuade our fathers that conquests achieved by main force, in the hazard of war, were not more available and advantageous than those obtained in all securitie by practices and stratagems. Lætius est, quoties magno sibi constat honestum. -- Luca. ix. 404. Honesty makes chiefest cheare When it does cost itself most dear. Moreover, this ought to comfort us, that naturally , if pain be violent, it is also short; if long, it is easy: Si gravis, brevis; si longus, levis. (Cic. De Fin. ii. Epic.) ’If it be grievous, it is short; if it be long, it is light.’ Thou shall not feel it over long; if you feel it over much, it will either end itself or end you: All comes to one: If you bear not it, it will bear you away. Memineris maximos morte finiri, parvos multa habere intervalla requietis; mediocrium nos esse dominos: ut si tolerabiles sint feramus: sin minus, e vita, quum ea non placeat, tanquam e theatre exeamus; (i.) ’Remember the greatest are ended with death, the lesser have many pauses of rest; we are masters of the meane ones: so as if they be tolerable, we may hear them; if not, we may make an exit from our life, which does not please, as from a stage. That which makes us endure pain with such impatience is, that we are not accustomed to take our chief contentment in the soul, and that we do not sufficiently rely on her, who is the only and sovereign mistris of our condition. The body has (except the least or most) but one course, and one byase. The soul is variable in all manner of formes, and rangeth to herself, and to her estate, whatsoever it be, the senses of the body, and all other accidents. Therefore must she be studied, enquired and sought after: and her powerful springs and wards should be rowzed up. There is neither reason, nor prescription, nor force can avail against her inclination and choice. Of so infinit byases that she has in her disposition, let us allow her one suitable and fit to our rest and preservation: Then shall we not only be sheltered from all offence, but if it please her, also gratified and flattered of all grievances and evils. She indifferently makes profit of all, even errours and dreames, do profitably bestead her, as a loyall matter, to bring us unto safety and contentment. It may easily be seen, that the point of our spirit is that which sharpeneth both pain and pleasure in us. Beasts wanting the same leave their free and natural senses unto their bodies: and by consequence, single well-nigh in every kind, as they show by the semblable application of their movings. If in our members we did not trouble the jurisdiction which in that belongs unto them, it may be thought w e should be the better for it, and that nature has given them a just and moderate temperature toward pleasure and toward pain; And it cannot chuse but be good and just, being small and common. But since we have freed and alienated ourselves from her rules, to abandon ourselves unto the vagabond liberty of our fantasies, let us at least help to bend them to the most agreeing side. Plato feareth our sharp engaging unto pain and voluptuousness, forasmuch as he over-strictly tieth and bindeth the soul unto the body: I am rather opposit unto him, because it is sundred and loosed from it. Even as an enemy becometh more furious when we flie from him, so does pain grow more proud if it see us tremble under it. It will stoop and yield upon better compositions to him that shall make head against it. A man must oppose and bandy against it. In recoyling and giving ground, we call and draw on the ruine threatning us. Even as the body is more steady and strong to a charge if it stand stiffely to it, so is the soul. But let us come to examples properly belonging to weak-backt men, as I am, where we shall find it is with pain as with stones, which take either higher or deeper colour according to the soyle that is laid under them, and holdeth no other place in us than we give it. Tantum doluerunt, quantum doloribus se inseruerunt (August.) ’So much they grieved, as they interessed themselves in griefes.’ We feel a dash of a chirurgions razor more than ten blows with a sword in the heat of fight. The painefull throwes of child bearing, deemed both by Physitians and by the word of God to be very great, and which our women pass with so many ceremonies, there are whole Nations that make no reckoning of them. I omit to speak of the Lacedemonian women; but come we to the Swizzers of our Infanterie, what change do you perceive in them? But that trudging and trotting after their husbands, to day you see them carrie the child about their neck which but yesterday they bare in their wombe. And those counterfeit roguing Gyptians, whereof so many are daily seen amongst us, do they not wash children so soone as they are borne, and in the next river that comes to hand? Besides so many harlots which daily steale their children in the delivery as in the conception. The beauteous and noble Lady of Sabinus, a Roman Patritian, for the interest of others did alone, without any bodies helpe or assistance an without noise or groning, endure the bearing and deliverie of two twins. A simple lad of Lacedemon having stolne a fox (for they more feared the shame of their foolishnesse in stealing than we fear the pain or punishment of mis-deeds) and hiding the same under his cloake, endured rather to have his guts gnawne out by her, than to discover himself. Another, while offering incense at a sacrifice, suffered his flesh to burne to the bone by a coale falne into his sleeve, rather than he would trouble that sacred mysterie. And a great number have been seen, for the only essay of virtue, following their institution, that at the age of seven years, without so much as changing their countenance, have endured to be whipped to death. And Cicero has seen whole troups to beat one another so long with their fists, with their feet, and with their teeth, till they have fainted and fallen down halfe dead, before ever they would confesse to be overcome. Nunquam naturam mos vinceret, est enim ea semper invicta: sed nos umbris, delitiis, otio, languore, desidia, animum infecimus: opinionibus maloque more delinitum mollivimus: (Cic. Tusc. Quest. v.) ’Custome should never overcome nature, for she is still invincible: but we have infected our mind with shadowes, daintinesse, idlenesse, faint-heartednesse, slothfulnesse, and have effeminaied it, inveagled with opinions and evil customs.’ Every man knows the story of Scævola, who being entered the enemies campe, with a full resolution to kill their Chieftaine, and having missed of his purpose, to checke his effect with a stranger invention, and to clear his country, confessed unto Prosenna (who was the King he intended to kill) not only his dessigne, but added, moreover, that in his campe there were a great many Romanes, who had undertaken and sworne the very same enterprise, and were confederates with him. And to make show of his dread-less magnanimity, having caused a pan of burning coales to be brought, he saw and suffred his right arm (in penance that it had not effected his project) to be parched and well-nigh roasted-off: until such time as his enemy himself, feeling a kind of remorcefull horror, commanded the fire to be carried away. What shall we say of him that would not vouchsafe to leave, or so much as to interrupt the reading of his book, whilst he had an incision made into him? And of him who resolved to skoffe and laugh, even in spight and contempt of the tortures which were inflicted upon him, so that the raging crueltie of the hangmen that held him, and all the inventions of torments that could be devised, being redoubled upon him, one in the necke of another gave him over? But he was a Philosopher; What of one of Cæsars gladiators, who with a cheerful and smiling countenance endured his wounds to be slit and sounded? Quis mediocres gladiator ingemuit? Quis vultum mutavit unquam? Qu is non modo stetit, verum etiam decubuit turpiter? Quis cum decubuisset, ferrum recipere jussus, collum contraxit? (Cic. Tusc. Quest. ii.) ’What meane Fencer has once groned? Which of them has once changed his countenance? Which of them not only has stood up, but even falne with shame? Which of them when he was down, and was willed to take his death, did once shrinke in his necke?’ But let us join some women unto them. Who has not heard of her at Paris, which only to get a fresher hew of a new skin, endured to have her face flayed all over? There are some, who being sound and in perfit health, have had some teeth puld-out, thereby to frame a daintier and more pleasing voice, or to set them in better order. How many examples of conternpt of pain or smart have we of that kind and sex? What can they not do? What will they not do? What fear they to do? So they may but hope for some amendment of their beautie? Vellere queis cura est albos a stirpe capillos, Et faciem dempta pell e refer novam. -- Tibul. i. El. viii. 43. Who take great care to root out their gray hair. And skin flayed-off a new face to repare. I have seen some swallow gravell, ashes, coales, dust, tallow, candles, and for the nonce labor and toyle themselves to spoile their stomacke, only to get a pale-bleake colour. To become slender in were, and to have a straight spagnolized body, what pinching, what girding, what cingling will they not endure? Yea sometimes with yron-plates, with whale- bones, and other such trash, that their very skin and quick flesh is eaten in and consumed to the bones; whereby they sometimes work their own death. It is common to diverse nations of our times, to hurt and gash themselves in good earnest, to give credit to their words. And our King reporteth sundrie examples of what himself saw in Polonia, and towards himself. But besides what I know to have by some been imitated in France; when I came from the famous Parliament of Blois, I had a little before seen a wench in Picardie to witnes the vehemence of her promises, and also her constancy, with the bodkin she wore in her hair to give herself foure or five thrusts in her arm, which made her skin to crack and gush out blood. The Turkes are wont to wound and scarre themselves for their Ladies sakes, and that the marke may the better appeare, and continue the longer, they will presently lay fire upon their cuttes; and to stanch the blood, and better to form the cicatrice, they wil keep it on an incredible while. Honest men that have seen it, have written the same, and sworne it unto me. And for ten Aspers you shall daily find some amongst them that will give themselves a deepe gash with a Scimitarie, either in their arms or thighes. I am very glad witnesses are so ready at hand where we have most need of them: For Christendome affordeth many. And after the example of our holy guide, there have been diverse who for devotion would needs bear the crosse. We learne by a worthy testimony of religion, that Saint Lewes the King wore a hair shirt, until such time as he was so aged that his confessor gave him a dispensation for it; and that every Friday he caused his priests to beat his shoulders with five little yron chaines, which to that purpose were ever caried with his nightgeare. William our last Duke of Guyenne, father to that Eleonore who transferred that Dutchy unto the houses of France and England, the last ten or twelve years of his life, for penance-sake, wore continually a corselet under a religious habit. Foulkes Earle of Anjou went to Jerusalem, there with a rope about his necke to be whipped by two of his servants, before our Saviours sepulchre. Doe we not upon every Good-Friday, in sundrie places, see a great number of men and women scourge and beat themselves so long, till they bruse and teare their flesh, even to the bones? I have often seen it my self; and that without enchantment; And some say (for they are masked) there were some amongst them, who for monie would undertake thereby to warrant other mens religion, by a contempt of smart-full pain, so much the greater by how much the stings of devotion are of more force than those of covetousnes. Q. Maximus buried his son who had been Consull: Marcus Cato his, being elected Pretor; and L. Paulus both his, within few days, with so cheerful and setled a countenance, and without any show of sorrow. I have sometimes by way of jesting told one that he had confronted divine justice: For, the violent death of three tall children of his, cumming unto his ears all upon one day, and sent him, as it may be imagined, as a great scourge: he was so far from mourning, that he rather took it as a favor and singular gratification at Gods hand. I do not follow these monstrous humors. Yet have I lost two or three my self, whilst they were young and at nurce, if not without apprehension of sorrow, yet without continuæce of griefs. And ’there is no accident woundeth mon deeper, or goeth so near the heart as the loss of children.’ I see diverse other common occasions of affliction which, were I assailed by them, I should scarcely feel. And I have contemned and neglected some, when it has pleased God to visit me with them, on which the world setteth so ugly and balefull a countenance, that I hardly dare boast of them without blushing. Ex quo intelligitur, non in natura, sed in opinione esse ægretudinem. (Cic. ib. iii.) ’Whereby it is understood that grief consisteth not in nature, but opinion.’ Opinion is a powerful, bould, and unmeasureable party. Who does ever so greedily search after rest-full ease and quietnes as Alexander and Cæsar have done after difficulties and unquietnesse? Terez, the father of Sitalcez, was wont to say, that when he had no wars, he thought there was no difference betweene him and his horse- keeper. Cato the Consull, to assure himself of certain townes in Spain, having only interdicted some of their inhabitants to weare arms, many of them killed themselves: Ferox gens nullam vitam rati sine, armis esse: ’A fierce kind of people, that thought there was no life without arms.’ How many know we who have abandoned and forsaken the pleasure of an ease-full and quiet life in their houses, and to live with their friends and acquaintance, to follow the toyling-horror of unfrequented deserts, and that yielded and cast themselves unto the abjectnesse, contempt and vilifying of the world, wherwith they have so pleased themselves, as nothing more; Cardinall Boromeus, who died lately at Milan, in the midst of the pleasures and debawches to which his nobility, and the great riches he possessed enticed him, and the air of Italy afforded him, and his youth allured him, did ever keep himself in so an austere form of life, that the same gowne which served him in summer he wore in winter. He never lay but upon straw: the hours which he might conveniently spare from his charge, he bestowed in continual study, ever kneeling, and having a smal quantitie of bread and water by his bookes side, which was all the provision for his repast, and time he employed in study. I know some who wittingly have drawne both profit and preferment from cuckoldrie, the only name whereof is so yrksome and bail-ful to so many men. If sight be not the most necessarie of our senses, at least is it the most pleasing: the most plausible and profitable of our members, seem those that serve to beget us: notwithstanding diverse have mortally hated them, only because they were over much amiable, and for their worths-sake have rejected them. So thought he of his eyes, that voluntarily put them out. The most common and soundest part of men holdeth multitude of children to be a signe of great happinesse and comfort; So do I, and many others, the want of them. And when Thales was demanded why he did not marrie, he answered, because he would leave no issue or line of himself behinde him. What our opinion endeareth and increaseth the price of things, it is seen in a great number of them, which we do not regard to esteeme them, but for our use. As we neither consider their qualities nor utilities, but only our cost to recover and attaine them; as if it were a part of their substance; and we call that worth in them, not what they bring us, but what we bring to them. According as it weigheth and is of consequence, so it serveth. Whereupon I perceive we are thriftie husbands of what we lay out. Our opinion never suffers it to run a false gallop. ’The price gives a Diamond his title, difficultie to virtue, pain unto devotion, and sharpnesse unto physicke.’ Such a one to come unto povertie, cast those fewe crownes he had into the same sea wherein so many others, with such carke, danger, and care, on all parts seek to fish for riches. Epicurus says, that ’To be rich is no ease, but a change of affairs.’ Verily, it is not want, but rather plentie that causeth avarice. I will speak of my own experience concerning this subject. I have lived in three kinds of condition since I came out of my infancie. The first time, which continued well-nigh twentie years. I have past it over as one who had no other means but casual, and depending from the direction and helpe of others, without any certain maintenance or regular prescription. My expences were so much the more carelessely layed out and lavishly employed, by how much more they wholy depended on fortunes rashnesse and exhibition. I never lived so well at ease: my fortune was never to find my friends purse shut; besides which, I was to frame my self to all necessities: the care I took to pay every man at his prefixed day, which a thousand times they have prolonged, seeing the care I took to satisfie them. So that I had gotten unto my self the credit of a thriftie kind of good husbandrie, though it were something shifting and deceitful. I do naturally feel a kind of pleasing contentment in paying of my debts, as if I rid my self of a burthenous weight, and free my self from the yoake of bondage and ingratitude. Besides, me thinks I feel a kind of delight that tickleth me to the quick, in performing a lawfully just action, and contenting of others. I except payments that require delayes, covenants, and after reckonings: for, if I find any body that will undertake them, I blushingly and injuriously deferre them as long as I can, for fear of that altercation or wrangling to which my humor and manner of speech is altogether incompatible. There is nothing I hate more than driving of bargaines: It is a meere commerce of dodging and impudencie. After an hours debating and paltring, both parties will go from their words and oaths for the getting or saving of a shilling: yet did I borrow with great disadvantage. For, having no heart to borrow before others, or by word of mouth, I would adventure it upon a peece of paper, which with some has no great power to move or force to persuade, and which greatly helps to refuse, I was wont to commit the success of my wants more freely and more carelessely unto fortune than I have done since unto my wit and providence. Most good husbands think it strange add horrible to live on such uncertainties, but they remember not that most men in the world live so. How many good and well-borne men have heretofore, and are daily seen to neglect and leave at six and seven their patrimonies and certain goods, to follow and seek after court-holy water and wavering favors of Princes and of fortune; Cæsar engaged and endebted himself above a million of gold more than he was worth to become Cæsar . And how many merchants and poore beginners set up and begin their traffike by the sale of their farmes or cottages which they ventur to the Indias? Tot per impotentia freta. -- Catul. Epig. iv. 18. In so great scarcitie of devotion we have thousands of Colleges, which pass the time very conveniently, daily gaping and expecting from the liberalitie of the heavens what they must dine withall to morrow. Secondly, they consider not that this certaintie on w hich the ground themselves, is not much less uncertaine and hazardous than hazard it self. I see misery as near beyond two thousand crownes rent, as if it were hard at hand. For, besides that fortune has many-many means to open a hundred gaps for povertie to enter at, even through the thickest of our riches, and that often there is no meane betweene the highest and lowest fortune. Fortuna vitrea est: tum quum splendet frangitur. -- Prov. Senec. f. Fortune is glasse-like, brittle as ’ tis bright: Light-gon, light-broken, when it lends best light. And to turn all our defences and raisings of high walls topsie-turvie: I find that want and necessitie is by diverse or different causes, as ordinarily seen to accompanie and follow those that are rich in goods, as those that have none at all: and that perhaps it is somewhat less incommodious when it is alone, than when it meeteth with riches. They rather come from order than from receit: Feber est sua quisq ue fortunæ: (Eras. Chil. ii. cent. iv. eid. 63) ’Every man is the forger of his own fortune.’ And methinkes that a rich man who is needy, full of business, carke and toyle, and troubled in mind, is more miserable than he that is simply poore. In divitiis inopes quod genus egestatis gravissimum est. (Sen. Epist. lxxiv. p.) ’In their abundance indigent, which is the most grievous kind of indigence.’ The richest and greatest princes are ordinarily urged by povertie and need unto extreme necessities. For, can any be more extreme than thereby to become Tyrants, and unjust usurpers of their subjects goods. My second manner of life has been to have money; which when I had once fingred, according to my condition I sought to hoard up some against a rainie day; esteeming that it was no having unless a man had ever somewhat besides his ordinary expenses in possession: and that a man should not trust that good which he must live in hope to receive; and that, be his hopes never so likely, he may many ways be prevented. For, I would say unto my self; what if I should be surprised by this chance or that accident? What should I do then? And in pursuit of these vain and vicious imaginations, I endeavour by hooke or crooke, and by wile or wit, to provide by this superfluous sparing for all inconveniences that might happen: And I could answer him that would alleage the number of inconveniences to be over infinit: which if they followed not all men, they accompanied some, and perhaps the greatest number. An apprehension which I did not pass without some painfull care. I kept the matter secret, and I (that dare say so much, of myself) would never speak of my money but falsly; as others do, who being rich, would seem to be poore, or being poore, would appeare rich: and dispense with their conscience, never to witness sincerely what they are worth. Oh ridiculous and shamefull prudence. Did I travell any where? me thought I was never sufficiently provided; and the more I had laden my self with coine, the more I had also burdened my self with fear: sometimes of my ways-safetie, othertimes of their trust that had the charge of my sumpters and baggage, whereof as some others that I know, me thought I was never throughly assured, except it were still in my sight. Left I my keyes or my purse behind me? how many suspitions and thornie imiginations, and which is worse, incommunicable, did uncessantly haunt me? My mind was ever on my halfpenny; my thoughts ever that way. The summe being rightly cast, there is ever more pain in keeping than in getting of monie. If I did not altogether so much as I say, I at the least endeavoured to do it. Of commoditie I had little or nothing. To have more means of expenses, is ever to have increase of sorrow. For (as said Bion) ’The hairie man does grieve as much as the bald, if he have his hair pulled out.’ And after you are once accustomed, and have fixed your thoughts upon a heape of monie, it is no longer at your service; you dare not diminish it; it is a building which, if you touch or take any part from it, you will think it will all fall. Necessitie must first pinch you by the throat, and touch you near, before you will lay hands on it. And I should sooner pawne my clothes, or sell my horse with less care and compulsion, than make a breach into that beloved purse which I kept in store. But the danger was that a man can hardly prefix a certain limits unto his desire (they are hard to be found in things a man deemeth good) and continue at one stay in sparing: A man shall ever encrease this heape from one number to another; indeed so long till he basely and niggardly deprive himself of enjoying his own goods, and wholly fix on the safe keeping of them, and never use them. According to this kind of usage, those are the richest people of the world have the charge of keeping the gates and walles of a rich Cittie. Every monied man is covetous, according to mine opinion. Plato marshalleth [thus] humane or corporall goods; health, beautie, strength, riches: And riches (says he) are not blind, but clear-seeing, if they be illummated by wisdom. Dionysius the younger plaid a notable part; who being advertised that one of his Siracusans had hidden a certain treasure under the ground, commanded him to bring it unto him, which he did, reserving secretly one part of it unto himself, with which he removed his dwelling unto another City, where having lost the humor of hoarding up of treasure, began to live a spending and riotous kind of life: which Dionysius hearing, commanded the remainder of his treasure, and which he had taken from him, to be restored unto him; saying, that ’sithence he had learned how to make use of it, he did most willingly redeliver the same unto him.’ I was some years of the same humor: I wot not what good Demon did most profitably remove me from it, like to the Siracusan, and made me to neglect my sparing. The pleasure I apprehended of a far and chargeable journey having overthrowne this foolish imagination in me; From which I am falne into a third kind of life (I speak what I think of it) assuredly much more pleasing and formall: which is, that I measure my garment according to my cloth , and let my expenses go together with my coming in; sometimes the one, otherwhilst the other exceeds: But they are never far asunder. I live from hand to mouth, from day to day, and have I but to supply my present and ordinary needs, I am satisfied: As for extraordinarie wants, all the provisions of the world will not suffice them. And it is folly to expect that fortune will ever sufficiently arm us against herself. It is with our own weapons that we must combat her. Casuall arms will betray us, when we shall have most need of them. If I lay up anything, it is for the hope of some employment at hand, and not to purchase lands, whereof I have no need, but pleasure and delight. Non esse cupidum, pecunia est: non esse emacem, vectigal est: (Cic. Parad. ult.) ’It is currant coine not to be covetous: it is a thriftie income not to be still buying.’ I am neither possessed with fear that my goods shall faile me, nor with desire that they should encrease and multiply. Divitiarum fructus est in copia; Copiam declarat satietas: (ibid.) ’The fruit of riches is in plentie: satietie content with enough, approves that plentie.’ And I singularly gratifie my self this correction came upon me in an age naturally inclined to covetousnesse and that I am free from that folly so common and peculiar to old men, and the most ridiculous of all humane follies. Feraulez who had passed through both fortunes, and found that encrease of goods was no accrease of appetite to drinke, to eat, to sleepe, or to embrace his wife; and who on the other side felt heavily on his shoulders the importunitie of ordering and directing his Oeconomicall affairs, as it does on mine, determined with himself to content a poore young man, his faithfull friend, greedily gaping after riches, and frankly made him a present donation of all his great and excessive riches; as also of those he was likely everie day to get by the liberalitie and bountie of his good master Cyrus and by war: always provided he should undertake to entertaine and find him, honestly and in good sort, as his guest and friend. In which estate they lived afterward most happily, and mutually content with the change of their condition. See here a part I could willingly find in my heart to imitate. And I much commend the fortune of an old prelate, whom I see to have so clearly given over his purse, his receits, and his expenses, now to one of his chosen servants, and now to another, that he has lived many years as ignorant of his household affairs as any stranger. The confidence in others honesty is no light testimony of ones own integritie: therefore does God willingly favor it. And for his regard, I see no household order, neither more worthily directed, nor more constantly managed than his. Happy is that man that has so proportionably directed his estate, as his riches may discharge and supply the same, without care or encombrance to himself: and that neither their consultation or meetings may in any sort interrupt other affairs, or disturbe other occupations, which followeth, more convenient, more quiet, and better agreeing with his heart. Therefore does ease and indigencie depend from every mans own opinion; and wealth and riches, no more than glory or health, have either more preheminence or pleasure, than he who possesseth them, lendeth them. Every man is either or ill, according as he findes himself. Not he whom another thinkes content, but he is content indeed that thinkes he is so himself; And only in that, opinion gives itself essence and veritie. Fortune does us neither good nor ill: She only offereth us the seed and matter of it, which our mind, more powerfull than she, turneth and applieth as best it pleaseth: as the efficient cause and mistris of condition, whether happy or unhappy. External accessions take both favor and colour from the internall constitution: As garments do not warme us by their heat, but by ours, which they are fit to cover and nourish: he that with clothes should cover a cold body, should draw the very same service from them by cold. So is snow and yce kept in summer. Verily as unto an idle and lazie body, study is but a torment: abstinence from wine to a drunkard is a vexation; frugality is a harts sorrow to the luxurious; and exercise molesteth an effeminate body: so is it of all things else. Things are not of themselves so irksome nor so hard, but our basenes and weaknesse maketh them such. To judge of high and great matters, a high and great mind is required; otherwise we attribute that vice unto them which indeed is ours. A straight oar, being under water seems to be crooked. It is no matter to see a thing, but the matter is how a man does see the same. Well, of so many discourses, which diversly persuade men to contemne death and patiently to endure pain, why shall we not find some one to make for our purpose; And of so severall and many kinds of imaginations, that have persuaded the same unto others, why does not every man apply one unto himself, that is most agreeing with his humor; If he cannot digest a strong and abstersive drug, for to remove his evil, let him at least take a lenitive pill to ease the same. Opinio est quædam effoeminata ac levis: nec in dolore magis, quam eadem in voluptate: qua, quum liquescimus fluimusque mollitia, apis aculeum sine clamore ferre, non possumus. Totum in eo est, ut tibi imperes: (Cic. Tusc. Quest. ii.) ’There is a certain effeminate and light opinion, and that no more in sorrow than it is in pleasure, whereby when we melt and run over in daintie tendernes, we cannot abide to be stung of a be, but must rore and crie out. This is the total summe of all, that you be master of your self.’ Moreover, a man does not escape from Philosophy by making the sharpnes of paines and humane weaknesse to provaile so far beyond measure: for she is compelled to cast herself over again unto these invincible replications. If it be bad to live in necessitie, at least there is no necessitie to live in necessitie. No man is long time ill but by his own fault. He that has not the heart to endure neither life nor death, and that will neither resist nor run away, what shall a man do to him? Return to CHAPTER XLI: THAT A MAN SHOULD NOT COMMUNICATE HIS GLORIE CHAPTER XLI: THAT A MAN SHOULD NOT COMMUNICATE HIS GLORIE F ALL the follies of the world, the most universall, and of most men received, is the care of reputation and study of glory, to which we are so wedded that we neglect and cast-off riches, friends, repose, life and health (goods effectuall and substantiall), to follow that vain image, and idlie-simple voice, which has neither body nor hold-fast. La fama, ch’invaghisce a un dolce suono Gli superbi mortali, et par si bella, E un echo, un sogn o, anzi d’un sogno un ombra, Ch’ad ogni vento si dilegua e sgombra. -- Tass. Gior. can. 14. Faine that enveagl’s high aspiring men With her harmonious sound, and seems so fair, An Eccho is, a dreame, dreames shadow rather, Which flies and fleets as any winde does gather. And of mens unreasonable humors, it seems that the best philosophers do most slowly and more unwillingly clear themselves of this than of another: it is the most peevish, the most froward, and the most opinative. Quia etiam bene proficientes animos tentare non cessat (Cic. Pro Arc. Po.). ’Because it ceaseth not to tempt even those Mindes that profit best.’ There are not many whereof reason does so evidently condemne the vanity, but it is so deeply rooted in us, as I wot not whether any man could ever clearely discharge himself of it. When you have alleged all the reasons you can, and beleeved all to disavow and reject her, she produces, contrary to your discourses, so intestine inclination, that you have small hold against her. For (as Cicero says), ’Even those that appugne her, will nevertheless have the bookes they write against her to bear their names upon their fronts, endeavouring to make themselves glorious by despising of glory.’ All other things fall within the compasse of commerce: we lend our goods, we employ our lives, if our friends stand in need of us: But seldom shall we see a man communicate his honor, share his reputation, and impart his glory unto others. Catulus Luctatius in the wars against the Cymbres, having done the utmost of his endeavors to stay his soldiers that fled before their enemies, put himself amongst the runawaies, and dissembled to be a coward, that so they might rather seem to follow their Captain than flie from the enemy: This was a neglecting and leaving off his reputatation, to conceal the shame and reproach of other. When Charles the fifth passed into Provence, the yeare a thousand five hundred thirty seven, some are of opinion that Anthony de Leva, seeing the Emperor his master resolutely obstinate to undertake that voyage, and deeming it wonderfully glorious, maintained nevertheless the contrary, and discounselled him from it, to the end that all the honor and glory of this counsell might be attributed unto his Master; and that it might he said, his good advice and foresight to have been such; that contrary to all mens opinions, he had achieved so glorious an enterprise: Which was, to honor and magnifie him at his own charges. Thracian Ambassadors comforting Archileonida, the mother of Brasidas, for the death of her son, and highly extolling and commending him, said he had not left his equall behind him. She refused this private commendation and particular praise, assigning it to the public state. ’Doe not tell me that (quoth she), for knowe the Cittie of Sparta has many greater and more valiant Citizens than he was.’ At the battle of Crecy, Edward the blacke Prince of Wales, being yet very young, had the leading of the vant-gard: The greatest and chief violence of the fight was in his quarter: The Lord and Captain that accompanied him, perceiving the great danger, sent unto King Edward, the Princes Father, to come and help them: which when he heard, he enquired what plight his son was in, and how he did, and hearing that he was living and on horse-backe, ’I should (quoth he) offer him great wrong to go now, and deprive him of the honor of this combats victory, which he already has so long sustained; what danger soever there be in it, it shall wholly be his:’ and would neither go nor send unto him: knowing that if he had gone or sent, it would have been said that without his ayd all had been lost, and that the advantage of this exploit would have been ascribed unto him. Semper enim quod postremum adjectum est, id rem totam videtur traxisse. ’For evermore that which was last added, seems to have drawne on the whole matter.’ In Rome many thought, and it was commonly spoken, that the chiefest glorious deeds of Scipio were partly due unto Lælius, who notwithstanding did ever advance the greatness, further the glory, and second the renown of Scipio, without any respect of his own. And Theopompus King of Sparta, to one who told him that the commonwealth should subsist and continue still, forasmuch as he could command so well: ’No,’ said he, ’it is rather because the people know so well how to obey.’ As the women who succeeded in the Peeredomes of France had (notwithstanding their sex) right to assist and privilege to plead in cases appertaining to the jurisdictions of Peeres: so the Ecclesiasticall Peeres, notwithstanding their profession and function, were bound to assist our Kings in their wars, not only with their friends, servants, and tenants, but in their own person. The Bishop of Beauvais, being with Philip Augustus in the battle of Bovines, did very courageously take part with him in the effect: but thought he should not be partaker of the fruit and glory of that bludy and violent exercise.He overcame and forced that day many of the enemies to yield whom he delivered unto the first gentleman he met withall to rifle, to take them prisoners, or at their pleasure to dispose of them. Which he also did with William Earle of Salisbury, whom he delivered unto the Lord John of Nesle with a semblable subtletie of conscience unto this other. He desired to fell and strike down a man, but not to wound or hurt him, and therefore never fought but with a great club. A man in my time being accused to the King to have laid violent hands upon a priest, denied it very stoutly, forasmuch as he had only thumped and trampled him with his feet. Return to : Book I CHAPTER XLII: OF THE INEQUALITIE THAT IS BETWEENE US CHAPTER XLII: OF THE INEQUALITIE THAT IS BETWEENE US LUTARKE says in some place, that he findes no such great difference betweene beast and beast, as he findeth diversitie betweene man and man.’ He speaks of the sufficience of the mind and of internall qualities. Verily I find Epaminondas so far (taking him as I suppose him) from some that I know (I meane capable of common sense) as I could find in my heart to endeare upon Plutarke, and say there is more difference betweene such and such a man than there is diversitie betweene such a man and such a beast. Hem vir viro quid præstat! -- Ter. Phor. act. v. sc. 3. O Sir, how much has one, Another man out-gone? And that there be so many degrees of spirits as there are steps betweene heaven and earth and as innumerable. But concerning the estimation of men, it is marvell that, except our selves, no one thing is esteemed but for its proper qualities. We commend a horse because he is strong and nimble, --- --volucrem Sic laudamus equum, facili cui plurima palma Fervet, et exultat rauco victoria circo. -- Juven. Sat. viii. 57. We praise the horse, that bears most bells with flying, And triumphs most in races hoarse with crying, and not for his furniture: a greyhound for his swiftnesse, not for his collar: a hawke for her wing, not for her cranes or bells. Why do we not likewise esteeme a man for that which is his own? He has a goodly traine of men following him, a stately pallace to dwell in, so great credit amongst men, and so much rent coming in. Alas, all that is about him and not in him. No man will buy a pig in a poke. If you cheapen a horse, you will take his saddle and clothes from him, you will see him bare and abroad: or if he be covered as in old times they wont to present them unto Princes to be sold, it is only his least necessarie parts, lest you should ammuse your self to consider his colour or breadth of his crupper; but chiefly to view his legs, his head, his eyes, and his foot, which are the most remarkable parts, and above all to be considered and required in him. Regibus hic mos est, ubi equos mercantur, opertos Inspiciunt, ne sifacies, ut sæpe, decora Molli fulta pedi est, emptorem inducat hiantem. Quod pulchra clunes, breve quod caput, ardua cervix. -- Hor. i. Sat. ii. 86. This is Kings manner, when they horses buy, They see them bare, lest if, as oft we try, Faire face have soft hoofes, gull’d the, buyer be, They buttockes round, short head, high crest may see. When you will esteeme a man, why should you survey him all wrapt and envelloped? He then but showeth us those parts which are no whit his own, and hideth those from us by which alone his worth is to be judged. It is the goodnesse of the sword you seek after, and not the worth of the scabbard; for which perhaps you would not give a farthing if it want his lyning. A man should be judged by himself, and not by his complements. And as an Ancient says very pleasantly: Doe you know why you esteeme him tall? You account the height of his pattens. The base is no part of his stature: measure him without his stilts. Let him lay aside his riches and externall honors, and show himself in his shirt. Hath he a body proper to his functions, sound and cheerful? What mind has he? Is it fair, capable and unpolluted, and happily provided with all her necessary parts? Is she rich of her own or of others goods? Hath fortune nothing of hers to survey therein? If broad-waking she wil looke upon a naked sword: if she care not which way her life goeth from her, whether by the mouth or by the throat, whether it be setled, equable, and contented. It is that a man must see and consider, and thereby judge the extreme differences that are betweene us. Is he ------ sapiens, sibique imperiosus, Quem neque pauperies, neque mors neque vincula terrent, Responsare cupidinibus, contemnere honores Fortis et seipso totus teres atque rotundus Externi ne quid valeat per læve morari, In quem manca ruit semper fortuna? A wise man, of himself commander high, Whom want, nor death, nor bands can terrifie, Resolv’d t’affront desires, honors to scorne, All in himself, close, round and neatly-borne, As nothing outward on his smooth can stay, Gainst whom still fortune makes a lame assay. Such a man is five hundred degrees beyond kingdomes and principalities: himself is a kingdome unto him self. Sapiens pol ipse fingit fortunam sibi. -- Plau. Trin. act. ii. sc. 2. Trust me, who bears a wise mans name, His fortune to himself may frame. What is there else for him to wish for? ------nonne videmus Nil aliud sibi naturam latrare, nisi ut quoi Corpore sejunctus dolor absit, mente fruatur Incundo sensu, cura semiotus metuque? -- Lucr. ii. 16. See we not nature nothing else does bark Unto her-self, but he, whose bodies barke Is free from paines-touch, should his mind enjoy. Remov’d from care and fear, with sense of joy! Compare unto him the vulgar troupes of our men, stupide, base, servile, wavering, and continually floting on the tempestuous ocean of diverse passions which tosse and retosse the same, wholy depending of others. There is more difference than is betweene heaven and earth, and yet such is the blindnesse of our custom that we make little or no account of it. Whereas, if we consider a Cottager and a King, a noble and a handycrafts man, a magistrate and a private man, a rich man and a poore, an extreme disparitie does immediately present itself unto our eyes, which, as a man may say, differ in nothing but in their clothes. In Thrace, the King was after a pleasant manner distinguished from his people, and which was much endeared. He had a religion apart: a God severall unto himself, whom his subjects might no waies adore. It was Mercurie: and he disdained their gods, which were Mars, Bacchus, and Diana; yet are they but pictures which make no essential dissemblance. For, as enterlude-plaiers, you shal now see them on the stage play a King, an Emperor, or a Duke, but they are no sooner off the stage but they are base rascals, vagabond abjects, and porterly hirelings, which is their natural and originall condition. Even so the Emperor whose glorious pomp does so dazzle you in public: Scilicet et grandes viridi cum luce smaragdi Auro includuntur, teriturque Thalassina vestis Assidue, et Veneris sudorem exercita potat. --Lucr. iv. 1137. Great emeralds with their grass-greene light in gold Are clos’d, nor long can marriage linnen hold, But worne with use and heat of Venerie drinks the sweat. View him behinde the curtaine, and you see but an ordinary man, and perhaps more vile and more seely than the least of his subjects. Ille beatus introrsum est; istius bracteata fælicitas est: (Sen. Epist. cxv.) ’One is inwardly happy: anothers felicitie is plated and guilt-over.’ Cowardise, irresolution, ambition, spight, anger, and envie, move and work in him as in another: Non enim gazæ, neque consularis Summovet lictor miseres tumultus Mentis, et curas, laqueata circum -- Tecta [volantes]: -- Hor. ii. Od. xvi. 9. Nor treasures, nor Maires officers remove The miserable tumults of the mind, Or cares that lie about, or flie above Their high-roof’t houses with huge beames combinde. And fear, and care, and suspect haunt and follow him, even in the middest of his armed troupes. Re veraque metus hominum, curæque sequaces, Nec metuunt sonitus armorum, nec fera tela, Audacterque inter reges, rerumque potentes Versantur, neque fulgorem reverentur ab auro. --Lucr. ii. 46. Indeed mens still-attending cares and fear, Nor armor’s clashing, nor fierce weapons fear, With Kings converse they boldly, and Kings peeres, Fearing no lightning that from gold appeares. Does the ague, the megrim, or the gout spare him more than us? When age shall once seize on his shoulders can then the tall yeomen of his guard discharge him of it? When the terror of ruthless balefull death shall assails him, can he be comforted by the assistance of the gentlemen of his chamber? If he chance to be jealous or capricious, will our lowting curtzies, or putting off of hatts, bring him in tune again? His bedstead enchased all with gold and pearles has no virtue to allay the pinching pangues of the cholicke. Nec calidæ citius decedent corpore febres, Textilibus si in picturis ostroque rubenti Iacteris, quam si plebeia in veste cubandum est. --Id. ib. 34. Feavers no sooner from your body flie If you on arms or red scarlet lie Tossing, than if you rest On coverlets home-drest. The flatterers of Alexander the great made him believe that he was the son of Jupiter; but being one day fore-hurt, and seeing the blood gush out of his wounds: ’And what think you of this? (said he unto them), Is not this blood of a lively red hew, and meerly humane? Methinkes it is not of that temper and which Homer faineth to trill from the gods wounds.’Hermodorus the Poet made certain verses in honor of Antigonus, in which he called him the son of Phoebus; to whom he replied: ’My friend, he that emptieth my close-stools knows well there is no such matter.’ He is but a man at all assaies: And if of himself he be a man ill-borne, the Empire of the whole world cannot restore him. -----puellæ Hunc rapiant, quicquid calcaverit, hic rosa fiat. -- Pers. Sat. ii. 37. Wenches must ravish him, what ever he Shall tread upon, eftsoones a rose must be. What of that? If he be of a grose, stupide, and senseles mind: voluptuousness and good fortune itself, are not perceived without vigor, wit and livelinesse. Hæc perinde sunt, ut illius animus qui ea possidet, Qui uti scit, ei bona, illi qui non utitur recte, mala. -- Ter. Heaut. act. i. sc. ii. 21. These things are such, as the possessors mind, Good, if well us’d; if ill, them ill we find. Whatsoever the goods of fortune are, a man must have a proper sense to favor them: It is the enjoying, and not the possessing of them, that makes us happy. Non domus et fundus, non æris acervus et auri, Aegroto domini deduxit corpore febres, Non animo curas; valeat possessor oportet, Qui comportatis rebus bene cogitat uti. Qui cupit, aut metuit, juvat illum sic domus aut res, Ut lippum pictæ tabulæ, fomenta podagram. -- Hor. i. Ep. ii. 47. Not house and land, and heapes of corne and gold Rid agues, which their sicke Lords body hold, Or cares from mind: the owner must be in health, That well does think to use his hoarded wealth. Him that desires or feares, house, goods delight As foments do the gout, pictures sore-sight. He is a foole, his taste is wallowish and distracted, he enjoyeth it no more than one that has a great cold does the sweetness of Greeke wine, or a horse the riches of a costly faired furniture, wherewith he is trapped. Even as Plato says, ’That health, beautie, strength, riches, and all things else he calleth good, are equally as ill to the unjust as good to the just; and the evil contrariwise.’ And then, where the body and the soul are in ill plight, what need these externall commodities? seeing the least pricks of a needle and passion of the mind is able to deprive us of the pleasure of the worlds Monarchy. The first fit of an ague, or the first gird that the gout gave him, what avails his goodly tales of Majesty? Totus et argento conflatus, totus et auro. -- Tibul. i. El. vii. 71. All made of silver fine, All gold pure from the mine Does he not forthwith lose the remembrance of his pallaces and states? If he be angrie or vexed, can his principalitie keep him from blushing, from growing pale, from gnashing his teeth like a Bedlam? Now if it be a man of worth, and well borne, his royalty and his glorious titles will add but little unto his good fortune. Si ventri bene, si lateri est, pedibusque tuis, nil Divitiæ poterunt regales addere majus. -- Hor. i. Ep. xii. 5. If it be well with belly, feet, and sides. A Kings estate, no greater good provides. He seeth they are but illusions and vain deceits. He may perhaps be of King Seleucus his advice: ’That he who fore-knew the weight of a sceptre, should he find it lying on the ground, he would not daigne to take it up.’ This he said by reason of the weightie, irksome and painfull charges that are incident unto a good King. Truely, it is no small in matter to govern others, since so many crosses and difficulties offer themselves, if we will govern ourselves well. Touching commanding of others, which in show seems to be so sweet, considering the imbecillitie of mans judgement, and the difficultie of choice in new and doubtful things: I am confidently of this opinion, that it is much more easy and plausible to follow than to guide: and that it is a great setling of the mind to be tied but to one beaten-path, and to answer but for himself. Ut satius multo jam sit, parere quietum, Quam regere imperio res velle. -- Lucr. v. 1137. Much better ’tis in quiet to obey, Than to desire with Kings-power all to sway. Seeing Cyrus said, that it belongs not to a man to command that is not of more worth than those whom he commandeth.’ But King Hieron in Xenophon addeth moreover, ’That in truly enjoying of carnall sensualities, they are of much worse condition than private men: forasmuch as ease and facilitie depriveth them of that sowre-sweet tickling which we find in them.’ Pinguis amor nimiumque potens, in tædia nobis, Vertitur, et stomacho dulcis ut esca nocet. -- Ovid. Am. ii. El. xix. 25. Fat over-powerfull love does loathsome grow, As fulsome sweet-meats stomackes overthrow. Thinke we, that high-minded men take great pleasure in music? That satietie thereof makes it rather tedious unto them. Feasts, banquets, revels, dancings, masks and turneys, rejoice them that but seldom see them, and that have much desired to see them: the taste of which becomes cloysome and unpleasing to those that daily see and ordinarily have them: Nor do ladies tickle those that at pleasure and without suspect may be glutted with them. He that cannot stay till he be thirsty, can take no pleasure in drinking. Enterludes and commedies, rejoice and make us merry, but to players they are tedious and tastelesse. Which to prove, we see it is a delight for Princes, and a recreation for them, sometimes to disguise themselves, and to take upon them a base and popular kind of life. Plerumque gratæ principibus vices, Mundæque parvo sub lare pauperum Cænæ sine aulæis et ostro, Sollicitam explicuere frontem. -- Hor. iii. Od. xxix. 13. Princes do commonly like enterchange, And cleanely meales where poore-men poorely house, Without all tapistrie or carpets strange, Unwrinkled have their care-knit, thought-bent browes. Nothing does sooner breed a distaste or satietie than plentie. What longing lust would not be alaid to see three hundred women at his dispose and pleasure as has the Grande Turke in his Seraille? And what a desire and show of hawking had he reserved to himself from his ancestors, that never went abroad without seven thousand falkners at least? Besides which, I think, the luster of greatness brings no small incommodities to the enjoying of sweeter pleasures: they lie too open and are too much in sight. And I wot not why a man should longer desire them to conceal or hide their fault; for what in us is indiscretion the people judgeth to be tyrannie, contempt, and disdaine of the laws in them: And besides the ready inclination unto vice, it seems they also adde unto it the pleasure of gourmandizing, and to prostrate publicke-observances under their feet. Verily Plato in his Gorgias defineth him to be a tyrant that in a City has leave and power to do whatever he list. And therefore often the show and publication of their vice hurteth more than the sinne itself. Every man feareth to be spied and controlled; which they are even in their countenances and thoughts: all the people esteeming to have right and interest to judge of them. And we see that blemishes grow either lesser or bigger according to the eminence and light of the place where they are set, and that a mole or a wart in ones forehead is more apparently perceived than a scarre in another place. And that is the reason why Poets faine Jupiters loves to have been effected under other countenances than his own; and of so many amorous shifts and love practices they impute to him, there is but one (as far as I remember) where he is to be seen in his greatness and majestie. But return we to Hieron: he also relateth how many incommodities he findeth in his royalty, being so barred that he cannot at his liberty travell go whether he pleaseth, being as it were a prisoner within the limits of his country; and that in all his actions he is encircled and hemd-in with an importunate and tedious multitude. Truely, to see Our Princes all alone, sitting at their meat, beleagred round with so many talkers, whisperers, and gazing beholders, unknown what they are or where they come, I have often rather pittied than envied them. King Alphonsus was wont to say, that ’burden bearing asses were in that in far better condition than Kings; for their masters suffer them to feed at their ease, whereas Kings cannot obtaine that privilege of their servants.’ And it could never fall into my mind that it might be any speciall commoditie to the life of a man of understanding to have a score of find-faults, picke-thanks, and controllers about his close-stoole, nor that the service of a man that has a thousand pound rent a yeare, or that has taken Casal, or defended Sienna, is more commodious or acceptable to him than that of a sufficient and well- experienced groom. Princelike advantages are in a manner but imaginarie preheminences. Every degree of fortune has some image of Principalitie: Cæsar termeth all the Lords, which in his time had justice in France, to be Kinglets, or petty Kings. And truly, except the name of Sire, we go very far with our Kings. Looke but in the Provinces remote and far from the court: As for example, in Britaine, the attending traine, the flocking subjects, the number of officers, the many affairs the diligent service, the obsequious ceremonies of a Lord, that liveth retired, and in his own house, brought up amongst his own servants, tenants, and followers: And note also the high pitch of his imaginations and humors, there is no greater royalty can be seen: He heareth no more talk of his master than of the Persian King, and hapily but once a year; And knowes but some far-streicht and old kindred or pedigree, which his Secretarie findes or keepes upon some ancient record or evidence. Verily our laws are very free, and the burden of soveraigntie does scarsly concerne a gentleman of France twice in his whole life. Essentiall and effectuall subjection amongst us does not respect any but such as allure themselves unto it, and that affect to honor, and love to enrich themselves by such service: For he that can shrowd and retire himself in his own home, and can manage and direct his house without sutes in lawe, or quarrell with his neighbors, or domesticall encombrances, is as free as the Duke of Venice. Paucos servitus, plures servitutem tenent: (Sen. Epist. 22.) ’Service holds few, but many hold service.’ But above all things Hieron seems to complain that he perceiveth himself deprived of all mutual friendship, reciprocall societie, and familiar conversation, wherein consisteth the most perfect and sweetest fruit of humane life. For, what undoubted testimony of affection and good will can I expect or exact from him, that, will he or nill he, oweth me all he has, all he can? Can I make account of his humble speech, of his low lowting curtzie, or of his courteous offers, since it lieth not in his power to refuse them me? The honor we receive of those which fear and stand in awe of us, is no true honor. Such respects are rather due to royalty, to majestie, than to me. -----maximum hoc regni bonum est, Quod facta domini cogitur populus sui Quam ferre, tam laudare. -- Sen. Thyest. act. ii. sc. 1. This is chief good of Princes domination, Subiects are forc’t their sovraignes actes and fashions To bear with patience, pass with commendations. Doe I not see, that both the bad and the good king are served likewise? That he who is hated and he that is beloved are both courted likewise? And the one as much fawned upon as the other? My predecessor was served with the same appearances, and waited upon with the like ceremonies, and so shall my successor be. If my subiects offend me not, it is no testimony of any good affection. Wherefore shall I take it in that sense, sithence they cannot, if they would? No man followeth me for any friendship that is betweene him and me: inasmuch as no firme friendship can be contracted where is so small relation, so slender correspondencie, and such disparitie. My high degree has excluded me from the commerce of men. There is too great an inequalitie and distant disproportion. They follow for countenance and of customs, or rather my fortune than my self: hoping thereby to increase theirs. Whatsoever they say, all they do unto me is but a glosse, and but dissimulation, their liberty being every where brideled and checked by the great power I have over them. I see nothing about me but inscrutable hearts, hollow mindes, feigned looks, dissembled speeches, and counterfeit actions. His Courtiers one day commended Julian the Emperor for ministring of rights and doing of justice. ’I should easily grow proud’ says he, ’for these praises, if they came from such as durst either accuse or discommend my contrary actions, should I commit any.’ All the true commodities that Princes have are common unto them with men of meane fortune. It is for Gods to mount winged horses, and to feed on Ambrosia. They have no other sleepe, nor no other appetite than ours. Their steele is of no better temper than that wherewith we arm ourselves. Their crowne, their diadem can neither hide them from the Sun, or shelter them from the raine. Dioclesian, that wore one, so much reverenced and so fortunate, did voluntarily resigne the same, to withdraw himself unto the pleasure of a private life; but a while after, the urgent necessitie of publicke affairs requiring his presence, and that he should return to re-assume his charge again, he answered those that solicited him unto it, ’You would never undertake to persuade me to that had you but seen the goodly rankes of trees which my self have planted in mine Orchard, or the fair muske-melons I have set in my garden.’ According to Anacharsis his opinion, ’The happiest estate of a well-ordered commonwealth should be, where all other things being equally common, precedencie should be measured and preferments suited according to virtue and desert, and the contrary according to vice.’ At what time King Pirrhus undertook to pass into Italy, Cyneas his wise and trustie counsellor, going about to make him perceive the vanity of his ambition, one day bespake him thus: ’My good sir,’ said he, ’to what end do you prepare for so great an enterprise?’ He answered suddenly, ’To make my self Lord of Italie.’ ’That done, what will you do then?’ replied Cyneas, ’I will then pass,’ said Pirrhus, ’into Gaule, and then into Spain.’ ’And what afterwards?’ ’I will then invade Affrike, and subdue the same; and at last, when I shall have brought all the world under my subjection, I will then take my rest, and live contented at mine ease.’ ’Now, for Gods sake, sir,’ replied Cyneas, ’tell me what hinders you that you be not now, if so you please, in that estate? Wherefore do you not now place your self where you meane to aspire, and save so much danger, so many hazards, and so great troubles as you enterpose betweene both?’ Nimirum quia non bene norat quæ esset habendi Finis, et omnino quoad crescat vera voluptas. -- Lucr. v. 1443. The cause forsooth, he knew not what should be the end Of leaving, nor how far true pleasure should extend. I will conclude and shut up this treatise with an ancient verse, which I singularly applaud and deem fit to this purpose. Mores cuique sui fingunt fortunam. --Cic. Parad. v. Cor. Nep. Ev’ry mans manners and his mind, His fortune to him frame and find. Return to CHAPTER XLIII: OF SUMPTUARIE LAWES, OR LAWES FOR MODERATING OF EXPENCES CHAPTER XLIII: OF SUMPTUARIE LAWES, OR LAWES FOR MODERATING OF EXPENCES HE manner wherewith our Lawes assay to moderate the foolish and vain expences of table-cheare and apparell seems contrary to its end. The best course were to beget in men a contempt of gold and silkwearinge as of vain and non-profitable things, whereas we encrease their credit and price: a most indirect course to withdraw men from them. As, for example, to let none but Princes eat dainties, or weare velvets and clothes of Tissew, and interdict the people to do it, what is it but to give reputation unto those things, and to encrease their longing to use them? Let Kings boldly quit those badges of honor; they have many other besides: Such excess is more excusable in other men than in Princes. We may, by the examples of diverse Nations, learne sundrie better fashions to distinguish ourselves and our degrees (which truly I esteeme requisit in an estate) without nourishing to that purpose this so manifest corruption and apparant inconvenience. It is strange how custom in these indifferent things does easily encroach and suddenly establish the footing of her authority. We had scarce worne cloth one whole yeare at the Court, what time we mourned for our King Henrie the second, but certainly in every mans opinion all manner of silks were already become so vile and abject, that was any man seen to weare them he was presently judged to be some countrie fellow or mechanicall man. They were left only for Chyrurgians and Physitians. And albeit most men were apparreled likewise, yet were there other sufficient apparant distinctions of mens qualities. How soone do plaine chamoy- jerkins and greasie canvase doublets creepe into fashion and credit amongst our soldiers if they lie in the field? And the garishnesse, neatnesse, and riches of silken garments grow in contempt and scorne? Let Kings first begin to leave these superfluous expenses. We shall all follow, and within a moneth, without edicts, ordinances, proclamations, and acts of Parliament, it will be observed as a law. The statutes should speak contrary, as thus: That no man or woman, of what quality soever, shall, upon pain of great forfeitures, weare any manner of silke, of scarlet, or any goldsmiths work, except only Enterlude- players, Harlots, and Curtizans. With such an invention did Zeleucus whilome correct the corrupted manners of the Locrines. His ordinances were such: ’Be it enacted that no woman of free condition shall have any more than one maid-servant to follow her when she goeth abroad, except when she shall be drunken: And further, that she-may not go out of the City by night, nor weare any jewels of gold or precious stones about her, nor any gowne beset with goldsmiths work or enbroiderie, except she be a public- professed whore: and moreover, that except panders and bawds, it shall not be lawfull for any man to weare any gold-rings on his fingers, nor any rich garments, as are such of cloth made in the City of Miletum.’ So did he by these reproachfull exceptions ingeniously drive his Citizens from vain superfluities and pernicious dainties. It was a most profitable course, by honor and ambition to allure men unto their dutie and obedience. Our Kings have the power to addresse all these externall reformations. Their inclination serveth them as a law. Quicquid Principes faciunt, præcipere videntur: ’Whatsoever Princes do, that they seem to command.’ The rest of France takes the modell of the court as a rule unto itself to follow. Let Courtiers first begin to leave off and loathe there filthy and apish breeches that so openly show our secret parts: t he bumbasting of long pease-cod bellied doublets, which makes us seem so far from what we are, and which are so cumbersome to arm: These long, effeminate, and dangling locks: That foolish custom to kisse what we present to others, and Beso las manos in saluting of our friends (a ceremony heretofore only due unto princes): And for a gentleman to come to any place of respect, without his rapier by his side, all unbraced, all untrust, as if he came from his close-stoole; And that against our forefathers manner, and the particular liberty of our French nobility, we should stand hare-headed, aloofe-off from them, wherever they be; and as about them, about many others: So many petty-kings and petty-petty-kinglets have we now adayes: And so of other like new-fangled and vicious introductions: They shall soone he seen to vanish and be left. Although but superficiall faults, yet are they of evil presages. And we are warned that the foundation or main summers of our houses faile and shrinke, when we see the quarters bend or wals to breake. Plato in his Lawes, thinkes there is no worse plague, or more pernicious in his City, than to suffer youth to have the reines of liberty in her own hand, to change in their attires, in their gestures, dances, exercises, and songs, from one form to another: And to remove their judgement, now to this, now to that place; following newfangled devices, and regarding their inventors: By which old customs are corrupted, and ancient institutions despised. In all things, except the wicked, mutation is to be feared; indeed, even the alteration of seasons, of winds, of livings, and of humors. And no laws are in perfect credit but those to which God has given some ancient continuance: so that no man know their, of-spring, nor that ever they were other than they are. Return to CHAPTER XLIV: OF SLEEPING CHAPTER XLIV: OF SLEEPING EASON does appoint us ever to walke in one path, but not alwaies to keep one place: and that a wise man should not permit humane passions to stray from the right carrier; he may (without prejudice unto his dutie) also leave it unto them either to hasten or to slow his pace, and not place himself in an immoveable and impassive Colossus. Were virtue herself corporeall and incarnate, I think her pulse would beat and work stronger, marching to an assault, than going to dinner: For it is necessarie that she heat and move herself. I have therefore markt it as a rare thing to see great personages sometimes, even in their weightiest enterprises and most important affairs, hold themselves so resolutely-assured in their states that they do not so much as breake their sleep for them. Alexander the Great, on the day appointed for that furious-bloudy battle against Darius, slept so soundly and so long that morning, that Parmenion was faine to enter his chamber, and approching near unto his bed, twice or thrice to call him by his name, to awaken him, the hour of the battle being at hand, and urging him. Otho the Emperor having determined to kill himself, the very same night, after he had given order for his domestical affairs, shared his monie among his servants, and whetted the edge of a sword, wherewith he intended to wound himself, expecting no other thing but to know whether all his friends were gone to rest, fell into so sound a sleepe that the groomes of his chamber heard him snort in another roome. This Emperours death has many parts semblable unto that of great Cato, and namely this: For Cato being prepared to defeat himself, while he expected to hear news whether the Senators, whom he caused to retire were lanched out from the haven of Utica, fell so fast asleep that he was heard to snort into the next chamber; and he whom he had sent toward the port having waked him to tell him the storme was so rough that the Senators could not conveniently put out to sea, he sent another, and lying down anew, fell a sleep again until the last messenger assured him they were gone. We may also compare him unto Alexander in that great and dangerous storme which threatned him, by the sedition of Metellus the Tribune, who laboured to publish the decree of Pompeys re-appeall unto the City, together with his army, at what time the commotion of Catiline was on foot: against which decree only Cato did insist, and to that purpose had Metellus and he had many injurious speeches, and menaced one another in the Senate-house: and it was the next day they were like to come to the execution in the market-place, where Metellus, besides the favor of the common people and of Cæsar, then conspiring and complotting for the advancement of Pompey should come, accompanied with a multitude of strange and forraine slaves and fencers, to do their utmost. And Cato, strengthened with his only constancy and with unmated resolve: so that his kinsmen, his familiars, and many honest men took great care, and were in heavy anxiety and pensivenesse for him: of which many never left him all night, but sat up together without rest, eating, or drinking, by reason of the danger they saw prepared for him; indeed, his wife and sisters did nought but weep and waile, and for his sake torment themselves in their house, whereas contrariwise he alone conforted every body, and blamed them for their demissenesse. And after he had supped (as he was wont) he went quietly to his bed, and slept very roundly until the next morning, that one of his copartners in the Tribune-ship came to call him to go to the skirmish. The knowledge we have of this mans unmated-haughty heart by the rest of his life, may make us judge with all securitie that it only proceeded from a spirit so far elevated above such accidents that he dained not so much as to trouble his mind with them no more than with ordinary chances. In the sea-fight which Augustus gained against Sextus Pompeius in Sicilie, ev en at the instant he should go to fight, was surprised with so heavy a sleep that his friends were compelled to awaken him to give the signall of the battle, which afterward gave occasion unto Marcus Antonius to charge him with this imputation, that he had not dared with open eyes to survey the marshalling of his army, and that his heart would not suffice him to present himself unto his soldiers until such time as Agrippa brought him news of the victory he had obtained of his enemies. But concerning young Marius, who committed a greater error (for on the day of his last battle against Sylla, after he had marshalled his army and given the word or signall of the battle) he lay down in the shadow under a tree a while to rest himself, and fell so fast asleep that he could hardly be waked with the rout and flight of his men, having seen no part of the fight, they say it was because he was so exceedingly aggravated with travell, and over-tired with weaknesse and want of sleep, that nature was overcome, and could no longer endure. And touching this point, Phisitians may consider whether sleep be so necessarie that our life must needs depend on it, for we find that Perseus King of Macedon, prisoner at Rome, being kept from sleep, was made to die; but Plinie aleageth that some have lived a long time without any sleep at all. And Herodotus reporteth there are nations where men sleep and make by halfe years. And those that write the life of Epimenides the wise, affirm, that he slept the continuall space of seven and fifty years. Return to CHAPTER XLV: OF THE BATTELL OF DREUX CHAPTER XLV: OF THE BATTELL OF DREUX HERE hapned diverse rare accidents and remarkable chances in our battle of Dreux, but those who do not greatly favor the reputation of the Duke of Guise do boldly aleage that he cannot be excused to have made a stand and temporised with the forces he commanded, whilst the Lord Constable of France, General of the Armie, was engaged and suppressed with the enemies artillerie, and that it had been better for him to hazard himself to charge the enemy flankwise, than by expecting any advantage to have him come behind him, to suffer so reproachfull an overthrow and so shamefull a loss. But omitting what the event thereof witnessed, he that shall without passion debate the matter shall easily (in my conceit) confesse that the ayme and drift, not only of a captaine, but of every particular souldier, ought chiefly to respect a victory in great: and that no particular occurrences, of what consequence soever , or what interest may depend on them, should ever divert him from that point. Philopoemen, in an encounter with Machanidas, having sent before a strong troupe of archers and good marke men to begin the skirmish, and the enemy, after he had put them to rout and disranked them, ammusing himself in mainly pursuing them, and following the victory alongst the main battle where Philopoemen was, although his soldiers were much moved and offended to see their fellows put to the worst, he could not be moved to bouge from his place, nor make head against his enemy to succour his men; but rather, having suffered them to be defeated and cut in peecesbefore his face, began then to charge his enemies in the battalion of their infanterie when he perceived them forsaken of their horsemen. And albeit they were Lacedemonians, forasmuch as he charged them at what time (supposing to have gained the day) they began to disorder themselves, he easily overcame them, which done, he pursued Machanidas. This case is cousin-german unto that of the Duke of Guise. In that sharpe-bloody battle of Agesilaus against Boeotians, which Xenophon (who was there present) says to have been the hottest and rudest that ever he had seen, Agesilaus refused the advantage which fortune presented him, to let the battallion of the Bæotians pass, and to charge them behind, what certain victory soever he saw likely to follow the same, esteeming that it were rather skill than valor; and to show his prowess and matchlesse-haughty courage, chose rather to charge them in the front of their forces. But what followed? He was well beaten and himself sore-hurt, and in the end compelled to leave his enterprise and embrace the resolution which in the beginning he had refused, causing his men to open themselves to give passage unto that torrent of the Boeotians who when they were past through, perceiving them to march in disaray, as they who persuaded themselves to be out of all danger, he pursued them and charged them flankwise. All which notwithstanding, he could never put to rout or force them run-away, for they orderly and fair and softly made their retreit, ever showing their face, until such time as they got safely into their holds, and trenches. Return to CHAPTER XLVI: OF NAMES CHAPTER XLVI: OF NAMES HAT diversitie soever there be in herbs, all are shuffled up together under the name of a sallade. Even so upon the consideration of names I will here huddle up a gallymafry of diverse articles. Every several nation has some names which, I wot not how, are sometimes taken in ill part: as with us, Iacke, Hodge, Tom, Will, Bat, Benet, and so forth. Item, it seems that in the genealogies of Princes there are certain names fatally affected; as Ptolomeus with the Egyptians, Henries in England, Charles in France, Baldwins in Flanders, and Williams in our ancient Aquitanie, whence some say came the name of Guyenne; which is but a cold invention: As if in Plato himself there were not some as harsh and ill-sounding. Item, it is an idle matter, yet nevertheless, by reason of the strangenesse, worthy the memory, and recorded by an ocular witness, that Henric Duke of Normandie, son to Henrie the second King of England, making a great feast in France, the assembly of the Nobilitie was so great, that for pastimes sake, being, by the resemblance of their names, divided into severall companies: in the first were found a hundred and ten Knights sitting at one table and all called Williams; besides private gentlemen and servants. It is as pleasant to distribute the tables by the names of the assistants as it was unto Geta the Emperor, who would have all his messes of dishes served in at his table orderly according the first letters of their names: As, for example, those that began with P, as pig, pie, pike, puddings, pouts, proke, pancakes, &c. were all served in together; and so of all the rest. Item, it is a common saying, ’That it is good to have a good name:’ As much to say, good credit or good reputation. Yet verily it is very commodious to have a well-sounding and smooth name, and which is easy to be pronounced, and facile to be remembered: For Kings, Princes, Lords, and Magistrates know and remember us the better by them, and will not so soone forget us. Marke but of those that serve and follow us, whether we do not more ordinarily command and sooner employ such whose names come readier to our tongue or memory. I have seen our King Henrie the second, who could never hit on the right name of a Gentleman of Gascoigne, and did ever call a Lady waiting on the Queene by the general surname of her house, because that of her father was so harsh and hard to be remembered. And Socrates says: ’It ought to be a fathers speciall care to give his children good and easy-sounding names.’ Item, it is reported that the foundation of our Lady, the great at Poitiers had this beginning: ’A licentious young man having his dwelling-house where the Church now standeth, had one night gotten a wench to lie with him, who so soone as she came to bed, he demanded her name, who answered Marie: The young man hearing that name, was suddenly so strucken with a motive of religion, and an awefull respect unto that sacred name of the virgin Marie, the blessed mother of our Saviour and Redeemer, that he did not only presently put her away from him, but reformed all the remainder of his succeeding life: And that in consideration of this miracle there was first erected a chappell in the place where this young mans house stood, consecrated unto that holy name, and afterward the fair great Church which yet continueth.’ This vocal and auricular correction, and so full of devotion, strucke right unto his soul. This other following, of the same kind, insinuated itself by the corporall senses. Pythagoras being in companie with two young men, whom he heard complot and consult ( being somewhat heated with feasting and drinking) to go and ravish a chast-house, commanded immediately the minstrels to change their tune; and so by a solemn, grave, severe, and spondaicall kind of music, did sweetly inchaunt, allay, and in-trance their rash, violent, and law-less lust. Item, shall not succeeding posterity say that our modern reformation has been exact and delicate, to have not only oppugned and resisted errors and vices, and filled the world with devotion, humility, obedience, peace, and every other kind of virtue, but even to have combated their ancient names of baptisme, Charles, Lewis, Francis, to people the world with Methusalem, Ezechiel, Malachie, much better feeling of a lively faith? A Gentleman my neighbour esteeming the commodities of ancient times in regard of our days, forgot not to sledge the fiercenesse and magnificence of the names of the Nobilitie of those times, as Don Grumedan, Quedragan, and Agesilan: And that, but to hear them sounded, a man might easily perceive they had been other manner of men than Peter, Guilliam, or Michell. Item, I commend and am much beholding to Iames Amiot, in the course of a French oration of his, to have still kept the full ancient Latine names, without disguising or changing them, to give them a new French cadence. At the first they seemed somewhat harsh unto the reader: but now, by reason of the credit which his Plutarke has deservedly gotten amongst us, custom has removed all strangenesse from us. I have often wished that those who write histories in Latine, would leave us our names whole, and such as they are: For, altering VaudemontVallemontanus, and metamorphosing them by muting them to the Greek or Latin tongue, we know not what to make of them, and are often at a non-plus. To conclude my discourse: It is an ill custom, and of exceeding bad consequence in our countrie of France, to call every man by the name of his Town, Mannor, Hamlet, or Lordship, as the thing that does most confound houses, and bring surnames out of knowledge. A cadet or yonger-brother of a good house, having had for his appanage a Lordship, by whose name he has been known and honoured, cannot well forsake and leave the same ten years after his death: his Lordship commeth unto a stranger, who does the like: Ghesse then where we are, and how we shall do to come to the perfect knowledge of these men. We need not go far for other examples, but looke into our Royall house, where so many partages, so many surnames, and so many severall titles have so encumbred us, that the originall of the stocke is utterly lost. There is so much liberty in these mutations, that even in my time I have seen no man nor woman advanced by fortune into some extraordinarie preferment, that has not immediately had adjoined unto him or her genealogicall titles, new and unknown to their fathers, and that has not been engraffed into some noble stocke or family. And as good lucke serveth, the basest upstart and most obscure houses are most apt unto adulteration and falsification. How many privat Gentlemen have we in FrancePeter or William that beareth the same (marke it well, reader) and to whom it belongeth. Is not hope a courageous facultie, which in a mortal subject, and in a moment, seeks to usurp infinitie and immensitie, and to replenish his Masters indigence with the po esession of all things he can imagine or desire before it would? Nature has given us a pleasant joy to play withall in that. Is it Peter or William. And what is that but a word for al mouths? or three or foure dashes of a pen, first, so easy to be varied, as I would willingly ask those whom the honor of so many victories concerneth, or whether Guesquin, or Glesquin, or Gueaquin? yet were there more apparence her than in Lucian that Σ did sue T. For, to which, according to their accompt and blazoning of their gentrie, are of the royall house or race? I believe more than others. Was it not prettily said, and with a good grace, by one of my friends? There was a great companie banded together about a quarrell which a Gentleman had with another, who in very truth had some prerogative of titles, honors, and alliances above the common sort of Nobilitie; upon which word of his prerogative, every one seeking to equall himself unto him, alleged, some one ofspring, some another, some the resemblance of his name, some of his arms, othersome an old farfetcht pedigree, and the meanest of them to be the great grandchild of some King beyond the seas. When they came all to dinner, this man, whom hitherto they had all followed, in liew of takin g his wonted place, making low lowting reverences, went to the lowest end of the board, entreating the companie to hold him excused, that through rash-unadvisednesse he had hitherto lived with them companion-like, but now being lately enformed of their right qualities, he began to know them according to their ancient degrees, and that it did not duly belong unto him to sit above so many Princes. And after he had acted his play, he began to rail upon them with a thousand injuries; saying thus unto them: For the love of God, content yourselves with what your forefathers have been contented, and with the state whereto God has called us; we have sufficient if we can maintaine it well, let us not disparage the fortune and condition of our predecessors, and reject we these foolish imagitiations, which cannot faile any man, whatsoever he be, that is so imprudent as to alleage them. Crests, Armes, and Coats have no more certaintie than surnames. I bear Azure seme of trefoiles, a Lions Paw in fæce. Or armed Gules. What privilege has this Coat, that it should for ever continue particularly to my house? A son in law will transferre the same into another family: Some silly upstart purchaser of Armes will make it his chief Coat. ’There is nothing wherein meet so many alterations and so much confusion. But this consideration draweth me perforce unto another field. Let us somewhat narrowly search into, and for God’s sake consider, on what foundation we ground this glory and reputation, for which the world is turned topsie-turvie. On what do we establish this transitorie renown, which with so great mind-possessing toyle and industrie we seek and gape-after? In fine, it is ----- non levia aut ludicra petuntur Præmia: -- Vir. Æn. xii. 764. No light prize, no reward in jest Is hunted after as the best. The wager goeth deepe: The question is, which letter must be paid with so many sieges, battles, hurts, emprisonments, and services done unto the Crowne of France by her ever renowned Constable. Nicholas Denisot has had no care but of the letters of his name, and has changed all the contexture of them, thereout to frame the Earl of Alsinoss, whom he has honoured and presenteth with the glory of his Poesie and Painting. And Suetonius the historian has loved but the sense of his own, and having taken away Lenis, which was his fathers surname, has left Tranquillus successor of his compositions reputation. Who would believe Captain Bayard has no honor but that which he has borrowed from the acts of Peter Terraill? And that Antonio Escalin (even before his eyes) suffered Captain Poulin, and the Baron of La Garde, to steal so many Navigations, voyages, and attempts, both by sea and land, from him? Secondarily, they are dashes and trickes of the pen, common unto a thousand men. many are there in all races or families both of one name and surname! And how many in diverse families, races, ages, and countries? Historie has known three Socrates, five Platoes, eight Aristotles, seven Xenophons, twenty Demetrius, twenty Theodores: besides which, imagine how many came not to her knowledge. Who letteth my horse boy to call himself Pompey the great? But after all, what means, what devices are there that annex unto my horse-keeper deceased, or to that other who had his head cut off in Egypt, or that join unto them this glorified and farrenowned word and these pen-dashes so much honoured, that they may thereby advantage themselves? Id cinerem et manes credis curare sepultos? -- IV 34. Thinke you, ghosts buried, ashes dead, Care much how we alive are sped? What feeling motion of revenge have the two companions in chief valor amongst men: Epaminondas of that glorious verse, which so many ages since is so common in our mouthes for him? Consiliis nostris laus est attrita Laconum. --Cic. Tusc. Qu. v. By our complots the haught renown, Of Spartan Gallants was brought down. And Africanus of that other; A sole exoriente supra Mæotis paludes Nemo est, qui factis me æquiparare queat? --Ibid. From Sun rise to the Scythian-lake, of fame None in exploits can equalize my name. Those that survive are tickled with the pleasure of these words, and by them solicited with jealousie and desire, do presently without consideration transmit by fantasie this their proper motion of revenge unto the deceased; and with a foolish-deceiving hope persuade, themselves, when their turn commeth, to be capable of it. God he knowes it, nevertheless: ----- ad hæc se Romanus Graiusque et Barbarus Induperator Erexit, causas dicriminis atque laboris Inde habuit, tanto major famæ sitis est, quam Virtutis. -- Juv. Sat. x. 137. Heerto himself the Roman General, The Greek, the Barbarian, rouz’d and rais’d; Here hence drew cause of perils, travells all: So more, than to be good, thirst to be prais’d. Renascence Editions Return to CHAPTER XLVII. OF THE UNCERTAINTIE OF OUR JUDGEMENT. CHAPTER XLVII. OF THE UNCERTAINTIE OF OUR JUDGEMENT. T is even as that verse says, ’Επεων δε πολυς υοηος ευθα και ευθα. Of words on either side, A large doale they divide. There is law sufficient to speak every where, both pro and contra. As for example: Vince Hannibal, et non seppe usar’ poi Ben la vittor iosa sua ventura. --Pet. Par. 1. son. lxxxvi. 1. Hanniball conquer’d, but he knew not after To use well his victorious good fortune. He that shall take this part, and with our men go about, to make that over-sight prevaile, that we did not lately pursue our fortune at Montcontour: Or he that shall accuse the King of Spain, who could not use the advantage he had against us at Saint Quintin, may say this fault to have proceeded from a mind drunken with his good fortune, and from a courage ful-gorged with the beginning of good lucke; loses the taste how to encrease it, being already hindred from digesting what he has conceived of it: He has his hands full, and cannot take hold any more: Unworthy that ever fortune should cast so great a good into his lap: For, what profit has he of it, if, notwithstanding, he give his enemy leisure and means to recover himself? What hope may one have, that he will once more adventure to charge these re-enforced und re-united forces, and new armed wit h despite and vengeance, that durst not, or knew not how to pursue them, being dismaied and put to rout? Dum fortuna calet, dum conficit omnia terror. Lucan. vii. 734. While fortune is at height in heat. And terror worketh all by great. But to conclude, what can he expect better than what he has lately lost? It is not, as at Fence, where the number of venies given gets the victory: So long as the enemy is on foot, a man is newly to begin. It is no victory, except it end the war. In that conflict where Cæsar had the worse, near the City of Oricum, he reprochfully said unto Pompeis soldiers, That he had utterly been overthrowne, had their Captain known how to conquer, and paid him home after another fashion when it came to his turn. But why may not a man also hold the contrary? That it is the effect of an insatiate and rash- headlong mind, not to know how to limit or period his covetousnesse: That it is an abusing of Gods favors to go about to make them lose the measure he has prescribed them, and that anew to cast himself into danger after the victory, is once more to remit the same unto the mercy of fortune: That one of the chiefest policies in militarie profession is not to drive his enemy unto despaire. Silla and Marius in the social war, leaving discomfited the Marsians, seeing one squadron of them yet on foot, which through despaire, like furious beasts were desperately coming upon them, could not be induced to stay or make head against them. If the fervor of Monsieur de Foix had not drewne him over rashly and moodily to pursue the straglers of the victory at Ravenna, he had not blemished the same with his untimely death; yet did the fresh-bleeding memory of his example serve to preserve the Lord of Anguien from the like inconvenience at Serisoles. It is dangerous to assaile a man whom you have bereaved of all other means to escape or shift for himself but by his weapons; for necessitie is a violent school mistris, and which teacheth strange lessons: Gravissimi stint morsus irritatæ necessitatis. ’No biting so grievous as that of necessitie provoked and enraged. Vincitur haud gratis jugulo qui provocat hostem. -- Lucan. iv. 278. For nought you over-come him not, Who bids his foe come cut his throat And this is the reason why Pharax empeached the King of Lacedemon, who came from gaining of a victory against the Mantinæans, from going to charge a thousand Argians, that were escaped whole from the discomfiture; but rather to let them pass with all liberty, lest he should come to make trial of provoked and despited virtue, through and by ill fortune. Clodomire King of Aquitaine, after his victory, pursuing Gondemar King of Burgundie, vanquished and running away, forced him to make a stand, and make head again: but his unadvised wilfulnesse deprived him of the fruit of the victory, for he dyed in the action. Likewise he that should chuse, whether it were best to keep his soldiers richly and sumptuously armed, or only for necessitie, should seem to yield in favor of the first, whereof was Sertorius, Philopoemen, Brutus, Cæsar, and others. urging that it is ever a spur to honor and glory for a souldier to see himself gorgeously attired and richly armed, and an occasion to yield himself more obstinate to fight, having the care to save his arms, as his goods and inheritince. A reason (says Xenophon) why the Asiatikes carried with them, when they went to wars, their wives and concubines; with all their jewels and chiefest wealth. And might also encline to the other side, which is, that a man should rather remove from his shoulder all care to preserve himself, than to increase it unto him: for by that means he shall doubly fear to hazard or engage himself, seeing these rich spoiles do rather increase an earnest desire of victory in the enemy: and it has been observed that the said respect has sometimes wonderfully encouraged the Romans against the Samnites. Antiochus shewing the army he prepared against them, gorgeously accoutred with all pompe and statelinesse, unto Hanniball, and demanding of him whether the Romanes would be contented with it: Yyea, verily, answered the other, they will be very well pleased with it: They must needs be so, were they never so covetous. Licurgus forbad his Soldiers, not only all manner of sumptuousnesse in their equipage, but also to unease or strip their enemies when they overcame them, willing, as he said, that frugality and povertie should shine with the rest of the battle. Both at sieges and elsewhere, where occasion brings us near the enemy, we freely give our soldiers liberty to brave, to disdaine, and injure him with all manner of reproaches: And not without apparence of reason; for it is no small matter to take from them all hope of grace and composition, in presenting unto them that there is no way left to accept it from him whom they have so egregiously outraged, and that there is no remedie left but from victory. Yet had Vitellius but had success in that; for, having to deale with Otho, weaker in his soldiers valor, and of long disaccustomed from war, and effeminated through the delights and pleasures of the City, himself in the end set them so on fire with his reproachfull and injurious words, upbrayding them with their pusilanimitie and faint- heartednesse, and with the regret of their ladies, banquettings and sensualities, which they had left at Rome, that he put them into heart again, which no persuasions or other means could do before; and thereby drew them, whom nought could have driven, to fight and fall upon him. And verily, when they are injuries that touch a man to the quick, they shall easily urge him, who was very backward to fight for his Kings quarrel, to be very forward in his own cause or interest. If a man but consider of what consequence the preservation and importance the safetie of a general is in an Armie, and how the enemies chiefest ayme is at the fairest marke, which is the head, from which all other depend, it seems that that counsell cannot be doubted of, which by sundrie great Chieftaines we have seen put in practice, which is, in the beginning of the fight, or in the fury of the battle, to disguise themselves. Notwithstanding the inconvenience a man may by this means incur, is no less than that mischief which a man seeketh to avoid: For the Captain being unseen and unknown of his soldiers, the courage they take by his example, and the heart they keep by his presence, is therewithall impaired and diminished; and losing the known ensignes and accustomed markes of their Leader, they either deem him dead, or, dispairing of any good success, to be fled. And touching experience, we sometimes see it to favor the one and sometimes the other partie. The accident of Pirrhus in the battle he had against the Consull Levinus in Italie serveth us for both uses: For, by concealing himself under the arms of Demagacles, and arming him with his own indeed he saved his life, but was in great danger to fall into the other mischief, and lose the day. Alexander, Cæsar, Lucullus, loved (at what time they were to enter fight) to arm and attire themselves with the richest arms, and garish clothes they had, and of particular bright-shining colours. Agis, Agesilaus, and that great Gilippus, contrairie, would ever go to wars meanely accoutred, and without any imperiall ornament. Among other reproaches that great Pompey is charged withall in the battle of Pharsalia, this is one speciall, that he idlely lingred with his Armie, expecting what his enemy would attempt; forasmuch as that (I will here borrow the very words of Plutarke, which are of more consequence than mine) weakneth the violence that running gives the first bIowes, and therewithall removeth the charging of the Combatants one against another, which more than any other thing is wont to fill them with fury and impetuosity, when with vehemence they come to enter-shocke one another, augmenting their courage by the crie and running; and in a manner alayeth and quaileth the heat of Soldiers: See-here what he says concerning this. But had Cæsar lost, who might not also have said, that contrariwise the strongest and firmest situation is that wherein a man keeps his stand without budginge and that who is settled in his march, closing, and against any time of need, sparing his strength in himself, has a great advantage against him that is in motion and disordered; and that running has already consumed part of his breath? Moreover, that an army being a body composed of so many several parts, it is impossible it should in such fury advance itself with so just a match, and proportioned a motion, and not breake and dis-rank, or at least alter her ordinance, and that the nimblest be not grapling before his fellowes may helpe him. In that drearie battle of the two Persian brethren, Clearchus the Lacedemonian, who commanded the Græcians that followed, Cyrus his faction, let them faine and gently without any halt-making to their charges, but when he came within fifty paces of his enemies he had them with all speed to run unto it; hoping by the shortnesse of the distance to manage their order and direct their breath; in the meane time giving them the advantage of the impetuositie, both for their bodies and for their shooting-arms. Others have ordered this doubt in their army after this manner: If your enemies headlong run upon you, stay for them and bouge not: If they without stirring stay for you, run with fury upon them. In the passage which the Emperor Charles the fifth made into Provence, our King Francis the first stood a good while upon this choice; whether it was best, by way of prevention, to go and meet with him in Italie, or to stay his coming into France. And albeit he considered what an advantage it is for one to preserve his house from the troubles and mischiefes that war brings with it, to the end that, possessing her whole strength, it may continually in all times of need store him with money, and supplie him with all other helps; and considering how the necessity of direfull war does daily enforce a General to make spoile of goods, and waste the Countrie, which cannot well be done in our own goods and countrie: and that the countriman does not as patiently endure this ravage at his friends hands as at his enemies, so as seditions may ensue amongst our onlie factions, and troubles amongst our friends: That license to rob and spoile, which in his countrie may not be to erated, is a great furtherance in a Souldier, and makes him the more willing to endure the miseries and toylings that follow war: And what a hard matter it is to keep the Souldier in office and heart, who has no other hope of profit but his bare pay, and is so near his wife, his children, his friends, and his home: That he who layeth the cloth is ever put to the greatest charges: That there is more pleasure in assailing than in defending: And that the apprehension of a battle lost in our ow ne home and entrailes is so violent, that it may easily shake the whole frame and distemper the whole body, seeing there is no passion so contagious as that of fear nor so easy apprehended and taken a- trust, or does more furiously possesse all parts of man: And that the Cities or Townes, which have either heard the hustling noise of the tempest or seen the sparkles of this all- consuming fire at their gates, or have perhaps received their Captains wounded, their Citizens pursued, and their soldiers spoiled, and all out of breath, if they be not more than obstinately constant, it is a thousand to one if in that brunt of fury they do not headlong cast themselves into some desperate resolution. Yet did he conclude and chuse this resolve for the best: First to revoke his forces he had beyond the Mountaines in Italie, and so stay his enemies approaches. For he might, on the contrairie part, imagine that being in his own countrie, and amidst good freinds, he had the better leisure io re-enforce his decayed forces, and more opportunity to strengthen Townes, to munite Castles, to store Rivers with all necessaries they wanted, and to keep all passages at his devotion, which done, all the ways should be open for him, and might by them have all manner of victuals, money, and other habilements of war brought him in safety, and without convoy: that he should have his subjects so much the more affectionate unto him, by how much nearer they should see the danger: That having so many Cities, Townes, Holds, Castles, and Barres for his securitie, he might at all times, according to opportunity and advantage, appoint and give Law unto the fight: And if he were pleased to temporize, while he took his ease, kept his forces whole, and maintained himself in safetie, he might see his enemy consume and waste himself by the difficulties which daily must necessarily assault, environ, and combat him, as he who should be engaged in an enemy- countrie and foe-land, where he should have nothing, nor meet with any thing, either before or behind him, or of any side, that did not offer him continuall war: no way nor means to refresh, to ease or give his army elbow-roome, if any sicknesse or contagion should come amongst his men; nor shelter to lodge his hurt and maymed Soldiers: where neither monie, munition, nor victuals might come unto him, but at the swords point; where he should never have leisure to take any rest or breath; where he should have no knowledge of places, passages, woods, foords, rivers, or countrie, that might defend him from ambuscados or surprises: And if he should unfortunately chance to lose a battle, no hope to save, or means to reunite the reliques of his forces. And there want not examples to strengthen both sides. Scipio found it better for him to invade his enemies countrie of Affrica, than to defend his own, and fight with him in Italie, where he was, wherein he had good success. But contrariwise, Hanniball in the same war wrought his own overthrow, by leaving the conquest of a forraine countrie for to go and defend his own. The Athenians having left the enemy in their own land for to pass into Sicilie, had very ill success, and were much contraried by fortune: whereas Agathocles, King of Siracusa, prospered and was favoured by her, what time he passed into Affrica, and left the war on foot in his own countrie. And we are accustomed to say with some show of reason, that especially in matters of war the events depend (for the greatest part) on fortune: which seldom will yield, or never subject herself unto our discourse or wisdom, as say these ensuing verses: Et male consultis pretium est, prudentia fallax, Nec fortuna probat causas sequiturque merentes: Sed vaga per cunctos nullo discrimine fertur: Scilicet est aliud quod nos cogatque regatque Majus, et in proprias ducat mortalia leges. --Manil. Astr. iv. 95. ’Tis best for ill advis’d, wisdom may faile, Fortune proves not the cause that should prevaile, But here and there without respect does saile, A higher power forsooth us over-draws, And mortal states guides with immortall laws. But if it be well taken, it seems that our counsels and deliberations do as much depend of her; and that fortune does also engage our discourses and consultations in her trouble and uncertaintie. We reason rashly, and discourse at random, says Timeus in Plato: for even as we, so have our discourses great participation with the temeritie of hazard. Return to CHAPTER XLVIII. OF STEEDS, CALLED IN FRENCH DESTRIERS CHAPTER XLVIII. OF STEEDS, CALLED IN FRENCH DESTRIERS EHOLD, I am now become a Gramarian, I, who never learn’t tongue but by way of roat, and that yet know not what either Adjective, Conjunctions or Ablative meaneth. As far as I remember, I have sometimes had certain horses which they call Funales, or Dextrarios, which on the right hand were led by, as spare horses, to take them fresh at any time of need and thence it commeth that we call horses of service Destriers; and our ancient Romanes do ordinarily say to Adexter, in steed of to accompanie. They also called Desultorios equos certain horses that were so taught, that mainly-running with all the speed they had, joyning sides to one another, without either bridle or saddle, the Roman gentlemen, armed at all assays, in the middest of their running race would cast and recast themselves from one to another horse. The Numidian men at arms were wont to have a second spare-horse led by hand, that in the greatest fury of the battle they might shift and change horse: Quibus, desultorum in modum, binos trahentibus equos, inter acerrimam sæpe pugnam in recentem equum ex fesso armatis transsultare, mos erat. Tanta velocitas ipsis, tamque docile equorum genus (Liv. Bel. Pun. dec. iii. 3.) Whose manner was as if they had been vaulters, leading two horses with them in armour to leap from their tired horse to the fresh-one, even in the hottest of the fight. So great agilitie was in themselves, and so apt to be taught was the race of their horses. There are many horses found that are taught to helpe their master, to run upon any man shall offer to draw a naked sword upon them; furiously to leap upon any man, both with feet to strike and with teeth to bite, that shall affront them; but that for the most part they rather hurt their friends than their enemies. Considering also, that if they once be grapled, you cannot easily take them off and you must needs stand to the mercy of their combat. Artibius, General of the Persian army had very ill luck to be mounted upon a horse fashioned in this schoole, at what time he fought man to man against Onesilus King of Salamis; for he was the cause of his death, by reason the shieldbearer or squire of Onesilus cut him with a faulchon betweene the two shoulders, even as he was leaping upon his master. And if that which the Italians report be true, that in the battle of Fornovo, King Charles his horse, with kicking, winching, and flying, rid both his master and himself from the enemies that encompast him, to dismount or kill him, and without that, he had been lost: He committed himself to a great hazard, and scap’t a narrow scowring. The Mammalukes boast that they have the nimblest and readiest horses of any men at arms in the world. That both by nature they are instructed to discerne, and by custom taught to distinguish their enemy, on whom they must leepe and wince with feet and bite with teeth, according to the voice their master speaks or rider gives them. And are likewise taught to take up from the ground, lances, darts, or any other weapons with their mouths, and as he commandeth to present them to their rider. It is said of Cæsar, and of Pompey the Great, that amongst their many other excellent qualities, they were also most cunning and perfect horsemen; and namely of Cæsar, that in his youth being mounted upon a horse, and without any bridle, he made him run a fall cariere, make a sodaine stop, and with his hands behind his backe, performe what ever can be expected of an excellent ready horse. And even as nature was pleased to make both him and Alexander two matchlesse miracles in militarie profession, so would you say she has also endevoured, indeed, enforced herself to arm them extraordinarily; For all men know that Alexanders horse, called Bucephalus, had a head shaped like unto that of a bull; that he suffered no man to get-on and sit him but his master; that none could weald and manage him but he; what honors were done him after his death all know, for he had a City erected in his name. Cæsar likewise had another who had his fore-feet like unto a mans, with hoofs cloven in form of fingers, who could never be handled, drest, or mounted but by Cæsar, who when he died dedicated his image to the Goddesse Venus. If I be once on horse-backe, I alight very unwillingly; for it is the seat I like best, whether I be sound or sicke. Plato commendeth it to be availefull for health: And Plinie affirmeth the same to be healthfull for the stomacke and for the joints. And sithence we be falne into this subject, let us a little follow it I pray you. We read of a law in Xenophon, by which all men that either had or were able to keep a horse were expresly forbidden to travell and go a foot. Trogus and Justinus report that the Parthians were not only accustomed to war on horse-backe, but also to dispatch all their business, and negotiate their affairs, both public and privat; as to bargaine, to buy, to sell, to parly, to meet, to entertaine one another, and to converse and walke together; and that the chiefest difference betweene free men and servants amongst them is that the first ever ride, and the other go alwaies on foot: an institution first devised by King Cyrus. There are many examples in the Roman histories (and Suetonius does more particularly note it in Cæsar) of Captains that commanded their horsemen to alight whensoever by occasion they should be urged unto it, thereby to remove all manner of hope from their Soldiers to save themselves by flight, and for the advantage they hoped for in this manner of fight: Quo haud dubie superat Romanus: (Liv. dec. 1. 3 & 7). Wherein undauntedly the Roman is superiour to all, says Titus Livius: yet shall we see, that the first provision and chief means they used to bridle rebellion amongst their new conquered nations was to deprive them of all arms and horses. Therefore find we so often in Cæsar: Arma proferri, jumenta produci, obsides dari jubat: (Cæs. Comment. vii.) He commands all their armour should be brought forth, all their cattell should be driven out, and hostages should be delivered. The great Turke does not permit, at this day, any Christian or Jew, to have or keep any horse for himself throughout all his large empire. Our ancestors, and especially at what time we had wars with the English, in all solemn combats or set battles, would (for the most part) alight from their horses, and fight on foot, because they would not adventure to hazard so precious a thing as their honor and life, but on the trust of their own proper strength and vigor of their undanted courage, and confidence of their limbs. Let Chrisanthes in Xenophon say what be pleaseth: whosoever fighteth on horse-backe engageth his valor and hazardeth his fortune on that of his horse; his hurts, his stumbling, his death, draws your life and fortune into consequence, if he chance to startle or be afraid, then are you induced to doubt or fear: if to leape forward, then to become rash and foolhardy: if he want a good mouth or a timely spurre, your honor is bound to answer for it. And therefore do not I find it strange, that those combats were more firme and furious than those which now we see fought on horse-backe. -- cedebant pariter, pariterque ruebant Victores, victique, neque his fuga nota, neque illis. Virg. Æn. x. 756. The victors and the vanquisht both together Gave backe, came on: the flight was known in neither. Their battles are seen much better compact and contrived: they are now but bickerings and routs: Primus clamor atque impetus rem decernit. The first shout and shocke makes an end of the matter. And the thing we call to help us, and keep us company in so great and hazardous an adventure, ought, as much as possible may be, lie still in our disposition and absolute power. As I would counsell a gentleman to chuse the shortest weapons, and such as he may best assure himself of: It is most apparant that a man may better assure himself of a sword he holdeth in his hand, than of a bullet shot out of a pistoll, to which belong so many severall parts, as powder, stone, locke, snap-hanse, harrell, stocke, scowring-peece, and many others, whereof if the least faile, or chance to breake, and be distempered, it is able to overthrow, to hazard, or miscarry your fortune. Seldome does that blow come or light on the marke it is aymed at, which the air does carry. Et quo ferre velint permittere vulnera ventis, Ensis habet vires et gens guæcunque virorum est, Bella gerit gladius. Lucan. viii, 384. Giving winds leave to give wounds as they list, But swords have strength, and right men never mist With sword t’assault, and with sword to resist. But concerning that weapon, I shall more amply speak of it where I will make a comparison betweene ancient and modern arms: And except the astonishment and frighting of the eare, which nowadaies is grown so familiar amongst men, that none does greatly fear it; I think it to be a weapon of small effect, and hope to see the use of it abolished. That wherewith the Italians were wont to throw with fire in it, was more frightfull and terrour-moving. They were accustomed to name a kind of javelin, Phalarica, armed at one end with an yron pike of three foot long, that it might pierce an armed man through, which lying in the field they used to lanch or hurle with the hand, and sometimes to shoot out of certain engines, for to defend besieged places: the staffe whereof being wreath’d about with hemp or flax, all pitched and oiled over, flying in the air, would soone be set afire, and lighting upon any body or target, deprived the partie hit therewith of all use of weapons or limbs: Me thinkes nevertheless, that coming to grapple, it might as well hinder the assailant as trouble the assailed, and that the ground strewed with such burning truncheons, might in a pell-mell confusion produce a common incommoditie. ----- magnum stridens contorta phalarica venit Fulminis acta modo. -- Virg. Æn. ix. 705. With monstrous buzzing came a fire-dart thirled As if a thunder-bolt had there been whirled. They had also other means, to the use of which custom enured them, and that by reason of inexperience seem incredible to us: wherewith they supplied the defect of our powder and bullets. They with such fury darted their Piles, and with such force hurled their javelins, that they often pierced two targets and two armed men through, as it were with a spit. They hit as sure and as far with their slings as with any other shot. Saxis globosis funda, mare apertum incessentes. . . coronas modici circuli magno ex intervallo loci assueti trajicere: non capita modo hostium vulnerabant, sed quem locum destinassent Liv. dec. iv. 8). While they were boyes, with round stones in a sling, making ducks and drakes upon the sea, they accustomed to cast through round marks of small compasse a great distance off: whereby they not only hit and hurt the heads of their enemies; but woufd strike any place they aymed at. Their battering or murthering peeces represented as well the effect as the clattering and thundering noise of ours: ad ictus mænium cum terribili sonitu editos, pavor el trepidatio cepit; At the battery of the walles made with a terrible noise, fear an d trembling began to attach them within. The Gaules, our ancient forefathers in Asia, hated mortally such treacherous and flying weapons, as they that were taught to fight hand to hand, and with more courage. Non tam patentibus plagis moventur, - ubi latior quam altior plaga est, etiam gloriosius se pugnare putant; iidem quum aculeus sagittæ, aut glandis abdita, introrsus tenui vulnere in speciem urit; tum in rabiem et pudorem tam parvæ perimentis pestis versi, prosternunt corpora humi (Liv. dec. iv. 8). They are not so much moved with wide gashes, where the wound is more broad than it is deepe, there they think that they fight with more bravery; but when the sting of an arrow or a bullet, with a small wound to show, gals them inwardly, then falling into rage and shame that so slight a hurt should kill them, they cast their bodies on the ground. A model or picture very near unto an harquebusada. The ten thousand Græcians in their long-lingring and far-famous retreat, encountered with a certain nation, that exceedingly much endomaged them with stiffe, strong, and great [bowes], and so long arrows, that taking them up, they might throw them after the manner of a dart, and with them pierce a target and an armed man through and through. The engines which Dionysius invented in Siracusa, to shoot and cast mightie big arrows, or rather timber-peaces, and huge-great stones, so far and with such force, did greatly represent and come very near our modern invention. We may not also forget the pleasant seat which one named Master Peter Pol, doctor in divinitie, used to sit upon his mule, who, as Monstrelet reporteth, was wont to ride up and down the streets of Paris, ever sitting sideling, as women use. He also says in another place, that the Gascoines had certain horses, so fierce and terrible, taught to turn and stop suddenly in running, whereat the French, the Piccards, the Flemmings, and Brabantins (as they who were never accustomed to see the like) were greatly amazed, and thought it a wonder: I use his very words. Cæsar, speaking of those of Swethen, saithe In any skirmish or fight on horsebacke, they often alight to combat on foot, having so trained and taught their horses, that so long as the fight lasteth they never bouge from their masters side, that if need require, they may suddenly mount up again: and according to their natural custom, there is nothing accounted more base or vile than to use saddles or bardels, and they greatly contemne and scorne such as use them: So that a few of them fear not to encounter with a troupe far exceeding them in number. That which I have other times wondered at, to see a horse fashioned and taught, that a man having but a wand in his hand, and his bridle loose hanging over his ears, might at his p leisure manage, and make him turn, stop, run, carrie, trot, gallop, and whatever else may be expected of all excellent ready horse, was common amongst the Massilians, who never used either bridle or saddle. Et gens que nudo residens Massilia dorso, Ora levi flectit, froenorum nescia, virga. --Lucan. iv. 681. Massilian horsemen on bare horse-backe sit Manage with light rod, without reynes or bit. Et Numidæ infroeni cingunt. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 41. Numidians who their horses ride Without bit, round about us bide. Equi sine froenis, deformis ipse cursus rigida cervice et extento capite currentiam: The horses being without bridles, their course is ill favoured, they running with a stiffe necke, and outstretcht head (like a roasted Pigge:) Alphonsus, King of Spain that first established the order of Knights called the order of the Bend or skarfe, amongst other rules devised this one, that none of them, upon pain to forfeit a marke of silver for every time offending, should ever ride either mule or mulet; as I lately read in Guevaras epistles, of which. whosoever called them his golden epistles gave a judgment far different from mine. The Courtier says, That before his time it was counted a great shame in a gentleman to be seen riding upon a mule: Whereas the Abyssines are of a contrary opinion, who accordingly as they are advanced to places of honor or dignitie about their Prince, called Prester-John, so do they more and more affect, in signe of pompe and state, to ride upon large-great mules. Xenophon reporteth that the Assirians were ever wont to keep their horses fast-tied in fetters or gyves, and ever in the stable, they were so wild and furious. And for that they required so much time to unshackle, and to harnish them (lest protracting of so long time might, if they should chance at unawares, and being un ready, to be surprised by their enemies, endomage them) they never took up their quarter in any place except it were well dyked and intrenched. His Cirus, whom he maketh so cunning in horsemanship, did always keep his horses at a certain stint, and would never suffer them to have any meat before they had deserved the same by the sweat of some exercise. If the Scithians in time of war chanced to be brought to any necessitie of victuals, the readiest remedy they had was to let their horses blood, and therewithall quenched their thirst and nourished themselves. Venit et epoto Sarmata pastus equo. --Mart. Spect. iii. 4. The Scithian also came, who strangely feedes On drinking out his horse (or that he bleedes). Those of Crotta being hardly besieged by Metellus, were reduced to so hard a pinch and strait necessitie of all manner of other beverage, that they were forced to drinke the stale or urine of their horses. To verifie how much better cheape the Turkes do both levie, conduct, and maintaine their armies than we Christians do, they report that besides their soldiers never drinke any thing but water, and feed on nothing but rice and drie salt flesh, which they reduce into a kind of powder (whereof every private man does commonly carry so much about him as will serve for a months provision), and for a shift will live a long time with the blood of their horses, wherein they use to put a certain quantitie of salt, as the Tartars and Moskovites do. These new discovered people of the Indies, when the Spaniards came first amongst them, esteemed that as well men as horses were either gods or creatures far beyond and excelling their nature in nobility. Some of which, after they were vanquished by them, coming to sue for peace and beg pardon at their hands, to whom they brought presents of gold and such viand’s as their countrie yielded, omitted not to bring the same and as much unto their horses, and with as solemn oration as they had made unto men, taking their neighings as a language of truce and composition. In the [he]ther Indies the chief and royallest honor was anciently wont to be to ride upon an elephant; the second to go in coaches drawne with foure horses; the third to ride upon a camell; the last and basest was to be carried or drawne by one horse alone. Some of our modern writers report to have seen some countries in that climate where the people ride oxen, with packe-saddles, stirrops, and bridles, by which they were carried very easily. Quintus Fabius Maximus Rutilianus, warring against the Samnites, and seeing that his horsemen in three or foure charges they gave had missed to breake and run through his enemies battalion, at last resolved thus, that they should all unbridle their horses, and with main force of sharpe spurres pricke and broach them; which done, the horses, as enraged, took such a running through, and athwart the enemies camp, arms and men, that nought was able to resist them, and with such a fury that by opening, shouldering, and overthrowing the battalion, they made way for his infanterie, which there committed a most bloody slaughter, and obtained a notable victory. The like was commanded and effected by Quintus Fulvius Flaccus against the Celtiberians: Id cum majore vi equorum facietis, si effrænatos in hostes equos immittitis; quod stæpe Romanos equites cum laude fecisse sua, memoriæ proditum est. Detractisqu e frænis bis ultro citroque cum magna strage hostium, infractis omnibus hastis, transcurrerunt:(Liv. dec. iv. 10). That shall you do with more violence of horse if you force your horse unbridled on the enemy, which it is recorded the Roman horsemen have often performed with great proofe and praise. So pulling off the bridles they twice ran through forward and backe again with great slaughter of the enemy, all their launces broken. The Duke of Moscovie did anciently owe this reverence unto the Tartars, at what time soever they sent any Ambassadors to him, that he must go meet them on foot, and present them with a goblet full of mares-milke (a drinke counted very delicious amongst them) which whilst they were drinking, if any drop chanced to be spilt upon their horses haires, he was by dutie hound to licke the same up with his tongue. The army which the Emperor Bajazeth had sent into Russia, was overwhelmed by so horrible a tempest of snow that to find some shelter, and to save themselves from the extremity of the cold, many advised to kill and unpanch their horses and enter into their panches to enjoy and find some ease by that vital heat. Bajazeth after that bloudy and tragical conflict wherein he was overthrowne by the Scithian Tamburlane in seeking to escape, had no doubt saved himself by the swiftnesse of an Arabian mare on which he was mounted that day, if unluckily he had not been forced to let her drinke her fill in passing over a river, which made her so faint and floundered that he was easily overtaken and apprehended by those that pursued him. The common saying is, that to let a horse stale after a full cariere does take down his speed, but I would never had thought that drinking had done it, but rather strengthened and heartned him. Croesus passing alongst the citie of Sardis found certain thickets, wherein were great store of snakes and serpents, on which his horses fed very hungerly, which thing, as Herodotus says, was an ill-boding prodigy unto his affairs. We call him an entire horse that has his full main and whole ears, and which in show, or at a muster, does not exceed others. The Lacedemonians having defeated the Athenians in Sicilie, returning in great pompe and glory from the victory into the citie of Siracusa, among other bravadoes of theirs, caused such horses as they had taken from their enemies to be shorne all over, and so led them in triumph. Alexander fought with a nation called Dahas, where they went to war two and two, all armed, upon one horse, but when they come to combat one must alight, and so successively one fought on foot and the other on horsebacke, each in his turn one after another. I am persuaded that in respect of sufficiencie, of comlinesse, and of grace on horseback no nation goeth beyond us. A good horse-man (speaking according to our phrase) seems rather to respect an undismayed courage than an affected clean seat. The man most skilfull, best and surest-fitting, comeliest-graced, and nimblest- handed, to sit, to ride, and mannage a horse cunningly that ever I knew, and that best pleased my humor, was Monsieur de Carnavalet, who was Master of the Horse unto our King Henry the second. I have seen a man take his full cariere, standing boult up-right on both his feet on the saddle, leap down to the ground from it, and turning backe take off the saddle, and presently set it on again as fast as ever it was, and then leap-into it again, and al this did he whilst his horse was running as fast as might be with his bridle on his necke. I have also seen him ride over a bonnet or cap, and being gone a good distance from it, with his bow shooting backward, to sticke many arrows in the same; then sitting still in the saddle to take up any thing from the ground, to set one foot to the ground and keep the other in the stirrop, and continually running do a thousand such tumbling and apish tricks, wherewith he got his living. There have in my time two men been seen in Constantinople, both at once upon one horse, and who in his speediest running would by turnes, first one and then another, leape down to the ground and then into the saddle again, the one still taking the others place. And another who only with teeth, and without the helpe of any hand, would bridle, currie, rub, dresse, saddle, girt, and harnish his horse. Another that betweene two horses, and both saddled, standing upright with one foot in the one and the second in the other, did bear another man on his arms standing upright, run a full speedy course, and the uppermost to shoot and hit any marke with his arrows. Divers have been seen who, standing on their heads and with their legs ourstretched aloft, having many sharp. pointed cimitaries fastened round about the saddle, to gallop at full speed. While I was a young lad, I saw the Prince of Sulmona at Naples manage a young, a rough and fierce horse, and show all manner of horsemanship; to hold testons or reals under his knees and toes so fast as if they had been nayled there, and all to show his sure, steady, and unmoveable sitting. Return to Renascence Editions CHAPTER XLIX. OF ANCIENT CUSTOMES WOULD willingly excuse our people for having no other patterne or rule of perfection, but his own customs, his own fashions: For, it is a common vice, not only in the vulgar sort, but as it were in all men, to bend their ayme, and frame their thoughts unto the fashions wherein they were borne. I am pleased when he shall see FabriciusLælius, who, because they are neither attired nor fashioned according to our manner, that he condemne their countenance to be strange and their cariage barbarous. But I bewaile his particular indiscretion, in that he suffereth himself to be so blinded and deceived by the authority of present custom, and that if custom pleaseth he is ready to change opinion and varie advice, every moneth, nay every day, and judgeth so diversly of himself. When he wore short-wasted doublets, and but little lower than his breast, he would maintaine by militant reasons that the waste was in his right place: but when not long after he came to weare them so long-wasted, indeed almost so low as his privates, than began he to condemne the former fashion, as foolish, intolerable and deformed; and to commend the latter as comely, handsome, and commendable. A new fashion of apparel creepeth no sooner into use but presently he blameth and dispraiseth the old, and that with so earnest a resolution and universall a consent, that you would say, it is some kind of madnesse or self-regarding humor that giddieth his understanding. And forasmuch as our changing or altering of fashion is so sudden and new-fangled, that the inventions and new devices of all the tailors in the world cannot so fast invent novelties, it must necessarily follow that neglected and stale rejected fashions do often come into credit and use again: And the latest and newest within a while after come to be outcast and despised, and that one self-same judgment within the space of fifteene or twentie years admitteth not only two or three different, but also cleane contrary opinions, with so light and incredible inconstancie, that any man would wonder at it. There is no man so suttle-crafty amongst us, that suffereth not himself to be enveigled and over-reached by this contradiction, and that is not insensibly dazeled both with his inward and externall eyes. I will here huddle- up some few ancient fashions that I remember: Some of them like unto ours, othersome far differing from them: To the end, that having ever this continuall variation of humane things in our mind, we may the better enlighten and confirme our transported judgment. That manner of fight which we use now adaies with rapier and cloke, was also used among the Romanes, as says Cæsar: Sini stras sagis involvunt, gladiosque distringunt: (Cæs. Bel. Civ. i.) they wrap their left arms in their clokes, and draw their swords. We may to this day observe this vice to be amongst us, and which we have taken from them, that is, to stay such passengers as we meet by the way, and force them to tell us who they are, whence they come, whither they go, and to count it as an injurie and cause of quarrell they refuse to answer our demand. In Baths, which our forefathers used daily before meals, as ordinarily as we use water to wash our hands, when first they came into them they washed but their arms and legs, but afterward (which custom lasted many after-ages, and to this day continueth amongst diverse nations of the world) their whole body over with compounded and perfumed waters, in such sort as they held it as a great testimony of simplicitie to wash themselves in pure and uncompounded water: Such as were most delicate and effeminate were wont to perfume their whole bodies over and over, three or four times every day: And often (as our French women have lately taken up) to picke and snip out the haires of their fore-head, so they of all their body. or Quod pectus, quod crura ubi, quod brachia vellis. Mart. ii. Epig. lxii. 1. That you from breast, legs, arms, the hair Neatly pull off (to make them fair). Although they had choice of ointments fit for the purpose. Psilotro nitet, aut arida latet abdita creta. Lib. vi. Epi. xciii. 9. She shines with ointments that make hair to fall. Or with dry chalke she over-covers all. They loved to lie soft, and on fine down beds, aleaging lying on hard mattresses as a signe of patience. They fed lying on their beds, near after the manner of the Turks nowadaies, Inde thoro pater æneas sic orsus ab alto. --Virg. Æn. ii.2. Father Æneas thus gan say, From stately couch where then he lay. And it is reported of Cato Junior that after the battle of Pharsalia, and that he began to mourne and bewaile the miserable state of the common-wealth, and ill condition of public affairs, he ever eat sitting on the ground, following an austere, and observing a strict kind of life. The Beso las manos was used as a signe of honor and humility only towards great persons. If friends met, after friendly salutations they used to kisse one another, as the Venetians do at this day. Gratatusque darem cum dulcibus oscula verbis. Ovid. Pont. iv. El. ix. 13. Give her I would with greetings graced, Kisses with sweet words enterlaced. And in saluting or suing to any great man they touched his knees, Pasicles the philosopher, brother unto Crates, coming to salute one, whereas he should have carried his hand to his knee, carried the same unto his genitories: The partie saluted having rudely pusht him away, What, quoth he, is not that part yours as well as the other? Their manner of feeding was as ours, their fruit last. They were wont to wipe their tailes (this vain superstition of words must be left unto women) with a sponge, and that’s the reason why Spongia in Latine is counted an obscene word: which sponge was ever tied to the end of a gaffe, as witnesseth the story of him that was carried to be devoured of the wild beasts before the people, who desiring leave to go toe a privie before his death, and having no other means to kill himself, thrust down the sponge and staffe he found in the privie into his throte wherewith he choked himself. Having ended the delights of nature, they were wont to wipe their privities with perfumed wooll. At ubi nil faciam, sed lota memtula lana. Mart. xi. Epig. li. 11. To you no such thing will I bring, But with washt wooll another thing. In every street of Rome were placed tubs and such other vessels, for passengers to make water in. Pusi seape lacum propter, se dolia curta Somno devincti credunt extollere vestem. Lucr. iv. 1018. Children asleepe oft think they take up all Neere to some pissing tub, some lake, some wall. They used to break their fast, and nonchion between meals, and all summer-time had men that sold snowe up and down the streets, wherewith they refreshed their wines, of whom some were so daintie that all winter long they used to put snow into their wine, not deeming it cold enough. Principall and noble men had their cup bearers, tasters, carvers, and buffons to make them merry. In Winter their viandes were brought and set on the boord upon arches, as we use chafing dishes; and had portable kitchens (of which I have seen some) wherein might be drawne wherever one list a whole service and messe of meat. Has vobis epulas habete, lauti. Nos offendimur ambulante cæna. Mart. vii. Epig. xlvii. 5. Take you daintie mouth’d such stirring feasts With walking meales we are offended guests. And in summer they often caused cold water (being carried through pipes) to drill upon them as they sate in their dining chambers, or lowe parlors, where in cisterns they kept store of fish alive, which the by-standers might at their pleasure chuse and take with their hands, and have it drest every man according to his fantasie. Fish has ever had this privilege, as at this day it has, that chief gentlemen are pleased and have skill to dress it best: And to say truth, the taste of fish is much more delicat and exquisit than that of flesh, at least in mine. But in all manner of magnificence, delitiousnes, riotous gluttonie, inventions of voluptuoushes, wantonnes, and sumptuositie, we truly endeavor, as much as may be, to equall and come near them: For our will and taste is as much corrupted as theirs, but our skill and sufficiencie is far short of them: Our wit is no more capable, and our strength no more able to approach and match them in these vitious and blame- worthy parts than in vertuous and commendable actions: For both proceede from a vigor of spirit and far-reaching wit, which, without comparison, was much greater in them than now in us. And mindes by how much more strong and excellent they are, so much less facultie and means have they to do, either excellently well or notoriously ill. The chiefest aime amongst them was a meane or mediocrity. The Foremost or Last, in writing or speaking, had no signification of preheminence or greatness, as may evidently appeare by their writings. They would familiarly and as soon say, Oppius and Cæsar, as Cæsar and Oppius; and as indifferently I and you, as you and I. And that’s the reason why I have heretofore noted in the life of Flaminius, in our French Plutarke, a place where it seems that the Author, speaking of the jealousie of glory that was between the Ætolians and the Romans, for the gain of a battle, which they had obtained in common, maketh for the purpose, that in Greeke songs the Ætolians were named before the Romans, except there be some Amphibology in the French words: for in that toung I read it. When Ladies came unto stoves or hot-houses, they made it not daintie to admit men into their companie, and to be washed, rubbed, chafed, and annointed by the hands of their groomes and pages. Inguina succinctus nigra ubi servus aluta Stat, quoties calidis nuda foveris æquis. -- Epig. xxxiv. 1. Your man, whose loynes blacke-lether girds, stands by, Whilst in warme water you stark-naked lie. They also used to sprinkle themselves all over with certain powders, thereby to allay and represse all manner of filth or sweat. The ancient Gaules (says Sidonius Apollinaris ) wore their hair long before, and all the hinder part of their head shaven, a fashion that our wanton youths and effeminate gallants have lately renued, and in this new-fangled and fond-doting age, brought up again, with wearing of long-dangling locks before. The ancient Romans paid the water-men their fare or due so soone as they came into the boat, whereas we pay it when they set us on shore. -- dum as exigitur, dum mula ligature Tota abit hora. While they call for their fare, tie drawe-mule to, There runs away a full hour, if not two. Women were wont to lie on the utmost side of the, bed, and therefore was Cæsar called Spondam Regis Nicomedis:3 ’King Nicomedes his beds side.’ They took breath while they were drinking, and used to baptise or put water in their wines. -- quis puer ocius Restinguit ardentis falerni Pocula prætereunte limpha? --Hor. ii.Od. xi. 18. What boy of mine or thine Shall coole our cup of wine With running water fine? Those cousening and mind-deceiving countenances of lakeis were also amongst them. O Jane, a tergo quem nulla ciconia pinsit, Nec manus auriculas imitata est mobilis albas, Nec lingæ quantum sitiet canis Apula tantum. O Janus, whom behinde no Storks-bill does deride, Nor nimble hand resembling mak’st ears white and wide, Nor so much tongue lil’d out as dogges with thirst ore-dride. The Argian and Roman Ladies mourned in white, as our dames wont to do, and if I might be credited, and bear-sway amongst them, they should continue it still. But because there are many bookes that treat of this argument, I will say no more of it. Return to CHAPTER L. OF DEMOCRITUS AND HERACLITUS CHAPTER L. OF DEMOCRITUS AND HERACLITUS UDGEMENT is an instrument for all subjects, and meddles every where, and therefore the Essayes I make of it, there is no manner of occasion I seek not to employ therein. If it be a subject I understand not my self, therein I make trial of it, sounding afarre off the depth of the ford, and finding the same over deepe for my reach, I keep my self on the shoare. And to acknowledge not to be able to wade through is a part of its effect, indeed of such whereof he vanteth most. If I light upon a vain and idle subject, I assaye to trie and endeavor to see whether I may find a good ground to work upon, and matter to frame a body, and wherewith to build and under-lay it. Sometimes I addresse my judgement and contrive it to a noble and out- worn subject, wherein is nothing found subsisting of itself, the high way to it being so bare-trodden that it cannot march but in other steps. There he pleaseth himself in chusing the course he thinkes best, and a thousand paths sometimes he says, this or that was best chosen. I take my first Argument of fortune: All are likewise unto me: And I never purpose to handle them throughly: For there is nothing wherein I can perceive the full perfection: Which they do not that promise to show it us. Of a hundred parts and visages that every thing has, I take one, which sometimes I slightly run over, and other times but cursorily glance at. And yet other whilst I pinch it to the quick and give it a Stockado, not the widest, but the deepest I can. And for the most part I love to seize upon them by some unwonted lustre. I would adventure to treat and discourse of some matter to the depth; knew I my self less, or were I deceived in my own impuissance; scattering here one and there another word, scantlings taken from their main groundwork, disorderly dispersed without any well- grounded designe and promise. I am not bound to make it good, nor without varying to keep my self close-tied unto it; whensoever it shall please me to yield my self to doubt, to uncertaintie, and to my Mistris’s form, which is ignorance. Each motion sheweth and discovereth what we are. The very same mind of Cæsar we see in directing, marshalling, and setting the battle of Pharsalia, is likewise seen to order, dispose, and contrive idle, trifling and amorous devices. We judge of a horse not only by seeing him ridden, and cunningly managed, but also by seeing him trot or pace; indeed, if we but looke upon him as he stands in the stable. Amongst the functions of the soul, some are but meane and base. He that seeth her no further, can never know her thorowly. And he that seeth her march her natural and simple pace, does perhaps observe her best. The winds or passions take her most in her highest pitch, seeing she entirely coucheth herself upon every matter, and wholy therein exerciseth herself: and handleth but one at once, not according to it, but according to herself. Things severall in themselves have perhaps weight, measure, and condition: But inwardly, in us, she cuts it out for them, as she understandeth the same herself. Death is fearefull and ugly unto Cicero; wished for and desired of Cato; and indifferent unto Socrates. Health, wellfare, conscience, authority, riches, glory, beautie, and their contraries are dispoyled at the entrance, and receive a new vesture at the soules hand. Yea, and what coulour she pleaseth: browne, bright, greene, sad, or any hew else; sharpe or sweet, deepe or superficiall, and what each of them pleaseth. For none of them did ever verifie their stiles, their rules, or formes in common; each one severally is a Queene in her own estate. Therefore let us take no more excuses from externall qualities of things. To us it belongeth to give ourselves accoumpt of it. Our good and our evil has no dependancy but from ourselves. Let us offer our vows and offerings unto it, and not to fortune. She has no power over our manners. Why should I not judge of Alexander as I am sitting and drinking at table, and talking in good company? Or if he were playing at Chesse, what string of his wit does not tone or harpe on this fool-childish and time-consuming play? I lothe and shun it, only because there is no sport enough in it, and that in his recreation he is over serious with us, being ashamed I must apply the attention therunto as might be employed on some good subject. He was no more busied in levying his forces and preparing for his glorious passage into India; nor this other in disintangling and discovering of a passage whence dependeth the well-fare and safety of mankind. See how much our mind troubleth this ridiculous ammuzing, if all her sinnewes bandy not. How amply she gives every one Law in that to know and directly to judge of himself. I do not more universally view and feel my self in any other posture. What passion does not exercise us therunto. Choller, spight, hatred, impatience, and vehement ambition to overcome, in a matter wherein it were perhaps more excusable to be ambitious for to be vanquished. For a rare pre-excellence, and beyond the common reach, in so frivolous a thing, is much mis-seeming a man of honor. What I say of this example may be spoken of all others. Every parcell, every occupation of a man, accuses and sheweth him equal unto another. Democritus and Heraclitus were two Philosophers, the first of which, finding and deeming humane condition to be vain and ridiculous, did never walke abroad but with a laughing, scorneful and mocking countenance: Whereas Heraclitus, taking pity and compassion of the very same condition of ours, was continually seen with a sad, mournful, and heavy cheere, and with tears trickling down his blubbered eyes. -- Alter Ridebat quoties a limine moverat unum Protuleratque pedem, flebat contrarius alter. Juven. Sat. x. 28. One from his doore, his foote no sooner past, But straight he taught; the other wept as fast. I like the first humor best, not because it is more pleasing to laugh than to weepe; but for it is more disdainfull, and does more condemne us than the other. And me thinkes we can never be sufficiently despised according to our merit. Bewailing and commiseration are commixed with some estimation of the thing moaned and wailed. Things scorned and contemned are thought to be of no worth. I cannot be persuaded there can be so much ill lucke in us as there is apparant vanity, nor so much malice as sottishnesse. We are not so full of evil as of voydnesse and inanitie. We are not so miserable as base and abject. Even so Diogenes, who did nothing but trifle, toy, and dally with himself, in rumbling and rowing of his tub, and flurting at Alexander, accompting us but flies and bladders puft with winde, was a more sharpe, a more bitter, and a more stinging judge, and by consequence more just and fitting my humor than Timon, surnamed the hater of all mankinde. For looke what a man hateth, the same thing he takes to hart. Timon wisht all evil might light on us: He was passionate in desiring our ruine. He shunned and loathed our conversation as dangerous and wicked, and of a depraved nature: Whereas the other so little regarded us, that we could neither trouble nor alter him by our contagion; he forsooke our company, not for fear, but for disdaine of our commerce: He never thought us capable or sufficient to do either good or evil. Of the same stampe was the answer of Statilius, to whom Brutus spake to win him to take part, and adhere to the conspiracie against Cæsar: He allowed the enterprize to be very just, but disalowed of the men that should performe the same, as unworthy that any man would put himself in any adventure for them: Conformable to the discipline of Hegesias, who said, That a man ought never to do anything but for himself; forasmuch as he alone is worthy to have any action performed for him: and to that of Theodorus,who thought it an injustice that a wise man would in any case hazard himself for the good and benefit of his countrie, or to endanger his wisdom for fooles. Our own condition is as ridiculous as risible, as much to be laught at as able to laugh. Return to CHAPTER LI. OF THE VANITIE OF WORDS CHAPTER LI. OF THE VANITIE OF WORDS RHETORICIAN of ancient times said that his trade was to make small things appeare and seem great. It is a shoemaker that can make great shooes for a little foot. Had he lived in Sparta he had doubtlesse been well whipped for professing a false, a couzening and deceitful art. And I think Archidamus King of that City did not with out astonishment listen unto the answer of Thucydides, of whom he demanded whether he or Pericles was the strongest and nimblest wrestler; whose answer was this, Your question Sir, is very hard to be decided; for if in wrestling with him I give him a fall, with his fair words he perswadeth those that saw him on the ground that he never fell, and so gets the victory. Those that maske and paint women commit not so foul a fault; for it is no great loss, though a man see them not, as they were naturally borne and unpainted: Whereas these profess to deceive and beguile not of eyes, but our judgement, and to bastardize and corrupt the offence of things. Those common-wealths that have maintained themselves in a regular formal, and well governed estate, as that of Creete and Lacedemon, did never make any great esteeme of orators. Ariston did wisely define Rhetorike to be a Science, to persuade the vulgar people: Socrates and Plato to be an Art to deceive and flatter. And those which denie it in the general description, do every where in their precepts verify the same. The Mahometans, by reason of its inutilitie, forbid the teaching of it to their children. And the Athenians, perceiving how pernicious the profession and use thereof was, and of what credit in their City, ordained that their principal part, which is to move affections, should be dismissed and taken away, together with all exordiums and perorations. It is an instrument devised to busie, to manage, and to agitate a vulgar and disordered multitude; and is an implement to be employed but about distempered and sicke mindes, as Physicke about crazed bodies. And those where either the vulgar, the ignorant, or the generalitie have had all power, as that of Rhodes, those of Athens, and that of Rome, and where things have ever been in continuall disturbance and uproar, thither have Orators and the professors of that Art flocked. And verily, if it be well looked into, you shall find very few men in those common-wealths that without helpe of eloquence have attained to any worthy estimation and credit: Pompey, Cæsar, Crassus, Lucullus, Lentulus, Metellus, have thence taken their greatest stay and furtherance, whereby they have ascended unto that height and greatness of authority whereunto they at last attained, and against the opinion of better times have more prevailed with words than with arms. For L. Volumnius, speaking publikely in favor of the election which some had made of Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius to be Consuls, says thus: They are men borne unto war, of high spirits, of great performance, and able to effect anything; but rude, simple, and unarted in the combat of talking: minds truly consulare. They only are good Pretors, to do justice in the City (says he), that are subtile, cautelous, well- spoken, wily, and lip-wise. Eloquence has chiefly flourished in Rome when the common- wealths affairs have been in worst estate and that the devouring Tempest of civill broyles, and intestine wars did most agitate and turmoil them. Even as a rancke, free and untamed soyle, beareth the rankest and strongest weeds, whereby it seems that those common weales which depend of an absolute Monarch, have less need of it than others: For that foolishnesse and facilitie which is found in the common multitude, and which does subject the same to be managed, persuaded, and led by the ears by the sweet, alluring and sense-entrancing sound of this harmonie, without duly weighing, knowing, or considering the trueth of things by force of reason: This facilitie and easy yielding, I say, is not so easily found in one only ruler, and it is more easy to warrant him from the impression of this poyson, by good institution and sound counsell. There was never seen any notable or far-renowned Orator to come out of Macedon or Persia. What I have spoken of it, has been upon the subject of an Italian, whom I have lately entertained into my service, who during the life of the whilom cardinall Caraffa served him in the place of steward of his house. Enquiring of his charge and particular quality, he told me a long, formall and eloquent discourse of the science or skill of epicurisme and gluttonie, with such an Oratorie-gravitie and Magistrale countenance as if he had discoursed of some high mysterious point of divinitie, wherein he has very methodically-decifred and distinguished sundrie differences of appetites: First of that which a man has fasting, then of that men have after the first, the second, and third service. The severall means how sometimes to please it simply, and other times to sharpen and provoke the same; the policy and rare invention of his sawces: First, in general terms then particularizing the qualities and severall operations of the ingredients, and their effects: The difference of salades according to their distinct seasons; which must be served in warme, and which cold: The manner how to dress, how to adorn and embellish them, to make them more pleasing to the sight. After that, he entered into a large and far-fetcht narration touching the true order and due method of service, full of goodly and important considerations. --Nec minimo sane discrimine refert, Quo gestu lepores, et quo gallina secetur. Sat. v. 127. What grace we use, it makes small diff’rence, when We carve a Hare, or else breake up a Hen. And all that filled up and stuffed with rich magnificent words, well couched phrases, oratorie figures, and patheticall metaphors; indeed such as learned men use and employ in speaking of the government of an empire, which made me remember my man. Hoc salsum est, hoc adustum est, hoc lautum est parum, Illud recte, iterum sic memento, sedulo Moneo quæ possum pro mea sapientia. Postremo tanquam in speculum, in patinas, Demea, Inspicere jubeo, et moneo quid facto usus sit. --Ter. Adel. act. iii. sc. iv.62 This dish is salt, this burnt, this not so fine, That is well done, do so again; Thus I As my best wisdom serves, all things assigne. Lastly, sir, I command, they neatly prie, On dishes, as a glasse, And show what needfull was. Yet did those strict Græcians commend the order and disposition which Paulus Æmilius observed in the banquet he made them at his return from Macedon: But here I speak not of the effects, but of the words. I know not whether they work that in others which they do in me. But when I hear our Architects mouth-out those big and ratling words of Pilasters, Architraves, Cornixes, Frontispices, Corinthian and Dorike works, and such like fustian-termes of theirs, I cannot let my wandering imagination from a sodaine apprehension of Apollidonius his pallace, and I find by, effect that they are the seely and decayed peeces of my Kitchen-doore. Doe but hear one pronounce Metonymia, Metaphore, Allegory, Etimologie and other such trash-names of grammar, would you not think they meant some form of a rare and strange language: They are titles and words that concerne your chamber-maids tittle-tattle. It is a fopperie and cheating tricke, cousin- germane unto this, to call the offices of our estate by the proud titles of the ancient Romans, though they have no resemblance at all of charge, and less of authority and power. And this likewise, which in mine opinion will one day remaine as a reproch unto our age, unworthily and undeservedly to bestow on whom we list the most glorious surnames and loftiest titles, wherewith antiquitie in many long-continued ages honoured but one or two persons. Plato has by such an universall consent borne- away the surname of Divine, that no man did ever attempt to envie him for it. And the Italians, which vaunt (and indeed with some reason) to have generally more lively and far-reaching wits, and their discourse more solid and sinnowy, than other nations of their times, have lately therewith embellished Peter Aretine; in whom, except it be an high-raised, proudly-puft, mind-moving, and heart-danting manner of speech, yet in good sooth more than ordinary wittie and ingenious; but so new-fangled, so extravagant, so fantastic, so deep-labored; and to conclude, besides the eloquence, which be it as it may be, I cannot perceive any thing in it beyond or exceeding that of many other writers of his age, much less that it in any sort approacheth that ancient divinitie. And the surname Great, we attribute and fasten the same on princes that have nothing in them exceeding popular greatness. Return to CHAPTER LII. OF THE PARCIMONIE OF OUR FOREFATHERS Send comments and corrections to the Publisher. CHAPTER LII. OF THE PARCIMONIE OF OUR FOREFATHERS TTILIUS REGULUS, General of the Romans Armie in Affrike, in the middest of his glory and victory against the Carthaginians, wrote unto the common-wealth, that a hyne or plough-boy, whom he had left alone to over-see and husband his land (which in all was but seven acres of ground) was run away from his charge, and had stolne from him all his implements and tools belonging to his husbandrie, craving leave to be discharged, and that he might come home to looke to his business, for fear his wife and children should thereby be endomaged: the Senate took order for him, and appointed another man to looke to his land and business, and made that good unto him which the other had stolne from him, and appointed his wife and children to be maintained at the common-wealths charge. Cato the elder, returning Consul from Spain, sold his horse of service to save the monie he should have spent for his transport by sea into Italie: And being chief governor in Sardinia, went all his visitations afoot, having no other traine but one officer of the commonwelth, who carried his gowne and a vessell to do sacrifice in, and for the most part carried his male himself. He boasted that he never woare gowne that cost him more than ten crowns, nor sent more than one shilling sterling to the market for one whole days provision, and had no country house rough-cast or painted over. Scipio Aemelianus, after he had triumphed twice, and twice been Consull, went on a solemn legation, accompanied and attended on only with seven servants. It is reported that Homer had never any more than one servant, Plato three, and Zeno, chief of the Stoics sect, none at all. Tiberius Gracchus, being then one of the principal men amongst the Romanes, and sent in commission about weightie matters of the common- wealth, was allotted but sixpence halfe-penie a day for his charges. Return to CHAPTER LII. OF THE PARCIMONIE OF OUR FOREFATHERS CHAPTER LIII OF A SAYING OF CÆSAR F we shall sometimes ammuse ourselves and consider our estate, and the time we spend in controling others, and to know the things that are without us; would we but emploie the same in sounding ourselves throughly, we should easily perceive how all this our contexture is built of weake and decaying peaces. Is it not an especiall testimony of imperfection that we cannot settle our contentment on any one thing, and that even of our own desire and imagination it is beyond our power to chuse what we stand in need of? Whereof, the disputation that has ever been amongst Philosophers beareth sufficient witnes, to find out the chief felicitie or summum bonum of man, and which yet does and shall eternally last without resolution or agreement. -- dum abest quod avemus, id exuperare videtur Cætera; post aliud, cum contigit illud, avemus, Et sitis, æqua tenet. --Lucr. iii. 25. While that is absent which we wish, the rest That seems to pass, when ought else is addrest, That we desire, with equall thirst opprest, Whatsoever it be that falleth unto our knowledge and jovissance, we find it does not satisfie us, and we still follow and gape after future, uncertaine, and unknown things, because the present and known please us not, and do not satisfie us. Not (as I think) because they have not sufficiently wherewith to satiate and please us, but the reason is that we apprehend and seize on them with an unruly, disordered, and diseased taste and hold- fast. Nam cum vidit hic ad usum flagitat usus, Onmia jam ferme mortalibus esse parata, Divitiis homines et honore et laude potentes Affluere, atque bona natorum excellere fama, Nec minus esse donmi cuiquam tamen anxia corda, Atque animum infestis cogi servire querelis: Intellexit ibi vitium vas facere ipsum, Omniaaque illius vitio corrumpier intus Quæ collata foris et commoda quæque venirent. Lucr. ix. For when the wiseman saw, that all almost, That use requires, for men prepared was, That men enriches, honors, praises boast, In good report of children others pass, Yet none at home did bear less pensive heart, But that the mind was forst to serve complaint He knew, that fault the vessell did empart, That all was marr’d within by vessels taint, Whatever good was wrought by any art. Our appetite is irresolute and uncertaine; it can neither hold nor enjoy any thing handsomly and after a good fashion. Man supposing it is the vice and fault of things he possesseth, feedeth and filleth himself with other things, which he neither knows nor has understanding of, whereto he applyeth both his desires and hopes, and taketh them as an honor and reverence to himself; as says Cæsar, Communi fit vitio naturæ, ut invisis, latitantibus atque incognitis rebus magis confidamus vehementiusque exterreamur: It happens by the common fault of nature that both we are more confident and more terrified by things unseen, things hidden and unknown. Return to CHAPTER LIV. OF VAINE SUBTILTIES, OR SUBTILL DEVICES CHAPTER LIV. OF VAINE SUBTILTIES, OR SUBTILL DEVICES HERE are certain frivolous and vain inventions, or as some call them subtilties of wit, by means of which some men do often endeavour to get credit and reputation, as diverse Poets that frame whole volumes with verses beginning with one letter. We see Egges, Whigs, Hatchets, Crosses, Globes, Columnes, and figures anciently fashioned by the Græcians, with the measure and proportion of their verses spreading, lengthening and shortening them in such sort as they justly represent represent such and such a figure. Such was the science and profession of him who long time busied himself to number how many severall waies the letters of the Alphabet might be ranged, and found out that incredible number mentioned by Plutarke. I allow of his opinion who, having one brought before him that was taught with such industrie, and so curiously to cast a graine of millet with his hand, that without ever missing he would every time make it go through a needles-eye, and being entreated to bestow some thing upon him (as a reward for so rare a skill), very pleasantly and worthily commanded that this cunning workman should have two or three peckes of millet delivered him, to the end his rare art and wittie labor might not remaine without dailie exercise. It is a wonderful testimony of our judgements imbecility that it should commend and allow of things, either for their rarenesse or noveltie, or for their difficultie, though neither goodnesse or profit be joined unto them. We come but now from my house, where we have a while recreated ourselves with devising who could find out most things that held by both extreme ends. As for example, Sir is in our tongue a title only given to the most eminent person of the state, which is the King, and yet is commonly given to some of the vulgar sort, as unto Merchants and Pedlars, and nothing concerneth those of the middle sort, and that are betweene both. Women of chiefest calling and quality are called Dames, the meane sort Damoisels, and those of the basest rank are also entitled Dames. The clothes of estate, which we see set over tables and chaires, are only allowed in Princes houses, yet we see them used in tavernes. Democritus was wont to say, That Gods and beasts had quicker senses and sharper wits than men who are of the middle rank. The Romanes used to weare one self-same garment on mourning and on festivall days. It is most certain that both an extreme fear and an exceeding heat of courage do equally trouble and distemper the belly. The nick-name of Tremblant, wherewith Zanchio the twelfth King of Navarre was surnamed, teacheth that boldness as well as fear engender a startling and shaking of the limbs. Those which armed either him or any other of the like nature, whose skin would quiver, assaid to re-assure him by diminishing the danger wherein he was like to fall: you have no perfect knowledge of me (said he), for if my flesh knew how far my courage will ere-long carry it, it would presently fall into a flat swoune. That chilnesse, or as I may terme it, faintnesse, which we feel after the exercises of Venus, the same does also proceed from an over vehement appetite and disordered heat. Excessive heat and extreme cold do both boile and rost. Aristotle says, That leaden vessels do as well melt and consume away by an excessive cold and rigor of winter as by a vehement heat. Both desire and satietie fill the sense with sorrow both above and under voluptuousness. Folly and wisdom meet in one point of feeling and resolution above the suffering of humane accidents. The wiser sort does gourmondise and command evil, and others know it not: The latter man would say) short of accidents, the other beyond, who after they have well weighed and considered their qualities, and duly measured and rightly judged what they are, overleap them by the power of a vigorous courage. They disdaine and tread them under foot, as having, a strong and solid mind, against which, if fortunes [darts] chance to light, they must of necessitie be blunted and abated meeting with so resisting a body, as they cannot pierce or make any impression therein. The ordinary and meane condition of men abideth betweene these two extremities, which are those that perceive and have a feeling of mischiefs but cannot endure them. Both infancie and decreptitude meet with weaknesse of the braine. Covetise and profusion in a like desire to acquire and hoard up. It may with likelihood be spoken that there is a kind of Abecedarie ignorance preceding science: another doctorall following science: an ignorance which science does beget, even as it spoileth the first. Of simple, less-curious, and least- instructed spirits are made good Christians; who simply believe through reverence and obedience, and are kept in awe of the laws. In the meane vigor of spirits, and slender capacitie is engendered the error of opinions. They follow the apparance of the first sense, and have some title to interpret it foolishnesse and sottishnesse, that we are confirmed in ancient waies respecting us that are nothing therein instructed by study. The best, most- settled, and clearest-seeing spirits make another sort of well-beleevers, who by long and religious investigation, penetrate a more profound and find out a more abstruse light in scriptures, and discover the mysterious and divine secrets of our ecclesiastical policy. And therefore see we some of them that have reached unto this last rank, by the second, with wonderful fruit and confirmation, as unto the furthest bounds of Christian intelligence, and enjoy their victory with comfort, thanksgiving, reformation of manners, and great modesty. In which rank my purpose is not to place these others who to purge themselves from the suspicion of their forepassed errors, and the better to assure us of them, become extreme, indiscreet, and unjust in the conduct of our cause, and tax and taint the same with infinite reproaches of violence. The simple peasants are honest men, so are philosophers (or as our time nameth them, strong and clear natures), enriched with a large instruction of profitable sciences. The mongrell sort of husbandmen, who have disdained the first form of ignorance of letters, and could never reach unto the other (as they that sit betweene two stooles, of which besides so many others I am one) are dangerous, peevish, foolish, and importunate, and they which trouble the world most. Therefore do I (as much as lieth in me) withdraw my self into the first and natural seat, whence I never assaied to depart. Popular and meerely natural Poesie has certain graces and ill-bred liveliness, whereby it concurreth and compareth itself unto the principal beautie of perfect and artificiall Poesie as may plainly be seen in the Villannelles, homely gigs, and countrie songs of Gasconie, which are brought us from Nations that have no knowledge at all, either of any learning or so much as of writing. Meane and indifferent Poesie, and that consisteth betweene both, is scorned and contemned and passed without honor or esteemed. But forasmuch as since the passage has been opened unto the spirit, I have found (as it commonly happens) that we had apprehended that which is neither so nor so for a difficult exercise and of a rare subject; and that since our invention has been set on fire it discovereth an infinite number of like examples. I will only adde this one: That if these Essayes were worthy to be judged of, it might in mine opinion happen that they would not greatly please the common and vulgar spirits, and as little the singular and excellent. The first will understand but little of them, the latter over much; they might perhaps live and rub out in the middle region. Return to CHAPTER LV. OF SMELS AND ODORS CHAPTER LV. OF SMELS AND ODORS T is reported of some, namely of Alexander, that their sweat, through some rare and extraordinary complexion, yielded a sweet smelling savour, whereof Plutarke and others seek to find out the cause. But the common sort of bodies are cleane contrary, and the best quality they have is to be clear of any smell at all. The sweetness of the purest breaths has nothing more perfect in them than to be without savour, that may offend us, as are those of healthy sound children. And therefore says Plautus: Mulier tum bene olet, ubi nihil olet. Plau. Mostel act. 1. sc. 3. Then smels a woman purely well, When she of nothing else does smell. The most exquisit and sweetest savour of a woman it is to smell of nothing; and sweet, well-smelling, strange savours may rightly be held suspicious in such as use them; and a man may lawfully think who useth them does it to cover some natural defect: whence proceed these ancient Poeticall sayings, To smell sweet, is to stinke, Rides nos, Coracine, nil olentes, Malo quam bene olere, nil oleres. --Mart. vi. Epig. lv. 4. You laugh at us that we of nothing savour, Rather smell so, than sweeter (by your favor). And else where: Posthume, non bene olet, qui bene semper olet. -- ii. Epig. xii. 4. Good sir, he smells not ever sweet, Who smells still sweeter than is meet. Yet love I greatly to be entertained with sweet smells, and hate exceedingly all manner of sowre and ill savours, which I shall sooner smell than any other. Namque sagacius unus odoror, Polypus, an gravis hirsutis cubet hircus in alis, Quam canis acer ubi lateat sus. -- Hor. Epod. xii. 4. Sooner smell I, whether a cancred nose, Or rank gote-smell in hairie arm-pits lie, Than sharpest hounds, where rowting bores repose. The simplest and meerely natural smells are most pleasing unto me; which care ought chiefly to concerne women. In the very heart of Barbarie, the Scithian women, after they have washed themselves, did sprinkle, dawbe, and powder all their bodies and faces over with a certain odoriferous drug that groweth in their countrie: which dust and dawbing being taken away, when they come near men, or their husband, they remaine very cleane, and with a very sweet savouring perfume. What odour soever it be, it is strange to see what hold it will take on me, and how apt my skin is to receive it. He that complaineth against nature, that she has not created man with a fit instrument, to carrie sweet smells fast-tied to his nose, is much to blame: for they carrie themselves. As for me in particular, my mustachoes, which are very thick, serve me for that purpose. Let me but approach my gloves or my hand-kercher to them, their smell will sticke upon them a whole day. They manifest the place I come from. The close-smacking, sweetness-moving, love-alluring, and greedie-smirking kisses of youth, were heretofore wont to sticke on them many hours after; yet am I little subject to those popular diseases that are taken by conversation and bred by the contagion of the air: And I have escaped those of my time of which there has been many and severall kinds, both in the Townes about me, and in our Armie: We read of Socrates that during the time of many plagues and relapses of the pestilence, which so often infested the City of Athens, he never forsooke or went out of the Town: yet was he the only man that was never infected, or that felt any sicknesse. Physitians might (in mine opinion) draw more use and good from odours than they do. For myself have often perceived that according unto their strength and quality they change and alter, and move my spirits, and work strange effects in me: which makes me approve the common saying, that the invention of incense and perfumes in Churches, so ancient and so far-dispersed throughout all nations and religions, had an especiall regard to rejoice, to comfort, to quicken, to rowze, and to purifie our senses, that so we might be the apter and readier unto contemplation. And the better to judge of it, I would I had my part of the skill which some Cookes have, who can so curiously season and temper strange odors with the savor and relish of their meats. As it was especially observed in the service of the King of Tunes, who in our days landed at Naples, to meet and enter-parly with the Enperour Charles the fifth. His viandes were so exquisitely farced, and so sumptuously seasoned with sweet odoriperous drugs and aromaticall spices, that it was found upon his book of accompt the dressing of one peacocke and two fesants amounted to one hundred duckets; which was their ordinary manner of cooking his meats. And when they were carved up, not only the dining chambers, but all the roomes of his palace and the streets round about it, were replenished with an exceeding odoriferous and aromaticall vapour, which continued a long time after. The principal care I take, wherever I am lodged, is to avoid and be far from all manner of filthy, foggy, ill-savouring and unwholesome aires. The goodly Cities of strangely-seated Venice, and huge-built Paris, by reason of the muddy, sharp, and offending savors which they yield; the one. by her fennie and marish situation, the other by her durtie uncleannesse and continuall mire, do greatly alter and diminish the favor which I bear them. Return to CHAPTER LVI OF PRAIERS AND ORISONS PROPOSE certain formelesse and irresolute fantasies, as do those schollers who in schooles publish doubtfull and sophisticall questions to be disputed and canvased: not to establish the truth, but to find it out, which I submit to their judgements, to whom the ordering and directing not only of my actions and compositions, but, also of my thoughts, belongeth. The condemnation, as well as the approbation of them, will be equally acceptable and profitable unto me, deeming it absurd and impious if anything be either ignorantly or unadvisedly set down in this rapsody, contrary unto the sacred resolutions and repugnant to the holy prescriptions of the Catholike, Apostolike, and Roman Church, wherein I was borne, and out of which I purpose not to die. And therefore alwaies referring myself unto their censures that have all power over me, do I meddle so rashly to write of all manner of purposes and discourses as I do here. I wot not whether I be deceived, but, sithence by an especiall and singular favor of Gods divine bounty, a certain form of prayer has by the very mouth of God, word by word, been prescribed and directed unto us, I have ever thought the use of it should be more ordinary with us than it is. And might I be believed, both rising and going to bed, sitting down and rising from boord, and going about any particular action or business, I would have all good Christians to say the Paternoster, and if no other praier, at least not to omit that. The Church may extend, amplifie, and diversifie praiers according to the need of our instruction: For I know it is alwaies the same substance, and the same thing. But that one should ever have this privilege, that all manner of people should at all times and upon every occasion have it in their mouth: For it is most certain that only it containeth whatsoever we want, and is most fit and effectuall in all events. It is the only praier I use in every place, at all times, and upon every accident; and instead of changing, I use often repetition of it: whence it commeth to pass that I remember none so well as that one. I was even now considering whence this general error commeth, that in all our desseignes and enterprises, of what nature soever, we immediately have recourse unto God, and in every necessitie we call upon his holy name: And at what time soever we stand in need of any help and that our weaknesse wanteth assistance, we only invoke him, without considering whether the occasion be just or unjust; and what estate or action we be in, or go about, be it never so vicious or unlawfull we call upon his name and power. Indeed, he is our only protector, and of power to affoord us all manner of helpe and comfort; but although he vouchsafe to honor us with this joy-bringing fatherly adoption, yet is he as just as he is good, and as good and just as he is mightie: But oftner useth his justice than his might, and favoureth us according to the reason of the same, and not according to our requests. Plato in his laws maketh three sorts of injurious beliefs in the Gods: First, that there is none at all; Secondly that they meddle not with our affairs; Thirdly, that they never refuse any thing unto our vows, offerings, and sacrifices. The first error, according to his opinion, did never continue immutable in man, even from his first infancie unto this latter age. The two succeeding may admit some constancy. His justice and power are inseparable. It is but in vain to implore his power in a bad cause. Man must have an unpolluted soul when he praieth (at least in that moment he addresseth himself to pray) and absolutely free from all vicious passions; otherwise we ourselves present him the rods to scourge us withall. In liew of redressing our fault, we redouble the same by presenting him with an affection fraught with irreverence, sinne, and hatred, to whom only we should sue for grace and forgivenesse. See here, why I do not willingly commend those Pharisaicall humors, whom I so often behold, and more than ordinary, to pray unto God, except their actions immediately preceding or succeeding their praiers witness some show of reformation or hope of amendment. -- Si nocturnus adulter Tempora sanctonico velas adoperta cucullo. Juven. Sat. viii. 144. If in a cape-cloake-hood befrenchifide Thou a night-whore-munger your head do hide And the state of a man that commixeth devotion unto an execrable life, seems in some sort to be more condemnable than that of one that is conformable unto himself, and every way dissolute. Therefore does our Church continually refuse the favor of her enterance and societie unto customs and manners wilfully obstinate on some egregious villanie. We only pray by custom and use, and for fashion sake, or, to say better we but read and pronounce our prayers: To conclude, it is nothing but a show of formalitie, and a formall show. And it greeveth me to see many men, who at grace before and after meat will with great show of devotion crosse themselves three or foure times (and it vexeth me so much the more, when I call to mind that it is a signe I greatly reverence, and have in continual use, indeed, if I be but gaping) and there whilst, shall you see them bestow all other hours of the day in all manner of hatred, malice, covetousnesse, and injustice. Many hours spend they about vice, but one to God, and that as it were by way of recompense and composition. It is wonderous to see so far different and diverse actions, continue with so even a tenor, that no interruptions or alteration at all can be perceived, either about their confines, or passage from one unto another. What prodigious conscience can be at any harts-ease, fostring, and feeding with so mutual, quiet, and agreeing society in one self same mansion, both crime and judge? A man whose Paillardize and luxurie does uncessantly sway and rule the head, and who judgeth the same abhominable and most hateful in the sight of God; what says he unto his all-seeing Majesty, when he openeth his lips, either of mouth or hart, to speak to him of it? He reclaimeth himself, but falleth sodainly again. If the object of his divine justice, and his presence should strike, (as he says) and chastise his soul, how short-soever the penitence were, fear itself would so often cast his thought on it, that he would presently perceive himself master of those vices which are habituated, inbred, setled, and enfleshed in him. But what of those which ground a whole life upon the fruit and benefit of that sinne they know to be mortal? How many trades, professions, occupations, and vocations have we daily and continually used, frequented, and allowed amongst us, whose essence is vicious and most pernicious? And he that would needs confesse himself unto me, and of his own accord told me, that for fear of losing his credit and to keep the honor of his offices; he had for a whole age made show and profession, and acted the effects of a religion, which in his own self- accusing conscience he judged damnable, and cleane contrary unto that he had in his hart: How could he admit and foster so contradictorie and impious a discourse in his hart? With what language entertaine they divine justice concerning this subject? Their repentance, consisting in visible amends and manageable reparation; they lose both towards God and us, the means to alleage the same. Are they so malapart and foolhardy as to crave pardon without satisfaction, and sans repentance? I think it goeth with the first as with the last: But obstinacy is not herein so easy to be vanquished. This so suddaine contrarietie, and violent volubilitie of opinion, which they faine unto us, seems to me a miracle. They present us with the state of an indigestible agonie. How fantastic seemed their imagination unto me, who these latter years had taken up a fashion, to checke and reprove all men that professed the Catholike Religion, in whom shined any extraordinarie brightnesse of spirit, saying, that it was but feigned: and to do him honor, held that whatsoever he said in apparance he could not inwardly chuse but have his beliefe reformed according to their byase. It is a peevish infirmitie for a man to think himself so firmely grounded as to persuade himself that the contrary may not be believed: And more peevish also, to be persuaded by such a spirit, that preferreth I wot not what disparitie of fortune, before the hopes and threats of eternall life. They may believe me: If any thing could have attempted my youth, the ambition of the hazard and difficultie which followed this late-modern enterprize, should have had good part therein. It is not without great reason, in my poor judgement, that the Church forbiddeth the confused, rash and indiscreet use of the sacred and divine songs which the holy spirit has indicted unto David. God ought not to be commixed in our actions, but with awful reverence, and an attention full of honor and respect. The word or voice is too divine, having no other use but to exercise our lungs and to please our ears. It is from the conscience and not from the tongue that it must proceed. It is not consonant unto reason that a prentise or shop-keeping boy, amiddest his idle, vain, and frivolous conceits, should be suffered to entertaine himself, and play therewith. Nor is it seemely or tolerable to see the sacred book of our beliefes Mysteries tossed up and down and plaid withall, in a shop, or a hall, or a kitchen. They have heretofore been accompted mysteries, but through the abuse of times they are now held as sports and recreations. So serious and venerable a study should not, by way of pastime and tumultuarie, be handled. It ought to be a fixed, a purposed, and setted action, to which this preface of our office sursum corda should ever be adjoind; and the very exterior parts of the body should with such a countenance be referred unto it, that to all mens eyes it may witness a particular attention and duteous respect. It is not a study fitting all men, but only such as have vowed themselves unto it, and whom God has, of his infinit mercy, called thereto. The wicked, the ungodly, and the ignorant, are thereby empaired. It is no historie to be fabulously reported, but a historie to be dutifully reverenced, awfully feared, and religiously adored. Are they not pleasantly conceited, who, because they have reduced the same into the vulgar tongues, and that all men may understand it, persuade themselves, that the people shall the better conceive and digest the same? Consisteth it but in the words, that they understand not all they find written? Shall I say more? By approaching thus little unto it, they go back from it. Meere ignorance, and wholly relying on others, was verily more profitable and wiser than is this verball and vain knowledge, the nurse of presumption and source of temeritie. Moreover, I am of opinion that the uncontrouled liberty, that all men have to wrest, dissipate, and wyredraw a word so religious and important, to so many severall idiomes, has much more danger than profit following it. The Jewes, the Mahometans, and well- nigh all other nations, are wedded unto and reverence the language wherein their mysteries and religion had originally been conceived; and any change or translation has not without apparance of reason been directly forbidden. Know we whether there be Judges enow in Basque and in Brittanie to establish this translation made in their tongue? The universall Church has no more difficult and solemn judgement to make. Both in speaking and preaching the interpretation is wandring, free, and mutable, and of one parcell; so it is not likewise. One of the Greek Historians does justly accuse his age, forasmuch as the secrets of Christian religion were dispersed in all public places, and even amongst the basest artificers; and that every man might, at his pleasure, dispute of it, and at random speak his mind of the same. And it should be a great shame for us, who by the unspeakable grace of God injoy the pure and sacred mysteries of piety, to suffer the same to be profaned in the mouthes of ignorant and popular people, seeing the very Gentiles interdicted Socrates and Plato, and the wisest, to meddle, enquire or speak of things communicated unto the Priestes of Delphos. Saying, moreover, That the factions of Princes, touching the subject of Divinities, are armed, not with zeale, but with anger, that zeale dependeth of divine reason and justice, holding an orderly and moderate course, but that it changeth into hatred and envie, and in stead of corne and grape, it produces nettles and darnell, if it be directed by humane passion. And justly says this other, who counselling the Emperor Theodosius, affirmed that disputations did not so much appease and lull asleepe the schismes of the Church, as stir up and cause heresies. And therefore it hehooved to avoid all contentions, controversies, and logicall arguing, and wholly and sincerely refer himself unto the prescriptions and orders of faith, established by our forefathers. And Andronicus the Emperor, finding by chance in his pallace certain principal men very earnestly disputing against Lapodius about one of our points of great importance, taunted and rated them very bitterly, and threatened if they gave not over, he would cause them to be cast into the river. Children and women do now adaies governe and sway the oldest and most experienced men concerning Ecclesasticall Lawes: whereas the first that Plato made forbiddeth them to enquire after the reason of civill Lawes, and which ought to stand in place of divine ordinances. Allowing aged men to communicate the same amongst themselves, and with the magistrate, adding moreover, alwaies provided it be not in the presence of young men and before profane persons. A notable Bishop has left written, that in the other end of the world there is an island called of our predecessours Dioscorida, very commodious and fertile of all sorts of fruits and trees, and of a pure and wholesome air; whose people are Christians, and have Churches and Altars, adorned with nothing else but crosses, without other images; great observers of fasting and holy days; exact payers of their priests tithes, and so chaste that none of them may lawfully all his life long know any more than one wife. And in all other matters so well pleased with their fortune, that being seated in the middest of the sea, they have and know no use of ships: and so simple, that of their religion, which they so diligently and awfully observe, they know not, nor understand so much as one only word. A thing incredible to him that knew not how the Pagans, who are so devout and zealous idolaters, know nothing of their Gods but only their bare names and statues. The ancient beginning of Menalippe, a tragedie of Euripides, importeth thus: Jupiter, car de toy rien sinon, Ie ne cognois seulement que le nom. --Eurip. O Jupiter, for unto me Only the name is known of you. I have also in my head certain writings complained of, for so much as they are meerely humane and philosophicall, without medling with the diviity. He that should say to the contrary, which a man might do with reason, that heavenly doctrine, as a Queene and governesse does better keep her rank apart; that she ought to be chief ruler and principal head everie where, and not suffragant and subsidiarie: And that perhaps examples in grammar, rethorike, and logike, might more fitly and sortably be taken from elsewhere, than from so sacred and holy a subject, as also the arguments of theatres, plots of plaies, and grounds of public spectacles: That mysteriously divine reasons are more venerably and reverently considered alone, and in their native stile, than joined and compared to human discourse. That this fault is oftener seen, which is, that Divines write too humanely, than this other, that humanists write not Theologically enough. Philosophy, says S. Chrysostome, is long since banished from sacred schools as an unprofitable servant, and deemed unworthy to bebold, but in passing by the entrie or the vestrie of the sacred treasures of heavenly doctrine. That the formes of humane speech are more base, and ought by no means to make any use of the dignitie, majestie and preheminence of divine speech. As for my part I give it leave to say, Verbis indisciplinatis, With undisciplined words Fortune, destinie, chance, accident, fate, good lucke, ill lucke, the Gods, and other phrases, as best it pleaseth. I repose humane fantasies and my own, simply as humane conceits, and severally considered; not as setled, concluded, and directed by celestiall ordinance, incapable of any doubt or alteration. A matter of opinion, and not of faith. What I discourse according to my self, not what I believe according unto God, with a laicall fashion, and not a clericall manner; yet ever most religious; As children propose their essays, instructable, not instructing. And might not a man also say without apparance, that the institution which wills no man shall dare to write of religion but sparingly and reservedly, except such as make express profession of it, would not want some show of profit and justice; and happily to me to be silent. It has been told me, that even those which are not of our consent do flatly inhibite amongst themselves the use of the sacred name of God in all their vulgar and familiar discourses. They would have no man use it as an interjection or exclamation, not to be alleged as a witness or comparison, wherein I find they have reason. And however it be that we call God to our commerce and societie, it should be zealously, seriously, and religiously. There is, as far as I remember, such a like discourse in Xenophon, wherein be declareth: That we should more rarely pray unto God: forasmuch as it is not easy we should so often settle our minds in so regular, so reformed, and so devout a seat, where indeed it ought to be, to pray aright and effectually: otherwise our praiers are not only vain and unprofitable, but vicious. Forgive us (say we) our offences, as we forgive them that trespasse against us. What else inferre we by that petition, but that we offer him our soul void of all revenge and free from all rancour? We nevertheless invoke God and call on his aid, even in the complot of our grievousest faults, and desire his assistance in all manner of injustice and iniquitie. Quæ nisi seductis nequeas committere -- Divis. Pers. Sat. ii. 4. Which you to Saints not drawne aside, Would think unfit to be applide. The covetous man sueth and praieth unto him for the vain increase and superfluous preservation of his wrong-gotten treasure. The ambitious he importuneth God for the conduct of his fortune, and that he may have the victory of all his desseignes. The theefe, the pirate, the murtherer, indeed the traitor, all call upon him, all implore his aid, and all solicite him, to give them courage in their attempts, constancy in their resolutions to remove all lets and difficulties, that in any sort may withstand their wicked executions and impious actions, or give him thanks if they have had good success; the one if he have met with a good bootie, the other if he return home rich, the third if no man has seen him kill his enemy, and the last though he have caused an execrable mischief. The souldier, if he but go to besiege a cottage, to scale a castle, to rob a church, to pettard a gate, to force a religious house, or any villanous act, before he attempt it praieth to God for his assistance, though his intents and hopes be full-fraught with crueltie, murther, covetise, luxurie, sacrilege, and all iniquitie. Hoc ipsum quo in Iovis aurem impellere tentas, Dic agedum, Staio: proh Jupiter, O bone, clamet, Jupiter! at sese non clamet Jupiter ipse. --21. Go-to then, say the same to some bad fellow, Which you prepar’st for Gods ears: let him bellow, God, good God; so God, On himself would not plod. Margaret, Queene of Navarre, maketh mention of a young prince (whom, although she name not expressly, yet his greatness has made him sufficiently known) who going about an amorous assignation, and to be with an advocates wife of Paris, his way lying alongst a church, he did never pass by so holy a place, whether it were in going or coming from his lecherie and cukolding-labor, but would make his praiers unto God, to be his help and furtherance. I would faine have an impartiall man tell me to what purpose this prince invoked and called on God for his divine favor, having his mind only bent to sinne, and his thoughts set on luxurie: Yet does she alleage him for a speciall testimony of singular devotion. But it is not only by this example a man might verifie that women are not very fit to manage or treat matters of religion and divinitie. A true and hartie praier, and an unfained religious reconciliation from us unto God, cannot likely fall into a wicked and impure soul, especially when Sathane swaieth the same. He that calleth upon God for his assistance, whilst he is engulphed and wallowing in filthy sinne, does as the cut-purse that should call for justice unto his ayd, or those that produce God in witness of a lie. -- tacito mala vota susurro Concipimus. --Lucan. v. 94 With silent whispering we, For ill things suppliants be. There are few men that would dare to publish the secret requests they make to God. Haud cuivis promptum est, murmur que humilesque susurros Tollere de Templis et aperto vivere voto. From Church low-whispering murmurs to expell, ’Tis not for all, or with known vows live well. And that’s the reason why the Pythagorians would have them public that all night hear them, that no man should abusively call on God, and require any undecent or unjust thing of him as that man: -- Clare cum dixit, Apollo, Labra movet metuens audiri: pulchra Laverna Da mihi fallere, da justum sanctumque videri. Noctem peccatis, et fraudibus objice nubem. Hor. i. Epist. xvi. 59. When he alowd has said, Apollo hear, Loth to be heard, Goddesse of theeves, said he, Grant me to cousen, and yet just appeare, My faults in night, my frauds in clouds let be. The Gods did grievously punish the unpious vows of Oedipus by granting them unto him. His praier was, that his children might betweene themselves decide in arms the succession of his estate; he was so miserable as to be taken at his word. A man should not request that all things follow our will, but that it may follow wisdom. Verily, it seems that we make no other use of our praiers, than of a companie of gibrish phrases: and as those who employ holy and sacred words about witchcraft and magicall effects; and that we imagine their effect dependeth of the contexture, or sound, or succession of words, or from our countenance. For, our soul, being full-fraught with concupiscence and all manner of ungodly thoughts, nothing touched with repentence, nor moved with new reconciliation towards God, we headlong present unto him those heedlesse words which memory affoordeth our tongue, by which we hope to obtaine an expiation and remission of our offences. There is nothing so easy, so sweet, so comfortable and favourable, as the law of God; she (of his infinit mercy) calleth us unto him, how faultie and detestable soever we be; she gently stretcheth forth her arms unto us and mildly receiveth us into her lap, how guiltie, polluted, and sinfull soever we are, and may be in aftertimes. But in recompence of so houndlesse and unspeakable a favor, she must be thankfully accepted, and cheerfully regarded: and so gracious a pardon must be received with a gratitude of the soul, and at least, in that instant, that we addresse ourselves unto her presence, to have our soul grieved for her faults, penitent of her sinnes, hating those passions and affections that have caused or provoked us to transgresse his laws, to offend his Majestie, and to breake his commandments. Plato says that neither the Gods nor holiest men will ever accept the offering of a wicked man. Immunis aram si tetigit manus, Non sumptuosa blandior hostia Mollivit aversos Penates, Farre pio et saliente mica. --iii. Od. xxiii. 17. If guiltlesse hand the Altar tuch, No offring, cost it neer so much, Shall better please our God offended, Than corne with crackling-corne-salt blended. Return to CHAPTER LVII. OF AGE CHAPTER LVII. OF AGE CANNOT receive that manner, whereby we establish the continuance of our life. I see that some of the wiser sort do greatly shorten the same in respect of the common opinion. What said Cato Iunior, to those who sought to hinder him from killing himself? ’Doe I now live the age, wherein I may justly be reproved to leave my life too soone?’ Yet was he but eight and fortie years old. He thought that age very ripe, indeed, and well advanced, considering how few men come unto it. And such as entertaine themselves with I wot not what kind of course, which they call natural, promiseth some few years beyond, might do it, had they a privilege that could exempt them from so great a number of accidents, unto which each one of us stands subject by a natural subjection and which may interrupt the said course they propose unto themselves. What fondnesse is it for a man to think he shall die, for and through a failing and defect of strength, which extreme age draweth with it, and to propose that terme unto our life, seeing it is the rarest kind of all deaths and least in use? We only call it natural, as if it were against nature to see a man breake his necke with a fall; to be drowned by shipwracke; to be surprised with a pestilence or pleurisie, and as if our ordinary condition did not present these inconveniences unto us all. Let us not flatter ourselves with these fool-goodly words: a man may perhaps rather call that natural which is general, common, and universall. To die of age is a rare, singular, and extraordinarie death, and so much less natural than others: It is the last and extremest kind of dying: The further it is from us, so much the less is it to be hoped for: Indeed it is the limit beyond which we shall not pass, and which the law of nature has prescribed unto us as that which should not be outgone by any: but it is a rare privilege peculiar unto herself, to make us continue unto it. It is an exemption, which through some particular favor she bestoweth on some one man, in the space of two or three ages, discharging him from the crosses, troubles, and difficulties she has enterposed betweene both in this long cariere and pilgrimage. Therefore my opinion is, to consider that the age unto which we are come is an age whereto few arive: since men come not unto it by any ordinary course, it is a signe we are very forward. And since we have past the accustomed bounds, which is the true measure of our life, we must not hope that we shall go much further. Having escaped so many occasions of death, wherein we see the world to fall, we must acknowledge that such an extraordinarie fortune as that is, which maintaineth us, and is beyond the common use, is not likely to continue long. It is a fault of the very laws to have this false imagination: They allow not a man to be capable and of discretion to manage and dispose of his own goods, until he be five and twentie years old, yet shall he hardly preserve the state of his life so long. Augustus abridged five years of the ancient Roman laws, and declared that for any man that should take upon him the charge of judgement, it sufficed to be thirty years old. Servius Tullius dispensed with the Knights who were seven and fortie years of age from all voluntarie services of war. Augustus brought them to fortie and five. To send men to their place of sojourning before they be five and fiftie or three score years of age, me seems carrieth no great apparance with it. My advice would be, that our vacation and employment should be extended as I far as might be for the public commoditie; but I blame some, and condemne most, that we begin not soone enough to employ ourselves. The same Augustus had been universall and supreme judge of the world when he was but nineteene years old, and would have another to be thirty before he shall be made a competent Judge of a cottage or farme. As for my part, I think our minds are as full grown and perfectly joynted at twentie years as they should be, and promise as much as they can. A mind which at that age has not given some evident token or earnest of her sufficiencie, shall hardly give it afterward, put her to what trial you list. Natural qualities and vertues, if they have any vigorous or beauteous thing in them, will produce and show the same within that time, or ever. They say in Dauphine, Si l’espine nou picque quand nai, A peine que picque jamai. --French prov. A thorne, unless at first it pricke, Will hardly ever pearce to the quick. Of all humane honorable and glorious actions that ever came unto my knowledge, of what nature soever they be, I am persuaded I should have a harder taske to number those which, both in ancient times and in ours, have been produced and atchieved before the age of thirty years, than such as were performed after: indeed, often in the life of the same men. May not I boldly speak it of those of Hanniball and Scipio his great adversarie? They lived the better part of their life with the glory which they had gotten in their youth: And though afterward they were great men in respect of all others, yet were they but meane in regard of themselves. As for my particular, I am verily persuaded, that since that age both my spirit and my body have more decreased than encreased, more recoyled than advanced. It may be, that knowledge and experience shall encrease in them, together with life, that bestow their time well: but vivacitie, promptitude, constancy, and other parts much more our own, more important and more essentiall, they droope, they languish, and they faint. --ubi jam validis quassatum est virihus ævi Corpus, et obtusia ceciderunt viribus artus, Claudicat ingenium, delirat lingtiaque meusque.-- Lucr. iii. 457. When once the body by shrewd strength of years Is shak’t, and limbs drawne down from strength that weares, Wit halts, both tongue and mind Doe daily doat, we find. It is the body which sometimes yieldeth first unto age, and other times the mind; and I have seen many that have had their braines weakened before their stomacke or legs. And forasmuch as it is a disease, little or nothing sensible unto him that endureth it, and maketh no great show, it is so much the more dangerous. Here I exclaime against our Lawes, not because they leave us so long and late in working and employment, but that they set us a work no sooner, and it is so late before we be employed. Me thinkes that considering the weaknesse of our life, and seeing the infinit number of ordinary rockes and natural dangers it is subject unto, we should not so soone as we come into the world, alot so great a share thereof unto unprofitable wantonnesse in youth, il-breeding idlenesse, and slow-learning prentissage. END OF THE FIRST BOOKE Return to : Book II Florio’s Epistle. Note on the e-text: this text was provided by Professor Emeritus Ben R. Schneider, Lawrence University, Wisconsin. It is in the public domain. "Florio’s Translation of was first published in 1603. In ’The World’s Classics’ the first volume was published in 1904, and reprinted in 1910 and 1924." Additional material was supplied by R.S. Bear from the Everyman’s Library edition of 1910. Content unique to this presentation is copyright © 1999 The University of Oregon. THE SECOND BOOKE xx Florio’s Preface I. II. Of the inconstancie of our Actions Of Drunkennesse III. A Custome of the Ile of Cea IV. To-morrow is a New Day V. VI. VII. VIII. IX. Of Conscience Of Exercise or Practice Of the Recompenses or Rewards of Honour Of the Affections of Fathers to their Children: To the Lady of Estissac Of the Parthians Armes X. Of Bookes XI. Of Crueltie XII. An Apologie of Raymond Sebond XIII. Of Judging of others’ Death XIV. How that our Spirit hindereth itself XV. XVI. That our Desires are encreased by Difficultie Of Glory XVII. Of Presumption XVIII. Of giving the Lie XIX. XX. XXI. XXII. Of the Liberty of Conscience We taste nothing purely Against Idlenesse, or doing Nothing Of Running Posts, or Couriers XXIII. Of Bad Meanes emploied to a Good End XXIV. Of the Roman Greatnesse XXV. XXVI. XXVII. XXVIII. XXIX. How a Man should not Counterfeit to be Sicke Of Thumbs Cowardize the Mother of Cruelty All Things have their Season Of Vertue XXX. Of a Monstrous Child XXXI. Of Anger and Choler XXXII. A Defence of Seneca and Plutarke XXXIII. The Historie of Spurina XXXIV. Observations concerning the means to war after the manner of Julius Cæsar XXXV. XXXVI. XXXVII. Of Three Good Women Of the Worthiest and Most Excellent Men Of the Resemblance betweene Children and Fathers The Epistle To the Right Ho- norable and all-praise-worthie Ladies, Elizabeth Countesse of Rutland, And Lady Penelope Riche. Give me leave (peerless, and in all good gifts unparagonized Ladies) though I make my fault double to aske leave for a fault, which I might leave; yet thus to pair you without dislike, who like (I imagine) each other above all other, and to whom a like pair long may I seek, but be long ere I find. Such pairing is no empairing, no disparaging, nor yet comparing, unless in that good comparison of excellence. This is the number appropritae, at least reciprocall, of true love: as the two Tables comprised in two commandements of due love. And such is Gods proceeding, when Mercie and Truth meete together, Righteousnesse and Peace have kissed each other. Even as body and soul, braine and heart, memory and understanding; so are yoru two honorablest Lordes made, as you should be, even: two Doves, two Loves: double kind, double kindness. Both like the two Cherubins on the toppes and sides of the propiriatorie, respective mutually; like the two starres of the North, which our Mariners call the Guardes, directive of our course; like your own eyes, their own only matches; yet as much pleasing others with their sight, as your themselves (Paul. Gio. Imp.).And hereby, as your Cognisance (noblest Countesse of R UTLAND ) bears the body or chief part of an Imprese made for a worthy Dutchesse of Florence: Cum pudore læta fæcunditas: to reape as much joy by Iuno, as labor by Lucina, and honor by them both:which being so well graffed shall be (as the Italian spake in Dutch) Wan Got will (Ibid.): wherof yet a fair patterne you have here (be it auspicious) associated to you: I meane you (truely-richest Lady R ICH ) in riches of Fortune not deficient, but of body incomparably richer, of mind most rich: who yet, like Cornelia, were you out-vied,or by riche shewes envited to show your richest jewelles, would stay till your sweet Images (your dear-sweet children) came from schoole. And if you may so joy in those your yong Schollers, of such hope, of such spirit, so nobly borne, so worthily proceeding: how then may I boast of both your Ladiships, of such proofe, of such merite, my not only proficient, but perfect Schollers? Yea, as of love, so of language, peerless Ladies? who likethat great and good Cornelia, not only with bountie entertaine, but of benignitie invite learned and vertuous stangers, not so much to employ, as rather to releeve, indeed oblige, indeed ammuse, indeed drive them to admiration or veneration of your singular sufficiencies, surmounting magananimitie, and inestimable value, even from forraine Princes that come to see this happy-happiest Iland to receive gratulations, and merit commendations. Who also, like another of the same name, to your great and good Pompeys brought an invaluable dowrie, not only of Nobilitie, Learning, Language, Musicke, but withall, an incurious gravitie, and all-accomplish’t virtue. So as into this familie of these Corneliaes, as many ciences into one stocke, the Orator may well conclude the wisdom and virtue of many engraffed and collected. And though this Montaigne-Lord, not so knightly as uncivilly, in this your part acknowledgeth no dozens of good women at any time in one place (Mont. l. ii. c. 35) (in France it may be, or of his knowledge) but only a bare trinity, and those Italians, and that about their husbandes death to die with or afore them; forgetting he had instanced but a little before, out of Propertius and others (Ibid. lib. ii. c. 29), in many Indians; who, did they ordinarily as much for their husbands, would out of doubt affectionately do more for them yet living: yet as even those Corneliaes, and in that very poynt, both in Plutarke (Plut. vit. Grac. & Pomp.), both (as God would have it) surviving their husbands, the one prevented by her husbands wise kindenesse, the other with all sympathy attending his extreme fortune; both while they lived, preserved the Dead in Honorable memory: as also in his kind three other in Plutarke went as far; namely Empona, Camma and Damocrita: or this mans Theoxena, Sextila, Praxea, Pelagia, Sophronia, Fulvia, and many more (Mont. lib. ii. c. 27 & c. 3); since in the Roman proscriptions, as one of their Historians does testifie, many wives were found exceeding faithful, but few men-servants, fewer friends, and fewest sons. So neyther is one virtue fit for all, not all fit for one virtue: nor is that one so excellent, but by more it might be mended: not deem I his three so good, but many have bin, and some be much better: Yea, as a Christian, I must deny them good, who cast backe Gods good gift before he call for it; leave their fair corps-de-guarde ere their General discharge them; hope to be deified for being their own murtherers, who should be damned if they were so to others; more savage to their own soules, than any beast would be to their own flesh; not of force, but for fear, or for fame at the best: though even in that (as Plinie thinkes of two of the same persons) the same fact diversly extolled or abased, as the person that does it, is diverse, high or base. Nor would a wiser Pætus than his, indeed a better man than his Seneca permitte as good an Arria as his herdaughter to die as she did; though as willingly she would, but charged her to live after for him and his. Better yet (but not much) like I that seely one, which this Author approveth by his wise Duke of Bretaigne in choice of Isabell of Scotland (Ibid. lib. i. c. 24). But since himself likes it better to be well used in life then at death, and better usage proceeds from better vertues (for better vertues make you love as well as be beloved: and loyall love from you makes up his mouth, with sweeter sawce than death) without that extreme trial, I can tell him we have, and by good hap, my dedications name unto him, halfe a dozen, better, because more vertuous, and therefore more loved, and as loving. Or, will he admitte but three, if not paires, yet their Peeres, I must say of three as Ariosto said of one, Credi ogn’ una d’esser quella Fenice (Orl. fu. can. 27): Or as my fellow Nolano in his heroycall furies wrote (noble Countesse) to your most heroicke father, and in a Sonnet to you Ladies of England, You are not women, but in their likenesse Nymphs, Goddeses, and of Celestiall substance (Gior. Bru. hero. fur. arg.) Et siete in terra quel’ ch’ in ciel’ le stelle, And above all, that only divine Diana, Qual’ e tra voi quel che tra gl’ astri il sole. And cleane contraie to this Censor, the Nobler and the Richer you are, the more vertuous and worthie we esteeme you by reason and experience. But while I follow my guide, I have forsaken my self, and while I would winne him friends he workes (I fear) foes both to him and me of my best friends; while he findes but three good, and that, when they did so, as I pray God keep mine both from cause and effect, intention and execution: wherein I follow, if not his Paris preacher, at least his douceur Francoise (Mon. lib. ii. c. 3). But is he then so capriccious, opiniative, so paradoxical? I grount, sometimes extravagant, often od-chocheted, and ever self-conceited to write of himself out of himself. Why wrote he then? for him and his. But why do I translate him? For your Ladiships and yours. What? to displease? Nay, neither does such extraordinarinesse ever displease, not is he ever in his humor: for, in the judgement (beside others, indeed even of the precise Genevians he has so bin judged, and amongest them allowed to be printed) of your your most learned wise and honorable kinsman, sir Edward Wotten (who encouraged and set me first upon this Worke) there are in it so pleasing passages, so judicious discourses, so delightsome varieties, so perswasive conclusions, such learning of all sortes, and above all, so elegant a French stile, as (I think) for E SSAYES , I may say of him, as he, in this Book, did of Homer (Ibid. lib. ii. c. 36); Here shines in him the greatest wit without example, without exception, deserving for his composition to be entituled, Sole Maister of Essayes: whose maister-poynt is this, none was before him, whom he might imitate; none has come after him who could well imitate; or at most equall him: and a wonder it is, he therein should be perfectest, whereof he is the first Authour. And for French eloquence, I may adde that of him, which the same Historian does of Tullie, It broke out in full streames, full beames, under this Prince thereof, Lord of Montaigne; so as before him you may be delighted with few, but wonder at none, that has not either seen him, or bin seen of him. His worth then being so eminent, his wit so excelent, his inventions so rare, his elocutions so ravishing; nor are my pains mis-spent in translating, nor will your Honours pleasure and leisure be mis-placed or mis-employed in perusing him. I know, nor this, nor any I have seen, or can conceive, in this or other language, can in aught be compared to that perfect-unperfect Arcadia, which all our world yet weepes with you, that your all praise-exceeding father (his praise-succeeding Countesse) your worthy friend (friend worthiest Lady) lived not to mend or end-it: since this end we see of it, though at first above all, now is not answerable to the precendents: and though it were much easier to mend out of an originall and well corrected copie, than to make-up so much out of a most corrupt, yet see we more marring that was well, then mending what was amisse. And if not any principal invention, much less may any translation at second hand come near it: yet as that Worthie did divinely even in French translating some part of that excellent du Plessis, and (as I have seen) the first septmaine of the Arch-Poet du Bartas (which good Ladies, be so good to all, as all this age may see, and after-ages honor) so though we much more meanely do in meaner workes (for still I say none can anneare him) yet where our Protonotaries do holde the chaire, let us poore Secondaries not be thrust out of doores. Of this your Honourable goodnesse dooth assure me, and for this, and much more, I must and ever shall avow my self To your Honours obliged and devoted in all service, I OHN F LORIO . To The Right Ho- norable, Elizabeth Countesse of Rutland. Thrise-happy Countesse, your thrise-honor’d Sire, An other Nature, Maro-like, sur-named, As he in Arte divenest Poems framed, In love did to a love divine aspire, In both wrought wonders of Prometheus fire; So got in kind an of-spring no less famed, His fame’s enheritrix to be proclaimed; That got, he got himself one of Heav’ns quire As then his, and your Mothers match you are In parents, match, and shall (we hope) in breeding, England to steade with ancient M ANORS race: So be you (when we you in praise compare) As kind, in kindness them as kind succeeding, Great good-wils gift not great, t’accept with grace. Il Candido. ¶ To the Honorably-vertuous Lady, La: Penelope Riche. Madame, to write of you, and do you right, What meane we, or what means to ayde meane might? Since HE, who admirably did endite, Entiteling you Perfections heir, loves light, Loves life, Lifes gemme, Vertues court, Heav’ns delight, Natures chief work, Fair’st book, his Muses spright, Heav’n on Earth, peerelesse Phoenix, Phoebe bright, Yet said, he was to seek, of you to write. Unless your self be of your self devising; Or that an other such you can inspire. Inspire you can; but ô none such can be: Your self as bright as your mid-day, as rising. Yet, though we but repeat who would flie higher, And though be but translate, take both in gree. Il Candido. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER I: OF THE INCONSTANCIE OF OUR ACTIONS Send comments and corrections to the CHAPTER I: OF THE INCONSTANCIE OF OUR ACTIONS HOSE WHICH exercise themselves in controuling humane actions, find no such let in any one part as to peece them together and bring them to one same lustre: For they commonly contradict one another so strangely, as it seems impossible they should be parcels of one Warehouse. Young Marias is sometimes found to be the son of Mars, and other times the child of Venus. Pope Boniface the Eight is reported to have entered into his charge as a Fox, to have carried himself therein as a Lion, and to have died like a Dog. And who would think it was Nero, that lively image of cruelty, who being required to sign (as the custom was) the sentence of a criminall offender that had been condemned to die, that ever he should answer, ’Oh would to God I could never have written?’ So neare was his heart grieved to doom a man to death. The world is so full of such examples that every man may store himself; and I wonder to see men of understanding trouble themselves with sorting these parcels: Sithence (me seems) irresolution is the most apparent and common vice of our nature: as witnesseth that famous verse of Publius the Commedian: Malum consilium est, quod mutari non potest. -- Pub. Mim. The counsel is but bad, Whose change may not be had. There is some apparence to judge a man by the most common conditions of his life but seeing the natural instability of our customs and opinions, I have often thought that even good Authors do ill and take a wrong course, wilfully to opinionate themselves about framing a constant and solid contexture of us. They chuse an universal air, and following that image, range and interpret all a mans actions; which if they cannot wrest sufficiently, they remit them unto dissimulation. Augustus has escaped their hands; for there is so apparent, so sudden and continual a variety of actions found in him through the course of his life, that even the boldest Judges and strictest censurers have been faine to give him over, and leave him undecided. There is nothing I so hardly believe to be in man as constancy, and nothing so easy to be found in him, as inconstancy. He that should distinctly and part by part judge of him, should often jumpe to speak truth. View all antiquity over, and you shall find it a hard matter to chuse out of a dozen of men that have directed their life unto one certain, setled, and assured course; which is the surest drift of wisdom. For to comprehend all in one word, says an ancient writer, and to embrace all the rules of our life into one, it is at all times to will, and not to will one same thing. I would not vouchsafe (says he) to adde anything: alwayes provided the will be just: for, if it be unjust, it is impossible it should ever continue one. Verily, I have heretofore learned that vice is nothing but a disorder and want of measure, and by consequence it is impossible to fasten constancy unto it. It is a saying of Demosthenes (as some report) that consultation and deliberation is the beginning of all virtue, and constancy the end and perfection. If by reason or discourse we should take a certain way, we should then take the fairest: but no man has thought on it. Quod petiit, spernit, repetit quod nuper omisit Astuat, et vitæ disconvenit ordine toto. -- Hor. i. Epist i. 98. He scornes that which he sought, seek’s that he scorn’d of late, He flowes, ebbes, disagrees in his lifes whole estate. Our ordinary manner is to follow the inclination of our appetite this way and that way, in the left and on the right hand; upward and downeward, according as the winde of occasions does transport us: we never think on what we would have, but at the instant we would have it: and change as that beast that takes the colour of the place wherein it is laid. What we even now purposed we alter by and by, and presently return to out former biase; all is but changing, motion and inconstancy: Ducimur ut nervis alienis mobile lignum. -- Hor. ii. Sat. vii. 82. So are we drawne, as wood is shoved, By others sinnewes each way moved. We go not, but we are carried: as things that flote, now gliding gently, now hulling violently, according as the water is, either stormy or calme. -------- nonne videmus Quid sibi quisque relit nescire et quaerere semper, Commuttare locum quasi onus deponere possit? -- Lucr. iii. 1100. See we not, every man in his thoughts height Knowes not what he would have, yet seekes he streight To change place, as he could lay down his weight? Every day new toyes, each hour new fantasies, and our humors move and fleet with the fleetings and movings of time. Tales sunt hominum mentes, quali Pater ipse Jupiter auctifero lustravit lumine terras. -- Cic. Fragm. Such are mens mindes, as that great God of might Surveies the earth with encrease bearing light. We float and waver betweene diverse opinions: we will nothing freely, nothing absolutely, nothing constantly. Had any man prescribed certain Lawes or established assured policies in his own head, in his life should we daily see to shine an equality of customs, an assured order and an infallible relation from one thing to another (Empedocles noted this deformitie to he amongst the Agrigentines, that they gave themselves so over unto delights as if they should die to morrow next, and built as if they should never die) the discourse thereof were easy to be made. As is seen in young Cato: He that touched but one step of it has touched all. It is an harmony of well according tunes and which cannnot contradict itself. With us it is clean contrary, so many actions, so many particular judgements are there required. The surest way (in mine opinion) were to refer them unto the next circumstances, without entering into further search, and without concluding any other consequence of them. During the late tumultuous broiles of our mangled estate, it was told me that a young woman not far from me had headlong cast herself out of a high window, with intent to kill herself, only to avoid the ravishment of a rascally-base souldier that lay in her house, who offered to force her: and perceiving that with the fall she had not killed herself, to make an end of her enterprize she would have cut her own throat with a knife, but that she was hindered by some that came into her: Nevertheless having sore wounded herself, she voluntarily confessed that the souldier had yet but urged her with importunate requests, suing solicitations, and golden bribes, but she feared he would in the end have obtained his purpose by compulsion: by whose earnest speeches, resolute countenance, and gored blood (a true testimony of her chaste virtue) she might appeare to be the lively patterne of another Lucrece, yet know I certainly that, both before that time and afterward, she had been enjoyed of others upon easier composition. And as the common saying is; Faire and soft, as squemish-honest as she seems, although you misse of your intent, conclude not rashly an inviolable chastitie to be in your Mistresse; for a groom or a horse- keeper may find an hour to thrive in; and a dog has a day. Antigonus having taken upon him to favor a souldier of his by reason of his virtue and valor, to have great care of him, and see whether they could recover him of a lingering and inward disease which had long tormented him, who being perfectly cured, he afterward perceiving him to be nothing so earnest and diligent in his affairs, demanded of him how he was so changed from himself, and become so cowardish: ’Your self, good sir,’ answered he, ’have made me so by ridding me of those infirmities which so did grieve me that I made no accompt of my life.’ A souldier of Lucullus, having by his enemies been robbed of all he had, to revenge himself undertook a notable and desperat atempt upon them; and having recovered his losses, Lucullus conceived a very good opinion of him, and with the greatest shewes of assured trust and loving kindness be could bethinke himself, made especiall accompt of him, and in any dangerous enterprize seemed to trust and employ him only: Verbis quæ timido quoque possent addere mentem./1 -- Hor. ii. Epist ii. 34. With words, which to a coward might Adde courage, had he any spright. "Imploy,’ said he unto him, "some wretch-stripped and robbed Souldier, ------- (quantumvis rusticus ibit, Ibit eo quo vis, qui zonam perdidit, inquit.) -- 39. (None is, says he, so clownish, but will-on, Where you will have him, if his purse be gone) and absolutely refused to obey him. When we read that Mahomet, having outrageously rated Chasan, chief leader of his Janizers, because he saw his troup well-nigh defeated by the Hungarians, and he to behave himself but faintly in the fight, Chasan without making other reply alone as he was, and without more adoe, with his weapon in his hand rushed furiously in the thickest throng of his enemies that he first met withall, of whom he was instantly slain: This, may perhaps be deemed rather a rash conceit than a justification, and a new spight than a natural prowes. He whom you saw yesterday so boldly venturous, wonder not if you see him a dastardly meacocke to morrow next: for either anger or necessitie, company or wine, a sudden fury or the clang of a trumpet, might rowse-up his heart and stir up his courage. It is no heart nor courage so framed by discourse or deliberation: These circumstances have setled the same in him: Therefore it is no marvell if by other contrary circumstance he become a craven and change coppy. This supple variation and easy yielding contradiction which is scene in us, has made some to imagine that we had two soules, and others two faculties; whereof every one as best she pleaseth, accompanieth and does agitate us; the one towards good, the other towards evil. Forasmuch as such a rough diversitie cannot well sort and agree in one simple subject. The blast of accidents does not only remove me according to his inclination; for, besides, I remove and trouble my self by the instability of my posture, and whosoever looketh narrowly about himself, shall hardly see himself twice in the same state. Sometimes I give my soul one visage and sometimes another, according unto the posture or side I lay her in. If I speak diversly of self it is because I looke diversly upon my self. All contrarieties are found in her, according to some turn or removing, and in some fashion or other; shamefast, bashfull, insolent, chaste, luxurious, peevish, pratling, silent, foolish, doting, labourious, nice, delicate, ingenious, slow, dull, froward, humorous, debonaire, wise, ignorant, false in words, true-speaking, both liberall, covetous, and prodigall. All these I perceive in some measure or other to be in me, according as I stir or turn my self; And whosoever shall heedfully survey and consider himself, shall find this volubility and discordance to be in himself, indeed in his very judgement. I have nothing to say entirely, simply, and with soliditie of my self, without confusion, disorder, blending, mingling, and in one word, Distinguo is the most universall part of my logike. Although I ever purpose to speak good of good, and rather to enterpret those things that will bear it, unto a good sense; yet is it that the strangenesse of our condition admitteth that we are often urged to do well by vice itself, if well doing were not judged by the intention only. Therefore may not a courageous act conclude a man to be valiant. He that is so, when just occasion serveth, shall ever be so, and upon all occasions. If it were an habitude of virtue, and not a sudden humor, it would make a man equally resolute at all assayes, in all accidents: Such alone, as in company; such in a single combat, as in a set battle: For, whatsoever some say, valor is all likewise, and not one in the street or town, and another in the campe or field. As courageously should a man bear a sicknesse in his hed as a hurt in the field, and fear death no more at home in his house than abroad in an assault. We should not then see one same man enter the breach, or charge his enemy with an assured and undouted fiercenesse, and afterward having escaped that, to vexe, to grive and torment himself like unto a seely woman, or faint-hearted milkesop for the loss of a sute, or death of a child. If one chance to be carelesly base-minded in his infancie, and constantly-resolute in povertie; if he be timorously-fearfull at sight of a barbers razor, and afterward stowtly-undismayed against his enemies swords: the action is commendable, but not the man. Divers Greeks (says Cicero) cannot endure to looke their enemy in the face, yet are they most constant in their sicknesses; whereas the Cimbrians and Celtiberians are meere contrary. Nihil enim potest esse aequabile, quod non a certa ratione proficiscatur: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ii. f.) ’For nothing can bear itself even which proceedeth not from resolved reason.’ There is no valor more extreme in his kind than that of Alexander; yet it is but in species, nor every where sufficiently full and universall. As incomparable as it is, it has his blemishes, which is the reason that in the idlest of suspitions he apprehendeth at the conspiracies of his followers against his life, we see him so earnestly to vex and trouble himself: In search and pursuit of whereof he demeaneth himself with so vehement and indiscreet an injustice, and with such a demiss fear that even his natural reason is thereby subverted. Also the superstition wherewith he is so thoroughly tainted beareth some show of pusilanimitie. And the unlimited excess of the repentance he showed for the murther of Clitus is also a witness of the inequalitie of his courage. Our matters are but parcels hudled up and peeces patched tog ether, and we endeavor to acquire honor by false means and untrue tokens. Vertue will not be followed but by herself: and if at any time we borrow her maske, upon some other occasion she will as soone pull it from our face. It is a lively hew and strong die, if the soul be once dyed with the same perfectly, and which will never fade or be gone, except it carry the skin away with it. Therefore to judge a man, we must a long time follow, and very curiously marke his steps; whether constancy do wholy subsist and continue upon her own foundation in him. Cui vivendi via considerata atque provisa est (Cic. Parad. v.). ’Who has forecast and considered the way of life;’ whether the variety of occurrences make him change his pace (I meane his way, for his pace may either be hastened or slowed) let him run on: such a one (as sayeth the imprease of our good Talbot) goeth before the wind. It is no marvell (says an old writer) that hazard has such power over us, since we live by hazard. It is impossible for him to dispose of his particular actions, that bath not in grose directed his life unto one certain end. It is impossible for him to range all peeces in order, that has not a plot or form of the totall frame in his head. What avayleth the provision of all sorts of colours unto one that knowes not what be is to draw? No man makes any certain designe of his life, and we deliberate of it but by parcels. A skilfull archer ought first to know the marke he aimeth at, and then apply his hand, his bow, his string, his arrow and his motion accordingly. Our counsels go astray because they are not rightly addressed, and have no fixed end. No winde makes for him that has no intended port to saile unto. As for me, I allow not greatly of that judgement which some made of Sophocles, and to have concluded him sufficient in the managing of domesticall matters, against the accusation of his own son, only by the sight of one of his tragedies. Nor do I commend the conjecture of the Parians sent to reforme the Milesians, as sufficient to the consequence they drew thence. In visiting and surveying the ile, they marked the landes that were best husbanded, and observed the country houses that were, best governed. And having registered the names of their owners, and afterward made an assembly of the Townesmen of the City, they named and instituted those owners as new Governours and Magistrates, judging and concluding, that being good husbands and careful of their housebold affairs, they must consequently be so of public matters. We are all framed of flaps and patches and of so shapelesse and diverse a contexture that every peece and every moment playeth his part. And there is as much difference found betweene us and ourselves as there is betweene ourselves and other. Magnam rem puta, unun hominem agere: ’Esteeme it a great matter to play but one man.’ Since ambition may teach men both valor temperance, liberality, indeed justice: sith covetousnesse may settle in the mind of a Shop-prentise-boy, brought up in ease and idlenesse, a dreadlesse assurance to leave his home-bred ease, and forgoe his place of education, and in a small barke to yield himself unto the mercy of blustring waves, mercilesse winds and wrathfull Neptune; and that it also teacheth discretion and wisdom; And that Venus herself ministreth resolution and hardinesse unto tender youth as yet subject to the discipline of the rod, and teacheth the ruthless Souldier the soft and tenderly effeminate heart of women in their mothers laps: Hac duce custodes furtim transgressa jacentes, Adjuvenem tenebris sola puella venit. -- Tib. ii. El. i. 75. The wench by stealeth her lodg’d guards having stript, By this guide, sole, i’th darke, to’ th yonker skipt. It is no part of a well-grounded judgement simply to judge ourselves by our exterior actions: A man must thorowly sound himself, and dive into his heart, and there see by what wards or springs the motions stir. But forasmuch as it is a hazardous and high enterprise, I would not have so many to meddle with it as do. Return to : Book II CHAPTER II: OF DRUNKENESSE Note on the e-text: this text was provided by Ben R. Schneider, Lawrence CHAPTER II: OF DRUNKENESSE HE WORLD is nothing but variety and dissemblance. Vices are all likewise, inasmuch as they are all vices: And so do perhaps the Stoics meane it. But though they are equally vices, they are not equall vices; and that he who has started a hundred steps beyond the limits Quos ultra citraque nequit consistere rectum, --Hor. i. Sat. i. 107. On this side, or beyond the which No man can hold a right true pitch, is not of worse condition than he that is ten steps short of it, is no whit credible: and that sacrilege is not worse than the stealing of a colewort out of a garden. Nec vincet ratio, tantumdem ut peccet, idemque, Qui teneros caules alieni fregerit horti, Et qui nocturnus divum sacra legerit. -- Sat. iii. 115 No reason can evict, as great or same sinne taints Him that breakes in anothers Garden tender plants, And him that steales by night things consecrate to Saints. There is as much diversity in that as in any other thing. The confusion of order and measure of crimes is dangerous: Murtherers, Traitors and Tyrants, have too much gain by it: it is no reason their conscience should be eased, in that some other is either idle or lascivious, or less assiduous unto devotion. Every man poiseth upon his fellowes sinne, and elevates his own. Even teachers do often range it ill in my conceit. As Socrates said, that the chiefest office of wisdom was to distinguish goods and evils. We others, to whom the best is ever in vice, should say the like of knowledge, to distinguish vices. Without which, and that very exact, both vertuous and wicked men remaine confounded and unknowen. Now drunkennesse amongst others, appeareth to me a grose and brutish vice. The mind has more part else where; and some vices there are, which (if it may lawfully be spoken) have a kind of I wot not what generosity in them. Some there are,, that have learning, diligence, valor, prudence, wit, cunning, dexterity, and subtlety joined with them; whereas this is merely corporall, and terrestriall. And the grosest and rudest nation, that liveth amongst us at this day, is only that which keepeth it in credit. Other vices but alter and distract the understanding, whereas this utterly subverteth the same, and astonishes the body. ---- cum vini vis penetravit, Consequitur gravitas membrorum, præpediuntur Crura vacillanti, tardescit lingua, madet mens, Nant oculi, clamor, sigultis, jurgia gliscunt. -- Lucr. iii. 479. When once the force of wine has inly pierst, Limbes-heaviness is next, legs faine would go, But reeling cannot, tongue drawles, mindes disperst, Eyes swimme, ciries, hickups, brables grow. The worst estate of man, is where he loses the knowledge and government of himself. And amongst other things, it is, said, that as must wine boyling and working in a vessell, workes and sends upward what ever it containeth in the bottome, so does wine cause those that drinke excessively of it, work up, and breake out their most concelaed secrets. ----tu sapientium Curas, et arcanum jocoso Consilium retegis Lyæo. -- Hor. iii. Od. xxi. 14. Thou (wine-cup) doest by wine reveale The cares, which wise men would conceal, And close drifts, at a merry meale. Josephus reporteth that by making an Ambassador to tipple-square, whom his enemies had sent unto him, he wrested all his secrets out of him. Nevertheless Augustus having trusted Lucius Piso, that conquered Thrace, with the secretest affairs he had in hand, had never cause to be discontented with him; nor Tiberius with Cossus, to whom he imparted all his seriousest counsels, although we know them both to have so given themselves to drinking of wine that they were often faine to be carried from the Senat, and both were reputed notable drunkards. -------- Hesterno inflatum venas de more Lyæo -- Virg. Buc. Ec. vi. 15. Veines pufft up, as it used alway By wine which was dranke yesterday. And as faithfully as the complot and purpose to kill Cæsar committed unto Cimber, who would daily be drunke with quaffing of wine, as unto Cassius, that drunke nothing but water, whereupon he answered very pleasantly, ’What! shall I bear a tyrant that am not able to bear wine?’ We see our carowsing tospot German soldiers, when they are most plunged in their cups and as drunke as rats, to have perfect remembrance of their quarter, of the watchword, and of their files. -------- Nec facilis victoria de madidis, et Bloesis, atque mero titubantibus. -- Juven. Sat. xv. 47. Nor is the conquest easy of men sow’st, Lisping and reeling with wine they carow’st. I would never have beleeved so sound, so deepe and so excessive drunkennesse had I not read in histories that Attalus having envited to sup with him (with intent to do him some notable indignity) the same Pausanias who for the same cause killed afterward Philip, King of Macedon (a king, who by the eminent fair qualities that were in him, bore a testimony of the education he had learned in the house and company of Epaminondas), made him so dead-drunke that insensibly and without feeling he might prostitute his beauty as the body of a common hedge-harlot, to Mulettiers, Groomes and many of the abject servants of his house. And what a lady (whom I much honor and highly esteeme) told me, protesting that near Bourdeaux, towards Castres, where her house is, a widdow country-woman, reputed very chaste and honest, suspecting herself to be with child, told her neighbors that had she a husband she should verily think she was with child; but the occasion of this suspition increasing more and more, and perceiving herseIfe so big- bellied that she could no longer conceal it, she resolved to make the Parish-priest acquainted with it, whom she entreated to publish in the Church that whosover he were that were guilty of the fact, and would avow it, she would freely forgive him, and if he were so pleased, take him to her husband. A certain swaine or hyne-boy of hers, emboldened by this proclamation, declared how that having one holliday found her welltippled with wine, and so sound asleep by the chimnie side lying so fit and ready for him, without awaking her he had the full use of her body. Whom she accepted for her husband, and both live together at this day. It is assured that antiquitie has not greatly described this vice. The compositions of diverse Philosophers speak but sparingly of it. Yea, and some of the Stoics deem it not amisse for man sometimes to take his liquor roundly, and drinke drunke, thereby to recreate his spirits. Hoc quoque virtutum quondam certamine magnum Socratem pa lmam promeruisse ferunt. -- Cor. Gal. El. i. They say, in this too, Socrates the wise, And great in vertues combats, bare the prize. Cato, that strict censurer and severe corrector of others, has been reproved for much drinking, Narratur et prisci Catonis Saepe mero coluisse virtus. -- Hor. iii. Od. xxi. 11. ’Tis said, by use of wine repeated Old Catoes virtue oft was heated. Cyrus, that so far-renowned king, amongst his other commendations, meaning to prefer himself before his brother Artaxerxes, and get the start of him, aleageth that he could drinke better and tipple more than he. And amongst the best policed and formalest nations, the custom of drinking and pledging of healths was much in use. I have heard Silvius, that excellelent phisitian of Paris, affirme that to preserve the vigor of our stomake from, empairing, it is not amisse once a month to rowze up the same by this excess of drinking, and lest it should grow dull and stupid thereby to stir it up. And it is written that the Persians, after they had well tippled, were wont to consult of their chiefest affairs. My taste, my rellish, and my complexion are sharper enemies unto this vice than my discourse, for besides that I captivatee more easily my conceits under the auctoritie of ancient opinions, indeed I find it to be a foolish, a stupid, and a base kind of vice, but less malicious and hurtful than others; all which shocke and with a sharper edge wound public societie. And if we cannot give ourselves any pleasure except (as they say) it cost us something; I find this vice to be less chargeable unto our conscience than others; besides it is not hard to be prepared, difficult to be found; a consideration not to be despised. A man well advanced in years and dignitie, amongst three principal commodities he told me to have remaining in life, counted this: and where shall a man more rightly find it than amongst the natural? But he took it ill, delicatenesse, and the choice of wines is therein to be avoided. If you prepare your voluptuousness to drinke it with pleasure and daintily neat, you tie your self unto an inconvenience to drinke it other than is alwayes to be had. A man must have a milder, a loose and freer taste. To be a true drinker a man should not have so tender and squeamish a palat. The Germans do in a manner drinke equally of all sorts of wine with like pleasure. Their end is rather to gulpe it down freely than to tast it kindly. And to say truth they have it better cheape. Their voluptuousness is more plenteous and fuller. Secondarily, to drinke after the French manner, as two droughts and moderately, is over much to restraine the favors of that God. There is more time and constancy required thereunto. Our forefathers were wont to spend whole nights in that exercise, indeed often times they joined whole long dayes unto them. And a man must proportion his ordinary more large and firme. I have in my dayes seen a principal Lord, a man of great employment and enterprises and famous for good success, who without straining himself and eating but an ordinary meales-meate, was wont to drinke little less than five pottles of wine, yet at his rising seemed to be nothing distempered, but rather, as we have found to our no small cost in managing our affairs, over-wise and considerate. The pleasure of that whereof we would make account in the course of our life ought to be employed longer space. It were necessary, as shop-boyes or labouring people, that we should refuse no occasion to drinke and continually to have this desire in our mind. It seems that we daily shorten the use of this, and that in our houses (as I have seen in mine infancie) breakfasts, nunchions, and beavers should be more frequent and often used than now adayes they are. And should we thereby in any sort proceed towards amendment? No verily. But it may be that we have much more given ourselves over unto paillardise and all manner of luxurie than our fathers were. They are two occupations that enter-hinder one another in their vigor. On the one side it has empaired and weakned our stomacke, and on the other sobrietie serveth to make us more jolly-quaint, lusty, and wanton for the exercise of love matters. It is a wonder to think on the strange tales I have heard my father report of the chastitie of his time. He might well speak of it as he that was both by art and nature proper for the use and solace of ladies. He spake little and well, few words, but to the purpose, and was ever wont to entermixe some ornament taken from vulgar bookes, and above all Spanish amongst his common speeches. And of all Spanish authors, none was more familiar unto him than Marcus Aurelius. His demeanour and carriage was ever mild, meeke, gentle, and, very modest, and above all grave and stately. There is nothing he seemed to be more careful of than of his honesty, and observe a kind of decencie of his person, and orderly decorum in his habits, were it on foot or on horsebacke. He was exceeding nice in performing his word or promise. And so strictly concscientious and obsequious in religion, that generally he seemed to incline toward superstition than the contrary. Though he were but a little man, his courage and vigor was great. He was of an upright and well proportioned stature, of a pleasing, cheerfull-Iooking countenance, of a swarthy hue, nimbly addicted, and exquisitely nimble unto all noble and gentleman-like exercises. I have seen some hollow staves of his filled with lead which he wont to use and exercise his arms withall, the better to enable himself to pitch the barre, to throw the sledge, to cast the pole, and to play at fence; and shoes with leaden soles, which he wore to ensure himself to leape, to vault, and to run. I may without blushing say, that in memory of himself, he has left certain petie miracles amongst us. I have seen him when he was past threescore years of age mocke at all our sports, and out-countenance our youthfull pastimes, with a heavy furr’d gowne about him to leap into his saddle. To make the pommada round about a table upon his thumb, and seldom to ascend any staires without skipping three or four steps at once. And concerning my discourse, he was wont to say that in a whole province there was scarce any woman of quality that had an ill name. He would often report strange familiarities, namely of his own, with very honest women, without any suspicion at all. And protested very religiously that when he was married he was yet a pure virgine; yet had he long time followed the wars beyond the mountaines, and therein served long, whereof he has left a Journall-book of his own collecting, wherein he has particularly noted whatsoever happened day by day worthy the observation so long as he served, both for the public and his particular use. And he was well strucken in years when he took a wife. For returning out of Italie in the yeare of our Lord one thousand five hundred eight and twenty, and being full three and thirty years old by the way he chose himself a wife. But come we to our drinking again. The incommodities of age wbich need some helpe and refreshing, might with some reason beget in me a desire or longing of this faculty, for it is in a man the last pleasure which the course of our years stealeth upon us. Good fellowes say that natural heat is first taken in our feet: that properly belongeth to infancie. From thence it ascendeth unto the middle region, where it is setled and contitlueth a long time, and in mine opinion there produces the only true and moving pleasures of this corporall life. Other delight and sensualities in respect of t hat do but sleepe. In the end, like unto a vapour which by little and little exhaleth and mounteth aloft, it comes unto the throat and there makes her last bode. Yet could I never conceive how any man may either encrease or prolong the pleasure of drinking beyond thirst, and in his imagination frame an artificial appetite, and against nature. My stomacke could not well reach so far: it is very much troubled to come to an end of that which it takes for his need. My constitution is to make no accompt of drinking but to succeed meat, and therefore do I ever make my last draught the greatest. And forasmmuch as in age we have the roofe of our mouthes covered with rhume, or distempered, distated and altered through some other evil constitution, wine seems better unto us and of a quicker relish, according as our pores be either more or less open and washed. At least I seldom relish the same very well, except it be the first drought I take. Anacharsis wondered to see the Greeks drinke in greater glasses at the end of their meales than in the beginning. It was (as I imagine) for the very same reason that the Germans do it, who never begin to carouse but when they have well fed. Plato forbiddeth children to drinke any wine before they be eighteene years of age, and to be drunke before they come to forty. But to such as have once attained the age of fortie he is content to pardon them, if they chance to delight themselves with it, and alloweth them somwhat to blend the influence of Dionysius in their banquets, that good God, who bestoweth cheerfulnesse upon men, and youth unto aged men, who layeth and aswageteh the passions of the mind, even as yron is made flexible by the fire: and in his profitable laws holds drinking- meetings or quaffing companies as necessary and commendable (alwaies provided there be a chief leader amongst them to containe and order them) drunkennesse being a good and certain tryall of every mans nature; and therewithall proper to give aged men the courage to make merry in dancing and music; things alowable and profitable, and such as they dare not undertake being sober and settled: That wine is capable to supply the mind with temperance and the body with health. Notwithstanding, these restrictions, partly borrowed of the Carthaginians, please him well. Let those forbeare it that are going about any expedition of war. Let every magistrate and all judges abstain from it at what time they are to execute their charge, and to consult of public affairs. Let none bestow the day in drinking, as the time that is due unto more serious negotiations, nor the nights wherein a man intendeth to get children. It is reported that Stilpo the Philosopher, finding himself surcharged with age, did purposely hasten his end by drinking of with pure wine. The like cause (though not wittingly) did also suffocate the vital forces, crazed through old age, of the Philosopher Arcesilaus. But it is an old and pleasant question whether a wise mans mind were like to yield unto the force of wine. Si munitae adhibet vim sapientiæ. -- Od. xxviii. 4. If unresisted force it bends, Gainst wisdom which itself defends. Unto what vanity does the good opinion we have of ourselves provoke us? The most temperate and perfectest mind of the world findes it too great a taske to keep herself upright, lest she fall by her own weaknesse. Of a thousand there is not one perfectly righteous and settled but one instant of her life, and question might be made whether according to her natural condition she might at any time be so. But to join constancy unto it [is] her last perfection: I meane if nothing should shocke her; which a thousand accidents may do. Lucretius, that famous Poet, may philosophie and bandie at his pleasure: See where be lieth senslesse of an amorous potion. Thinkes any man that an apoplexie cannot as soone astonish Socrates as a poore labouring man? Some of them have by the force of a sicknesse forgot their own names, and a slight hurt has overthrown the judgement of others. Let him be as wise as he can, in the end he is but a man; what is more fraile, more miserable, or more vain? Wisdome forceth not our natural conditions. Sudores itaque, et pallorem existere toto Corpore, et infringi linguam, vocemque aboriri Caligare, oculos, sonari aures, succidere art us, Denique concidere ex animi terrore videmus. -- Lucr. iii. 155. We see therefore, paleness and sweats oregrow Our bodies, tongues do falter, voice does breake, Eyes dazle, ears buzze, joints do shrinke below, Lastly we swoune by hart-fright, terrours weake. He must [s]eele his eyes against the blow that threateneth him; being. near the brimme of a precipice, he must cry out like a child: Nature having purposed to reserve these light markes other aucthoritie unto herself, inexpugnable unto our reason, and to the Stoice virtue: to teach him his mortalitie and our insipiditie. He waxeth pale for fear, be blusheth for shame, he groaneth feeling the cholike, if not with a desperate and lowd- roaring voice, yet with a low, smothered, and hoarse-sounding noise. Humani a se nihil alienum putat. -- Ter. Heaut. act. i. sc. i. 25. He thinkes, that nothing strange be can To him, that longs to any man. Giddie-headed Poets, that faine what they list, dare not so much as discharge their Heroes from tears. Sic fatur lachrymans, classigue immitit habemas. -- Virg. Æn. vi. 1. So said he weeping, and so said, Himselfe hand to the sterage laide. Let it suffice him to bridle his affections, and moderate his inclinations; for it is not in him to bear them away. Plutarke himself, who is so perfect and excellent a judge of human actions, seeing Brutus and Torquatus to kill their own children, remaineth doubtfull whether virtue could reach so far and whether such men were not rather moved by some other passion. All actions beyond the ordinary limits are subject to some sinister interpretation. Forasmuch as our taste does no more come unto that which is above it, than to that which is under it. Let us omit that other sect which maketh open profession of fierceness. But when in the very same sect which is esteemed the most demiss, we hear the bragges of Metrodorus: Occupavite, Fortuna, atqe cepi; omnesque aditus tuos interclusi, ut ad me amirare non posses: (Metr. Cic. Tusc. Quest. 5.) ’Fortune, I have prevented, caught, and overtaken you: I have mured and ramd up all your passages, whereby you mightest attaine unto me:1 When Anaxarchus, by the appointment of Nicocreon, the tyrant of Cipres, being laid along in a trough of stone, and smoten with yron sledges, ceaseth not to crie out, ’Streeke, smite and breake; it is not Anaxarchus, it is but his veil you martyr so:’ When we hear our martyrs in the middst of a flame crie aloud unto the Tyrant, ’This side is roasted enough, chop it, eat it, it is full roasted, now begin on the other:’ When in Josephus we here a child all to rent with biting snippers, and pierced with the breath of Antiochus, to d fie him to death, crie with a lowde-assured and undismaid voice, ’Tyrant, you losest time, lo I am still at mine ease; where is that smarting pain, where are those torments wherewith whilom you didst so threaten me? My constancy does more trouble you than I have feeling of your crueltie: Oh faint hearted varlet, doest you yield when I gather strength? Make me to faint or shrinke, cause me to moan or lament, force me to yield and sue for grace if you canst; encourage your satallities, hard en your executioners; lo how they droope and have no more power; arm them, strengthen them, flesh them.’ Verely we must needs confesse there is some alteration, and some fury (how holy soever) in those mindes, When we come unto these Stoic evasions: I had rather be furious than voluptuous: the saying of Antisthenes, Μανειην αλλον η ησθειην (Antist. Diogen. Laert. vi. c. 1.) ’Rather would I be mad than merry;’ when Sextius telleth us, he had rather be surprised with pain than sensuality; when Epicurus undertakes to have the goute to wantonize and faune upon him, and refuseth ease and health, with a hearty cheerefullnesse defie all evils, and scornefully despising less sharpe griefs disdaining to grapple with them, he blithely desires and calleth for sharper, more forcible and worthy of him. Spumantemque dari, pecora inter inertia, votis Optat aprum, aut fulvum descendere monte leonem: -- Virg. Æn. iv. 158. He wisht, mongst hartlesse beasts some foming Bore, Or mountaine-Lyon would come down and rore; Who would not judge them to be prankes of a courage removed from his wonted seate? Our mind cannot out of her place attaine so higb. She must quit it and raise herself aloft, and taking the bridle in her teeth, carry and transport her man so far, that afterward he wonder at himself, and rest amazed at his actions. As in exploit of war, the heat and earnestnesse of the fight does often provoke the noble minded soldiers to adventure on so dangerous passages that afterward being better advised, they are the first to wonder at it. As also Poets are often surprised and rapt with admiration at their own labours, and forget the trace by which they pass so happy a career. It is that which some terme a fury or madnesse in them. And as Plato says that a setled and reposed man does in vain knocke at Poesies gate; Aristotle likewise says that no excellent mind is freely exempted from some or other entermixture of folly. And be has reason to call any starting or extraordinarie conceit (how commendable soever) and which exceedeth our judgement and discourse, folly. Forasmuch as wisdom is an orderly and regular managing of the mind, and which; she addresseth with measure, and conducteth with proportion; and taketh her own word for it. Plato disputeth thus: that the facultie of prophesying and divination is far above us, and that when we treat it, we must be besides ourselves: our wisdom must be darkened and over shadowed by sleepe, by sicknesse, or by drowzinesse; or by some celestial fury, ravished from her own seat. Return to : Book II CHAPTER III: A CUSTOME OF THE ILE OF CEA CHAPTER III: A CUSTOME OF THE ILE OF CEA F, AS some say, to philosophate be to doubt; with much more reason to rave and fantastiquize, as I do, must necessarily be to doubt: For, to enquire and debate belongeth to a scholler, and to resolve appertaines to a cathedrall master. But know, my cathedrall, it is the authority of Gods divine will, that without any contradiction does sway us, and has her rank beyond these humane and vain contestations. Philip being with an armed band entered the countrie of Peloponnesus, some one told Damidas the Lacedemonians were like to endure much if they sought not to reobtaine his lost favor. ’Oh varlet as you are (answered he). And what can they suffer who have no fear at all of death?’ Agis being demanded, how a man might do to live free, answered; ’Despising and contemning to die.’ These and a thousand like propositions, which concurre in this purpose, do evidently inferre some thing beyond patient expecting of death itself to be suffered in this life: witness the Lacedemonian child, taken by Antigonus, and sold for a slave, who urged by his master to perform some abject service; ’Thou shall see (said he) whom you hast bought, for it were a shame for me to serve, having liberty so near at hand;’ and therewithall threw himself headlong down from the top of the house. Antipater, sharply threatning the Lacedemonians, to make them yield to a certain request of his; they answered, should you menace us worse than death, we will rather die. And to Philip, who having written unto them that he would hinder all their enterprises; ’What? (say they) wilt you, also hinder us from dying?’ That is the reason why some say that the wise man liveth as long as he ought, and not so long as he can. And that the favourablest gift nature has bequeathed us, and which removeth all means from us to complain of our condition, is, that she has left us the key of the fields. She has appointed but one entrance unto life, but many a thousand ways out of it: Well may we want ground to live upon, but never ground to die, in; as Boiocalus answered the Romanes. Why do you complain against this world? It does not containe you: If you livest in pain and sor row, your base courage is the cause of it. To die there wanteth but will. Ubique mors est. optime hoc cavit Deus, Eripere vitam memo non homini potest: At nemo mortem: mille ad hanc aditus patent. -- Sen. Theb. act. i. sc. I. Each where death is: God did this well purvey, No man but can from man life take away, But none bars death, to it lies many a way. And it is not a receipt to one malady alone; Death is a remedy against all evils: It is a most assured haven, never to be feared, and often to be sought: All comes to one period, whether man make an end of himself, or whether he endure it; whether he run before his day, or whether he expect it: whence soever it come, it is ever his own, where ever the threed be broken, it is all there, it’s the end of the web. The voluntariest death is the fairest. Life dependeth on the will of others, death on ours. In nothing should we so much accommodate ourselves to our humors as in that. Reputation does nothing concerne such an enterprise, it is folly to have any respect unto it. To live is to serve, if the liberty to dye be wanting. The common course of curing any infirmitie is ever directed at the charge of life: we have incisions made into us, we are cauterized, we have limbs cut and mangled, we are let blood, we are dieted. Goe we but one step further, we need no more physicke, we are perfectly whole. Why is not our jugular or throat-veine as much at our command as the mediane? To extreme sicknesses, extreme remedies. Servius the Grammarian being troubled with the gowt, found no better means to be rid of it than to apply poison to mortifie his legs. He cared not whether they were Podagrees or no, so they were insensible. God gives us sufficient privilege, when be placeth us in such an estate, as life is worse than death unto us. It is weaknesse to yield to evils, but folly to foster them. The Stoics say it is a convenient natural life, for a wise man, to forgoe life, although he abound in all happinesse, if he do it opportunely: And for a foole to prolong his life, albeit he be most miserable, provided he be in most part of things, which they say to be according unto nature; As I offend not the laws made against theeves when I cut mine own purse, and carry away my own goods; nor of destroyers when I burne my own wood; so am I nothing tied unto laws made against m urtherers, if I deprive my self of my own life. Hegesias was wont to say, that even as the condition of life, so should the quality of death depend on our election. And Diogenes meeting with the Philosopher Speusippus, long time afflicted with the dropsie, and therefore carried in a litter, who cried out unto him, All haile Diogenes: And to you no health at all (replied Diogenes), that endurest to live in so wretched an estate. True it is, that a while after, Speusippus, as overtired with so languishing a condition of life, compassed his own death. But this goeth not without some contradiction: For many are of opinion, that without the express commandment of him that has placed us in this world, we may by no means forsake the garrison of it, and that it is in the hands of God only, who therein bath placed us, not for ourselves alone, but for his glory, and others services when ever it shall please him to discharge us hence, and not for us to take leave: That we are not borne for ourselves, but for our Countrie: The Lawes for their own interest require an accompt at our hands for ourselves, and have a just action of murther against us. Else as forsakers of our own charge, we are punished in the other world. Proxima deinde tenent maesti loca, qui sibi lethum Insontes peperere manu, lucemque perosi Projecere animas. -- Virg. Æn. vi. 434. Next place they lamentable hold in hell, Whose hand their death caused causelesse, (but not well) And hating life did thence their soules expell. There is more constancy in using the chaine that holds us than in breaking the same; and more trial of stedfastnesse in Regulus than in Cato. It is indiscretion and impatience that hastneth our way. No accidents can force a man to turn his backe from lively virtue: She seeketh out evils and sorrowes as her nourishment. The threats of fell tyrants, tortures and torments, executioners and torturers, do animate and quicken her. Duris ut ilex tonsa bipennibus Nigræ feraci frondis in Algido Per damna, per cædes, ab ipso Ducit opes animumque fero. -- Hor. iv. Od. iv. 57. As holme-tree does with hard axe lopt On hils with many holme-trees topt, From loss, from cuttings it does feel, Courage and store rise ev’n from steele, And as the other says, Non est putas virtus, pater, Timere vitam, sed malis ingentibus Obstare, nec se vertereac vetro dare. -- Sen. Theb. act. i. sc. I. Sir, ’tis not virtue, as you understand, To fear life, but grosse mischief to withstand, Not to retire, turn backe, at any hand. Rebus in adversis facile est contemnere mortem. Fortius ille facit, qui miser esse potest. -- Mart. xi. Ep. lvii. 15. Tis easy in crosse chance death to despise: He that can wretched be, does stronger rise. It is the part of cowardlinesse, and not of virtue, to seek to squat itself in some hollow lurking hole, or to hide herself under some massie tombe, thereby to shun the strokes of fortune. She never forsakes her course, nor leaves her way, what stormie weather soever crosse her. Si fractus illabatur orbis, Impa vidam ferient ruinæ. -- Hor. iii. Od. iii. 7. If the world broken should upon her fall, The ruines may her strike, but not appall. The avoyding of other inconveniences does most commonly drive us into this, indeed, sometimes the shunning of death makes us to run into it. Hic, rogo, non furor est, ne moriare, mori? -- Mart. ii. Epig. lxxx. 2. Madnesse is’t not, say I, To dye, lest you should dye? As those who for fear, of a break-necke down-fall, do headlong cast themselves into it. --- multos in summa pericula misit Venturi timor ipse mali fortissimus ille est, Qui promptus metuenda pati, si cominus instent, Et diferre potest. -- Lucan. vii. 104. The very fear of ils to come, has sent Many to mighty dangers: strongest they, Who fearfull things t’endure are ready bent If they confront them, yet can them delay. ---usque adeo mortisformidine, vitæ Percepit humanos odium, lucisqe videndæ, Ut sibi consciscant maerenti pectore lethum, Obliti fonte currarum hunc esse timorem. -- Lucr. iii. 79. So far by fear of death, the hate of life, And seeing light, does men as men possesse, They grieving kill themselves to end the strife, Forgetting, fear is spring of their distresse. Plato in his Lawes, alots him that has deprived his neerest and deerest friend of life (that is to say, himself) and abridged him of the destinies course, not constrained by any public judgement, nor by any lewd and inevitable accident of fortune, nor by any intolerable shame or infamy, but through basenesse of mind, and weakenesse of a faint- fearful courage, to have a most ignominious and ever-reproachfull burial. And the opinion which disdaineth our life is ridiculous: For in fine it is our being. It is our all in all. Things that have a nobler and richer being nay accuse ours: But it is against nature, we should despise, and carelesly set ourselves at naught: It is a particular infirmitie, and, which is not seen in any other creature, to hate and disdaine himself. It is of like vanity, that we desire to be other than we are. The fruit of such a desire does not concerne us, forasmuch as it contradicteth and hindereth itself in itself. He that desires to be made of a man an Angell does nothing for himself: He should be nothing the better by it: And being no more, who shall rejoice or conceive any gladnesse of this change or amendment for him? Debet enim misere cui forte ægreque futuram est, Ipse quoque esse in eo tum tempore, cum male possit Accidere. -- Ibid. 905. For he, who shall perchance prove miserable, And speed but ill, should then himself be able To be himself, when ils may chance unstable. The security, indolencie, impassibility, and privation of this lifes evils, which we purchase at the price of death, bring us no cornmoditie at all. In vain does he avoid war that cannot enjoy peace; and bootlesse does he shun pain that has no means to feel rest. Amongst those of the first opinion, great questioning has been, to know what occasions are sufficiently just and lawfull to make a man undertake the killing of himself, they call that ευλογον εζαγωγην (Alex. Aphrod.) a reasonable orderly out-let. For, although they say a man must often dye for slight causes, since these that keep us alive are not very strong; yet is some measure required in them. There are certain fantastic and brainesicke humors, which have not only provoked particular men, but whole Nations to defeat themselves. I have heretofore aleaged some examples of them: And moreover we read of certain Milesian virgins, who upon a furious conspiracie hanged themselves one after another, until such time as the Magistrate provided for it, appointing that such as should be found so hanged, should with their own halters be dragged naked through the streets of the citie. When Threicion perswadeth Cleomenes to kill himself, by reason of the bad and desperate estate his affairs stood in, and having escaped a more honorable death in the battle which he had lately lost, moveth him to accept of this other, which is second to him in honor, and give the Conqueror no leisure to make him endure, either another death, or else a shamefull life, Cleomenes, with a Lacedemonian and Stoike courage, refuseth this counsell as base and effeminate: It is a receipt (says he) which can never faile me, and whereof a man should make no use, so long as there remaineth but one inch of hope: That to live, is sometimes constancy and valor; That he will have his very death serve his Countrie, and by it show an act of honor and of virtue. Threicion then beleeved, and killed himself. Cleomenes did afterwards as much, but not before he had tried and assayed the utmost power of fortune. All inconveniencies are not so much worth that a man should dye to eschue them. Moreover, there being so many sudden changes and violent alterations in humane things, it is hard to judge in what state or point we are justly at the end of our hope: Sperat et in saeva victus gladiator arena, Sit licet infesto pollice turba minax. The Fencer hopes, though down in lists he lie, And people with turn’d hand threat’s he must dye. All things, says an ancient Proverb, may a man hope for so long as he liveth: indeed, but answereth Seneca, why shall I rather have that in mind; that fortune can do all things for him that is living, than this; that fortune has no power at all over him who knows how to dye? Josephus is seen engaged in so apparent-approaching danger, with a whole nation against him, that according to humane reason there was no way for him to escape; notwithstanding being (as he says) counselled by a friend of his, at that instant, to kill himself, it fell out well for him to opinionate himself yet in hope: for fortune, beyond all mans discourse, did so turn and change that accident, that without any inconvenience at all, he saw himself delivered: whereas on the contrary Brutus and Cassius, by reason of the down-fall and rashnesse, wherewith before due time and occasion they killed themselves; did utterly lose the reliques of the Roman liberty, whereof they were protectors. The Lord of Anguien in the battle of Serisolles, as one desperate of the combats success, which on his side went to wracke, attempted twice to run himself through the throat with his rapier and thought by precipitation to bereave himself of the enjoying of so notable a victory. I have seen a hundred Hares save themselves even in the Grey-hounds jawes: Aliquis carnifici suo superstes fuit. (Sen. Epist. xiii.) ’Some man has outlived his Hang-man.’ Multa dies variusque labor mutabilis evi Rettulit in melius, multos alterna revisens Lusit, et in solido rursus fortuna locavit. -- Virg. Æn. xi. 426. Time, and of turning age the diverse strain, Hath much to better brought, fortunes turn’d traine, Hath many mock ’d, and set them fast again. Plinie says there are but three sorts of sicknesses, which to avoid, a man may have some colour of reason to kill himself. The sharpest of all is the stone in the bladder, when the urine is there stopped. Seneca, those only, which for long time disturbe and distract the offices of the mind. To avoid a worse death, some are of opinion, a man should take it at his own pleasure. Democritus, chief of the Ætolians, being led captive to Rome, found means to escape by night but being pursued by his keepers, rather, than he would be taken again, ran himself through with his sword. Antinous and Theodotus, their City of Epirus being by the Romans reduced unto great extremity, concluded, and persuaded all the people to kill themselves. But the counsell, rather to yield, having prevailed, they went to seek their own death, and rushed amidst the thickest of their enemies, with an intention rather to strike than to ward themselves. The Iland of Gosa, being some years since surprised and over-run by the Turkes, a certain Sicilian therein dwelling, having two fair daughters ready to be marrried, killed them both with his own hands, together with their mother, that came in to help them. That done, running out into the streets, with a crossebow in one hand and a caliver in the other, at two shoots slew the two first Turks that came next to his gates, then resolutely drawing his sword, ran furiously among them, by whom he was suddenly hewen in peeces: Thus, did he save himself from slavish bondage, having first delivered his own from it. The Jewish women, after they had caused their children to be circumcised, to avoid the crueltie of Antiochus, did headlong precipitate themselves and them unto death. I have heard it credibly reported that a gentleman of good quality being prisoner in one of our Gaols, his parents advertized that he should assuredly be condemned to avoid the infamie of so reproachfull a death, appointed a priest to tell him that the best remedy was to recommend himself to such a with such a saint, with such, and such a vow, and to continue eight dayes without taking any sustenance, what faintnesse or weaknesse soever he should feel in himself. He believed them, and so without thinking on it, was delivered out of life and danger. Scribonia perswading Libo her nephew, to kill himself, rather than to await the stroke of justice, told him that for a man to preserve his own life, to put it into the hands of such as three or foure dayes after should come and seek it, was even to dispatch another man’s business, and that it was no other than for one to serve his enemies to preserve his blood, therewith to make food. We read in the Bible that Nicanor the persecutor of Gods law, having sent his satellites to apprehend the good old man Rasi as for the honor of his virtue, surnamed the father of the Jewes; when that good man saw no other means left him, his gate being burned, and his enemies ready to lay hold on him, chose rather than to fall into the hands of such villaines and be so basely abused against the honor of his place, to dye nobly, and so smote himself with his own sword; but by reason of his haste, having not thoroughly slain himself, he ran to throw himself down from an high wall, amongst the throng of people, which making him roome, he fell right upon his head. All which notwithstanding, perceiving life to remaine in him, he took heart again; and getting up on his feet, all goared with blood and loaden with strokes, making way through the prease, came to a craggy and down-steepy rock, where, unable to go any further, by one of his wounds with both his hands pulled out his guts, and tearing and breaking them cast them amongst such as pursued him, calling and attesting the vengeance of God to light upon them. Of all violences committed against conscience, the most in mine opinion to be avoided is that which is offered against the chastitie of women. Forasmuch as there is naturally some corporall pleasure commixt with it, and therefore the dissent cannot fully enough be joined thereunto; and it seems that force is in some sort intermixed with some will. The ecclesiastical story has in especiall reverence sundry such examples of devout persons who called for death to warrant them from the outrages which some tyrants prepared against their religion and consciences. Pelagia and Sophronia, both canonised, the first, together with her mother and sisters, to escape the outrageous rapes of some soldiers, threw herself into a river; the other, to shun the force of Maxentius, the Emperor, slew herself. It shall perhaps redound to our honor in future ages, that a wise author of these dayes, and namely a Parisian,, does labor to persuade the ladies of our times rather to hazard upon any resolution than to embrace so horrible a counsell of such desperation. I am sorie that to put amongst his discourses he knew not the good saying I learnt of a woman at Tholouse, who had passed through the hands of some soldiers: ’God be praised,’ said she, ’that once in my life I have had my belly full without sinne.’ Verify these cruelties are not worthy of the French curtesie. And God be thanked, since this good advertisement, our air is infinitely purged of them. Let it suffice that in doing it they say no, and take it, following the rule of Marot. The historie is very full of such, who a thousand ways have changed lingering, toylsome life with death. Lucius Aruntius killed himself, as he said to avoid what was past and eschue what was to come. Granius Sylvanus and Statius Proximus, after they had been pardoned by Nero, killed themselves, either because they scorned to live by the favor of so wicked a man, or because they would not another time be in danger of a second pardon, seeing his so easy-yielding unto suspicions and accusations against honest men. Spargapises, son unto Queene Tomiris, prisoner by the law of war unto Cyrus, employed the first favor that Cyrus did him by setting him free, to kill himself, as he who never pretended to reap other fruit by his liberty, than to revenge the infamie of his taking upon himself. Boges, a Governor for King Xerxes, in the country of Ionia, being besieged by the Athenians army, under the conduct of Cymon, refused the composition to return safely, together with his goods and treasure, into Asia, as one impatient to survive the loss of what his master had given him in charge; and after he had stoutly, and even to the last extremity, defended the town, having no manner of victuals left him; first he all the gold and treasure, with whatsoever he imagined the enemy might reap any commoditie by, into the river Strimon . Then having caused a great pile of wood to be set on fire, and made all women, children, concubines and servants to be stripped and throwne into the flames, afterward ran in himself, where all were burned. Ninachetuen, a lord in the East Indies, having had an inkling of the King of Portugales viceroys deliberation to dispossess him, without any apparent cause of the charge he had in Malaca, for to give it unto the King of Campar, of himself took this resolution: First, he caused an high scaffold to be set up, somewhat longer than broad, underpropped with pillars, all gorgeously hanged with rich tapestrie, strewed with flowers and adorned with precious perfumes. Then, having put on a sumptuous long robe of cloth of gold, richly beset with store of precious stones of inestimable worth, he came out of the palace into the street, and by certain steps ascended the scaffold, in one of the corners whereof was a pile of aromaticall wood set afire. All the people of the citie were flocked together to see what the meaning of such unaccustomed preparation might tend unto. Ninachetuen, with an undanted, bold, yet seeming discontented countenance, declared the manifold obligations which the Portugal nation was endebted unto him for, expostulated how faithfully and truly he had dealt in his charge; that having so often witnessed, armed at all assayes for others, that his honor was much dearer unto him than life, he was not to forsake the care of it for himself; that fortune refusing him all means to oppose himself against the injurie intended against him, his courage at the least willed him to remove the feeling thereof, and not become a laughing stocke unto the people, and a triumph to men of less worth than himself, which words, as he was speaking, he cast himself into the fire. Sextilia, the wife of Scaurus, and Praxea, wife unto Labeo, to encourage their husbands to avoid the dangers which pressed them, wherein they had no share (but in regard of the interest of their conjugal affection), voluntarily engaged their life, in this extreme necessitie, to serve them as an example to imitate and company to regard. What they performed for their husbands, Cocceius Nerva acted for his countrie, and though less profitable, yet equall in true love. That famous interpreter of the laws, abounding in riches, in reputation, in credit, and flourishing in health about the Emperor, had no other cause to rid himself of life but the compassion of the miserable estate, wherein he saw the Roman commonwealth. Nothing can be added unto the daintinesse of the wifes death of Fulvius who was so inward with Augustus. Augustus perceiving he had blabbed a certain secret of importance, which he on trust had revealed unto him, one morning coming to visit him, he seemed to frowne upon him for it; whereupon as guilty, he returneth home as one full of despaire, and in piteous sort told his wife that sithence he was falne into such a mischief, he was resolved to kill himself; she, as one no whit dismaied, replied unto him: ’Thou shall do but right, since having so often exprienced the incontinence of my tongue, you hast not learnt to beware of it, yet give me leave to kill my self first,’ and without more adoe ran herself through with a sword. Vibius Virius despairing of his cities safetie, besieged by the Romans, and mistrusting their mercy, in their Senates last consultation, after many remonstrances employed to that end, concluded that the best and fairest way was to escape fortune by their own hands. The very enemies should have them in more honor, and Hanniball might perceive what faithfull friends he had forsaken. Enviting those that should allow of his advice to come and take a good supper, which was prepared in his house, where, after great cheere, they should drinke together whatsoever should be presented unto him; a drinke that shall deliver our bodies from torments, free our mindes from injuries, a nd release our eyes and ears from seeing and hearing so horrible mischiefes, which the conquered must endure at the hands of most cruel and offended conquerors. ’I have,’ quoth he, ’taken order that nen fit for that purpose shall be ready, when we shall be expired, to cast us into a great burning pile of wood.’ Diverse approved of his high resolution, but few did imitate the same. Seven and twentie Senators followed him, who after they had attempted to stifle so irkesome and suppress so terror-moving a thought, with quaffing and swelling of wine, they ended their repast by this deadly messe: and enter-bracing one another, after they had in common deplored and bewailed their countries misfortunes, some went home to their own house, othersome stayed there, to be entombed with Vibius in his own fire, whose death was so long and lingering, forasmuch as the vapor of the wine having possessed their veines, and slowed the effect and operation of the poyson, that some lived an hour after they had seen their enemies enter Capua, which they caried the next day after, and incurred the miseries and saw the calamities which at so high a rate they had sought to eschue. Taurea Iubellius, another citizen there, the Consull Fulvius returning from that shameful slaughter which he had committed of 225 Senators, called him churlishly by his name, and having arrested him; ’Co;nmand, ’quoth he unto him, ’that I also be massacred after so many others, that so you mayest brag to have murthered a much more valiant man than ever you were.’ Fulvius, as one enraged, disdaining him; forasmuch as be had newly received letters from Rome contrary to the inhumanitie of his execution, which inhibited him to proceed any further; Iubellius, continuing his speech, said: ’Sithence my Countrie is taken, my friends butchered, and having with my own hands slain my wife and children, as the only meane to free them from the desolation of this ruine, I may not dye the death of my fellow citizens, let us borrow the vengeance of this hateful life from virtue:’ And drawing a blade he had hidden under his garments, therewith ran himself through, and falling on his face, died at the Consuls feet. Alexander besieged a City in India, the inhabitants whereof, perceiving themselves brought to a very narrow pinch, resolved obstinately to deprive him of the pleasure he might get of his victory, and to gether with their City, in despite of his humanitie set both the Town and themselves on a light fire, and so were all consumed. A new kind of warring, where the enemies did all they could, and sought to save them, they to loose themselves, and to be assured of their death, did all a man can possibly effect to warrant his life. Astapa, a City in Spain, being very weake of wals and other defences, to withstand the Romanes that besieged it; the inhabitants drew all their riches and wealth into the market-place, whereof having made a heap, and on the top of it placed their wives and children, and encompassed and covered the same with drie brush wood that it might burne the easier, and having appointed fifty lusty young men of theirs for the performance of their resolution, made a sally, where following their determined vow, seeing they could not vanquish, suffered themselves to be slain every mothers child. The fifty, after they had massacred every living soul remaining in the City, and set fire to the heap joyfully leaped there-into, ending their generous liberty in a state rather insensible than dolorous and reproachfull; showing their enemies that, if fortune had been so pleased, they should as well have had the courage to bereave them of the victory as they, had to yield it them both vain and hideous, indeed, and mortal to those who allured by the glittering of the gold that moulten ran from out the flame, thicke and threefold approching greedily unto it, were therein smothered and burned, the formost being unable to give back, by reason of the throng that followed them. The Abideans, pressed by Philip, resolved upon the very same, but being prevented, the King whose heart abhorred to see the fool-rash precipitation of such an execution (having first seized upon and saved the treasure and moveables, which they had diversly condemned to the flames and utter spoyle) retiring all the Soldiers, granted them the full space of three dayes to make themselves away, that so they might do it with more order and leisure; which three dayes they replenished with blood and murther beyond all hostile cruelty: And which is strange, there was no one person saved that had power upon himself. There are infinite examples of such-like popular conclusions, which seem more violent by how much more the effect of them is more universall. They are less than when severall. What discourse would not do in each one, it does in all the vehemence of societie ravishing particular judgements. Such as were condemned to dye in the time of Tiberius, and delaid their execution any while, lost their goods, and could not be buried; but such as prevented the same, in killing themselves, were solemnly enterred, and might at their pleasure bequeath such goods as they had to whom they list. But a man does also sometimes desire death, in hope of a greater good. ’I desire,’ says Saint Paul, ’to be out of this world, that I may be with Jesus Christ: and who shal release me out of these bonds?’ Cleombrotus Ambraciota, having read Platoes Pheadon, was so possessed with a desire and longing for an after-life, that without other occasion or more adoe, he went and headlong cast himself into the sea. Whereby it appeareth how improperly we call this voluntarie dissolution despaire; unto which the violence of hope does often transport us, and as often a peacefull and setled inclination of judgement. Iaques du Castell, Bishop o Soissons, in the voyage which Saint Lewes undertook beyond the seas, seeing the King and all his army ready to return into France, and leave the affairs of Religion imperfect, resolved with himself rather to go to heaven; And having bidden his friends farewell, in the open view of all men, rushed alone into the enemies troops, of whom he was forthwith hewen in pieces. In a certain kingdome of these late-discovered Indies, upon a day of a solemn procession, in which the idols they adore are publikely carried up and down upon a chariot of exceeding greatness: besides that, there are many seen to cut and slice great mammocks of their quick flesh to offer the said idols; there are numbers of others seen who, prostrating themselves alongst the ground, endure very patiently to be mouldred and crushed to death under the chariots wheels, thinking thereby to purchase after their death a veneration of holinesse, of which they are not defrauded. The death of this Bishop, armed as we have said, argueth more generositie and less sense: the heat of the combat ammusing one part of it. Some common-wealths there are that have gone about to sway the justice and direct the opportunity of voluntarie deaths. In our City of Marseille they were wont in former ages ever to keep some poison in store, prepared and compounded with hemlocke, at the Cities charge, for such as would upon any occasion shorten their days, having first approved the reasons of their enterprise unto the six hundred Elders of the Town, which was their Senate: For otherwise it was unlawfull for any body, except by the Magistrates permission, and for very lawfully-urgent occasions, to lay violent hands upon himself. The very same law was likewise used in other places. Sextus Pompeius, going into Asia, passed through the Iland of Cea, belonging to Negropont; it fortuned while he abode there (as one as one reporteth that was in his companie) that a woman of great authority, having first yielded an accompt unto her Citizens and showed good reasons why she was resolved to end her life, earnestly entreated Pompey to be an assistant at her at her death, that so it might be esteemed more honorable, which he assented unto; and having long time in vain sought, by virtue of his eloquence (wherein be was exceeding ready) and force of persuasion, to alter her intent and remove her from her purpose, in the end yielded to her request. She had lived foure score and ten years in a most happy state of mind and body, but when lying on her bed, better adorned than before she was accustomed to have it, and leaning on her elbow, thus she bespoke: ’The Gods, O Sextus Pompeius, and rather those I forgoe than those I go unto, reward and appay you, for that you hast vouchsafed to be both a counsellor of my life and a witness of my death. As for my part, having hitherto ever tasted the favourable visage of fortune, for fear the desire of living overlong should make me taste of her frownes, with an happy and successfull end I will now depart, and set free the remainder of my soul, leaving behind me two daughters of, mine, with a legion of grand-children and nephewes.’ That done, having preached unto and exhorted all her people and kinsfolks to an unitie and peace, and divided her goods amongst them, and recommended her household Gods unto her eldest daughter, with an assuredly-staide hand she took the cup wherein the poyson was, and having made her vows unto Mercurie, and prayers to conduct her unto some happy place in the other world, roundly swallowed that mortal potion; which done, she intertained the progresse of her behaviour, and as the parts of her body were one after another possessed with the cold operation of that venom: until such time as she felt it work at the heart and in her entrals, she called her daughter to do her the last office and close her eyes. Plinie reporteth of a certain Hiperborean nation, wherein, by reason of the mild temperature of the aire, the inhabitants thereof commonly never dye, but when they please to make themselves away, and that being weary and tired with living they are accustomed at the end of a long-long age, having first made merry and good cheare with their friends, from the top of an high-steepy rocke appointed for that purpose, to cast themselves headlong into the sea. Grieving-smart, and a worse death seem to me the most excusable incitations. Return to : Book II CHAPTER IV: TO-MORROW IS A NEW DAY. CHAPTER IV: TO-MORROW IS A NEW DAY. DO with some reason, as me seems, give pricke and praise unto Jaques Amiot above all our French writers, not only for his natural purity, and pure elegancie of the tongue, wherin he excelleth all others, nor for his indefatigable constancy of so long and toilesome a labor, nor for the unsearchable depth of his knowledge, having so successfully-happy been able to explaine an Author so close and thorny, and unfold a writer so mysterious and entangled (for let any man tell me what he list, I have no skill of the Greeke, but I see thorowout al his translation a sense so closely- joynted, and so pithily-continued, that either he has assuredly understood and inned the very imagination, and the true conceit of the Author, or having through a long and continuall conversion, lively planted in his mind a general Idea of that of Plutarke, he has at least lent him nothing that dot h belye him, or misseeme him) but above all, I kon him thanks that he has had the hap to chuse, and knowledge to cull-out so worthy a work, and a book so fit to the purpose, therewith to make so unvaluable a present unto his Countrie. We that are in the number of the ignorant had been utterly confounded, had not his book raised us from out the dust of ignorance: God-a-mercy his endevours we dare not both speak and write: Even Ladies are therewith able to confront Masters of arts: It is our breviarie. If so good a man chance to live, I bequeath Xenophon unto him, to do as much. It is an easier peece of work, and so much the more agreeing to his age. Moreover I wot not how meseemeth, although he roundly and clearly disintangle himself from hard passages,, that notwithstanding his stile is more close and nearer itself when it is not laboured and wrested, and that it glideth smoothly at his pleasure. I was even now reading of that place where Plutarke speaks of himself, that Rusticus being present at a declamation of his in Rome, received a packet from the Emperor, which he temporized to open until he had made an end: wherein (says he) all the assistants did singularly commend the gravitie of the man. Verily, being on the instance of curiosity and on the greedy and insatiate passion of news, which with such indiscreet impatience and impatient indiscretion, induceth us to neglect all things f or to entertaine a new-come guest, and forget all respect and countenance whersoover we be, suddenly to break up such letters as are brought us; he had reason to commend the gravitie of Rusticus: to which he might also have added the commendation of his civilitie and curtesie, for that be would not interrupt the course of his declamation: But I make a question whether he might be commended for his wisdom; for receiving unexpected letters, and especially from an Emperor, it might very well have fortuned that this deferring to read them might have caused some notable inconvenience. Recklesness is the vice contrary unto curiosity, towards which I am naturally inclined, aud wherein I have seen many men, so extremely plunged, that three or foure days after the receiving of letters which have been sent them, they have been found in their pockets yet unopened. I never opened any, not only of such as had been committed to my keeping, but of such as by any fortune came to my hands. And I make a conscience standing neare some great person if mine eyes chance unawares to steale some knowledge of any letters of importance that he readeth. Never was man less inquisitive, or pryed less into other mens affairs than I. In our fathers time the Lord of Boutieres was like to have lost Turin, forasmuch as being one night at supper in very good company he deferred the reading of an advertisement which was delivered him of the treasons that were practised and complotted against that City where he commanded. And Plutarke himself has taught me that Julius Cæsar had escaped death, if going to the Senate-house that day wherein he was murdered by the conspirators he had read a memorial which was presented unto him. Who likewise reporteth the story of Archias, the Tyrant of Thebes, how the night fore-going the execution of the enterprize that Pelopidas had complotted to kill him, thereby to set his Countrie at liberty: another Archias of Athens wrote him a letter wherein he particularly related unto him all that was conspired and complotted against him; which letter being delivered him whilst he sate at supper, he deferred the opening of it, pronouncing this by-word: ’To morrow is a new day,’ which afterward was turned to a Proverb in Greece. A wise man may, in mine opinion, for the interest of others, as not unmannerly to breake companie like unto Rusticus, or not to discontinue some other affaire of importance, remit and defer to understand such news as are brought him; but for his own private interest or particular pleasure, namely, if he be a man having public charge, if he regard his dinner so much that he will not break it off, or his sleepe that he will not interrupt it: to do it, is inexcusable. And in former ages was the Consulate-place in Rome, which they named the most honorable at the table, because it was more free and more accessible for such as might casually come in, to entertaine him that should be there placed. Witness, that though they were sitting at the board, they neither omitted nor gave over the managing of other affairs and following of other accidents. But when all is said, it is very hard, chiefely in humane actions, to prescribe so exact rules by discourse of reason, that fortune do not sway, and keep her right in them. Return to : Book II CHAPTER V: OF CONSCIENCE CHAPTER V: OF CONSCIENCE Y BROTHER the Lord of Brouze and myself, during the time of our civill wars, travelling one day together, we fortuned to meet upon the way with a Gentleman in outward semblance, of good demeanour: He was of our contrary faction, but forasmuch as he counterfeited himself otherwise, I knew it not. And the worst of these tumultuous intestine broyles is, that the cards are so shuffled (your enemy being neither by language nor by fashion, nor by any other apparent marke distinguished from you; nay, which is more, brought up under the same laws and customs, and breathing the same air) that it is a very hard matter to avoid confusion and shun disorder. Which consideration made me not a little fearefull to meet with our troopes, especially where I was not known, lest I should be urged to tell my name, and perhaps do worse. As other times before it had befalne me; for, by such a chance, or rather mistaking, I fortuned once to lose all my men and horses and hardly escaped myself: and amongst other my losses and servants that were slain, the thing that most grieved me was the untimely and miserable death of a young Italian Gentlemen whom I kept as my Page, and very carefully brought up, with whom dyed as forward, as budding and as hopefull a youth as ever I saw. But this man seemed fearfully dismaid, and at every encounter of horseman and passage by, or through any Town that held for the King, I observed him to be so strangely distracted that in the end I perceived and guessed they were but guilty alarums that his conscience gave him. It seemed unto this seely man that all might apparently, both through his blushing self-accusing countenance, and by the crosses he wore upon his upper garments, read the secret intentions of his faint heart. Of such marvailous-working power is the sting of conscience: which often induceth us to bewray, to accuse, and to combat ourselves; and for want of other evidences she produces ourselves against our selves. Occultum quaetiens animo tortore flagellum. -- Juven Sat. xiii. 195. Their mind, the tormentor of sinne, Shaking an unseen whip within. The story of Bessus the Paeonian is so common, that even children have it in their mouths, who being found, fault withal, that in mirth he had beaten down a nest of young Sparrowes and then killed them, answered, he had great reason to do it; forasmuch as those young birds ceased not falsly to accuse him to have murthered his father, which parricide was never suspected to have been committed by him, and until that day had layen secret; but the revengeful furies of the conscience made the same partie to reveale it, that by all right was to do penance for so hateful and unnaturall a murther. Hesiodus corrects the saying of Plato, that punishment does commonly succeed the guilt, and follow sinne at hand: for, he affirmeth, that it rather is borne at the instant and together with sinne itself, and they are as twinnes borne at one birth together. ’Whosoever expects punishment suffe reth the same, and whosoever deserveth it, he does expect it. Impietie does invent, and iniquitie does frame torments against itself,’ Malum constilium consultori pessimum. -- Eras. Chil. i. cent. ii. ad. 14. Bad counsell is worst for the counsellor that gives the counsell. Even as the Waspe stingeth and offendeth others, but herself much more; for, in hurting others, she loses her force and sting for ever. -----itasque in vulnere ponunt. -- Virg. Georg. iv. 238. They, while they others sting, Death to themselves do bring. The Cantharides have some part in them, which by a contrarietie of nature serveth as an antidot or counter-poison against their poison: so likewise, as one taketh pleasure in vice, there is a certain contrary displeasure engendred in the conscience, which by sundry irksome and painfull imaginations, perplexeth and tormenteth us, both waking and asleep. Quippe ubi se multi per somnia saepe loquentes, Aut morbo delirantes protraxe ferantur, Et celata diu in medium peccata delisse. --Lucr. v. 1168. Many in dreames oft speaking, or unhealed, In sicknesse raving have themselves revealed, And brought to light their sinnes long time concealed. Apollodorus dreamed he saw himself first flayed by the Scythians, and then boiled in a pot, and that his own heart murmured, saying: ’I only have caused this mischief to light upon you.’ Epicurus was wont to say, that no lurking hole can shroud the wicked, for they can never assure themselves to be sufficiently hidden, sithence conscience is ever ready to disclose them to themselves. -------- prima est haec ultio, quod se Judice nemo nocens absolvitur. -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 2. This is the first revenge, no guilty mind Is quitted, though itself be judge assign’d. Which as it does fill us with fear and doubt, so does it store us with assurance and trust. And I may boldly say that I have waded through many dangerous hazards with a more untired pace, only in consideration of the secret knowledge I had of my own will, and innocencie of my desseignes. Conscia mens ut cuique sua est, ita concipit intra Pectora pro facto spemque metumque suo. --Ovid. Fast. i. 485. As each mans mind is guiltie, so does he Inlie breed hope and fear, as his deeds be. Of examples there are thousands: It shall suffice us to alleage three only, and all of one man. Scipio being one day accused before the Roman people of an urgent and capital accusation, in stead of excusing himself, or flattering the Judges; turning to them, he said: ’It will well beseeme you to undertake to judge of his head, by whose means you have authority to judge of all the world.’ The same man, another time, being vehemently urged by a Tribune of the people, who charged him with sundry imputations, in lieu of pleading or excusing his cause, gave him this sudden and short answer: ’Let us go (quoth he), my good Citizens; let us forthwith go (I say) to give hartie thanks unto the Gods for the victory, which even upon such a day as this is they gave me against the Carthaginians.’ And therewith advancing himself to march before the people, all the assembly, and even his accuser himself did undelayedly follow him towards the Temple. After that, Petilius having been animated and stirred up by Cato to solicite and demand a strict accompt of him, of the money he had managed, and which was committed to his trust while he was in the Province of Antioch, Scipio, being come into the Senate-house of purpose to answer for himself, pulling out the book of his accompts from under his gowne, told them all that that book contained truly both the receipt and laying out thereof; and being required to deliver the same unto a Clarke to register it, he refused to do it, saying he would not do himself that wrong or indignitie; and thereupon with his own hands, in presence of all the Senate, tore the book in peeces. I cannot apprehend or believe that a guiltie-cauterized conscience could possibly dissemble or counterfet such an undismayed assurance: His heart was naturally too great, and enured to overhigh fortune (says Titus Livius) to know how to be a criminall offender, and stoopingly to yield himself to the baseness to defend his innocencie. Torture and racking are dangerous inventions, and seem rather to be trials of patience than Essayes of truth. And both he that can, and he that cannot endure them, conceal the truth. For why shall pain or smart rather compell me to confesse that which is so indeed than force me to tell that which is not? And contrariwise, if he who has not done that whereof he is accused, is sufficiently patient to endure those torments, why shall not he be able to tolerate them who has done it, and is guilty indeed; so dear and worthy a reward as life being proposed unto him? I am of opinion that the ground of this invention proceedeth from the consideration of the power and facultie of the conscience. For, to the guilty, it seems to give a kind of furtherance to the torture, to make him confesse his fault, and weakneth and dismayeth him: and on the other part, it encourageth and strengthneth the innocent against torture. To say truth, it is a meane full of uncertainty and danger. What would not a man say, nay, what not do, to avoid so grievous paines and shun such torments? Etiam innocentes cogit mentiri dolor. -- Sen. Prover. Torment to lie sometimes will drive, Ev’n the most innocent alive. Whence it followeth that he whom the Judge has tortured, because he shall not dye an innocent, he shall bring him to his death, both innocent and tortured. Many thousands have thereby charged their heads with false confessions. Amongst which I may well place Phylotas, considering the circumstances of the endictment that Alexander framed against him, and the progresse of his torture. But so it is, that (as men say) it is the least evil humane weaknesse could invent; though, in my conceit, very inhumanely, and there withall most unprofitably. Many Nations less barbarous in that than the Greek or the Roman, who terme them so, judge it a horrible and cruel thing to racke and torment a man for a fault whereof you are yet in doubt. Is your ignorance long of him? What can he do withall? Are not you unjust who because you will not put him to death without some cause, you do worse than kill him? And that it is so, consi der but how often he rather chuseth to dye guiltlesse than pass by this informat1on, much more painfull than the punishment or torment; and who many times, by reason of the sharpnesse of it, preventeth, furthereth, indeed, and executeth the punishment. I wot not whence I heard this story, but it exactly has reference unto the conscience of our Justice. A countrie woman accused a souldier before his General, being a most severe Justicer, that he, with violence, had snatched from out her poore childrens hands, the small remainder of some pap or water- gruell, which she had only left to sustain them, forasmuch as the Army had ravaged and wasted all. The poore woman had neither witness nor proofe of it: it was but her indeed his no; which the General perceiving, after he had summoned her to be well advised what she spake, and that she should not accuse him wrongfully; for, if she spake an untruth, she should then be culpable of his accusation: But she constantly persisting to charge him, he forthwith, to discover the truth, and to be thoroughly resolved, caused the accused Soldiers belly to be ripped, who was found faulty, and the poore woman to have said true; whereupon she was discharged. A condemnation instructive to others. Return to : Book II CHAPTER VI: OF EXERCISE OR PRACTICE CHAPTER VI: OF EXERCISE OR PRACTICE T IS a hard matter (although our conceit do willingly apply, itself unto it) that Discourse and Instruction should sufficiently be powerful to direc t us to action, and addresse us to performance, if, over and besides that, we do not by experience exercise and frame our mind to the traine whereunto we will range it: otherwise, when we shall be on the point of the effects, it will doubtlesse find itself much engaged and empeached. And that is the reason why amongst Philosophers, those that have willed to attaine to some greater excellence, have not been content, at home and at rest, to expect the rigors of fortune, for fear she should surprise them unexperienced and find them novices, if she should chance to enter fight with them but have rather gone to meet and front her before, and witting-earnestly cast themselves to the trial of the hardest difficulties. Some have thereby voluntarily forsaken great riches, only to practise a voluntarie povertie; others have willingly found out labor, and an austeritie of a toylesome life thereby to harden and enure themselves to evil and travell; othersome have frankly deprived themselves of the dearest and best parts of their body, as of their eyes and members of generation, lest their overpleasing and too-too wanton service might in any sort mollifie and distract the constant resolution of their mind. But to dye, which is the greatest work we have to do, exercise can nothing avail us thereunto. A man may, by custom aud experience, fortifie himself against grief, sorrow, shame, want, and such like accidents; but concerning death, we can but once feel and trie the same. We are all novices, and new to learne when we come unto it. There have, in former times, been found men so good husbands and thrifty of time, that even in death they have assayed to taste and savor it; and bent their mind to observe and see what manner of thing that passage of death was; but none did ever yet come backe again to tell us tidings of it.. -------- nemo expergitus extat Frigida quem semel est vita i pausa sequuta. --Lucr. iii. 973. No man does ever-after wake, Whom once his lifes cold rest does take. Canius Iulius, a noble Roman, a man of singular virtue and constancy, having been condemned to death by that lewdly-mischievous monster of men, Caligula: besides many marvelous evident assurances he gave of his matchlesse resolution, when he was even in the nicke to endure the last stroke of the executioner; a Philosopher, being his friend, interrupted him with this question, saying: ’Canius, in what state is your soul now? what does she? what thoughts possesse you now? ’I thought,’ answered he, to keep me ready and prepared with all my force, to see whether in this instant of death, so short and so near at hand, I might perceive some dislodging or distraction of the soul, and whether it will show some feeling of her sudden departure; that (if I apprehend or learne any thing of her) I may afterward, if I can, return and give advertisement thereof unto my friends.’ See-here a Philosopher, not only until death, but even in death itself: what assurance was it, and what fiercenes of courage, to will that his own death should serve him as a lesson, and have leisure to think else where in a matter of such consequence; -------- jus hoc animi morientis habebat. --Lucan. viii. 636. This power of mind had he, When it from him did flee. Me seems, nevertheless, that in some sort there is a meane to familiarize ourselves with it, and to assay it. We may have some experience of it, if not whole and perfect, at least such as may not altogether be unprofitable, and which may yield us better fortified and more assured. If we cannot attaine unto it, we may at least approch it, and discerne the same: And if we cannot enter her fort, yet shal we see and frequent the approches unto it. It is not without reason we are taught to take notice of our sleepe for the resemblance it has with death. How easily we pass from wakmg to sleeping; with how little interest we lose the knowledge of light and of ourselves. The facultie of sleepe might perhaps seem unprofitable and against nature, sithence it depriveth up of all actions and barreth us of all sense, were it not that nature does thereby instruct us that she has equally made us as well to live as to die; and by life presenteth the eternal state unto us which she after the same reserveth for us, so to accustome us thereunto, and remove the fear of it from us. But such as by some violent accident are falne into a faintness of heart, and have lost all senses, they, in mine opinion, have well-nigh been where they might behold her true and natural visage: For, touching the instant or moment of the passage, it is not to be feared it should bring any traveil or displeasure with it, forasmuch as we can have nor sense nor feeling without pleasure. Our sufferances have need of time, which is so short, and plunged in death, that necessarily it must be insensible. It is the approches that lead unto it we should fear; and those may fall within the compasse of mans experience. Many things seem greater by imagination than by effect. I have passed over a good part of my age in sound and perfect health. I say not only sound but blithe and wantonly lustfull. That state full of lust, of prime and mirth, made me deem the consideration of sicknesses so yrkesome and horrible, that when I came to the experience of them I have found their fits but weake, and their assaults but faint, in respect of my apprehended fear. See here what I daily prove. Let me be under a roofe, in a good chamber, warme-clad, and well at ease, in some tempestuous and stormy night. I am exceedingly perplexed and much grieved for such as are abroad and have no shelter: But let me be in the storme my self, I do not so much as desire to be else-where: Only to be continually pent up in a chamber seemed intolerable to me. I have now enured my self to live a whole weeke, indeed a moneth in my chamber, full of care, trouble, alteration, and weaknesse; and have found that in the time of my best health I moaned such as were sicke much more than I can well moan my self when I am ill at ease: and that the power of my apprehension did well-nigh halfe endeare the essence and truth of the thing itself. I am in good hope the like will happen to me of death: and that it is not worth the labor I take for so many preparations as I prepare against her; and so many helpes as I call to sustain, and assemble to endure the shocke and violence of it. But hab or nab we can never take too much advantage of it. During our second or third troubles (I do not well remember which) I fortuned one day, for recreation sake, to go forth and take the air, about a league from my house, who am seated even in the bowels of all troubles of our civill wars of France, supposing to be most safe, so near mine own home and retreite, that I had no need of better attendance or equipage. I was mounted upon a very easy-going nag, but not very sure. At my returning home again, a sudden occasion being offered me to make use of this nag in a peece of service whereto he was neither trained nor accustomed, one of my men (a strong sturdy fellow), mounted upon a young strongheaded horse, and that a desperate hard mouth, fresh, lusty and in breath, to show his courage, and to outgoe his fellowes, fortuned with might and main to set spurrs unto him, and giving him the bridle, to come right into the path where I was, and as a Colossus with his weight riding over me and my nag, that were both very little, he overthrew us both, and made us fall with our heels upward: so that the nag lay along astonied in one place, and I in a trance groveling on the ground ten or twelve paces wide of him: my face all torn and brused, my sword which I had in my hand a good way from me, my girdle broken, with no more motion or sense in me than a stocke. It is the only swooning that ever I felt yet. Those that were with, me, after they had assayed all possible means to bring me to my self again, supposing me dead, took me in their arms, and with much adoe were carrying me home to my house, which was about halfe a French league thence: upon the way, and after I had for two hours space by all been supposed dead and past all recoverie, I began to stir and breathe: for so great aboundance of blood was falne into my stomake, that to discharge it nature was foreed to rowse up her spirits. I was immediately set upon my feet, and bending forward, I presently cast up in quantitie as much clottie pure blood as a bucket will hold and by the way was constrained to do the like diverse times before I could get home, whereby, I began to recover a little life, but it was by little and little, and so long adoing, that my chief senses were much more enclining to death than to life. Perche dubbiosa ancor del suo ritorno Non s’assicura attonita la mente. For yet the mind doubtfull of it’s return Is not assured, but astonished. The remembrance whereof (which yet I bear deepely imprinted in my mind) representing me her visage and Idea so lively and so naturally, does in some sort reconcile me unto her. And when I began to see, it was with so dim, so weake and so troubled a sight, that I could not discerne anything of the light, -------- come quel ch’or apre, or chiude Gli occhi, mezzo tra l’ sonno e l’esser desto. As he that sometimes opens, sometimes shuts His eyes, betweene sleepe and awake. Touching the functions of the soul, they started up and came in the same progresse as those of the body. I perceived my self all bloudy; for my doublet was all sullied with the blood I had cast. The first conceit I apprehended was that I had received some shot in my head; and in truth, at the same instant, there were diverse that shot round about us. Me thought my self had no other hold of me but of my lips-ends. I closed mine eyes to help (as me seemed) to send it forth, and took a kind of pleasure to linger and languishingly to let my self go from my self. It was an imagination swimming superficially in my mind, as weake and as tender as all the rest: but in truth, not only exempted from displeasure but rather commixt with that pleasant sweetesse which they feel that suffer themselves to fall into a soft-slumbring and sense-entrancing sleepe. I believe it is the same state they find themselves in, whom in the agony of death we see to droop and faint through weaknesse: and am of opinion we plaine and moan them without cause, esteeming that either they are agitated with grievous pangs, or that their soul is pressed with painfull cogitations. It was ever my conceit against the opinion of many, indeed against that of Stephanus la Boetie, that those whom we see so overwhelmed and faintly- drooping at the approches of their end, or utterly cast down with the lingring tediousnesse of their deseases, or by accident of some apoplexie or falling-evil, ----- (vi morbi sæpe coactus Ante oculos aliquis nostros ut fulminis ictu, Concidit, et spumas agit, ingemit, et fremit artus, Desipit exentant nervos torquetur, anhelat, Inconstanter et in jactando membra fatigat), -- Lucr. iii. 490. (Some man by force of sicknesse drivn does fall, As if by thunder stroke, before our eyes; He fomes, he grones, he trembles over all, He raves, he stretches, he’s vext, panting lyes, He tyr’s his limbs by tossing, Now this now that way crossing,) or hurt in the head, whom we hear throb and rattle, and send forth grones and gaspes, although we gather some tokens from them, whereby it seems they have yet some knowledge left and certain motions we see them make with their body: I say, I have ever thought they had their soul and body buried and asleepe. Vivat et est vitæ nescius ipse suæ. -- Ovid. Trist. i. El. iii. 12. He lives yet knowes not he, That he alive should be. And I could not believe that at so great an astonishment of members and deffailance of senses the soul could maintaine any force within, to know herself; and therefore had no manner of discourse tormenting them, which might make them judge and feel the misery of their condition, and that consequently they were not greatly to be moaned. As for my self, I imagine no state so intolerable nor condition so horrible, as to have a feelingly- afflicted soul, void of means to disburthen and declare herself: As I would say of those we send to execution, having first caused their tongue to be cut out, were it not that in this manner of death the most dumbe seems unto me the fittest, namely, if it be accompanied with a resolute and grave countenance. And as those miserable prisoners which light in the hands of those hard-harted and villenous Soldiers of these times, of whom they are tormented with all manner of cruel entreaty, by compulsion to drawe them unto some excessive and unpossible ransoms, keeping them al that while in so hard a condition and place, that they have no way left them to utter their thoughts and express their misery. The Poets have feigned there were some Gods that favoured the release of such as suffered so languishing deaths. -----hunc ego Diti Sacrum jussa fero, teque isto corpore solvo.-- Virg. Æn. iv. 703, Iris. This to death sacred, I, as was my charge, Doe bear, and from this body you enlarge. And the faltering speeches and uncertaine answers, that by continuall ringing in their ears and incessant urging them, are sometimes by force wrested from them, or by the motions which seem to have some sympathy with that whereof they are examined, is notwithstanding no witnes that they live at least a perfect sound life. We do also in yawning, before sleep fully seize upon us, apprehend as it were in a slumber, what is done about us, and with a troubled and uncertains hearing, follow the voyces, which seem to sound but on the outward limits of our soul; and frame answers according to the last words we heard, which taste more of chance than of sense: which thing now I have proved by experience, I make no doubt but hitherto I have well judged of it. For, first lying as in a trance, I laboured even with my nailes to open my doublet (for I was unarmed), and well I wot that in my imagination I felt nothing did hurt me. For, there are several motions in us which proceed not of our free wil. Semianimesque micant digiti, ferrumque retractant. -- x. 396. The halfe-dead fingers stir, and feel, (Though it they cannot stir) for steele. Those that fall, do commonly by a natural impulsion cast their arms abroad before their falling, which sheweth that our members have certain offices, which they lend one to another, and possesse certain agitations, apart from our discourse: Falciferos memorant currus abscindere membra, Ut tremere in terra videatur ab artubus, id quod Decidit abscissum, cum mens tamen atque hominis vis Mobilitate mali non quit sentire dolorem. -- Lucr. iii. 648. They say, sith-bearing chariots limbes bereave, So as on earth, that which cut-off they leave, Does seem to quake; when yet mans force and mind Does not the pain, through so quick motion, find. My stomacke was surcharged with clotted blood, my hands of themselves were still running to it, as often they are wont (indeed against the knowledge of our will) where we feel it to itch. There are many creatures, indeed some men, in whom after they are dead we may see their muskles to close and stir. All men know by experience, there be some parts of our bodies which often without any consent of ours do stir, stand, and lie down again. Now these passions, which but exteriourly touch us, cannot properly be termed ours; for, to make them ours, a man must wholy be engaged unto them: And the paities that our feet or hands feel whilst we sleepe are not ours. When I came near my house, where the tidings of my fall was already come, and those of my household met me, with such outcries as are used in like times, I did not only answer some words to what I was demanded, but some tell me I had the memory to command my men to give my wife a horse, whom I perceived to be overtired, and labouring in the way, which is very hilly, foul, and rugged. It seems this consideration proceeded from a vigilant soul: yet was I cleane distracted from it, they were but vain conceits, and as in a cloud, were only moved by the senses of the eyes and ears: they came not from my self. All which not withstanding, I knew neither whence I came nor whither I went, nor could I understand or consider what was spoken unto me. They were but light effects, that my senses produced of themselves, as it were of custom. Whatsoever the soul did assist it with was but a dreame, being lightly touched, and only sprinkled by the soft impression of the sense. In the meane time my state was verily most pleasant and easefull. I felt no manner of care or affliction, neither for my self nor others. It was a slumbering, languishing and extreme weaknesse, without any pain at all. I saw my own house and knew it not; when I was laid in my bed, I felt great ease in my rest, For I had been vilely hurried and hauled by those poore men, which had taken the paines to carry me upon their arms a long and wearysome way, and to say truth, they had all been wearied twice or thrice over, and were faine to shift severall times. Many remedies were presently offered me, but I took none, supposing verily I had been deadly hurt in the head. To say truth, it had been a very happy death: For, the weaknesse of my discourse hindered me from judging of it, and the feeblenesse of my body from feeling the same. Me thought I was yielding up the ghost so gently, and after so easy and indolent a manner, that I feel no other action less burthensome than that was. But when I began to come to life again and recover my former strength, Vt tandem sensus convaluere mei. -- Ovid. Trist. i. El. iii. 14. At last when all the sprites I bear, Recalled aild recollected were, which was within two or three hours after, I presently felt my self full of aches and paines all my body over; for, each part thereof was with the violence of the fall much brused and tainted; and for two or three nights after I found my self so ill, that I verily supposed I shold have had another fit of death: But that a more lively, and sensible one: (and to speak plaine) I feel my bruses yet, and fear me shall do while I live: I will not forget to tell you, that the last thing I could rightly fall into again was the remembrance of this accident, and I made my men many times to repeat me over and over again, whither I was going, whence I came, and what hour that chance befell me, before I could throughly conceive it. Concerning the manner of my falling, they in favor of him who had been the cause of it, concealed the truth from me, and told me other flim flam tales. But a while after and the morrow next, when my memory began to come to itself again, and represent the state unto me wherein I was at the instant, when I perceived the horse riding over me (for being at my heels, I chanced to espy him and held my self for dead: yet was the conceit so sudden that fear had no leisure to enter my thoughts) me seemed it was a flashing or lightning that smote my soul with shaking, and that I came from another world. This discourse of so slight an accident is but vain and frivolous were not the instructions I have drawne from thence for my use: For truly, for a man to acquaint himself with death, I find no better way than to approach unto it. Now, as Plinie says, every man is a good discipline unto himself, alwayes provided he be able to prie into himself. This is not my doctrine, it is but my study and not another man’s lesson, but my own: Yet ought no man to blame me if I impart the same. What serves my turn may perhaps serve another mans: otherwise I marre nothing; what I make use of is mine own. And if I play the foole, it is at my own cost, and without any other bodies interest, For it is but a kind of folly that dies in me, and has no traine. We have notice but of two or three former ancients that have trodden this path; yet can we not say, whether altogether like unto this of mine, for we know but their names. No man since has followed their steps; it is a thorny and crabbed enterprise, and more than it makes show of, to follow so strange and vagabond a path as that of our spirit: to penetrate the shady, and enter the thicke-covered depths of these infernall winding crankes; to chuse so many and settle so severall aires of his agitatations: And tis a new extraordinary ammusing that distracts us from the common occupation of the world, indeed, and from the most recommended: Many years are past since I have no other aime whereto my thoughts bend, but my self, and that I controule and study nothing but my self. And if I study anything else, it is immediately to place it upon, or to say better in myself. And methinks I err not, as commonly men do in other sciences, without all comparison less profitable. I impart what I have content not my self therein. ’There is no description so hard, nor so profitable, as is the description of a man own life.’ Yet must a man handsomely trimme- up, indeed dispose and range himself to appeare on the Theatre of this world. Now I continually tricke up my self; for I uncessantly describe my self. Custome has made a mans speech of himself vicious, and obstinately forbids it in hatred of boasting, which ever seems closely to follow one’s self witnesses. Whereas a man should wipe the childs nose, that is now called to unnose himself. In vicium ducit culpæ fuga. -- Hor. Art. Poet. 31. Some shunning of some sinne, Doe draw some further in. I find more evil than good by this remedy: But suppose it were true, that for a man to entertaine the company with talking of himself were necessarily presumption, I ought not, following my general intent, to refuse an action that publisheth this crazed quality, since I have it in my seIfe: and I should not conceal this fault, which I have not only in use but in profession. Nevertheless, to speak my opinion of it, this custom to condemne wine is much to blame, because many are there with made drunke. Only good things may be abused. And I believe this rule has only regard to popular defects: They are snares wherewith neither Saints, nor Philosophers, nor Divines, whom we hear so gloriously to speak of themselves, will in any sort be bridled. No more do I, though I be no more the one than the other. If they write purposely or directly of it, yet when occasion does conveniently lead them unto it, faine they not head long to cast themselves into the lists? Whereof does Socrates treat more at large than of himself? To what does he more often direct his disciples discourses, than to speak of themselves, not for their bookes lesson, but of the essence and moving of their soul? We religiously shrive ourselves to God and our Confessor, as our neighbors to all the people. But will some answer me, we report but accusation; we then report all: For even our virtue itself is faulty and repentable. My art and profession is to live. Who forbids me to speak of it according to my sense, experience, and custom; let him appoint the Architect to speak of buildings, not according to himself, but his neighbors according to anothers skill, and not his own. If it be a glory for a man to publish his own worth himself, why does not Cicero prefer the eloquence of Hortensius, and Hortensius that of Cicero? Some may perhaps suppose that by deeds and effects, and not simply by words, I witness of my self. I principally set forth my cogitations; a shapelesse subject, and which cannot fall within the compasse of a workemanlike production; with much adoe can I set it down in this ayrie body of the voice. Wiser men, and more learned and devout, have lived avoiding all apparent effects. Effects would speak more of fortune than of me. They witness their part and not mine, unless it be conjecturally and unc ertainly: parcels of a particular show. I wholy set forth and expose my self: It is a Sceletos; where at first sight appeare all the vaines, muskles, gristles, sinnewes and tendons, each severall part in his due place. The effect of the cough produces, one part, that of palenesse or panting of the heart another, and that doubtfully. I write not my gests, but my self and my essence. I am of opinion that a man must be very wise to esteeme himself, and equally consciencious to give test imony of it: be it low, be it high indifferently. If I did absolutely seem good and wise unto my self, I would boldly declare it. To speak less of himself than he possesseth, is folly, and not modesty. To say himself for less than he is worth is basenesse and pusilanimity, says Aristotle. No virtue aids itself with false- hood, and truth is never a matter of error. And yet for a man to say more of himself than he can well prove, is not ever presumption though often sottishnesse. For a man to over-weene and please himself exceedingly with what he is, and fall into indiscreet love with himself, is in my conceit the substance of this vice. The best remedy to cure him, is to do cleane contrary to that which those appoint, who in forbidding men to speak of themselves, do consequentiy also inhibit more to think of themselves. Pride consisteth in conceit. The tongue can have no great share in it. For one to ammuse on himself is i n their imagination to please himself: And for a man to frequent and practise himself, is at an over-dear rate to please himself. But this excess does only breed in them, that but superficially feel and search themselves that are seen to follow their affairs, which call idleness and fondnesse for a man to entertaine, to applaud, and to endeare himself, and frame Chimeræs or build Castles in the air, deeming themselves as a third person and strangers to themselves. If any be besotted with his own knowledge looking upon himself, let him cast his eyes towards former ages, his pride shall be abated, his ambition shall be quailed; for there shall he find many thousands of spirits that will cleane suppress and tread him under. If he fortune to enter any self- presumption of his own worth, let him but call to remembrance the lives of Scipio and Epaminondas; so many armies, and so many Nations which leave him so far behind them. No particular quality shall make him proud, that therewith shall reckon so many imperfect and weak qualities that in him and at last the nullity of the human condition. Forasmuch as Socrates had truly only nibled on the precept of his God to know himself, and had learned to contemne himself, he alone was esteemed worthy of the name of Wise. Whosoever shall so know himself let him boldly make himself known by his own mouth. Return to : Book II CHAPTER VII: OF THE RECOMPENSES OR REWARDS OF HONOUR. CHAPTER VII: OF THE RECOMPENSES OR REWARDS OF HONOUR. HOSE which write the life of Augustas Cæsar note this in his military discipline, that he was exceeding liberal and lavish in his gifts to such as were of any desert; but as sparing and strait-handed in meere recompences of honor. Yet so it is that himself had been liberally gratified by his Unkle with militarie rewards, before ever he went to wars. It has been a witty invention, and received in most parts of the worlds Common-wealths, to establish and ordaine certain vain and worthles markes, therewith to honor and recompence virtue: As are the wreathes of Lawrell, the Chaplets of Oake, and the Garlands of Myrtle, the form of a certain peculiar garment; the privilege to ride in Coach through the City; or by night to have a Torch carried before one: Some particular place to sit in in common assemblies; the prerogatives of certain surnames and titles, and proper additions in arms, and such like things; the, use whereof has been diversly received according to the opinion of nations which continueth to this day. We have for our part, together with diverse of our neighbour- nations, the orders of knighthood, which only were established to this purpose. Verily it is a most laudable use and profitable custom, to find means to reward the worth and acknowledge the valor of rare and excellent men, to satisfie and content them with such payments as in no sort charge the commonwealth, and put the prince to no cost at all. And that which was ever known by ancient experience, and at other times we have plainly perceived amongst ourselves, that men of quality were ever more jealous of such recompences than of others wherein was both gain and profit, which was not without reason and great apparence. If to the prize, which ought simply to be of honor, there be other commodities and riches joined, this kind of commixing, instead of encreasing the estimation thereof, does empaire, dissipate, and abridge it. The order of the Knights of Saint Michæl in France, which of so long continuance has been in credit amongst as, had no greater commoditie than that it had no manner of communication with any other advantage or profit, which has heretofore been the cause that there was no charge or state of what quality soever, whereto the nobility pretended with so much desire, or aspired with more affection, as it did to obtaine that order; nor calling that was followed with more respect or greatness. Vertue embracing with more ambition, and more willingly aspiring after a recom pense, that is meerely and simply her own, and which is rather glorious than profitable. For, to say truth, other gifts have no use so worthy, inasmuch as they are employed to all manner of occasions. With riches a man does reward the service of a groom, the diligence of a messenger, the hopping of a dancer, the tricks of a vaulter, the breath of a lawyer, and the basest offices a man may receive; indeed, with the same paultry pelfe mony, vice is payed and sin requited, as flattery, murther, treason , Maquerelage, and what not? It is then no marvel, if virtue does less willingly desire this kind of common trash, mony, than that which is only proper and peculiar to herself, and is altogether noble and generous. Augustus had therefore reason to be much more niggardly amd sparing of this last than of the former, forasmuch as honor is a privilege that draws his preincipall essence from rareness; and so does verture itself. Cui malus est nemo, quis bonus esse potest? -- MART. xii. Epig. lxxxii To him who good can seem, Who does none bad esteeme? We shall not see a man highly regarded, or extraordinarily commended, that is curiously careful to have his children well nurtured, because it is a common action, how just and worthy praise soever it be, no more than one great tree, where the forrest is full of such. I do not think that any Spartane Citizen did boastingly glorifie himself for his valor, because it was a popular virtue in that nation, and as, little for his fidelity and contempt of riches. There is no recompence falls unto virtue, how great soever it be, if it once have past into custom; and I wot not whether we might call it great, being common. Since then the rewards of honor have no other prise and estimation than that few enjoy it, there is no way to disannul them but to make a largesse of them. Were there now more men found deserving the same than in former ages, yet should not the reputation of it be corrupted. And it may easily happen that more deserve it, for there is no virtue does so easily spread itself as military valiancie. There is another true, perfect, and philosophicall, whereof I speak not (I use this word according to our custom), far greater and more full than this,, which is a force and assurance of the soul, equally contemning all manner of contrary accidents, upright, uniform, and constant, whereof ours is but an easy and glimmering raie. Custome, institution, example and fashion, may effect what ever they list in the establishing of that I speak of, and easily make it vulgare, as may plainely be seen by the experience our civill wars give us of it. And whosoever could now join us together, and eagerly flesh all our people to a common enterprise, we should make our ancient military name and chivalrous credit to flourish again. It is most certain that the recompense of our order did not in former times only concerne prowis and respect valor; it had a further aime. It was never the reward or payment of a valiant souldier, but of a famous Captain. The skill to obey could not deserve so honorable an hire; for, cast we back our eyes to antiquity, we shall perceive that for the worthy obtaining thereof, there was required more universal warrelike expertnesse, and which might embrace the greatest part, and most parts of a military man. Neque enim eædem militares et imperatoriæ artes sunt, ’For the same arts and parts belong not to a general and common Souldier;’ and who besides that should also be of a fit and accommodable condition for such a dignitie. But I say, that if more men should now adayes be found worthy of it than have been heretofore, yet should not ounr princes be more liberall of it, and it had been much better not to bestow it upon all them to whom it was due, than for ever to lose, as of late we have done, the use of so profitable an invention. No man of courage vouchsafeth to advantage himself of that which is common unto many. And those which in our dayes be least merited that honorable recompence, seem, in all apparence, most to disdaine it, by that means place themselves in the rank of those to whom the wrong is offered by unworthy bestowing and vilifying of that badge which particularly was due unto them. Now by defacing and abolishing this to suppose, suddenly to be able to bring into credit and renew a semblable custom, is no convenient enterprise in so licentious, so corruptedi and so declining age, as is this wherein we now live. And it will come to pass that the last shall even from her birth incur the incommodities which have lately ruined and overthrowne the other. The rules of this new orders dispensation had need to be otherwise wrested and constrained for to give it authority, and this tumultuous season is not capable of a short and ordered bridle. Besides, before a man is able to give credit unto it, it is requisite a man lose the memory of the first, and of the contempt whereinto it is fallen. This place might admit some discourse upon the consideration of valor, and difference betweene this virtue and others. But Plutarch having often spoken of this matter, it were in vain here for me to repeat what he says of it. This is worthy to be considered, that our nation gives the chief preheminence of all virtue unto valiancie, as the etymology of the word sheweth, which cometh of valor or worth; and that according to our received custom, when after the phrase of our court and nobility we speak of a worthy man, or of an honest man, we thereby inferre no other thing than a valiant man; after the usual Roman fashion. For the general denomination of virtue does amongst them take her etymology of force or might. The only proper and essentiall form of our nobility in France is military vocation. It is very likely that the first virtue that ever appeared amongst men, and which to some has given preheminence over others, has been this by which the strongest and most courageous have become masters over the weakest, and purchased a particular rank and reputation to themselves. Whereby this honor and dignity of speech is left unto it: or else these nations, being very warlike, have given the price unto that of vertues, which was the worthiest and more familiar unto them. Even as our pa ssion, and this heart-panting and mind-vexing careful diligence, and diligent carefulnesse, which we continually apprehend about woman’s chastity, causeth also that a good woman, an honest woman, a woman of honor and virtue, does in effect and substance signifle no other thing unto us than a chaste wife or woman; as if to bind them to this duty, we did neglect all others, and give them free liberty to commit any other fault, to covenant with them never to quit or forsake this duty. Return to : Book II CHAPTER VIII: OF THE AFFECTIONS OF FATHERS TO THEIR CHILDREN. TO THE LADY OF ESTISSAC CHAPTER VIII: OF THE AFFECTIONS OF FATHERS TO THEIR CHILDREN. TO THE LADY OF ESTISSAC ADAME, if strangenesse do not save or novelty shield me, which are wont to give things reputation, I shall never, with honesty, quit myself of this enterprise yet is it so fantastic and bears a show so differient from common custom, that that may perhaps purchase it free passage. It is a melancholy humor, and consequently a hateful enemy to my natural complexion, bred by the anxietie and produced by the anguish of carking care, whereinto some years since I cast myself, that first put this humorous conceipt of writing into my head. And finding myself afterward wholy unprovided of subject, and void of other matter, I have presented myself unto myself for a subject to write and argument to descant upon. It is the only book in the world of this kind, and of a wild extravagant designe. Moreover, there is nothing in it worthy the marking but this fantasticalnesse. For, to so vain a ground and base a subject, the worlds best workman could never have given a fashion deserving to be accompted of. Not (worthy Lady) sithence I must portray my self to the life, I should have forgotten a part of importance, if therewithall I had not represented the honor I have ever yielded to your deserts, which I have especially been willing to declare in the forefront of this chapter; Forasmuch as amongst your other good parts and commendable qualities, that of loving amity, which you have shewen to your children, holdeth one of the first rankes. Whosoever shall understand and know the age, wherein your late husband the Lord of Estissac left you a Widdow, the great, and honorable matches have been offered you (as worthy and as many as to any other Lady in France of your condition) the constant resolution, and resolute constancy, wherewith so many years you have sustained, and even in spight or athwart so manifold thorny difficulties, the charge and conduct of their affairs, which have tossed, turmoyled and removed you in all comers of France, and still hold you besieged; the happy and successfull forwardnes you, which only through your wisdom or good fortune have given them, he will easily say with me, that in our age we have no patterne of motherly affecttion more exemplarie than yours. I praise God (Madame) it hathe been so well employed : For, the good hopes, which the young Lord of Estissac, your son, gives of himself, fore-show he shall come to an undoubted assurance that when he shall come to years of discretion, you shall reape the obedience of a noble, and find the acknowledgement of a good child. But because, by reason of his child-hood, he could not take notice of the exceeding kindness and many-fold offices he has received from you, my meaning is, that if ever these my compositions shall perhaps one day come into his hands (when perhaps I shall neither have mouth nor speech to declare it unto him), he receive this testimony in all veritie from me; which shall also more lively be testified unto him by the good effects, (whereof, if so it please God, be shall have a sensible feeling) that there is no Gentleman in France more endebted to his mother than he; and that hereafter he cannot yield a more certain proofe of his goodnes, and testimony of his virtue, than in acknowledging and confessing you for such. If there be any truly-natural law, that is to say, any instinct, universally and perpetually imprinted, both in beasts and us, (which is not without controversie) I may, according to mine opinion, say, that next to the care which each living creature has to his preservation, and to flie what does hurt him, the affection which the engenderer beareth his off-spring holds the second place in this rank. And forasmuch as nature seems to have recommended the same unto us, ayming to extend, encrease, and advance the successive parts or parcels of this her frame; it is no wonder if back again it is not so great from children unto fathers. This other Aristotelian consideration remembred: that he who does benefit another, loves him better than he is beloved of him again; and he to whom a debt is owing, loves better than he that oweth: And every workman loves his work better than he should be beloved of it again, if it had sense or feeling. Forasmuch as we love to be, and being consisteth in moving and action; therefore is every man, in some sort or other, in his own workmanship. Whosoever does a good deed, exerciseth a fair and honest action: whosoever receiveth exerciseth only a profitable action. And profit is nothing so much to be esteemed or loved as honesty. Honesty is firme and permanent, affording him that did it a constant gratification. Profit is very slipperie and easily lost, nor is the memory of it so sweet or so fresh. Such things are dearest unto us, that have cost us most; and to give is of more cost that to take. Since it has pleased God to endow us with some capacitie of discourse, that as beasts we should not servily be subjected to common laws, but rather with judgement and voluntary liberty apply ourselves unto them; we ought somewhat to yield unto the simple auctoritie of Nature, but not suffer her tyranny to carry us away: only reason ought to have the conduct of our inclinations. As for me, my tast is strangely distasted to its propensions, which in us are produced without the ordinance and direction of our judgement. As upon this subject I speak of, I cannot receive this passion, wherewith some embrace children scarsly borne, having neither motion in the soul, nor form well to be distinguished in the body whereby they might make themselves lovely or amiable. And I could never well endure to have them brought up or nursed near about me. A true and well ordered affection ought to be borne and augmented, with the knowledge they owe us of themselves; and then, if they deserve it (natural inclination marching hand in hand with reason) to cherish and make much of them, with a perfect fatherly love and loving friendship, and conformably to judge of them if they be otherwise, alwayes yielding ourselves unto reason, notwithstanding natural power. For the most part, it goeth cleane contrary, and commonly we feel ourselves more moved with the sports, idlenesses wantonnesse, and infant-trifles of our children, than afterward we do with all their actions, when they be men: As if we had loved them for our pastimes, as we do apes, monkies, or perokitoes, and not as man. And some that liberally furnish them with sporting bables while they be children, will miserably pinch it in the least expense for necessaries when they grow men. Nay, it seems that the jelousie we have to see them appeare into, and injoy the world, when we are ready to leave them, makes us more sparing and close-handed toward them. It vexeth and grieveth us when we see them following us at our heels, supposing they solicite us to be gone hence: And if we were to fear that since the order of things beareth, that they cannot indeed, neither be, nor live, but by our being and life, we should not meddle to be fathers. As for me, I deem it a kind of cruelty and injustice, not to receive them into the share and society of our goods, and to admit them as Partners in the understanding of our domestical affairs (if they be once capable of it and not to cut off and shut-up our commodities to provide for theirs, since we have engendred them to that purpose. It is meere injustice to see an old, crazed, sinnow-shronken, and nigh dead father sitting alone in a Chimny-corner, to enjoy so many goods as would suffice for the preferment and entertainment of many children, and in the meane while, for want of means, to suffer them to lose their best dayes and years, without thrusting them into public service and knowledge of men; whereby they are often cast into despair, to seek, by some way how unlawfull soever to provide for their necessaries. And in my dayes, I have seen diverse yong-men, of good houses so given to stealing and filching, that no correction could divert them from it. I know one very well alied, to whom, at the instance of a brother of his (a most honest, gallant, and vertuous Gentleman) I spake to that purpose, who boldly answered and confessed unto me, that only by the rigor and covetism of his father he had been forced and driven to fall into such lewdnesse and wickednesse. And even at that time he came from stealing certain jewels from a Lady, in whose bed-chamber he fortuned to come with certain other Gentlemen when she was rising, and had almost been taken. He made me remember a tale I had heard of another Gentleman, from his youth so fashioned and inclined to this goodly trade of pilfering that coming afterward to be heir and Lord of his own goods, resolved to give over that manner of life, could notwithstanding (if he chanced to come near a shop, where he saw any thing he stood in need of) not chuse but steale the same, though afterward he would ever send mony and pay for it. And I have seen diverse so inured to that vice, that amongst their companions they would ordinarily steale such things as they would restore again. I am a Gascoine, and there is no vice wherein I have less skill: I hate it somewhat more by complexion than I accuse it by discourse. I do not so much as desire another mans goods. And although my Countrey-men be indeed somewhat more taxed with this fault than other Provinces of France, yet have we seen, of late dayes, and that sundry times, men well borne and of good parentage in other parts of France, in the hands of justice, and lawfully convicted of many most horrible robberies. I am of opinion that in regard of these debauches and lewd actions, fathers may, in so me sort, be blamed, and that it is only long of them. And if any shall answer me, as did once a Gentleman of good worth and understanding, that he thriftily endevoured to hoard up riches, to no other purpose, nor to have any use and commodity of them, than to be honoured, respected and suingly sought unto by his friends and kinsfolke and that age having bereaved him of all other forces, it was the only remedy he had left to maintaine him self in authority with his houshold, and keep him from falling into contempt and disdaine of all the world. And truly according to Aristotle, not only old-age, but each imbecility, is the promoter and motive of covetousnesse. That is something, but it is a remedy for an evil, whereof the birth should have been hindered, and breeding avoyded. That father may truly be said miserable that holdeth the affection of his children tied unto him by no other means than by the need they have of his helpe, or want of his assistance, if that may be termed affection: A man should yield himself respectable by virtue and sufficiency, and amiable by his goodnesse, and gentlenesse of manners. The very cinders of so rich a matter have their value: so have the bones and relics of honorable men, whom we hold in respect and reverence. No age can be so crazed and drooping in a man that has lived honourably, but must needs prove venerable, and especially unto his children, whose minds ought so to be directed by the parents, that reason and wisdom, not necessity and need, nor rudenesse and compulsion, may make them know and performe their dutie. ----- et errat longe, mea quidem sententia, Qui imperium credat esse gravius aut stabilius, Vi quod fit, quam illud quod amicitia adjungitur. --Ter. Adelph. act. i. sc. i. 39. In mine opinion he does much mistake, Who, that command more grave, more firme does take, Which force does get, than that which friendships make. I utterly condemne all manner of violence in the education of a young spirit, brought up to honor and liberty. There is a kind of slavishnesse in churlish rigour and servility in compulsion; and I hold that that which cannot be compassed by reason, wisdom, and discretion, can never be attained by force and constraint. So was I brought up: they tell me that in all my youth I never felt rod but twice, and that very lightly. And what education I have had myself, the same have I given my children. But such is my ill hap, that they dye all very yong: yet has Leonora my only daughter escaped this misfortune, and attained to the age of six years, and somewhat more; for the conduct of whose youth and punishment childish faults (the indulgence of her mother applying itself very mildly unto it) was never other means used but gentle words. And were my desire frustrate there are diverse other causes to take hold of without reproving my discipline, which I know to be just and natural. I would also have been much more religious in that towards male- children, not borne to serve as women and of a freer condition. I should have loved to have stored their mind with ingenuity and liberty. I have seen no other effects in rods, but to make childrens mindes more remisse, or more maliciously headstrong. Desire we to be loved of our children! Will we remove all occasions from them to wish our death? (although no occasion of so horrible and unnaturall wishes can either be just or excusable) nullum scelus rationem habet, no ill deed has a good reason. Let us reasonably accommodate their life with such things as are in our power. And therefore should not we marry so young that our age do in a manner confound itself with theirs. For, this inconvenience does unavoidably cast us into many difficulties and encombrances. This I speak chiefly unto nobility, which is of an idle disposition, or loitering condition, and which (as we say) liveth only by her lands or rents: for else, where life standeth upon gain, plurality and company of children is an easefull furtherance of husbandry. They are as many new implements to thrive, and instruments to grow rich. I was married at thirty years of age and commend the opinion of thirty-five, which is said to be Aristotles. Plato would have no man married before thirty, and has good reason to scoffe at them that will defer it till after fifty-five and then marry; and condemneth their breed as unworthy of life and sustenance. Thales appointed the best limits, who by his mother being instantly urged to marry while he was young, answered that it was not yet time; and when he came to be old, he said it was no more time. A man must refuse opportunity to every importunate action. The ancient Gaules deemed it a shamefull reproach to have the acquaintance of a woman before the age of twenty years; and did especially recommend unto men that sought to be trained up in wars the careful preservation of their maiden-head until they were of good years, forasmuch as by losing it in youth, courages are thereby much weakned and greatly empaired, and by coupling with women diverted from all vertuous action. Ma hor congiunto i giovinetta sposa, Lieto homai de’ figli’, era invilito Ne gli afetti di padre et di marito. But now conjoyn’d to a fresh-springing spouse, Joy’d in his children, he was thought-abased, In passions twixt a sire and husband placed. Muleasses King of Thunes, he whom the Emperor Charles the fifth restored unto his own state again, was wont to upbraid his fathers memory for so dissolutely-frequenting of women, terming him a sloven, effeminate, and a lustfull engenderer of children. The Greek story does note Iccus the Tarentine, Crisso, Astyllus, Diopompus, and thers, who to keep their bodies tough and strong for the service of the Olympicke courses, wrestlings and such bodily exercises they did, as long as they were possessed with that care, heedefully abstaine from all venerian acts and touching of women. In a certain country of the Spanish Indies, no man was suffered to take a wife before he were thirty years old, and women might marry at ten years of age. There is no reason, neither is it convenient, that a Gentleman of five and thirty years should give place to his son, that is but twenty: For then is the father as seemly and may as well appear and set himself forward, in all manner of voyages of wars as well by land as sea, and do his prince as good service, in court or elsewhere, as his son: He has need of all his parts and ought truly to impart them, but so that be forget not himself for others: And to such may justly that answer serve which fathers have commonly in their mouthes: ’I will not put off my clothes before I be ready to go to bed.’ But a father over-burdened with years and crazed through sicknesse and by reason of weaknesse and want of health barred from the common society of men, does both wrong himself, injure his, idly and to no use to hoord up and keep close a great heape of riches and deal of pelfe. He is in state good enough, if he be wise to have a desire to put off his clothes to go to bed. I will not say to his shirt, but to a good warme night gowne, As for other pomp and trash whereof he has no longer use or need, he ought willingly to distribute and bestow them amongst those to whom by natural degree they ought to belong. It is reason he should have the use and bequeath the fruition of them, since nature does also deprive him of them, otherwise without doubt there is both envy and malice stirring. The worthiest action that ever the Emperor Charles the fifth performed was this, in imitation of some ancients of his quality, that he had the discretion to know that reason commanded us to strip or shift our selves when our cloathes trouble and are too heavy for us, and that it is high time to go to bed when our legs faile us. He resigned his means, his greatness and Kingdome to his Sonne, at what time he found his former undanted resolution to decay, and force to conduct his affairs to droope in himself, together with the glory he had thereby acquired. Solve senescentem m ature sanus equum ne Peccet ad extremum ridentus, et ilia ducat. -- Hor. i. Ep. i. 8. If you be wise, the horse grown-old betimes cast-off, Lest he at last fall lame, foulter, and breed a skoffe. This fault for a man not to be able to know himself betimes and not to feel the impuissance and extreme alteration that age does naturally bring, both to the body and the mind (which in my opinion is equall if the mind has but one halfe), has lost the reputation of the most part of the great men in the world. I have in my dayes both seen and familiarly knowen some men of great authority, whom a man might easily discerne, to be strangely fallen from that ancient sufficiency, which I know by the reputation they had thereby attained unto in their best years. I could willingly for their honors sake have wisht them at home about their own business, discharged from all negotiations of the commonwealth and employments of war that were no longer fit for them. I have sometimes been familiar in a Gentleman’s house, who was both an old man and a widdower, yet lusty of his age. This man had many daughters marriageable and a son grown to mans state and ready to appeare in the world; a thing that drew-on and was the cause of great charges and many visitations, wherein he took but little pleasure, not only for the continuall care he had to save but more by reason of his age, he had betoken himself to a manner of life far different from ours. I chanced one day to tell him somewhat boldly (as my custom is) that it would better beseeme him to give us place and resigne his chief house to his son (for he had no other mannor-house conveniently well furnished), and quietly retire himself to some farme of his where no man might trouble him or disturbe his rest, since he could not otherwise avoid our importunitie, seeing the condition of his children; who afterward followed my counsell and found great ease by it. It is not to be said that they hate any thing given them by such a way of obligation, which a man may not recall again: I, that am ready to play such a part, would give over unto them the full possession of my house and enjoying of my good and limited condition as if they should give me occasion, I might repent myself of my gift and revoke my deed. I would leave the use and fruition of all unto them, the rather because it were no longer fit for me to weald the same. And touching the disposing of all matters in grosse, I would reserve what I pleased unto my self. Having ever judged that it must be a great contentment to an aged father, himself to direct his children in the government of his household affairs, and to be able while himself liveth to checks and controule their demeanors, storing them with instruction and advised counsell, according to the experience he has had of them, and himself to address the ancient honor and order of his house in the hands of his successours, and that way warrant himself of the hope he may conceive of their future conduct and or success. And to this effect I would not shun their company. I would not be far from them, but as much as the condition of my age would permit, enjoy and be a partner of their sports, mirths, and feasts. If I did not continually live amongst them (as I could not well without offending their meetings and hindering their recreation, by reason of the peevish forwardnesse of my age and the trouble of my infirmities, and also without forcing their rules, and resisting the form of life I should then follow), I would at least live near them, in some corner of my house, not the best and fairest in show, but the most easefull and commodious. And not, as some years since I saw a Deane of S. Hillarie of Poictiers, reduced by reason and the incommoditie of his melancholy to such a continuall solitarinesse, that when I entered into his chamber he had never removed one step out of it in two and twenty years before; yet had all his faculties free and easy, only a rheume excepted that fell into his stomacke. Scarce once a weeke would he suffer any body to come and see him. He would ever be shut up in his chamber all alone, where no man should come, except a boy, who once a day brought him meat, and who might not tarry there, but as soone as he was in must go out again. All his exercise was sometimes to walke up and down his chamber, aud now and then read on some book (for he had some understanding of letters) but obstinately resolved to live and dye in that course, as he did shortly after. I would endeavor by a kind of civil demeanour and mild conversation to breede and settle in my children a true- harty loving friendship, and unfained good will towards me: a thing easily obtained amongst well-borne mindes, For if they prove, or be such surly-furious beasts, or given to churlish disobedience, as our age bringeth forth thousands, they must as beasts be hated, as churls neglected, and as degenerate avoided. I hate this custom, to forbid children to call their fathers father, and to teach them another strange name, as of more reverence; as if nature had not sufficiently provided for our authority. We call God Almighty by the name of father, and disdaine our children should call us so. I have reformed this fault in my own household. It is also folly and injustice to deprive children, especially being of competent age, of their fathers familiaritie, and ever to show them a surly, austere, grim, and disdainefall countenance, hoping thereby, to keep them in awful fear and duteous obedience. For it is a very unprofitable proceeding and which maketh fathers yrkesome unto children, and which is worse, ridiculous. They have youth and strength in their hands, and consequently the breath and favor of the world; and do with mockery and contempt receive these churlish, fierce, and tyrannical countenances, from a man that has no lusty blood left him, neither in his heart nor in his vaines; meere bugbeares, and scar- crowes, to scare birdes withall. If it lay in my power to make my self feared, I had rather make my self beloved. There are so many sorts of defects in age, and so much impuissance; it is so subject to contempt, that the best purchase it can make is the good will, love and affection of others. Commandement and fear are no longer her weapons. I have known one whose youth had been very imperious and rough, but when he came to mans age, although he live in as good plight and health as may be, yet he chaseth, he scoldeth, he brawleth, he fighteth, he sweareth, and biteth, as the most boistrous and tempestuous master of France; he frets and consumes himself with carke and care and vigilancy (all which is but a jugling and ground for his familiar to play upon, and cozen him the more) as for his goods, his garners, his cellars, his coffers, indeed his purse, whilst himself keepes the keyes of them close in his bosome and under his boulster, as charily as he does his eyes, other enjoy and command the better part of them; whilst he pleaseth and flattereth himself with the niggardly sparing of his table, all goth to wracke, and is lavishly wasted in diverse corners of his house, in play, in riotous spending, and in soothingly entertaining the accompts or tales of his vain chasing, foresight, and providing. Every man watcheth and keepeth sentinell against him, if any silly or heedless servant do by fortune apply himself unto it, he is presently made to suspect him. A quality on which age does immediately bite of itself. How many times has he vaunted and applauding himself the strict orders of his house, of his good husbandry, of the awe he kept his household in, and of the exact obedience and regardfull reverence he received of all his family, and how clear-sighted he was in his own business: Ille solus nescit omnia. -- Ter. Adel. act. iv. sc. ii. 9. Of all things none but he, Most ignorant must be. I know no man that could produce more parts, both natural and artificiall, fit to preserve his masterie, and to maintaine his absolutenesse, than he does; yet is he cleane falne from them like a child. Therefore have I made choice of him amongst many such conditions that I know, as most exemplare. It were a matter beseeming a scholasticall question, whether it be better so or otherwise. In his presence all things give place unto him. This vain course is ever left unto his authority, that he is never gain-said. He is had in awe, he is feared, he is beleeved, he is respected his belly-full, Does he discharge any boy or servant? he presently trusseth up his packe, then he is gone; but whither? only out of his sight, not out of his house. The steps of age are so slow, the senses so troubled, the mind so distracted, that he shall live and do his office a whole year in one same house, and never be perceived. And when fit time or occasion serveth, letters are produced from far places, humbly suing and pittifully complayning, with promises to do better and to amend, by which he is brought into favor and office again. Does the master make any bargaine or dispatch that pleaseth not, it is immediately smothered and supressed soon after forging causes, and devising colourable excuses, to excuse the want of execution or answer. No forraine letters being first presented unto him, he seeth but such as are fit for his knowledge. lf perhaps they come into his hands, as he that trusteth some one of his men to read them unto him, he will presently devise what he thinketh good, whereby they often invent that such a one seems to aske him forgivenesse, that wrongeth him by his letter. To conclude, he never looks into his own business, but by a disposed, designed and as much as may be pleasing image, so contrived by such as are about him, because they will not stir up his choler, move his impatience, and exasperate his frowardnesse. I have seen under different formes many long and constant, and of like effect, economies. It is ever proper unto women to be readily bent to contradict and crosse their husbands. They will with might and main, hand over head, take hold of any colour to thwart and withstand them: the first excuse they meet with serves them as a plenary justification. I have seen some that would in grosse steale from their husbands to the end (as they told their Confessor) they might give the greater almes. Trust you to such religious dispensations. They think no liberty to have or managing to possesse sufficient authority, if it come from their husbands consent: They must necessarily usurpe it, either by wily craft or main force, and ever iniuriously, thereby to give it more grace and authority. As in my discourse, when it is against a poore old man, and for children, then take they hold of this title, and therewith gloriously serve their turn and passion, and as in a common servitude, easily usurpe and monopolize against his government and domination. If they be men-children, tall, of good spirit, and forward, then they presently suborne, either by threats, force, or favor, both Steward, Bailiffe, Clarke, Receiver, and all the Fathers Officers, and Servant. Such as have neither wife nor children, do more hardly fall into his mischief; but yet more cruelly and unworthily. Old Cato was wont to say, ’So many servants, so many enemies.’ Note whether according to the distance that was between the purity of his age, and the corruption of our times, he did not fore-warne us that wives, children, and servants are to us so many enemies. Well fits it decrepitude to store us with the sweet benefit of ignorance and unperceiving facility wherewith we are deceived. If we did yield unto it, what would become of us? Doe we not see that even then if we have any suits in lawe, or matters to be decided before Judges, both Lawyers and Judges will commonly take part with and favor our childrens causes against us, as men interested in the same? And if I chance not to spy or plainly perceive how I am cheated, cozoned and beguiled, I must of necessitie discover in the end how I am subject, and may be cheated, beguiled, and cozened. And shall the tongue of man ever be able to express the ynvaluable worth of a friend, in comparison of these civill bonds? The lively image and idea whereof I perceive to be among beasts so unspotted. Oh, with what religion do I respect and observe the same! If others deceive me, yet do I not deceive my self, to esteeme my self capable and of power to looke unto my self, nor to trouble my braines to yield my self unto it. I do beware and keep my self from such treas ons, and cunny-catching in my own bosome, not by an unquiet and tumultuary curiosity, but rather by a diversion and resolution. When I hear the state of any one reported or discoursed of, I ammuse not my self on him, but presently cast mine eyes on my self, and all my wits together, to see in what state I am, aud how it goeth with me. Whatsoever concerneth him, the same has relation to me. His fortunes forewarn me, and summon up my spirits that way; There is no day nor hour but we speak that of others we might properly speak of ourselves, could we as well enfold as we can infold our consideration. And many authours do in this manner wound the protection of their cause by over-rashly running against that which they take hold of, thirling such darts at their enemies that might with much more advantage be cast at them. The Lord of Montluc, late one of the Lord Marshals of France, having lost his son, who died in the Iland of Madera, a worthy, forward and gallant young gentleman, and truely of good hope, amongst other his griefes and regrets did greatly move me to condole the infinite displeasure and hearts-sorrow that he felt, inasmuch as he had never communicated and opened himself vnto him: for, with his austere humor and continuall endeavoring to hold a grimme-stern-fatherly gravity over him, he had lost the means perfectly to find and throughly to know his son, and so to manifest vnto him the extreme affection he bare him, and the worthy judgement he made of his virtue. ’Alas,’ was he wont to say, ’the poore lad saw never anything in me but a severe-surly countenance, full of disdaine, and perhaps was possessed with this conceit, that I could neither love nor esteeme him according to his merits. Ay-me, to whom did I reserve, to discover that singular and loving affection which in my soul I bare unto him? Was it not he that should have had all the pleasure and acknowledgenient thereof? I have forced and tormented my self to maintaine this vain maske, and have vtterly lost the pleasure of his conversation, and therwithal his good will, which surely was but faintly cold towards me, forasmuch as he never received but rude entertainement of me, and never felt but a tyrannical proceeding in me towards him. I am of opinion his complaint was reasonable and well grounded. For, as I know by certain experience, there is no comfort so sweet in the loss of friends, as that our own knowledge or conscience tels vs we never omitted to tell them everything, and expostulate all matters vnto them, and to have had a perfect and free communication with them. Tell me, my good friend, am I the better or the worse by having a taste of it? Surely I am much the better. His grief does both comfort and honor me. Is it not a religious and pleasing office of my life for ever to make the obsequies thereof? Can there be any pleasure worth this privation? I do unfold and open my self as much as I can to my own people, and willingly declare the state of my will and judgment towards them, as commonly I do towards all men: I make haste to produce and present my self, for I would have no man mistake me, in what part soever. Amongst other particular customs which our ancient Gaules had as Cæsar affirmeth), this was one, that children never came before their fathers, nor were in any public assembly seen in their company, but when they began to bear arms: as if they would infer that then was the time fathers should admit them to their acquaintance and familiarity. I have also observed another kind of indiscretion in some fathers of our times, who during their own life would never be induced to acquaint or impart unto their children that share or portion which, by the Law of Nature, they were to have in their fortunes: nay, some there are who, after their death, bequeath and commit the same auctoritie over them and their goods , unto their wives, with full power and law to dispose of them at their pleasure. And my self have knowen a Gentleman, a chief officer of our crowne, that by right and hope of succession (had he lived unto it) was to inherit above fifty thousand crownes a yeere good land, who at the age of more then fifty yeeres, fell into such necessity and want, and was run so far in debt, that he had nothing left him, and, as it is supposed, died for very need: while his mother, in her extreme decrepitude, enjoyed all his lands and possessed all his goods, by virtue of his fathers will and testament, who had lived very near foure-score years: a thing (in my conceit) no way to be commended, but rather blamed. Therefore do I think that a man but little advantaged or bettered in estate who is able to liue of himself, and is out of debt, especially if he have children, and goeth about to marry a wife that must have a great joynter out of his lands, assuredly there is no other debt that brings more ruine vnto houses than that. My predecessors have commonly followed this counsell, and so have I, and all have found good by it. But those that disswade vs from marrying of rich wives, lest they might proove over disdainful and peevish, or less tractable and loving, are also deceived to make us neglect and forgoe a reall commoditie for so frivolous a conjecture, To an unreasonable woman, it is all one cost to her whether they pass under one reason or under another. ’They love to be where they are most wronged.’ Injustice does allure them, as the honor of their vertuous actions enticeth the good. And by how much richer they are, so much more mild and gentle are they; as more willingly and gloriously chaste, by how much fairer they are. Some colour of reason there is, men should leave the administration of their goods and affairs unto mothers while their children are not of competent age, or fit according to the laws to manage the charge of them: And ill has their father brought them up, if he cannot hope, these coming to years of discretion, they shal have no more wit, reason, and sufficiencie, than his wife, considering the weaknesse of their sexe. Yet truly were it as much against nature so to order things that mothers must wholy depend on their childrens discretion. They ought largely and competently to be provided wherewith to maintaine their estate according to the quality of their house and age: because ’need and want is much more unseemely and hard to he indured in women than in men:’ And children rather than mothers ought to be charged therewith. In general, my opinion is that the best distribution of goods is, when we die, to distribute them according to the custom of the Country. The laws have better thought upon them than we: And better is it to let them erre in their election than for us rashly to hazard to faile in ours. They are not properly our own, since without us, and by a civil prescription, they are appointed to certain successours. And albeit we have some further liberty, I think it should be a great and most apparent cause to induce us to take from one, and barre him from that which Fortune has allotted him, and the common laws and Justice has called him unto: And that against reason we abuse this liberty, by suting the same unto our private humors and frivolous fantasies. My fortune has been good, inasmuch as yet it never presented me with any occasions that might tempt or divert my affections from the common and lawful ordinance. I see some towards whom it is but labor lost, carefully to endeavor to do any good offices. A word ill taken defaceth the merit of ten yeeres. Happy he that, at this last passage, is ready to sooth and applaud their will. The next action transporteth him; not the best and most frequent offices, but the freshest and present work the deede. They are the people that play with their wils and testaments as with apples and rods, to gratify or chastize every action of those who pretend any interest thereunto. It is a matter of over- long pursute, and of exceeding consequence, at every instance to be thus dilated, and wherein the wiser sort establish themselves once for all, chiefely respecting reason and public observance. We somewhat over-much take these masculine substitutions to hart, and propose a ridiculous eternity unto our names. We also over-weight such vain future conjectures, which infant-spirits give us. It might perhaps have been from out my rancke, because I was the dullest, the slowest, the unwillingest, the most leaden-pated to learn my lesson or any good, that ever was not only of all my brethren, but of all the children in my countrie, were the lesson concerning my exercise of the mind or body. It is folly to trie any extraordinarie conclusions upon the trust of their divinations, wherein we are so often deceived. If this rule may be contradicted, and the destinies corrected, in the choice they have made of our heirs, with so much more apparence, may it be done in consideration of some remarkable and enormous corporall deformitie; a constant and incorrigible vice; and according to us great esteemers of beautie; a matter of important prejudice. The pleasant dialogue of Plato the law-giver, with his citizens, will much honor this passage: "Why then,’ say they, perceiving their end to approach, ’shall we not dispose of that which, is our own to whom and according as we please? O Gods, what cruelty is this? That it shall not be lawfull for us to give or bequeath more or less, according to our fantasies, to such as have served us, and taken paines with us in our sicknesses, in our age, and in our business?’ To whom the law-giver answereth in this manner: ’My friends,’ says he, ’who doubtlesse shall shortly die, it is a hard matter for you both to know yourselves and what is your’s according to the Delphike inscription: As for me, who am the maker of your laws, I am of opinion that neither yourselves are your own, nor that which you enjoy. And both you and your goods, past and to come, belong to your familie; and, moreover, both your families and your goods are the commonwealth’s. Wherefore, lest any flatterer, either in your age or in time of sickness, or any other passion, should unadvisedly induce you to make any unlawfull conveyance or unjust will and testament, I will looke to you and keep you from it. But having an especiall respect both to the universall interest of your City, and particular state of your houses, I will establish laws, and by reason make you perceive and confesse that a particular commoditie ought to yield to a public benefit. Follow that course meerely whereto humane necessitie does call you.’ To me it belongeth, who have no more regard to one thing than to another, and who, as much as I can, take care for the general, to have a regardful respect of that which you leave behind you. But to return to my former discourse, me thinkes we seldom see that woman borne to whom the superioritie or majestie over men is due, except the motherly and natural; unless it be for the chastisement of such as by some fool-febricitant humor have voluntarily submitted themselves unto them: But that does nothing concerne old women, of whom we speak here. It is the apparence of this consideration has made us to frame and willingly to establish this law (never seen elsewhere) that barreth women from the succession of this crowne, and there are few principalities in the world where it is not alleged, as well as here, by a likely and apparent reason, which authoriseth the same. But fortune has given more credit unto it in some places than in other some. It is dangerous to leave the dispensation of our succession unto their judgement, according to the choyse they shall make of their children, which is most commonly unjust and fantastic. For the same unrulie appetite and distasted relish, or strange longings, which they have when they are great with child, the same have they at al times in their minds. They are commonly seen to affect the weakest, the simplest and most abject, or such, if they have any, that had more need to sucke. For, wanting reasonable discourse to chuse, and embrace what they ought, they rather suffer themselves to be directed where nature’s impressions are most single as other creatures, which take no longer knowledge of their yonng ones than they are sucking. Moreover, experience does manifestly show unto us that the same natural affection to which we ascribe so much authority, has but a weake foundation. For a very small gain we daily take mothers own children from them and induce them to take charge of ours. Doe we not often procure them to bequeath their children to some foolish, filthie, sluttish, and unhealthie nurce, to whom we would be very loth to commit ours, or to some brutish goat, not only forbidding them to nurce and feed their own children, what danger soever may betide them, but also to have any care of them, to the end they may the more diligently follow and carefully attend the service of ours? Whereby we soone see through custom a certain kind of bastard affection to be engendered in them, more vehement than the natural, and to be much more tender and careful for the welfare and preservation of other men’s children than for their own. And the reason why I have made mention of goats is, because it is an ordinary thing round about me where I dwell to see the countrie women, when they have not milke enough to feed their infants with their own breasts, to call for goats to helpe them. And myself have now two lackies wayting on me, who except it were eight days never suck’t other milk than goats. They are presently to come at call and give young infants sucke, and become so well acquainted with their voice that when they hear them crie they run forthwith unto them. And if by chance they have any other child put to their teats then their nurseling, they refuse and reject him, and so does the child a strange goat. Myselfe saw that one not long since, from whom the father took a goat, which he had sucked two or three days, because he had but borrowed it of one of his neighbors, who could never be induced to sucke any other, where by he shortly died, and, as I verily think, of meere hunger. Beasts, as well as we, do soon alter, and easily bastardize their natural affection. I believe that in that which Herodotus reporteth of a certain province of Libia, their often followeth great error and- mistaking. He says that men do indifferently use, and as it were in common frequent women, and that the child, as soone as he is able to go, coming to any solemn meetings and great assemblies, led by a natural instinct, findeth out hes own father; where being turned loose in the middest of the multitude, looke what man the child does first addresse his steps unto, and then go to him, the same is ever afterward reputed to be his right father. Now if we shall duly consider this simple occasion of loving our children, because we have begotten them, for which we call them our other selves; it seems there is another production coming from us, and which is of no less recommendation and consequence. For what we engender by the mind, the fruits of our courage, sufficiencie, or spirit, are brought forth by a far more noble part than the corporall, and more our own. We are both father and mother together in this generation; such fruits cost us much dearer and bring us more honor, and chiefly if they have any good or rare thing in them. For the value of our other children is much more theirs than ours. The share we have in them is but little, but of these all the beautie, all the grace, and all the worth is ours. And therefore do they represent and resemble us much more lively than others. Plato addeth, moreover, that these are immortant issues, and immortalize their fathers, indeed desire them, as Licurgus, Solon, and Minos. All histories being full of examples of this mutual friendship of fathers toward their children, I have not thought it amisse to set down some choice ones of this kind. Heliodorus, that good Bishop of Tricea, loved rather to lose the dignity, profit, and devotion of so venerable a prelateship than to forgoe his daughter, a young woman to this day commended for her beautie, but perhaps somewhat more curiously and wantonly pranked up than beseemed the daughter of a churchman and a Bishop, and of over-amorous behaviour. There was one Labienus, in Rome, a man of great worth and authority, and amongst other commendable qualities, most excellent in all manner of learning, who, as I think, was the son of that great Labienus, chief of all the captaines that followed and were under Cæsar in the wars against the Gaules, and who afterward taking great Pompey’s part, behaved himself so valiantly and so constantly, that he never forsooke him until Cæsar defeated him in Spain. This Labienus, of whom I spake, had many that envied his vertues: but above all, as it is likely, courtiers, and such as in his time were favored of the Emperors, who hated his franknesse, his fatherly humors, and distaste he bare still against tyrannie, wherewith it may be supposed he had stuffed his bookes and compositions. His adversaries vehemently pursued him before the magistrate of Rome, and prevailed so far that many of his works which he had published were condemned to be burned. He was the first on whom this new example of punishment was put in practice, which after continued long in Rome, and executed on diverse others, to punish learning, studies, and writings with death and consuming fire. There were neither means enough, or matter sufficient of crueltie, unless we had entermingled among them things which nature has exempted from all sense and sufferance, as reputation, and the inventions of our mind: and except we communicated corporall mischiefs unto disciplines and monuments of the muses. Which loss Labienus could not endure, nor brooke to survive those his dear and highly-esteemed issues, and therefore caused himself to be carried, and shut up alive within his authors monument, where, with a dreadlesse resolution, he at once provided both to kill himself and be buried together. It is hard to show any more vehement fatherly affection than that. Cassius Severus, a most eloquent man, and his familiar friend, seeing his bookes burnt, exclaimed, that by the same sentence he should therewithall be condemned to be burned alive, for he still bare and kept in mind what they contained in them. A like accident happened to Geruntius Cordus, who was accused to have commended Brutus and Cassius in his bookes. That base, senile, and corrupted Senate, and worthie of a far worse master than Tiberius, adjudged his writings, to be consumed by fire; and he was pleased to accompany them in their death, for he pined away by abstaining from all manner of meat. That notable man Lucane, being adjudged by that lewd varlet, Nero, to death, at the latter end of his life, when al his blood was well- nigh spent from out the veins of his arm, which by his physician he had caused to be opened to hasten his death, and that a chilling cold began to seize the uttermost parts of his limbes, and approach his vital spirits, the last thing he had in memory was some of his own verses, written in his book of the Pharsalian wars, which with a distinct voice he repeated, and so yielded up the ghost, having those last words in his mouth. What was that but a kind, tender, and fatherly farewell which he took of his children? representing the last adiewes, and parting embracements, which at our death we give vnto our dearest issues? And an effect of that natural inclination, which in that last extremity puts us in mind of those things which in our life we have held dearest and most precious? Shall we imagine that Epicurus, who (as himself said) dying tormented with the extreme pain of the chollik, had all his comfort in the beauty of the doctrine which he left behinde him in the world, would have received as much contentment of a number of well-borne and better-bred children (if he had had any) as he did of the production of his rich compositions? And if it had been in his choise, to leave behind him either a counterfeit, deformed, or ill-borne child, or a foolish, triviall, and idle book, not only he, but all men in the world besides of like learning and sufficiency, would much rather have chosen to incur the former than the latter mischief. It might perhaps be deemed impiety in Saint Augustine (for example-sake) if on the one part one should propose unto him to bury all his bookes, whence our religion receiveth so much good, or to interre his children of in case he had any) that he would not rather chuse to bury his children, or the issue of his loynes, than the fruits of his mind. And I wot not well, whether my self should not much rather desire to beget and produce a perfectly-well-shaped and excellently-qualited infant, by the acquaintance of the Muses, than by the acquaintance of my wife. Whatsoever I give to this, let the world allow of it as it please, I give it as purely and irrevocable as any man can give it to his corporall children. That little good which I have done him is no longer in my disposition. He may know many things that my self know no longer, and hold of me what I could not hold my self: and which (if need should require) I must borrow of him as of a stranger. If I be wiser than be, he is richer than I. There are few men given unto Poesie that would not esteeme it for a greater honor to be the fathers of Virgils Æneidos than of the goodliest boy in Rome, and that would not rather endure the loss of the one than the perishing of the other. For, according to Aristotle, ’Of all workemen, the Poet is principally the most amorous of his productions and conceited of his Labours.’ It is not easy to be beleeved that Epaminondas, who wanted to leave some daughters behind him, which unto all posterity, should one day highly honor their father (they were the two famous victories which be had gained of the Lacedemonians) would ever have given his free consent to change them with the best-borne, most gorgeous, and goodliest damsels of all Greece: or that Alexander and Cæsar did ever wish to be deprived of the greatness of their glorious deeds of war, for the commodity to have children and heirs of their own bodies, how absolutely-perfect and well accomplished so ever they might be. Nay, I mahe a great question whether Phidias, or any other excellent Statuary, would as highly esteeme and dearely love the preservation and successfull continuance of his natural children, as be would an exquisite and matchlesse-wrought Image, that with long study and diligent care he had perfected according unto art. And as concerning those vicious and furious passions which sometimes have inflamed some fathers to the love of their daughters, or mothers towards their sons, the very same and more partially-earnest is also found in this other kind of child-bearing and alliance. Witness that which is reported of Pigmalion, who having curiously framed a goodly statue of a most singularly-beauteous woman, was so strange-fondly and passionately surprised with the lustfull love of his own workmanship that the Gods through his raging importunity were faine in favor of him to give it life. Tentatum mollescit ebur, positogue rigore Subsidit digitis. -- Ovid. Metam. x. 283. As he assaid it, the ivory softned much, And (hardnesse left) did yield to fingers touch. Return to : Book II CHAPTER IX:. OF THE PARTHIANS ARMES. CHAPTER IX:. OF THE PARTHIANS ARMES. T is a vitious, foolish, fashion of the Nobility and Gentry of our age, and full of nice-tenderness, never to betake themselves to arms, except upon some urgent and extreme necessitie: and to quit them as soone as they perceive the least hope or apparence that the danger is past; Whence ensue many disorders, and inconveniences: For, every one running and calling for his arms when the alarm is given, some have not yet buckled their cuirace when their fellowes are already defeated. Indeed our forefathers would have their Caske, Lance, Gantlets, and Shields carried, but so long as the service lasted, themselves would never leave-off their other peeces. Our troopes are now all confounded and disordered, by reason of bag and baggage, of carriages of lackies, and foot-boies, wh ich because of their masters arms they carry, can never leave them. Titus Livius, speaking of the French, says, Intolerantissima laboris corpora vix arma humeris gerebant (LIV. Dec. i. 10.). ’Their bodies most impatient of labor could hardly bear armour on their backes.’ Divers Nations, as they did in former times, so yet at this day, are seen to go to the wars, without any thing about them, or if they had, it was of no defense; but were all naked and bare. Tegmina quas capitum raptus de suber e cortex. -- VIR. Æn. 1. 742. Whose caske to cover all their head, Was made of barke from Corke-tree flea’d. Alexander, the most daring and hazardous Captain that ever was, did very seldom arm himself: And those which amongst us neglect them, do not thereby much empaire their reputation. If any man chance to be slain for want of an armour, there are as many more that miscarry with the over-heavy burden of their arms, and by them are engaged, and by a counterbutte are brused, or otherwise defeated. For in truth to see the unweildy weight of our and their thicknesse, it seems we but endeavor to defend ourselves, and we are rather charged than covered by them. We have enough to do to endure the burden of them, and are so engived and shackled in them, as if we were to fight but with the shocke or brunt of our arms, and as if we were as much bound to defend them as they to shield us. Cornelius Tacitus does pleasantly quip and jest at the men of war of our ancient Gaules, so armed, only to maintaine themselves, as they that have no meane either to offend or to be offended, or to raise themselves being overthrowne. Lucullus seeing certain Median men at arms, which were in the front of Tigranes Army, heavily and unweildily armed, as in an iron prison, apprehended thereby an opinion that he might easily defeat them, and began to charge them first, and got the victory. And now that our Muskettiers, are in such credit, I think we shall have some invention found to immure us up, that so we may be warranted from them, and to traine us to the wars in Skonces and Bastions, as those which our fathers caused to be carried by Elephants. A humor far different from that of Scipio the younger, who sharply reprooved his soldiers because they had scattered certain Calthropes under the water alongst a dike, by which those of the Town that he had besieged might sally out upon him, saying, that those which assailed should resolve to enterprise and not to fear: And had some reason to fear that this provision might secure and lull their vigilancy asleepe to guard themselves. Moreover he said to a young man, that showed him a fair shield he had, ’Indeed good youth, it is a fair one; but a Roman souldier ought to have more confidence in his right hand than in his left.’ It is only custom that makes the burden of our arms intolerable unto us. L’usbergo in dosso haveano, e l’elmo in testa, Due di quelli guerrier dei quali io canto. Ne notte o di dopo ch’entraro in questa Stanza, gl’haveano mai messi da canto; Che facile a portar come la resta Era lor, perche in vso l’havean tanto. -- ARIOST. Orl. can. xii. stan. 30. Cuirasse on backe did those two warriors bear, And caske on head, of whom I make report, Nor day, nor night, after they entered there, Had they them laid aside from their support They could with ease them as a garment weare, For long time had they usde them in such sort. The Emperor Caracalla in leading of his Army was ever wont to march afoot armed at all assaies. The Roman footmen caried not their motions, sword, and target only, as for other arms (says Cicero) they were so accustomed to weare them continually, that they hindered them no more than their limbs: Arma enim, membra militia esse dicunt: for they say, armor and weapon are a soldiers limbs; but therewithal such victuals as they should need for a fortnight and a certain number of stakes to make their rampards or palisadoes with, so much as weighed three score pound weight. And Marius, his soldiers thus loden, marching in battal array, were taught to march five leagues in five hours, indeed six if need required. Their military discipline was much more laboursome than ours: so did it produce far different effects. Scipio the younger, reforming his army in Spain, appointed his soldiers to eat no meat but standing, and nothing sodden or rosted. It is worth there membrance how a Lacedemonian souldier being in an expedition of war, was much noted and blamed because he was once seen to seek for shelter under a house. They were so hardened to endure all manner of labor and toyle that it was counted a reprochfull infamy for a souldier to be seen under any other roofe than that of heavens vault, in what weather soever. Were we to do so, we should never lead our men far. Marcellinus, a man well trained in the Roman wars, does curiously observe the manner which the Parthians used to arm themselves, and noteth it so much the more by how much it was far different from the Romans. They had (says he) certain arms so curiously enter-wrought as they seemed to be made like feathers, which nothing hindered the stirring of their, bodies and yet so strong, that our darts hitting them did rather rebound, or glance by, than hurt them (they be the scales our ancestors were so much wont to use). In another place they had (says he) their horses stiffe and strong, covered with thick hides, and themselves armed from head to foot with massie iron plates so artificially contrived that where the joints are there they furthered the motion and helped the stirring. A man would have said they had been men made of yron, for they had peeces so handsomly fitted, and so lively representing the form and parts of the face, that there was no way to wound them but at certain little holes before their eyes, which served to give them some light, and by certain chinkes about their nostrils by which they hardly drew breath. Flexilis inductis animator lamina nembris, Horribilis visu, credas simulacra moveri Ferrea, cognatoque viros spirare metallo. Par vestitus equis, ferrata fronte minantur, Ferratosque movent securi vulneris armos. --CLAUD. in Ruf. l. ii. 358. The bending plate is hook’t on limbes orespread, Fearefull to fight, steele images seem’d lead, And men to breathe in mettall with them bred, Like furniture for horse, with steeled head, They threat, and safe from wound, With barr’d limbs tread the ground. See-here a description much resembling the equipage of a complete French-man-at- arms with all his bards. Plutarke reporteth that Demetrius caused two armours to be made, each one weighing six score pounds: one for himself, the other for Alcinus, the chief man of war that was next to him: whereas all common armours weighed but three score. Return to : Book II CHAPTER X: OF BOOKS CHAPTER X: OF BOOKS MAKE no doubt but it shall often befall me to speak of things which are better, and with more truth, handled by such as are their crafts- masters. Here is simply an essay of my natural faculties, and no whit of those that I have acquired. And he that shall task me with ignorance shall have no great victory at my hands; for hardly could I give others reasons for my discourses that give none unto my self, and am not well satisfied with them. He that shall make search after knowledge, let him seek it where it is: there is nothing I professe less. These are but my fantasies by which I endeavor not to make things known, but my self. They may perhaps one day be known unto me, or have bin at other times, according as fortune has brought me where they were declared or manifested. But I remember them no more. And if I be a man of some reading, yet I am a man of no remembering. I conceive no certainty, except it be to give notice how far the knowledge I have of it does now reach. Let no man busie himself about the matters, but on the fashion I give them. Let that which I borrow be surveied, and then tell me whether I have made good choice of ornaments to beautifie and set foorth the invention which ever comes from me. For I make others to relate (not after my own fantastie, but as it best falleth out) what I cannot so well express either through unskill of language or want of judgement. I number not my borrowings, but I weigh them. And if I would have made their number to prevail, I would have had twice as many. They are all, or almost all, of so famous and ancient names that me thinks they sufficiently name themselves without me. If in reasons, comparisons, and arguments, I transplant any into my soile, or confound them with my own, I purposely conceal the author, thereby to bridle the rashnesse of these hastie censures that are so headlong cast upon all manner of compositions, namely young writings of men yet living; and in vulgare that admit all the world to talk of them and which seems to convince the conception and public designs likewise. I will have them to give Plutarch a bob upon my own lips, and vex themselves in wronging Seneca in me. My weaknesse must be hidden under such great credits. I will love him that shal trace or unfeather me; I meane through clearenesse of judgement, and by the only distinction of the force and beautie of my discourses. For my self, who for want of memory am ever to seek how to trie and refine them by the knowledge of their country, knowe perfectly, by measuring my own strength, that my soyle is no way capable of some over-pretious flowers that therein I find set, and that all the fruits of my increase could not make it amends. This am I bound to answer for if I hinder my self, if there be either vanity or fault in my discourses that I perceive not or am not able to discerne if they be showed me. For many faults do often escape our eyes; but the infirmitie of judgement consisteth in not being able to perceive them when another discovereth them unto us. Knnowledge and truth may be in us without judgement, and we may have judgement without them indeed, the acknowledgement of ignorance is one of the best and surest testimonies of judgement that I can find. I have no other sergeant of band to marshall my rapsodies than fortune. And looke how my humors or conceits present themselves, so I shuffle them up. Sometimes they prease thicke and three fold, and other times they come out languishing one by one. I will have my natural and ordinary pace seen as loose and shuffling as it is. As I am so go I on plodding. And besides, these are matters that a man may not be ignorant of, and rashly and casually to speak of them. I would wish to have a more perfect understanding of things, but I will not purchase it so dear as it cost. My intention is to pass the remainder of my life quietly and not laboriously, in rest and not in care. There is nothing I will trouble or vex myself about, no not for science itself, what esteeme soever it be of. I do not search and tosse over books but for an honester recreation to please, and pastime to delight my self: or if I studie, I only endeavor to find out the knowledge that teacheth or handleth the knowledge of my self, and which may instruct me how to die well and how to live well. Has meus ad metas sudet oportet equus. -- Propert. iv. El. i. 70. My horse must sweating run, That this goale may be wonne. If in reading I fortune to meet with any difficult plants, I fret not my self about them, but after I have given them a charge or two, I leave them as I found them. Should I earnestly plod upon them, I should loose both time and my self, for I have a skipping wit. What I see not at the first view, I shall less see it if I opinionate my self upon it. I do nothing without blithnesse; and an over obstinate continuation and plodding contention does dazle, dull, and wearie the same: my sight is thereby confounded and diminished. I must therefore withdraw it, and at fittes go to it again. Even as to judge well of the lustre of scarlet we are taught to cast our eyes over it, in running over by diverse glances, sodaine glimpses and reiterated reprisings. If one book seem tedious unto me I take another, which I follow not with any earnestnesse, except it be at such hours as I am idle, or that I am weary with doing nothing. I am not greatly affected to new books, because ancient Authors are, in my judgement, more full and pithy: nor am I much addicted to Greeke books, forasmuch as my understanding cannot well rid his work with a childish and apprentise intelligence. Amongst modern bookes meerly pleasant, I esteeme Bocace his Decameron, Rabelais, and the kisses of John the second (if they may be placed under this title), worth the paines-taking to read them. As for Amadis and such like trash of writings, they had never the credit so much as to allure my youth to delight in them. This I will say more, either boldly or rashly that this old and heavy-pased mind of mine will no more be pleased with Aristotle, or tickled with good Ovid: his facility and quaint inventions, which heretofore have so ravished me, they can now a days scarcely entertaine me. I speak my mind freely of all things, indeed, of such as perhaps exceed my sufficiencie, and that no way I hold to be of my jurisdiction. What my conceit is of them is told also to manifest the proportion of my insight, and not the measure of things. If at any time I find my self distasted of Platoes Axiochus, as of a forceles work, due regard had to such an Author, my judgement does nothing believe itself: It is not so foolhardy, or self-conceited, as it durst dare to oppose itself against the authority of so many other famous ancient judgements, which he reputeth his regents and masters, and with whom he had rather erre. He chafeth with, and condemneth himself, either to rely on the superficiall sense, being unable to pierce into the centre, or to view the thing by some false lustre. He is pleased only to warrant himself from trouble and unruliness: As for weaknesses he acknowledgeth and ingeniously avoweth the same. He thinks to give a just interpretation to the apparences which his conception presents unto him, but they are shallow and imperfect. Most of Aesopes fables have diverse senses, and severall interpretations: Those which Mythologize them, chose some kind of colour well sutirig with the fable; but for the most part, it is no other than the firsthand superficiall glosse: There are others more quick, more siniaowie, more essentiall, and more internall, into which they could never penetrate; and thus think I with them. But to follow my course, I have ever deemed that in Poesie, Virgil, Lucretius, Catullus, and Horace, do doubtles by far hold the first rank: and especially Virgil in his Georgiks, which I esteeme to be the most accomplished peece of.work of Poesie: In comparison of which one may easily discerne, that there are some passages in the Æneidos to which the Author (had he lived) would no doubt have given some review or correction: The fifth book whereof is (in my mind) the most absolutely perfect. I also love Lucan, and willingly read him, not so much for his stile, as for his own worth and truth of his opinion and judgement. As for good Terence, I allow the quaintness and grace of his Latine tongue, and judge him wonderful conceited and apt, lively to represent the motions and passions of the mind, and the condition of our manners: our actions make me often remember him. I can never read him so often but still I discover some new grace and beautie in him. Those that lived about Virgil’s time, complained that some would compare Lucretius unto him. I am of opinion that verily it is an unequall comparison; yet can I hardly assure my seffe in this opinion whensoever I find my self entangled in some notable passage of Lucretius. If they were moved at this comparison, what would they say now of the foolish, hardy and barbarous stupidity of those which now adayes compare Ariosto unto him? Nay, what would Ariosto say of it himself? O seclum insipiens et infacetum. Catul. Epig. xl. 8. O age that has no wit, And small conceit in it. I think our ancestors had also more reason to cry out against those that blushed not to equall Plautus unto Terence (who makes more show to be a Gentleman) than Lucretius unto Virgil. This one thing does greatly advantage the estimation and preferring of Terence, that the father of the Roman eloquence, of men of his quality does so often make mention of him; and the censure which the chief Judge of the Roman Poets gives of his companion. It has often come unto my mind, how such as in our dayes give themselves to composing of comedies (as the Italians who are very happy in them) employ three or foure arguments of Terence and Plautus to make up one of theirs. In one only comedy they will huddle up five or six of Bocaces tales. That which makes them so to charge themselves with matter, is the distrust they have of their own sufficiency, and that they are not able to undergoe so heavy a burden with their own strength. They are forced to find a body on which they may rely and leane themselves: and wanting matter of their own wherewith to please us, they will have the story or tale to busie and ammuse us: where as in my Authors it is cleane contrary: The elegancies, the perfections and ornaments of his manner of speech, make us neglect and lose the longing for his subject. His quaintness and grace do still retaine us to him. He is every where pleasantly conceited, Liquidus puroque simillimus amni, Hor. ii. Epist. ii. 120. So clearely-neate, so neately-clear, As he a fine-pure River were, and does so replenish our mind with his graces that we forget those of the fable. The same consideration draws me somewhat further. I perceive that good and ancient Poets have shunned the affectation and enquest, not only of fantastic, new fangled, Spagniolized and Petrarchisticall elevations, but also of more sweet and sparing inventions, which are the ornament of all the Poeticall workes of succeeding ages. Yet is there no competent Judge that findeth them wanting in those Ancient ones, and that does not much more admire that smoothly equall neatnesse, continued sweetness, and flourishing comelinesse of Catullus his Epigrams, than all the sharpe quips and witty girds wherewith Martiall does whet and embellish the conclusions of his. It is the same reason I spake of erewhile, as Martiall of himself. Minus illi ingenio laborandum fuit, in cuius locum mate ria successerat: (Mart. præf. viii.) ’He needed the less work with his wit, in place whereof matter came in supply.’ The former without being moved or pricked cause themselves to be beard lowd enough: they have matter to laugh at every where, and need not tickle themselves; where as these must have foraine helpe: according as they have less spirit, they must have more body. They leape on horse-backe, because they are not sufficiently strong in their legs to march on foot. Even as in our dances, those base conditioned men that keep dancing schooles, because they are unfit to represent the port and decencie of our nobility, endeavor to get commendation by dangerous lofty trickes, and other strange tumbler-like friskes and motions. And some Ladies make a better show of their countenances in those dances, wherein are diverse changes, cuttings, turnings, and agitations of the body, than in some dances of state and gravity, where they need but simply to tread a natural, measure, represent an unaffected cariage, and their ordinary grace; And as I have also seen some excellent Lourdans, or Clownes, attired in their ordinary workyday clothes, and with a common homely countenance, affoord us all the pleasure that may be had from their art: but prentises and learners that are not of so high a form, besmeare their faces, to disguise themselves, and in motions counterfeit strange visages and antickes, to enduce us to laughter. This my conception is no where better discerned than in the comparison betweene Virgils Æneidos and Orlando Furioso. The first is seen to soare aloft with full-spread wings, and with so high and strong a pitch, ever following his point; the other faintly to hover and flatter from tale to tale, and as it were skipping from bough to bough, alwayes distrusting his own wings, except it be for some short flight, and for fear his strength and breath should faile him, to sit down at every fields-end. Excursusque breves tentat. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 194. Out-lopes sometimes he does assay, But very short, and as he may. See here then, concerning this kind of subjects, what Authors please me best: As for my other lesson, which somewhat more mixeth profit with pleasure, whereby I learne to range my opinions and addresse my conditions, the Bookes that serve me thereinto are Plutarke (since he spake French) and Seneca, both have this excellent commodity for my humor, that the knowledge I seek in them is there so scatteringly and loosely handled, that whosoever readeth them is not tied to plod long upon them, whereof I am uncapable. And so are Plutarkes little workes and Senecas Epistles, which are the best and most profitable parts of their writings. It is no great matter to draw me to them, and I leave them where I list. For they succeed not and depend not one of another. Both jumpe and suit together, in most true and profitable opinions: And fortune brought them both into the world in one age. Both were Tutors unto two Roman Emperours: Both were strangers, and came from far Countries; both rich and mighty in the common-wealth, and in credit with their masters. Their instruction is the prime and creame of Philosophy, and presented with a plaine, unaffected, and pertinent fashion. Plutarke is more uniform and constant; Seneca more waving and diverse. This does labor, force, and extend himself, to arm and strengthen virtue against weaknesse fear, and vitious desires; the other seems nothing so much to fear their force or attempt, and in a manner scorneth to hasten or change his pace about them, and to put himself upon his guard. Plutarkes opinions are Platonicall, gentle and accommodable unto civill societie: Senecæs Stoicall and Epicurian, further from common use, but in my conceit more proper particular, and more solid. It appeareth in Seneca that he somewhat inclineth and yieldeth to the tyrannie of the Emperors which were in his days; for I verily believe, it is with a forced judgement he condemneth the cause of those noblie-minded murtherers of Cæsar; Plutarke is every where free and open hearted; Seneca fullfraught with points and sallies; Plutarke stuft with matters. The former does move and enflame you more; the latter content, please, and pay you better: This does guide you, the other drive you on. As for Cicero, of all his works, those that treat of Philosophie (namely morall) are they which best serve my turn, and square with my intent. But boldly to confess the truth (for, since the bars of impudencie were broken down, all curbing is taken away), his manner of writing seems very tedious unto me, as does all such like stuffe. For his prefaces, definitions, divisions, and Etymologies consume the greatest part of his works; whatsoever quick, wittie, and pithie conceit is in him is surcharged and confounded by those his long and far-fetcht preambles. If I bestow but one hour in reading them, which is much for me, and let me call to mind what substance or juice I have drawne from him, for the most part I find nothing but wind and ostentation in him; for he is not yet come to the arguments which make for his purpose, and reasons that concerne the knot or pith I seek after. These Logicall and Aristotelian ordinances are not availfull for me who only endeavour to become more wise and sufficient and not more wittie or eloquent. I would have one begin with the last point; I understand sufficiently what death and voluptuousuesse are: let not a man busie himself to anatomize them. At the first reading of a book I seek for good and solid reasons that may instruct me how to sustain their assaults. It is neither grammaticall subtilties or logicall quiddities, nor the wittie contexture of choice words or arguments and syllogismes, that will serve my turn. I like those discourses that give the first charge to the strongest part of the doubt; his are but flourishes, and languish everywhere. They are good for schooles, at the barre, or for Orators and Preachers, where we may slumber: and though we wake a quarter of an hour after, we may find and trace him soone enough. Such a manner of speech is fit for those judges that a man would corrupt by hooke or crooke, by right or wrong, or for children and the common people, unto whom a man must tell all, and see what the event would be. I would not have a man go about and labor by circumlocutions to induce and winne me to attention, and that (as our Heralds or Criers do) they shall ring out their words: Now hear me, now listen, or ho- yes. The Romanes in their religion were went to say, ’Hoc age;’ which in ours we say, ’Sursum corda.’ There are so many lost words for me. I come readie prepared from my house. I neede no allurement nor sawce, my stomacke is good enough to digest raw meat: And whereas with these preparatives and f lourishes, or preambles, they think to sharpen my taste or stir my stomacke, they cloy and make it wallowish. Shall the privilege of times excuse me from this sacrilegious boldness, to deem Platoes Dialogismes to be as languishing, by overfilling and stuffing his matter? And to bewaile the time that a man who had so many thousands of things to utter, spends about so many, so long, so vain, and idle interlocutions, and preparatives? My ignorance shall better excuse me, in that I see nothing in the beautie of his language. I generally enquire after bookes that use sciences, and not after such as institute them. The two first, and Plinie, with others of their rank, have no Hoc age in them, they will have to do with men that have forewarned themselves; or if they have, it is a materiall and substantiall Hoc age, and that has his body apart. I likewise love to read the Epistles and ad Atticum, not only because they contains a most ample instruction of the historic and affairs of his times, but much more because in them I descrie his private humors. For (as I have said elsewhere) I am wonderful curious to discover and know the mind, the soul the genuine disposition and natural judgement of my authors. A man ought to judge their sufficiencie and not their customs, nor them by the show of their writings, which they set forth on this world’s theatre. I have sorrowed a thousand times that ever we lost the book that Brutus wrote of Vertue. Oh it is a goodly thing to learne the Theorike of such as understand the practice well. But forasmuch as the Sermon is one thing and the Preacher another, I love as much to see Brutus in Plutarke as in himself: I would rather make choice to know certainly what talk he had in his tent with some of his familiar friends, the night fore-going the battle, than the speech he made the morrow after to his Armie and what he did in his chamber or closet, than what in the senate or market place. As for Cicero, I am of the common judgement, that besides learning there was no exquisite eloquence in him: He was a good citizen, of an honest, gentle nature, as are commonly fat and burly men: for so was he: But to speak truly of him, full of ambitious vanity and remisse niceness. And I know not well how to excuse him, in that be deemed his Poesie worthy to be published. It is no great imperfection to make bad verses, but it is an imperfection in him that he never perceived how unworthy they were of the glory of his name. Concerning his eloquence, it is beyond all comparison, and I verily believe that none shall ever equall it. Cicero the younger, who resembled his father in nothing but in name, commanding in Asia, chanced one day to have many strangers at his board, and amongst others, one Cæstius sitting at the lower end, as the manner is to thrust in at great mens tables: Cicero inquired of one of his men what he was, who told him his name, but he dreaming on other matters, and having forgotten what answere his man made him, asked him his name twice or thrice more: the servant, because he would not be troubled to tell him one thing so often, and by some circumstance to make him to know him better, ’It is,’ said he, ’the same Cæstius of whom some have told you that, in respect of his own, maketh no accompt of your fathers eloquence:’ Cicero being suddainly mooved, commanded the said Cæstius to be presently taken from the table, and well whipped in his presence: See here an uncivill and barbarous host. Even amongst those which (all things considered) have deemed his eloquence matchlesse and incomparable, others there have been who have not spared to note some faults in it. As great Brutus said, that it was an eloquence broken, halting, and disjoynted, fractam et elumbem. ’Incoherent and sinnnowlesse.’ Those Orators that lived about his age, reproved also in him the curious care he had of a certain long cadence at the end of his clauses, and noted these words, esse videatur, which he so often useth. As for me, I rather like a cadence that falleth shorter, cut like Iambikes: yet does he sometimes confounde his numbers, but it is seldom: I have especially observed this one place; ’Ego vero me minus diu senem esse mallem, quam esse senem, antequam essem: (Cic. De Senect.) ’But I had rather not be an old man, so long as I might be, than to be old before I should be.’ Historians are my right hand, for they are pleasant and e asie; and therewithall the man with whom I desire generally to be acquainted may more lively and perfectly be discovered in them than in any other composition: the varietie and truth of his inward conditions, in grosse and by retale: the diversitie of the means of his collection and composing, and of the accidents that threaten him. Now those that write of mens lives, forasmuch as they ammuse and busie themselves more about counsels than events, more about that which commeth from within than that which appeareth outward; they are fittest for me: And that’s the reason why Plutarke above all in that kind does best please me. Indeed I am not a little grieved that we have not a dozen of Lærtius, or that be is not more known, or better understood; for I am no less curious to know the fortunes and lives of these great masters of the world than to understand the diversitie of their decrees and conceits. In this kind of studie of historie a man must, without distinction, tosse and turn over all sorts of Authors, both old and new, both French and others, if he will learne the things they so diversly treat of. But me thinkes that Cæsar above all does singularly deserve to be studied, not only for the understanding of the historie as of himself; so much perfection and excellencie is there in him more than in others, although Salust be reckoned one of the number. Verily I read that author with a little more reverence and respects than commonly men read profane and humane Workes: sometimes considering him by his actions and wonders of his greatness, and other times waighing the puritie and inimitable polishing and elegancie of his tongue, which (as Cicero says) has not only exceeded all historians, but perhaps Cicero himself: with such sinceritie in his judgement, speaking of his enemies, that except the false colours wherewith he goeth about to cloakebis bad cause, and the corruption and filthinesse of his pestilent ambition, I am persuaded there is nothing in him to be found fault with: and that he has been over- sparing to speak of himself; for so many notable and great things could never be executed by him, unless he bad put more of his own into them than be setteth down. I love those Historians that are either very simple or most excellent. The simple who have nothing of their own to adde unto the story and have but the care and diligence to collect whatsoever come to their knowledge, and sincerely and faithfully to register all things, without choice or culling, by the naked truth leave our judgment more entire and better satisfied. Such amongst others (for examples sake) plaine and well-meaning Froissard, who in his enterprise has marched with so free and genuine a puritie, that having committed some oversight, he is neither ashamed to acknowledge nor afraid to correct the same, wherever has either notice or warning of it: and who representeth unto us the diversitie of the news then current and the diferent reports that were made unto him. The subject of an historie should be naked, bare, and formelesse; each man according to his capacitie or understanding may reap commoditie out of it. The curious and most excellent have the sufficiencie to cull and chuse that which is worthie to be known and may select of two relations that which is most likely: from the condition of Princes and of their humors, they conclude their counsels and attribute fit words to them: they assume a just authority and bind our faith to theirs. But truly that belongs not to many. Such as are betweene both (which is the most common fashion), it is they that spoil all; they will needs chew our meat for us and take upon them a law to judge, and by consequence to square and encline the story according to their fantasie; for, where the judgement bendeth one way, a man cannot chose but wrest and turn his narration that way. They undertake to chuse things worthy to be known, and now and then conceal either a word or a secret action from us, which would much better instruct us: omitting such things as they understand not as incredible: and perhaps such matters as they know not how to declare either in good Latin or tolerable French. Let them boldly enstall their eloquence and discourse: Let them censure at their pleasure, but let them also give us leave to judge after them: And let them neither alter nor dispense by their abridgements and choice anything belonging to the substance of the matter; but let them rather send it pure and entire with all her dimensions unto us. Most commonly (as chiefly in our age) this charge of writing histories is committed unto base, ignorant, and mechanicall kind of people, only for this consideration that they can speak well; as if we sought to learne the Grammer of them; and they have some reason, being only hired to that end, and publishing nothing but their tittle-tattle to aime at nothing else so much. Thus with store of choice and quaint words, and wyre drawne phrases, they huddle up and make a hodge-pot of a laboured contexture of the reports which they gather in the market places or such other assemblies. The only good histories are those that are written by such as commanded or were imploied themselves in weighty affairs or that were partners in the conduct of them, or that at least have had the fortune to manage others of like quality. Such in a manner are all the Græcians and Romans. For many eyewitness having written of one same subject it hapned in those times when Greatnesse and Knowledge did commonly meet) if any fault or oversight have past them, it must be deemed exceeding light and upon some doubtfull accident. What may a man expect at a Phisitians hand that discourseth of war, or of a bare Scholler treating of Princes secret designes? If we shall but note the religion which the Romans had in that, we need no other example: Asinus Pollio found some mistaking or or oversight in Cæsars Commentaries, whereinto he was faine, only because he could not possiblie oversee all things with his own eyes that hapned in his Armie, but was faine to rely on the reports of particular men, who often related untruths unto him; or else because he had not been curiously advertised and distinctly enformed by his Lieutenants and Captains of such matters as they in his absence had managed or affected. Whereby may be seen that nothing is so hard or so uncertaine to be found out as the certaintie of the truth, sithence no man can put any assured confidence concerning the truth of a battle, neither in the knowledge of him that was General or commanded over it, nor in the soldiers that fought, of anything that has hapned amongst them; except after the manner of a strict point of law, the severall witnesses are brought and examined face to face, and that all matters be nicely and thorowly sifted by the objects and trials of the success of every accident. Verily the knowledge we have of our own affairs is much more barren and feeble. But this has sufficiently been handled by Bodin, and agreeing with my conception. Somewhat to aid the weaknesse of my memory and to assist her great defects; for it has often been my chance to light upon bookes which I supposed to be new and never to have read, which I had not understanding diligently read and ran over many years before, and all bescribled with my notes: I have a while since accustomed my self to note at the end of my book (I meane such as I purpose to read but once) the time I made an end to read it, and to set down what censure or judgement I gave of it; that so it may at least at another time represent unto my mind the aire and general idea I had conceived of the author in reading him. I will here set down the Copie of some of my annotations, and especially what I noted upon my Guicciardine about ten years since (For what language soever my books speak unto me I speak unto them in my own.) He is a diligent Historiographer and from whom in my conceit a man may as exactly learne the truth of such affairs as passed in his time, as of any other writer whatsoever and the rather because himself has been an Actor of most part of them and in very honorable place. There is no signe or apparance that ever he disguised or coloured any matter, either through hatred, malice, favor, or vanity; whereof the free and impartiall judgements he gives of great men, and namely of those by whom he had been advanced or employed in his important charges, as of Pope Clement the seaventh, beareth undoubted testimony. Concerning the parts wherein be most goeth about to prevaile, which are his digressions and discourses, many of them are very excellent and enriched with fair ornaments, but he has too much pleased himself in them: for endeavouring to omit nothing that might be spoken, having so full and large a subject, and almost infinite, he proveth somewhat languishing, and gives a taste of a kind of scholasticall tedious babling. Moreover, I have noted this, that of so severall and diverse arms, successes, and effects he judgeth of; of so many and variable motives, alterations, and counsels, that be relateth, he never referreth any one unto virtue, religion, or conscience as if they were all extinguished and banished the world: and of all actions how glorious soever in apparance they be of themselves, he does ever impute the cause of them to some vicious and blame-worthie occasion, or to some commoditie and profit. It is impossible to imagine that amongst so infinite a number of actions whereof he judgeth, some one have not been produced and compassed by way of reason. No corruption could ever possesse men so universally but that some one must of necessity escape the contagion; which makes me to fear he has had some distaste or blame in his passion, and it has perhaps fortuned that he has judged or esteemed of others according to himself. In my Philip de Comines there is this: In him you shall find a pleasing-sweet and gently-gliding speech, fraught with a purely sincere simplicitie, his narration pure and unaffected, and wherein the Authours unspotted good meaning does evidently appeare, void of all manner of vanity or ostentation speaking of himself, and free from all afection or envie-speaking of others; his discourses and persuasions accompanied more with a well-meaning zeale and meere veritie than with any laboured and exquisite sufficiencie, and allthrough with gravitie and authority, representing a man well-borne and brought up in high negotiations. Upon the menioires and historie of Monsieur du Bellay. It is ever a well-pleasing thing to see matters written by those that have assaid how and in what manner they ought to be directed and managed: yet can it not be denied but that in both these Lords there will manifestly appeare a great declination from a free liberty of writing, which clearely shineth in ancient writers of their kind: as in the Lord of Jonville, familiar unto Saint Lewis; Eginard, Chancellor unto Charlemaine; and of more fresh memory in Philip de Comines. This is rather a declamation or pleading for king Francis against the Emperor Charles the fifth, than an Historie. I will not believe they have altered or changed any thing concerning the generalitie of matters, but rather to wrest and turn the judgement of the events many times against reason, to our advantage, and to omit whatsoever they supposed to be doubtful or ticklish in their masters life: they have made a business of it: witness the recoylings of the Lords of Momorancy and Byron, which therein are forgotten; and which is more, you shall not so much as find the name of the Lady of Estampes mentioned at all. A man may sometimes colour and perhaps hide secret actions, but absolutely to conceal that which all the world knows, and especially such things as have drawne-on public effects, and of such consequence, it is an inexcusable defect, or as I may say unpardonable oversight. To conclude, whosoever desires to have perfect information and knowledge of king Francis the first, and of the things hapned in his time, let him addresse himself elsewhere if he will give any credit unto me. The profit he may reap here is by the particular description of the battles and exploits of war wherein these gentlemen were present; some privie conferences, speeches, or secret actions of some princes that then lived, and the practices managed, or negotiations directed by the Lord of Langeay, in which doubtless are very many things well worthy to be known, and diverse discourses not vulgare. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XI: OF CRUELTIE CHAPTER XI: OF CRUELTIE ETHINKS Virtue is another manner of thing, and much more noble than the inclinations unto Goodnesse, which in us are engendered. Mindes wellborne, and directed by themselves, follow one same path, and in their actions represent the same visage that the vertuous do. But Vertue importeth and soundeth somewhat I wot not what greater and more active than by an happy complexion, gently and peaceably, to suffer itself to be led or drawne to follow reason. He that through a natural facilitie and genuine mildness should neglect or contemne injuries received, should no doubt performe a rare action, and worthy commendation: but he who being touched and stung lo the quick with any wrong or offence received, should arm himself with reason against this furiously blind desire of revenge, and in the end after a great conflict yield himself master over it, should doubtlesse do much more. The first should do well, the other vertuously: the one action might be termed Goodnesse, the other Vertue. For it seems that the very name of Vertue presupposeth difficulties and inferreth resistance, and cannot well exercise itself without an enemy. It is perhaps the reason why we call God good, mightie, liberall, and just, but we term him not vertuous. His workes are all voluntarie, unforced, and without compulsion. Of Philosophers, not only Stoics, but also Epicureans (which phrasing I borrow of the common received opinion, which is false, whatsoever the nimble saying or wittie quipping of Arcesilaus implied, who answered the man that upbraided him, how diverse men went from his schoole to the Epicureans, but no one came from thence to him: I easily believe it (said he) for Of cocks are many capons made, but no man could ever make a cock of a capon. For truly in constancy opinion and strictnesse of precepts, the Epicurean sect does in no sort yield to the Stoice. And a Stoike acknowledging a better faith than those disputers who, to contend with Epicurus and make sport with him, make him to infer and say what he never meant, wresting and wyre-drawing his words to a contrary sense, arguing and silogizing, by the grammarians privilege, another meaning, by the manner of his speech and another opinion than that they knew he had either in his mind or manners, says that he left to be an Epicurean for this one consideration amongst others, that he findeth their pitch to be over high and inaccessible: Et φιλοχαλοι vocantur, sunt φιλοχανοι et φιλοιχαιοι omnesque virtutes et colunt et retinent: (Sen. Epist. xiii.) ’And those that are called lovers of pleasures, are lovers of honestie and justice, and do reverence and retaine all sorts of virtue.’ Of Stoice and Epicurean Philosophers, I say, there are diverse who have judged that it was not sufficient to have the mind well placed, well ordered, and well disposed unto virtue; it was not enough to have our resolutions and discourse beyond all the affronts and checks of fortune; but that, moreover, it was very requisite to seek for occasions whereby a man might come to the trial of it. They will diligently quest and seek out for pain, smart, necessitie, want, and contempt, that so they may combat them, and keep their mind in breath: Multum sibi adjicit virtus lacessitæ: ’Vertue provoked addes much to itself.’ It is one of the reasons why Epaminondas (who was of a third sect) by a very lawfull way refuseth some riches fortune had put into his hands, to the end (as he says) he might have cause to strive and resist povertie, in which want and extremity he ever continued after. Socrates did in my mind more undauntedly enure himself to this humor, maintaining for his exercise the peevish frowardnesse of his wife, than which no essay can be more vexfull, and is a continuall fighting at the sharpe. Metellus of all the Roman senators he only having undertaken with the power of virtue, to endure the violence of Saturninus Tribune of the people in Rome, who by main force went about to have a most unjust law pass in favor of the Communaltie: by which opposition, having incurred all the capital paines that Saturninus had imposed on such as should refuse it, entertained those that led him to the place of execution, with such speeches: That to do evil was a thing very easy, and too demissely base, and to do well where was no danger, was a common thing, but to do well where was both perill and opposition, was the peculiar office of a man of virtue. These words of Metellus do clearly represent unto us what I would have verified ; which is, that virtue rejects facilitie to be her companion: And that an easefull, pleasant, and declining way by which the regular steps of a good inclination of nature are directed is not the way of true virtue. She requireth a craggie, rough, and thornie way. She would either have strange difficulties to wrestle withall (as that of Metellus) by whose means fortune herself is pleased to breake the roughnesse of his course; or such inward incombrances as the disordinate appetites and imperfections of our condition bring unto her. Hitherto I have come at good ease; but at the end of this discourse one thing commeth into my mind, which is that the soul of Socrates, which is absolute the perfectest that ever came to my knowledge, would, according to my accompt, prove a soul deserving but little commendation: For I can conceive no manner of violence or vicious concupiscence in him: I can imagine no manner of difficultie or compulsion in the whole course of his virtue. I know his reason so powerfull, and so absolute mistress over him, that she can never give him way in any vicious desire, and will not suffer it so much as to breed in him. To a virtue so exquisite and so high raised as his is, I can persuade nothing. Me thinks I see it march with a victorious and triumphant pace, in pompe and at ease, without let or disturbance. If virtue cannot shine but by resisting contrary appetites, shall we then say it cannot pass without the assistance of vice, and oweth him this, that by his means it attaineth to honor and credit? What should also betide of that glorious and generous Epicurean voluptuousness that makes accompt effeminately to pamper virtue in her lap, and there wantonly to entertaine it, allowing it for her recreation, shame, reproch, agues, povertie, death, and tortures? if I presuppose that perfect virtue is known by combating sorrow and patiently under going pain, by tolerating the fits and agonies of the gout, without stirring out of his place; if for a necessarie object I appoint her sharpnesse and difficultie, what shall become of that virtue which has attained so high a degree, as it does not only despise all manner of pain, but rather rejoyceth at it, and when a strong fit of the collike shall assaile it, to cause itself to be tickled, as that is which the Epicureans have established, and whereof diverse amongst them have by their actions left most certain proofes unto us? As also others have, whom ill effect find to have exceeded the very rules of their discipline; witness Cato the younger; when I see him die, tearing and mangling his entrails, I cannot simply content my self to believe that at that time he had his soul wholly exempted from all trouble or free from vexation: I cannot imagine be did only maintaine himself in this march or course which the rule of the Stoike sect had ordained unto him, setled, without alteration or emotion, and impassible. There was, in my conceit, in this mans virtue overmuch cheerefulnesse and youthfulnesse to stay there. I verily believe he felt a kind of pleasure and sensualitie in so noble an action, and that therein he more pleased himself than in any other he ever performed in his life. Sic abiit e vita, ut causam moriendi nactum se esse gauderet: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’So departed he his life, that he rejoiced to have found an occasion of death.’ I do so constantly believe it, that I make a doubt whether he would have had the occasion of so noble an exploit taken from him. And if the goodnesse which induced him to embrace public commodities more than his own did not bridle me, I should easily fall into this opinion, that he thought himself greatly beholding unto fortune to have put his virtue unto so noble a trial, and to have favoured that robber to tread the ancient liberty of his countrie under foot. In which action me thinks I read a kind of unspeakable joy in his mind, and a motion of extraordinary pleasure, joined to a manlike voluptuousness, at what time it beheld the worthinesse, and considered the generositie and haughtinesse of his enterprise, Deliberata morte ferocior -- Hor. i. Od. xxxvii. 29. Cleopatra. Then most in fiercenesse did he pass, When he of death resolved was, not urged or set-on by any hope of glory, as the popular and effeminate judgements have judged: For, that consideration is over base, to touch so generous, so haughtie, and so constant a heart; but for the beautie of the thing itself, which he, who managed all the springs and directed all the wards thereof, saw much more clearer, and in its perfection, than we can do. Philosophie has done me a pleasure to judge that so honorable an action had been undecently placed in any other life than in Catoes, and that only unto his it appertained to make such an end. Therefore did he with reason persuade both his son and the Senators that accompanied him, to provide otherwise for themselves. Catoni quum incredibilem natura tribuisset gravitatem, eamque ipse perpetua constantia roboravisset, semperque in proposito consilio permansisset: mortendum potius quam tyranni vultus aspiciendus erat: ’Whereas nature had affoorded Cato an incredible gravitie, and he had strengthened it by continuall constancy, and ever had stood firme in his proposed desseignes, rather to die than behold the Tyrants face. ’ Each death should be such as the life has been. By dying we become no other than we were. I ever interpret a mans death by his life. And if a man shall tell me of any one undanted in apparance, joined unto a weake life; I imagine it to proceed of some weake cause, and suitable to his life. The ease therefore of his death, and the facilitie he had acquired by the vigor of his mind, shall we say, it ought to abate something of the lustre of his virtue? And which of those that have their spirits touched, be it never so little, with the true tincture of Philosophie, can content himself to imagine Socrates, only, free from fear and passion, in the accident of his imprisonment, of his fetters, and of his condemnation? And who does not perceive in him, not only constancy and resolution (which were ever his ordinary qualities) but also a kind of I wot not what new contentment, and carelesse rejoycing in his last behaviour, and discourses? By the startling at the pleasure, which he feeleth in clawing of his legs, after his fetters were taken-off; does he not manifestly declare an equal glee and joy in his soul for being rid of his former incommodities, and entering into the knowledge of things to come? Cato shall pardon me (if he please) his death is more tragical, and further extended, whereas this in a certain manner is more fair and glorious. Aristippus answered those that bewailed the same, ’When I die, I pray the Gods send me such a death.’ A man shall plainly perceive in the minds of these two men, and of such as imitate them (for I make a question whether ever they could be matched) so perfect an habitude unto virtue, that it was even converted into their complexion. It is no longer a painefull virtue, nor by the ordinances of reason, for the maintaining of which their mind must be strengthened: It is the very essence of their soul; it is her natural and ordinary habit. They have made it such, by a long exercise and observing the rules and precepts of Philosophic, having lighted upon a fair and rich nature. Those vicious passions which breed in us find no entrance in them. The vigor and constancy of their soules, does suppresse and extinguish all manner of concupiscences so soone as they but begin to move. Now that it be not more glorious, by an undaunted and divine resolution, to hinder the growth of temptations, and for a man to frame himself to virtue, so that the very seeds of vice be cleane rooted out; than by mayne force to hinder their progresse; and having suffred himself to be surprised by the first assaults of passions, to arm and bandie himself, to stay their course and to suppresse them: And that this second effect be not also much fairer than to be simply stored with a facile and gentle nature, and of itself distasted and in dislike with licentiousnesse and vice, I am persuaded there is no doubt. For this third and last manner seems in some sort to make a man innocent, but not vertuous: free from doing ill, but not sufficiently apt to do well. Seeing this condition is so near unto imperfection and weaknesses that I know not well how to clear their confines and distinctions. The very names of goodnesse and innocencie, are for this respect in some sort names of contempt. I see that many vertues, as chastitie, sobrietie, and temperance, may come unto us by means of corporall defects and imbecilities. Constancie in dangers (if it may be termed constancy) contempt of death, patiencie in misfortunes, may happen and are often seen in men, for want of good judgeent in such accidents, and that they are not apprehended for such as they are indeed. Lacke of apprehension and stupidity counterfeit vertuous effects. As I have often seen come to pass, that some men are commended for things they rather deserve to be blamed. An Italian gentleman did once hold this position in my presence, to the prejudice and disadvantage of his nation; That the subtiltie of the Italians, and the vivacitie of their conceptions was so great that they foresaw such dangers and accidents as might betide them so far-off that it was not to be deemed strange if in times of war they were often seen to provide for their safetie, indeed, before they had perceived the danger: That we and the Spaniards, who were not so warie and subtill, went further; and that before we could be frighted with any perill, we must be induced to see it with our eyes, and feel it with our hands, and that even then we had no more hold: But that the Germanes and Switzers, more shallow and leaden-headed, had scarce the sense and wit to re-advise themselves, at what times they were even overwhelmed with misery, and the axe readie to fall on their heads. It was perhaps but in jest that he spake it, yet is it most true that in the art of war- fare new trained souldlers, and such as are but novices in the trade, do often headlong and hand over head cast themselves into dangers, with more inconsideration than afterward when they have seen and endured the first shocks, and are better trained in the schoole of perils. ------ haud iqnarus, quantum nova gloria in armis, Et prædulce decus primo certamine possit. Not ignorant, how much in arms new praise, And sweetest honor, in first conflict weighes. See here the reason why when we judge of a particular action, we must first consider many circumstances, and throughly observe the man, that has produced the same before we name and censure it. But to speak a word of my self: I have sometimes noted my friends to terme that wisdom in me which was but meere fortune, and to deem that advantage of courage and patience that was advantage of judgement and opinion; and to attribute one title for another unto me, sometimes to my profit, and now and then to my loss. As for the rest, I am far from attaining unto that chief and most perfect degree of excellences, where a habitude is made of virtue, that even of the second I have made no great trial. I have not greatly strived to bridle the desires wherewith I have found my self urged and pressed. My virtue is a virtue, or to say better innocencie, accidentall and casual. Had I been borne with a less regular complexion, I imagine my state had been very pitiful, and it would have gon hard with me: for, I could never perceive any great constancy in my soul, to resist and undergoe passions, had they been any thing violent. I cannot foster quarels, or endure contentions in my house. So am I not greatly beholding unto my self, in that I am exempted from many vices: ------- si vitiis mediocribus, et mea paucis Mendosa est natura, alioqui recta, velut si Egregio inspersos reprehendas corpore nævos. -- Hor. i. Sat. vi. 65. If in a few more faults my nature faile, Right otherwise: as if that you would rail On prettie moles well placed, On body seemely graced. I am more endebted to my fortune than to my reason for it: Shee has made me to be borne of a race famous for integritie and honestie, and of a very good father. I wot not well whether any part of his humors have descended into me, or whether the domestike examples and good institution of my infancie have insensibly set their helping hand unto it; or whether I were otherwise so borne: Seu Libra, seu me Scorpius aspicit Formidolosus, pars violentior Natalis horæ, seu tyrannus Hesperiæ Capricornus undæ -- Hor. ii. Od. xvii. 17. Whether the chief part of my birth-hour were Ascendent Libra, or Scorpius full of fear, Or in my Horoscope were Capricorne, Whose tyrannie near westerne seas is borne: But so it is, that naturally of my self I abhorre and detest all manner of vices. The answer of Antisthenes to one that demanded of him which was the best thing to be learned; To unlearne evil, seemed to be fixed on this image, or to have an ayme at this. I abhorre them (I say) with so natural and so innated an opinion, that the very same instinct and impression which I suckt from my nurse, I have so kept that no occasions could ever make me alter the same: no, not my own discourses, which, because they have been somewhat lavish in noting or taxing something of the common course, could easily induce me to some actions which this my natural inclination makes me to hate. I will tell you a wonder, I will tell it you indeed: I thereby find in many things more stay and order in my manners than in my opinion: and my concupiscence less debauched than my reason. Aristippus established certain opinions so bold, in favor of voluptuousness and riches, that he made all Philosophie to mutiny against him. But concerning his manners, Dionysius the tyrant, having presented him with three fair young wenches, that he might chuse the fairest, he answered he would chuse them all three, and that Paris had very ill successes forasmuch as he had preferred one above her fellowes. But they being brought to his own house, he sent them backe again, without tasting them. His servant one day carrying store of money after him, and being so overcharged with the weight of it that he complained, his master commanded him to cast so much thereof away as troubled him. And Epicurus, whose positions are irreligious and delicate, demeaned himself in his life very laboriously and devoutly. He wrote to a friend of his, that he lived but with browne bread and water, and entreated him to send him a piece of cheese, against the time he was to make a solemn feast. May it be true, that to be perfectly good we must be so by an hidden, natural, and universall proprietie, without law, reason, and example? The disorders and excesses wherein I have found my self engaged are not (God be thanked) of the worst. I have rejected and condemned them in my self, according to their worth; for my judgement was never found to be infected by them. And on the other side, I accuse them more rigorously in my self than in another. But that is all: as for the rest, I applie but little resistance unto them, and suffer my self over-easily to encline to the other side of the balance, except it be to order and empeach them from being commixt with others, which (if a man take not good heed unto himself) for the most part entertaine and enterchaine themselves the one with the other. As for mine, I have, as much as it has laine in my power, abridged them, and kept them as single and as alone as I could: ------nec ultra, Errorem foveo -- Juven. Sat. viii. 164. Nor do I cherish any more, The error which I bred before. For, as touching the Stoics opinion, who say, that when the wise man worketh, he worketh with all his vertues together; howbeit, according to the nature of the action, there be one more apparent than other (to which purpose the similitude of mans body might, in some sort, serve their turn; for the action of choler cannot exercise itself, except all the humors set-to their helping hand, although choler be predominant) if thence they will draw a like consequence, that when the offender trespasseth, he does it with all the vices together, I do not so easily believe them, or else I understand them not: for, in effect, I feel the contrary. They are sharpe-wittie subtilties, and without substance, about which Philosophie does often busie itself. Some vices I shun; but othersome I eschew as much as any saint can do. The Peripatetikes do also disavow this connexitie and indissoluble knitting together. And Aristotle is of opinion, That a wise and just man may be both intemperate and incontinent. Socrates avowed unto them, who in his phisiognomie perceived some inclination unto vice, that indeed it was his natural propension, but that by discipline he had corrected the same. And the familiar friends of the Philosopher Stilpo were went to say, that being borne subject unto wine and women, he had, by studie, brought himself to abstaine from both. On the other side; what good I have, I have it by the lot of my birth: I have it neither by law nor prescription, nor by any apprentiship. The innocencie that is in me is a kind of simple- plaine innocencie, without vigor or art. Amongst all other vices, there is none I hate more than Crueltie, both by nature and judgement, as the extremest of all vices. But it is with such an yearning and faint- hartednesse, that if I see but a chickins necke puld off, or a pigge stickt, I cannot chuse but grieve, and I cannot well endure a seelie dewbedabled hare to groan when she is seized upon by the houndes, although hunting be a violent pleasure. Those that are to withstand voluptuousness do willingly use this argument, to show it is altogether vicious and unreasonable: That where she is in her greatest prime and chief strength, she does so over- sway us, that reason can have no accesse unto us, and for a further trial, alleage the experience we feel and have of it in our acquaintance with women. -----cum iam præsagit gaudia corpus Atque in eo est Venus, ut muliebria conserat arva. -- Lucr. iv. 1097. When now the body does light-joyes fore-know, And Venus set the womans fields to sow. Where they think pleasure does so far transport us beyond ourselves, that our discourse, then altogether overwhelmed, and our reason wholie ravished in the gulfe of sensualitie, cannot by any means discharge her function. I know it may be otherwise: and if a man but please, he may sometimes, even upon the very instant cast his mind on other conceits. But she must be strained to a higher key, and heedfully pursued. I know a man may gourmandize the earnest and thoughtconfounding violence of that pleasure: for I may with some experience speak of it, and I have not found Venus to be so imperious a Goddesse as many, and more reformed than my self, witness her to be. I think it not a wonder, as does the Queene of Navarre, in one of the tales of her Heptameron (which, respecting the subject it treateth of, is a very prettie book) nor do I deem it a matter of extreme difficultie for a man to weare out a whole night, in all opportunity and liberty, in companie of a fair mistresses long time before sued-unto, and by him desired; religiously keeping his word, if he have engaged himself, to be contented with simple kisses and plaine touching. I am of opinion that the example of the sport in hunting would more fit the same: wherein as there is less pleasure, so there is more distraction and surprising, whereby our reason being amazed, looseth the leisure to prepare herself against it: when as after a long game, the beast does suddenly start, or rowse up before us, and perhaps in such a place where we least expected the same. That suddaine motion and the earnestnesse of showting, jubeting and hallowing, still ringing in our ears, would make it very hard for those who love that kind of close or chamber-hunting, at that very instant, to withdraw their thoughts elsewhere. And poets make Diana victoriously to triumph both over the firebrand and arrows of Cupid. Quis non malarum quas amor curas habet Hæc inter obliviscitur? -- Hor. Epod. ii. 37. While this is doing, who does not forget The wicked cares wherewith Love’s heart does fret? But to return to my former discourse, I have a very feeling and tender compassion of other mens afflictions, and should more easily weep for companie sake, if possible for any occasion whatsoever I could shed tears. There is nothing sooner moveth tears in me than to see others weepe, not only fainedly, but however, whether truly or forcedly. I do not greatly waile for the dead, but rather envie them. Yet do I much waile and moan the dying. The canibales and savage people do not so much offend me with roasting and eating of dead bodies; as those which torment and persecute the living. Let any man be executed by law, how deservedly soever, I cannot endure to behold the execution with an unrelenting eye. Some one going about to witness the clemencie of Julius Cæsar; ’He was,’ says he, ’tractable and mild in matters of revenge. Having compelled the pirates to yield themselves unto him, who had before taken him prisoner and put him to ransome, forasmuch as he had threatned to have them all crucified, he condemned them to that kind of death, but it was after he had caused them to be strangled.’ Philemon his secretarie, who would have poysoned him, had no sharper punishment of him than an ordinary death. Without mentioning the Latin Author, who for a testimony of clemencie, dared to alleage the only killing of those by whom a man has been offended, it may easily be guessed that he is tainted with vile and horrible examples of cruelties such as Roman Tyrants brought into fashion. As for me, even in matters of justice, whatsoever is beyond a simple death, I deem it to be meere crueltie: and especiall amongst us, who ought to have a regardfull respect that their soules should be sent to heaven, which cannot be, having first by intolerable tortures agitated, and as it were brought them to despair. A souldier, not long since, being a prisoner, and perceiving from a loft a tower, where he was kept, that store of people flocked together on a greene, and carpenters were busie at work to erect a skaffold, suppposing the same to be for him, as one desperat, resolved to kill himself, and searching up and down for something to make himself away, found nothing but an old rustie cart-naile, which fortune presented him with; he took it, and therewithall, with all the strength he had, strooke and wounded himself twice in the throat, but seeing it would not rid him of life, he then thrust it into his bellie up to the head, where he left it fast- sticking. Shortly after, one of his keepers coming in unto him, and yet living, finding him in that miserable plight, but weltring in his goare-blood and readie to gasp his last, told the Magistrates of it, which, to prevent time before he should die, hastned to pronounce sentence against him: which when he heard, and that he was only condemned to have his head cut off, he seemed to take heart of grace again, and to be sorie for what be had done, and took some comfortable drinks, which before be had refused, greatly thanking the Judges for his unhoped gentle condemnation: And told them, that for fear of a more, sharply-cruel, and intolerable death by law, he had resolved to prevent it by some violent manner of death, having by the preparations he had seen the carpenters make, and by gathering of people together, conceived an opinion that they would torture him with some horrible torment, and seemed to be delivered from death only by the change of it. Were I worthie to give counsell, I would have these examples of rigor, by which superior powers go about to keep the common people in awe, to be only exercised on the bodies of criminall malefactors: For, to see them deprived of Christian burial, to see them hauled, disbowelled, parboyled, and quartered, might perhaps touch the common sort as much as the paines they make the living to endure: howbeit in effect it be little or nothing, as says God, Qui corpus occidunt, et postea non habent quod faciant. (Luke xii. 4.) ’Those that kill the body’, but have afterwards no more to do:’ And Poets make the horror of this picture greatly to prevaile, indeed, and above death. Heu reliquias semiassi Regis, denudatis ossibus, Per terram sanie delibutas foede divexarier. -- Cic. Tusc. Qu. i. O that the reliques of an halfe burnt King, bones bared, On earth besmear’d with filth, should be so fouly marred. It was my fortune to be at Rome upon a day that one Catena, a notorious high-way theefe, was executed: at his strangling no man of the companie seemed to be mooved to any ruth; but when he came to be quartered, the Executioner gave no blow that was not accompanied with a piteous voice and hartie exclamation, as if every man had had a feeling sympathie, or lent his senses to the poor mangled wretch. Such inhumane outrages and barbarous excesses should be exercised against the rinde, and not practised against the quick. In a case somewhat like unto this, did Artaxerxes assuage and mitigate the sharpnesse of the ancient laws of Persia, appointing that the Lords which had trespassed in their estate, whereas they were wont to be whipped, they should be stripped naked, and their clothes whipped for them; and where they were accustomed to have their hair pulled off, they should only have their hat taken off. The Egyptians, so devout and religious, thought they did sufficiently satisfie divine Justice, in sacrificing painted and counterfeit hogges unto it: An over-hardy invention to go about with pictures and shadowes to appease God, a substance so essentiall and divine. I live in an age wherein we abound with incredible examples of this vice, through the licentiousnesse of our civill and intestine wars: and read all ancient stories, be they never so tragical, you shall find none to equall those we daily see practised. But that has nothing made me acquainted with it. I could hardly be persuaded before I had seen it, that the world could have afforded so marble-hearted and savage- minded men, that for the only pleasure of murther would commit it; then cut, mangle, and hacke other members in pieces to rouze and sharpen their wits, to invent unused tortures and unheard-of torments: to devise new and unknown deaths, and that in cold blood, without any former enmitie or quarrell, or without any gain or profit; and only to this end, that they may enjoy the pleasing spectacle of the languishing gestures, pitifull notions, horror-moving yellings, deep fetcht groanes, and lamentable voyces of a dying and drooping man. For that is the extremest point whereunto the crueltie of man may attaine. Ut homo hominem, non iratus, non timens, tantum spectaturus occidat; (Sen. Clem. ii. c. 4.) ’That one man should kill another, neither being angrie nor afeard, but only to looke on.’ As for me, I could never so much as endure, without remorse or grief, to see a poore, sillie, and innocent beast pursued and killed, which is harmlesse and void of defense, and of whom we receive no offence at all. And as it commonly happens, that when the Stag begins to be embost, and finds his strength to faile him, having no other remedie left him, does yield and bequeath himself unto us that pursue him, with tears suing to us for mercy: ------ questuque cruentus Atque imploranti similis: -- Virg. Æn. vii. 521. With blood from throat, and tears from eyes, It seems that he for pittie cryes: was ever a grievous spectacle unto me. I seldom take any beast alive but I give him his liberty. Pythagoras was wont to buy fishes of fishers, and birds of fowlers to set them free again. ----- primoque a cæde ferarum Incaluisse puto maculatum sanguine ferrum. -- Ovid. Metam. xv. 106. And first our blades in blood embrude deem With slaughter of poore beasts did reeking steeme. Such as by nature show themselves bloody-minded towards harmlesse beasts, witness a natural propension unto crueltie. After the ancient Romanes had once enured themselves without horror to behold the slaughter of wild beasts in their shewes, they came to the murther of men and Gladiators. Nature (I fear me) has of her own self added unto man a certain instinct to inhumanitie. No man taketh delight to see wild beasts sport and wantonly to make much one of another: Yet all are pleased to see them tugge, mangle, and enterteare one another. And lest any body should jeast at this sympathie, which I have with them, Divinitie itself wills us to show them some favor: And considering that one self-same master (I mean that incomprehensible worlds-framer) has placed all creatures in this his wondrous palace for his service, and that they, as well as we, are of his household: I say it has some reason to injoyne us to show some respect and affection towards them. Pythagoras borrowed Metempsychosis of the Egyptians, but since it has been received of diverse Nations, and especially of our Druides: Morte carent animæ, semperique priore relicta Sede, novis domibus vivunt, habitantque receptæ. -- 158. Our death-less soules, their former seats refrained, In harbors new live and lodge entertained. The Religion of our ancient Gaules inferred, that soules being eternall, ceased not to remove and change place from one body to another: to which fantasie was also entermixed some consideration of divine justice. For, according to the soules behaviors, during the time she had been with Alexander, they sayd that God appointed it another body to dwell in either more or less painfull, and suitable to her condition. ----- muta ferarum Cogit vincla pati truculentos ingerit ursis, Prædonesque lupis, fallaces vilpibus addit. Atque per varios annos per mille figuras Egit, letheo purgatos flumine tandem Rursus ad humanæ revocat primordia formæ. -- Claud. in Ruff. i. 482, 491. Dumbe hands of beasts he makes men’s soules endure, Blood-thirstie soules he does to Beares enure, Craftie to Foxes, to Woolves bent to rapes; Thus when for many years, through many shapes, He has them dri v’n in Lethe lake at last, Them purg’d he turns to mans forms whence they past. If the soul had been valiant, they placed it in the body of a Lion: if Voluptuous, in a Swine: if faint-harted, in a Stagge or a Hare; if malicious, in a Foxe; and so of the, rest, until that being purified by this punishment, it re-assumed and took the body of some other man again. Ipse ego, nam memini, Troiani tempore belli Panthoides Euphorbus eram. -- Ovid. Metam. xv. 160. When Troy was won, I, as I call to mind, Euphorbus was, and Panthus son by kind. As touching that alliance betweene us and beasts, I make no great accompt of it, nor do I greatly admit it, neither of that which diverse Nations, and namely of the most ancient and noble, who have not only received beasts into their societie and companie, but allowed them a place far above themselves; sometimes deeming them to be familiars and favored of their Gods, and holding them in a certain awful respect and reverence more than humane, and others acknowledging no other God nor no other Divinity than they. Belluæ a barbaris propter beneficium consecratæ: (Cic. Nat. Deor. i.) ’Beasts by the Barbarians were made sacred for some benefit.’ ----- crocodilon adorat Pars hæc, illa pavet saturam serpentibus Ibin, Effigies sacri hic nitet aurea Corcopitheci. Juven. Sat. xv. 2. This Country does the Crocodile adore, That feares the Storks glutted with Serpents gore, The sacred Babion here, In gold shape does appeare. -----hic piscem fluminis, illic Oppida tota canem venerantur. -- 7. A fish here whole Townes reverence most, A dog they honor in that coast. And the very same interpretation that Plutarke gives unto this error, which is very well taken, is also honorable for t hem. For, he says, that (for example sake) it was neither the Cat nor the Oxe that the Egyptians adored, but that in those beasts they worshipped some image of divine faculties. In this patience and utility, and in that vivacity, or (as our neighbors the Borgonians with all Germany) the impatience to see themselves shut up: Whereby they represented the liberty which they loved and adored beyond all other divine faculty, and so of others. But when amongst the most moderate opinions I meet with some discourses that go about and labor to show the near resemblance betweene us and beasts, and what share they have in our greatest privileges, and with how much likely- hood they are compared unto us, truly I abate much of our presumption, and am easily removed from that imaginary soveraigntie that some give and ascribe unto us above all other creatures. I f all that were to be contradicted, yet is there a kind of respect and a general duty of humanity which tieth us not only unto brute beasts that have life and sense, but even unto trees and plants. Unto men we owe Justice, and to all other creatures that are capable of it, grace and benignity. There is a kind of interchangable commerce and mutual bond betweene them and us. I am not ashamed nor afraid to declare the tenderness of my childish Nature which is such that I cannot well reject my Dog if he chance (although out of season) to fawne upone me, or beg of me to play with him. The Turkes have almes and certain hospitals appointed for brute beasts. The Romans have a public care to breed and nourish Geese, by whose vigilance their capital had been saved. The Athenians did precisely ordaine that all manner of Mules which had served or been imploied about the building of their temple called Hecatompedon should be free and suffered to feed wherever they pleased, without any let or impeachment. The Agrigentines had an ordinary custom seriously and solemnly to bury all such beasts as they had held dear; as horses of rare worth and merit, speciall dogs, choice or profitable birds, or such as had but served to make their children sport. And the sumptnous magnificence which in all other things was ordinary and peculiar unto them, appeared also almost notably in the stately sumptuousnesse and costly number of monuments erected to that end, which many ages after have endured and been maintained in pride and state. The Egyptians were wont to bury their Wolves, their Dogs, their Cats, their Beares, and Crocodiles in holy places, embalming their carcasses, and at their deaths, to weare mourning weeds for them. Cymon caused a stately honorable tombe to be erected for the Mares, wherewith he had three times gained the prize at running in the Olimpike games. Ancient Xantippus caused his Dog to be enterred upon a hill by the sea shore, which ever since has been named by him. And Plutarch (as himself says) made it a matter of conscience, in hope of a small gain to sell or send an Oxe to the shambles that had served him a long time. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XII: AN APOLOGIE OF RAYMOND SEBOND CHAPTER XII: AN APOLOGIE OF RAYMOND SEBOND NOWLEDGE is without all Contradiction a most profitable and chief ornament, Those who despise it declare evidently their sottishnesse: Yet do not I value it at so excessive a rate as some have done; namely Herillus the Philosopher, who grounded his chief felicitie upon it, and held that it lay in her power to make us content and wise: which I cannot believe, nor that which others have said, that Knowledge is the mother of all virtue, and that all vice proceedeth of ignorance. Which if it be it is subject to a large interpretation. My house has long since ever stood open to men of understanding, and is very well known to many of them: for my father, who commanded the same fifty yeeres and upward, set on fire by that new kind of earnestnesse wherewith King Francis the first imbraced Letters, and raised them unto credit, did with great diligence and much cost endeavor to purchase the acquaintance of learned men; receiving and entertaining them as holy persons, and who had some particular inspiration of divine wisdom; collecting their sentences and discourses as if they had been Oracles; and with so much more reverence and religious regard by how much less authority he had to judge of them: for he had no knowledge of Letters no more than his predecessors before him. As for me I love them indeed, but yet I worship them not. Amongst others, Peter Bunel (a man in his time by reason of his learning of high esteeme) having sojourned a few days at Montaigne with my father and others of his coat being ready to depart thence, presented him with a book entituled Theologia naturalis; sive liber creaturarum magistri Raimondi de Sebonde. And for so much as the Italian and Spanish tongues were very familiar unto him, and that the book was written in a kind of latinized Spanish, whereof diverse words had Latine terminations; he hoped that with little aid he might reape no small profit by it, and commended the same very much unto him, as a book most profitable, and fitting the dayes in which he gave it him. It was even at what time the new fangles of Luther began to creepe in favor, and in many places to shake the foundation of our ancient beleefe. Wherein he seemed to be well advised, as he who by discourse of reason fore-saw that this budding disease would easily turn to an execrable Atheisme: For the vulgar wanting the faculty to judge of things by themselves, suffering itself to be carried away by fortune and led on by outward apparances, if once it be possessed with the boldness to despise and malapertnesse to impugne the opinions which tofore it held in awful reverence (as are those wherein consisteth their salvation) and t hat some articles of their religion be made doubtfull and questionable, they will soon and easily admit an equal uncertainty in all other parts of their beleefe, as they that had no other grounded authority or foundation but such as are now shaken and weakned, and immediately reject (as a tyrannical yoke) all impressions they had in former times received by the authority of Lawes, or reverence of ancient custom. Nam cupide conculcatur nimis anti metutum. -- Lucr. v. 1150. That which we fear’d before too much, We gladly scorne when tis not such. Undertaking thenceforward to allow of nothing, except they have first given their voice and particular consent to the same. My father, a few days before his death, lighting by chance upon this book, which before he had neglected, amongst other writings commanded me to translate the same into French. It is easy to translate such Authors, where nothing but the matter is to be represented; but hard and dangerous to undertake such as have added much to the grace and elegancy of the language, namely to reduce them into a weaker and poorer tongue. It was a strange taske and new occupation for me: but by fortune being then at leisure and unable to gainsay the commandement of the best father that ever was, I came ere long (as well as I could) to an end of it: wherein he took singular delight, and commanded the same to be printed, which accordingly was after his decease performed. I found the conceits of the author to be excellent, the contexture of his work well followed, and his project full of pietie. Now forasmuch as diverse ammuse themselves to read it, and especially Ladies, to whom we own most service, it has often been my hap to help them, when they were reading it, to discharge the book of two principal objections, which are brought against the same. His drift is bold, and his scope adventurous for he undertaketh by humane and natural reasons, to establish and verifie all the articles of Christian religion against Atheists. Wherein (to say truth) I find him so resolute and so happy, as I deem it a thing impossible to do better in that argument, and think that none equalleth him. Which book seeming to me both over-rich and exquisite, being written by an author whose name is so little known, and of whom all we know is, that he was a Spaniard, who about two hundred yeeres since professed Physicke in Tholouse: I demanded once of Adrianus Turnebus (a man who knew all things) what such a book might be; who answered, that he deemed the same to be some Quintessence extracted from out Saint Thomas Aquinas: For, in good truth, only such a spirit fraught with so infinite erudition, and so full admirable subtilities was capable of such and so rare imitiations. So it is, that whosoever be the author or deviser of it (the title whereof ought not without further reason to be taken from Sebond) he was a very sufficient-worthie man, and endowed with sundrie other excellent qualities. The first thing he is reproved for in his Book is, that Christians wrong themselve much, in that they ground their beleefe upon humane reasons, which is conceived but by faith and by a particular inspiration of God. Which objection seems to containe some zeale of pietie; by reason whereof we ought, with so much more mildnes and regard, endeavor to satisfie them that propose it. It were a charge more befitting a man conversant, and suitable to one acquainted with the holy Scriptures, than me, who am altogether ignorant in them. Nevertheless I think, that even as to a matter so divine and high, and so much exceeding al humane understanding, as is this verity, wherwith it has pleased the goodness of God to enlighten as, it is most requisit that he affoord and lend us his helpe; And that; with an extraordinary and privileged favor, that so we may the better conceive and entertaine the same: For, I suppose that means meerely humane can no way be capable of it; which if they were, so many rare and excellent mindes, and so plenteously stored with natural faculties, as have been in times past, would never by their discourse have mist the attayning of this knowledge. It is faith only which lively and assuredly embraceth the high mysteries of our Religion. And no man can doubt but that it is a most excellent and commendable enterprise, properly to accommodate and fit to the service of our faith, the natural helpes and humane implements which God has bestowed upon us. And no question is to be made but that it is the most honorable employment we can put them unto; and that there is no occupation or intent more worthy a good Christian, than by all means, studies, and imaginations, carefully to endeavor how to embellish, amplifie, and extend the truth of his beleefe and religion. It is not enough for us to serve God in spirit and soul; we owe him besides, and we yield unto him , a corporall worshipping; we applie our limbs, our motions, and all external things, to honor him. The like ought to be done, and we should accompany our faith with all the reason we possesse: Yet alwayes with this proviso, that we think it does not depend of us, and that all our strength and arguments can never attaine to so supernaturall and divine a knowledge: Except it seize upon us, and as it were enter into us by an extraordinarie infusion: And unless it also enter into us not only by discourse, but also by humane means, she is not in her dignitie nor in her glory. And verily I fear therfore, that except this way, we should not enjoy it. Had we fast-hold on God; by the interposition of a lively faith; had we hold-fast on God by himself, and not by us; had we a divine foundation; then should not humane and worldly occasions have the power so to shake and totter us, as they have. Our hold would not then yield to so weake a battery: The love of noveltie; the constrainte of Princes; the good success of one partie; the rash and casual changing of our opinions, should not then have the power to shake and alter our beleefe. We should not suffer the same to be troubled at the wil and pleasure of a new argument, and at the persuasion , no, not of all the rhetorike that ever was we should withstand these boistrous billowes with an inflexible and unmoveable constancy: Illisos fluctus rupes, ut vasta refundit Et varias circumlatrantes dissipat undas, ---Mole sua. -- VIRG. Æn. vii. 587. As huge rocks do regorge the invective waves, And dissipate the billowes brawling braves, Which these gainst those still bellowe out. Those being big and standing stout. If this raie of Divinitie did in any sort touch us, it would everie where appeare: Not only our words, but our actions, would bear some show and lustre of it. Whatsoever should proceed from us, might be seen inligh tned with this noble and matchlesse brightness. We should blush for shame, that in humane sects there was never any so factious, what difficultie or strangenesse soever his doctrine maintained, but some sort conforme his behaviors and square his life unto it: Whereas so divine and heavenly an institution never markes Christians but by the tongue. And will you see whether it be so? Compare but our manners unto a Turke, or a Pagan, and we must needs yield unto them: Whereas in respect of our religious superioritie, we ought by much, indeed by an incomparable distance, out-shine them in excellencie: And well might a man say, Are they so just, so charitable, and so good? Then must they be Christians. All other outward shewes and exterior apparences are common to all religious: As hope, affiance, events, ceremonies, penitence, and martyrdoms. The peculiar badge of our truth should be virtue; As it is the heavenliest and most difficult marke, and worthiest production of Verity itself, And therefore was our good Saint Lewis in the right, when that Tartarian King, who was become a Christian, intended to come to Lyons, to kisse the Popes feet, and there to view the sanctitie he hoped to find in our lives and manners, instantly to divert him from it, fearing lest our dissolute manners and licentious kind of life might scandalize him, and so alter his opinion fore- conceived of so sacred a religion. Howbeit the contrary happened to another, who for the same effect being come to Rome, and there viewing the disolutenesse of the Prelates and people of those dayes, was so much the more confirmed in our religion; considering with himself what force and divinity it must of consequence have, since it was able, amidst so many corruptions and so viciously-poluted hands, to maintaine her dignitie and splendor. Had we but one only graine of faith, we should then be able to remove mountaines from out their place, says the Holy Writ. Our actions being guided and accompanied with Divinitie, should not then be meerely humane, but even as our beliefe, containe some wonder-causing thing. Brevis est institutio vitæ honestæ beatæque, si credas: ’The institution of an honest and blessed life is but short, if a man believe.’ Some make the world believe that they believe things they never do. Others (and they are the greater number) persuade themselves they do so, as unable to conceive what it is to believe. We think it strange if in wars, which at this time do so oppresse our state we see the events to float so strangely, and with so common and ordinary a manner to change and alter: The reason is, we adde nothing unto it but our own. Justice, which is on the one side, is used but for a cloake and ornament; she is indeed alleadged, but not received, nor harboured, nor wedded. She is as in the mouth of a Lawyer, and not as she ought in the heart and affection of the partie. God oweth his extraordinarie assistance unto faith and religion, and not to our passions. Men are but directors unto it and use religion for a show: It ought to be cleane contrary. Doe but marke if we do not handle it as it were a peece of waxe, from out so right and so firme a rule, to draw so many contrary shapes. When was this better seen than now-adaies in France? Those which have taken it on the left, and those who have taken it on the right hand: Such as speak the false, and such who speak the truth of it, do so likewise employ and fit the same to their violent and ambitious enterprises, proceede unto it with so conformable a proceeding in riotousnesse and injustice, they make the diversitie they pretend in their opinions doubtfull, and hard to be beleeved, in a thing from which depends the conduct and law of our life. Can a man see from one same School and Discipline, more united and like customs and fashions to proceed? View but the horrible impudencie wherewith we tosse divine reasons to and fro, and how irreligiously we have both rejected and taken them again, according as fortune has in these public stormes transported us from place to place. This solemn proposition: Whether it be lawfull for a subject, for the defense of religion, to rebell and take arms against his Prince: Call but to mind in what mouthes but a twelve-moneth agoe the affirmative of the same was the chief pillar of the one part; the negative was the main-underprop of the other: And listen now from whence commeth the voice and instruction of one and other: and whether arms clatter and clang less for this than for that cause. And we burne those men which say that truth must be made to abide the yoke of our need: And how much worse does France than speak it. Let us confesse the truth: he that from out this lawfull army should cull out first those who follow it for meere zeale of a religious affection than such as only regard the defense and protection of their countries laws or service of their Prince; whether he could ever erect a compleat company of armed men. How comes it to pass that so few are found who have still held one same wil and progresse in our public revolutions, and that we see them now and then but faintly and sometimes as fast as they can headlong to run into the action? And the same men, now by their violence and rashnesse, and now through their slowness demissnes, and heavines to spoile, and as it were overthrow our affairs, but that they are thrust into them by casual motives, and particular consideration, according to the diversities wherewith they are moved? I plainly perceive we lend nothing unto devotion but the offices that flatter our passions. There is no hostilitie so excellent as that which is absolutely Christian. Our zeale worketh wonders, whenever it secondeth our inclinations towards hatred, crueltie, ambition, avarice, detraction, or rebellion. Towards goodnes, benignitie, or temperance it goeth but slowly, and against the hair, except miraculously, some rare complexion leade him unto it, it neither runnes nor flieth to it. Our religion was ordained to root out vices, but it shrowdeth, fostreth, and provoketh them. As commonly we say, ’We must not make a foole of God.’ Did we believe in him, I say not through faith, but with a simple beleefe; indeed (I speak it to our confusion) did we but believe and know him, as we do an other story, or as one of our companions; we should then love him above all other things, by reason of the infinite goodnes and unspeakable beauty that is and shines in him: Had he but the same place in our affections that riches, Pleasures, glory, and our friends have: The best of us does not so much fear to wrong him as he does to injure his neighbour, his kinsman, or his master. Is there so simple a mind who, on the one side having before him the object of one of our vicious pleasures, and on the other to his full view perfect knowledge and assured persuasion, the state of an immortall glory, that would enter into contention of one for the other? And so we often refuse it through meere contempt: for what draws us to blaspheming, unless it be at all adventures, the desire it self of the offence? The Philosopher Antisthenes, when he was initiated in the mysteries of Orpheus, the priest saying unto him that such as vowed themselves to that religion should after death receive eternall and perfect felicities, replied, ’If you believe it, why do you not die your self?’ Diogenes more roughly (as his manner was) and further from our purpose, answered the priest who persuaded him to be one of his order, that so he might come unto and attaine the happinesse of the other world: ’Wilt you have me believe that those famous men, Agesilaus and Epaminondas, shall be miserable, and that you, who art but an asse, and does nothing of any worth; shall be happy, because you are a Priest?’ Did we but receive these large promises of everlasting blessednesse with like authority as we do a philosophicall discourse, we should not then have death in that horror as we have: Non jam se moriens dissolvi conquereretur, Sed magis ire foras, vestemque relinquere ut anguis Gauderet, prælonga senex aut cornua cervus. -- Lucr. iii. 630 He would not now complains to be dissolved dying, But rather more rejoice , that now he is forth-flying, Or as a Snake his coat out-worne, Or as old Harts, does cast his horne. I will be dissolved, should we say, and be with Jesus Christ. The forcible power of Platoes discourse of the immortality of the soul provoked diverse of his Schollers unto death, that so they might more speedily enjoy the hopes he told them of. All which is a most evident token that we receive our religion but according to our fashion and by our own hands, and no otherwise than other religions are received. We are placed in the countrie where it was in use; where we regard her antiquity, or the authority of those who have maintained her; where we fears the menaces wherewith she threatneth all misbeleevers, or follow her promises. The considerations ought to be applied and employed to our beleefe, but as subsidiaries: they be human bonds. Another country, other testimonies, equall promises, likewise menaces, might semblaby imprint a cleane contrary religion in us: we are Christians by the same title as we are either Perigordins or Germans. And as Plato says: ’There are few so confirmed in Atheisme but some great danger will bring unto the knowledge of God’s divine power.’ The part does not touch or concerne a good Christians: It is for mortal and worldly religions to be received by a humane convoy. What faith is that like to be which cowardice of heart does plant and weaknesse establish in us? A goodly faith, that beleeves that which it beleeveth only because it wanteth the courage not to believe the same. A vicious passion, as that of inconstancie and astonishment is, can it possibly ground any regular production in our mindes or soules? They establish, says he, by the reason of their judgement, that whatsoover is reported of hell, or of after-coming paines, is but a fiction: but the occasions to make trial of it, offering itself at what time age or sicknesse does summon them to death, the error of the same, through the horrour of their future condition, does then replenish them with another kind of beleefe. And because such impressions make mens hearts fearfull, he by his laws inhibiteth all instruction of such threats and the persuasion that any evil may come unto man from the Gods, except for his greater good, and for a medicinable effect, whensoever he falleth into it. They report of Bion that being infected with the Atheismes of Theodorus, he had for a long time made but a mockerie of religious men; but when death did once seize upon him he yielded unto the extremest superstitious: As if the Gods would either be removed or come again, according to Bions business. Plato and these examples conclude that we are brought to believe in God either by reason or by compulsion, Atheisme being a proposition as unnaturall and monstrous as it is hard and uneasie to be established in any mans mind, how insol ent and unruly soever he may be: many have been seen to have conceived either through vanity or fiercenesse, strange and seld-known opinion, as if they would become reformers of the world by affecting a profession only in countenance: who though they be sufficiently foolish, yet are they not powerfull enough to ground or settle it in their consciences. Yet will not such leave to lift up their joined hands to heaven, give them but a stoccado on their breast: and when fear shall have supprest, or sicknesse vanquished this licentious fervour of a wavering mind, then will they suffer themselves gently to be reclaimed, and discreetly to be persuaded to give credit unto true beliefe and public examples. A decree seriously digested is one thing, and these shallow and superficiall impressions another, which bred by the dissolutenesse of a loose spirit, do rashly and uncertainely float up and down the fantasie of a man. Oh men, most braine-sicke and miserable, that endeavour to be worse than they can! The error of Paganisme and the ignorance of our sacred truth, was the cause of this great soules-fall: but only great in worldly greatnes; also in this next abuse, which is, that children and old men are found to be more susceptible or capable of religion, as if it were bred and had her credit from our imbecillitie. The bond which should binde our judgement, tie our will, enforce and join our soules to our Creator, should be a bond taking his doubling and forces, not from our considerations, reasons, and passions, but from a divine and supernaturall compulsion, having but one form, one countenance, and one grace, which is the authority and grace of God. Now our heart being ruled and our soul commanded by faith, reason wills that she draws all our other parts to the service of her intent, according to their power and facultie. Nor is it likely but that this vast worlds-frame must bear the impression of some markes, therein imprinted by the hand of this great wondrous architect, and that even in all things therein created there must be some image, somewhat resembling and having coherencie with the workeman that wrought and framed them. He has left imprinted in these high and misterious works the characters of his divinitie: and only our imbecility is the cause we can not discover nor read them. It is that which himself telleth us, that by his visible operations be does manifest those that are invisible to us. Sebond has much travelled about this worthie studie, and sheweth us, that there is no parcell of this world that either belyeth or shameth his Maker. It were a manifest wronging of God’s goodnesse if all this universe did not consent and sympathise with our beleefe. Heaven, earth, the elements, our bodies, our soul, indeed all things else, conspire and agree unto it: only the means how to make use of them must be found out: They will instruct us sufficiently, be we but capable to learne and to to understand. For this world is a most holy temple, into which man is brought there to behold statues and images not wrought by mortal hand, but such as the secret thought of God has made sensible, as the Sunne, the Starres, the Waters and the Earth, thereby to represent the intelligible unto us. ’The invisible things of God,’ says St. Paul, ’do evidently appeare by the creation of the world, judgeing of his eternall Wisdome and Divinity by his workes. Atque adeo faciem coeli non invidet orbi Ipse Deus, vultusque suos corpusque recludit Semper volvendo seque ipsum inculcat et offert Ut bene coqnosci possit, doceatque videndo Qualis est, doceatque suas attendere leges. -- Manil. iv. 840. God to the world does not heav’ns face envie, But by still moving it does notifie His face and essence, does himself applie, That he may well be knowen, and teach by seeing, How he goes, how we should marke his decreeing. Now our reason and humane discourse is as the lumpish and barren matter, and the Grace of God is the form thereof. ’Tis that which gives both fashion and worth unto it. Even as the vertuous actions of Socrates and Cato are but frivolous and unprofitable because they had not their end, and regarded not the love and obedience of the true creator of all things, and namely, because they were ignorant of the true knowledge of God: So is it of our imaginations and discourse; they have a kind of body, but a shapelesse masse, without light or fashion, unless faith and the grace of God be ioyned thereunto. Faith, giving as it were a tincture and lustre unto Sebonds arguments, make them the more firme and solid: They may well serve for a direction and guide to a young learner, to lead and set him in the right way of this knowledge. They in some sort fashion and make him capable of the grace of God, by means whereof our beliefe is afterwards achieved and made perfect. I know a man of authority, brought up in letters, who confessed unto me that he was reclaimed from out the errours of mis-beleeving by the arguments of Sebond. And if it happen they be dispoyled of this ornament, and of the helpe and approbation of faith, and taken but for meere humane fantazies, yet to combat those that headlong are fallen into the dreadfull error and horrible darkenesse of irreligious even then shall they be found as firme and forcible as any other of that condition that may be opposed against them. So that we shall stand upon terms to say unto our parties, Si melius quid habes, accerse, vel imperium fer. -- Hor. i. Epist.v. 6. If you have any better, send for me, Or else that I bid you, contented be. Let them either abide the force of our proofes, or show us some others, upon some other subject, better compact and more full. I have in a manner unawares half engaged my self in the second objection, to which I had purposed to frame an answer for Sebond. Some of his arguments are weake and simple to verifie what he would, and undertake to front him easily. Such fellowes must somewhat more roughly be handled, for they are more dangerous and more malicious than the first. Man does willingly apply other mens sayings to the advantage of the opinions he has fore-judged in himself. ’To an Atheist all writings make for Atheisme. He with his own venome infecteth the innocent matter. These have some preoccupation of judgment that makes their taste wallowish and tastelesse, to conceive the reasons of Sebond. As for the rest, they think to have fair play offered them if they have free liberty to combat our religion with meere worldly weapons; which they durst not charge, did they behold her in her majesty, full of authority and commandement. The means I use to suppresse this frenzy, and which seems the fittest for my purpose, is to crush and trample this humane pride and fiercenesse under foot, to make them feel the emptinesse, vacuitie, and no worth of man: and violently to pull out of their hands the silly weapons of their reason; to make them stoop, and bite and snarle at the ground, under the authority and reverence of God’s Majesty. Only to her belongeth science and wisdom, it is she alone can judge of herself; and from her we steale whatsoever we repute, value, and count ourselves to be. Ου γαρ εα φρονειν ο θεος εγα αλλον η εαυτον. Of greater, better, wiser mind than he, God can abide no mortal man should be. Let us suppress this overweening, the first foundation of the tyrannie of the wicked spirit. Deus superbis resistit: humilibus autem dat gratiam: (Prov. iii. 14, iv. 6. 1. Pet. v. 5.) ’God resisteth the proud, but gives grace to the humble.’ Plato says ’that intelligence is in all the Gods, but little or nothing at all in men.’ Meanewhile it is a great comfort unto a Christian man to see our mortal implements and fading tooles so fitly sorted to our holy and divine faith; that when they are employed to the mortal and fading subjects of their nature, they are never more forcible nor more joyntlie appropriated unto them. Let us then see whether man has any other stronger reasons in his power then Sebondes, and whether it be in him, by argument or discourse, to come to any certainty. For, St. Augustine, pleading against these kind of men, because he would upbraid them with their injustice, in that they hold the parts of our beleefe to be false, and that our reason faileth in establishing them: and to show that many things may be, and have been, whereof our discourse can never ground the nature and the causes: he proposeth and setteth down before them certain knowen and undoubted experiments, wherein man confesseth to see nothing, which he does as all things else, with a curious and ingenious search. More must be done, and they must be taught, that to convince the weaknesse of their reason we need not go far to cull out rare examples. And that it is so defective and blinde, as there is no facility so clear that is clear enough unto her: that easy and uneasie is all one to her; that all subjects equally, and Nature in general disavoweth her jurisdiction and interposition. What preacheth truth unto us, when it biddeth us flie and shun worldly philosophy; when it so often telleth us ’that all our wisdom is but folly before God; that of all vanities man is the greatest; that man, who presumeth of his knowledge, does not yet know what knowledge is: and that man, who is nothing, if he but think to be something, seduceth and deceiveth bimselfe?’ These sentences of the Holy Ghost do so lively and manifestly express what I would maintaine, as I should neede no proofe against such as with all submission and obeysance would yield to his authority. But these will needs be whipt to their own cost, and cannot abide their reason to be combatted, but by itself. Let us now but consider man alone without other help, armed but with his own weapons, and unprovided of the grace and knowledge of God, which is all his honor, all his strength, and all the ground of his being. Let us see what hold-fast or free-hold he has in this gorgeous and goodly equipage. Let him with the utmost power of his discourse make me understand upon what foundation he has built those great advantages and ods he supposeth to have over other creatures. Who has persuaded him that this admirable moving of heavens vaults, that the eternal light of these lampes so fiercely rowling over his head, that the horror-moving and continnall motion of this infinite vaste ocean were established, and continue so many ages for his commoditie and service? Is it possible to imagine anything so ridiculous as this miserable and wretched creature, which is not so much as master of himself, exposed and subject to offences of all things, and yet dareth call himself Master and Emperor of this Universe? In whose power it is not to know the least part of it., much less to command the same. And the Privileges which he so fondly challengeth to be the only absolute creature in this huge worlds frame, perfectly able to know the absolute beautie and several parts thereof, and that he is only of power to yield the great architect thereof due thanks for it, and to keep account both of the receipts and layings out of the world. Who has sealed him his patent? Let him show us his letters of privilege for so noble and so great a charge. Have they been granted only in favor of the wise? Then concerne they but a few. Are the foolish and wicked worthy of so extraordinary a favor, who being the worst part of the world, should they be preferred before the rest? Shall we believe him: Quorum igitur causa quis dixerit effectum esse mundum? Eorum scilicet animantium quo ratione utuntur. Hi sunt dii et homines, quibus profecto nihil est melius: (CIC. Nat. Deor. ii.) ’For whose cause then shall a man say that the world was made? In sooth, for those creatures sake which have the use of reason; those are Gods and men, than whom assuredly nothing is better.’ We shall never sufficiently baffle the impudency of this conjoyning. But silly wretch, what has he in him worthie such an advantage? To consider the incorruptible life of the celestiall bodies, their beauty, greatness, and agitation, continued with so just and regular a course. ----- cum suspicimus magni celestia mundi Templa super, stellisque micantibus Æthera fixum, Et venit in mentem Lunæ Solisque viarum. -- LUCR. v. 1214 When we of this great world the heavenly temples see Above us, and the skies with shine-starres fixt to be, And marks in our discourse, Of Sunne and Moone the course. To consider the power of domination these bodies have not only upon our lives and condition of our fortune. Facta etenim et vitas hominum suspendit ab astris. -- MANIL. Astron. iii. 58. For on the stars he does suspend Of men, the deeds, the lives, and end. But also over our dispositions and inclinations, our discourses and wils, which they rule, provoke, and move at the pleasure of their influences, as our reason finds and teacheth us. ------ speculataque longe Deprendit tacitis dominantia legibus astra. Et totum alterna mundum ratione moveri, Fatorumque vices certis discernere signis. -- MANIL. Astron. i. 62. By speculation it from far discerns, How stars by secret laws do guide our sterns, And this whole world is moov’d by entercourse And by sure signes of fates to know the course. Seeing that not a man alone, nor a king only, but monarchies and empires; indeed, and all the world below is moved at the shaking of one of the least heavenly motions. Quantaque quam parvi faciant discrimina motus: Tantum est hoc regnum quod regibus imperat ipsis. -- MANIL. Astron. iv. 93. How little motions make, how different affection: So great this Kingdoms is, that has Kings in subjection. If our virtue, vices, sufficiency and knowledge, and the same discourse we make of the power of the starres, and the comparison betweene them and us, commeth as our reason judgeth by their meane and through their favor; --furit alter amore, Et pontum tranare potest, et vertere Troiam, Alterius sors est scibendis legibus apta: Ecce patrem nati perimunt, natosque parentes, Mutuaque armati coeunt in vuln era fratres, Non nostrum hoc bellum est; coquntur tanta movere, Inque suas ferri ponas, lacerandaque membra: Hoc quoque fatale est sic ipsum expandere fatum. -- MANIL. Astron. iv. 78, 118. One with love madded, his love to enjoy Can crosse the seas, and overturns all Troy Anothers lot is to set laws severe. Lo sons kill fathers, fathers sons destroy, Brothers for mutual wounds their arms do bear, Such war is not our own, forc’t are we to it, Drawne to our own paines, our own limbs to teare Fates so t’observe t’is fatall, we must do it. If we hold that portion of reason, which we have from the distribution of heaven, how can she make us equall unto it? How can she submit his essence and conditions unto our knowledge? Whatsoever we behold in those high bodies does affright us: Quæ molitio, quæ ferramenta, qui vectes, quo machinæ, qui ministri tanti operis fuerunt? (CIC. Nat. Deor. i.) ’What workmanship? What yron-braces? What main beames, what engines? What masons and carpenters were to so great a work?’ Why do we then deprive them of soul, of life, and of discourse? Have we discovered or knowen any unmoveable or insensible stupidity in them? We, who have no commerce but of obedience with them? Shall we say we have seen the use of a reasonable soul in no other creature but in man? What? Have we seen anything comparable to the sunne? Leaveth he to be, because we have seen nothing semblable unto it? And does he leave his moving because his equall is nowhere to be found? If that which we have not seen is not, our knowledge is wonderful abridged. Quæ sunt tantæ, animi angustia? ’What narrownesse of my heart is such?’ Be they not dreames of humane vanity, to make a celestiall earth or world of the moone, as Anaxagoras did? And there in to plant habitations, and as Plato and Plutarch do, erect their colonies for our use. And to make of our known earth a bright shining planet? Inter cætera mortalitatis incommoda, et hoc est caligo mentium: nec tantum necessitas errandi, sed errorum amor: (SEN. Ira. ii. cap. 9.) ’Among other discommodities of our mortality this is one, there is darknesse in our minds, and in us not only necessity of erring, but a love of errors.’ Corruptibile corpus aggravat animam, et deprimit terrena inhabitatio sensum multa cogitantem: (Ibid. Epist. xcv.) ’Our corruptible body does overlode our soul, and our dwelling on earth weighs down our sense that is set to think of many matters.’ Presumption is our natural and originall infirmitie. Of all creatures man is the most miserable and fraile, and therewithall the proudest and disdainfullest. Who perceiveth and seeth himself placed here amidst the filth and mire of the world, fast-tied and nailed to the worst, most senselesse, and drooping part of the world, in the vilest corner of the house, and farthest from heavens coape, with those creatures that are the worst of the three conditions; and yet dareth imaginarily place himself above the circle of the moon, and reduce heaven under his feet. It is through the vanity of the same imagination that he dare equall himself to God, that he ascribeth divine conditions unto himself, that he selecteth and separateth himself from out the rank of other creatures; to which his fellow-brethren and compeers he cuts out and shareth their parts, and allotteth them what portions of means or forces he thinkes good. How knows he by the virtue of his understanding the inward and secret motions of beasts? By what comparison from them to us does he conclude the brutishnesse he ascribeth unto them? When I am playing with my cat, who knowes whether she have more sport in dallying with me than I have in gaming with her? We entertaine one another with mutual apish trickes. If I have my hour to begin or to refuse, so has she hers. Plato in setting forth the golden age under Saturne, amongst the chief advantages that man had then, reporteth the communication he had with beasts, of whom enquiring and taking instruction, he knew the true qualities and differences of every one of them: by and from whom he got an absolute understanding and perfect wisdom, whereby he led a happier life than we can do. Can we have a better proofe to judge of mans impudency touching beasts? This notable author was of opinion that in, the greatest part of the corporall form which nature has bestowed on them, she has only respected the use of the prognostications, which in his days were thereby gathered. The defect which hindreth the communication betweene them and us, why may it not as well be in us as in them? It is a matter of divination to guesse in whom the fault is that we understand not one another. For we understand them no more than they us. By the same reason, may they as well esteeme us beasts as we them. It is no great marvell if we understand them not: no more do we the Cornish, the Welch, or Irish. Yet have some boasted that they understood them, as Apollonius Thyaneus, Melampus, Tiresias, Thales, and others. And if it be (as Cosmographers report that there are nations who receive and admit a dogge to be their king, it must necessarily follow that they give a certain interpretation to his voice and moving. We must note the parity that is betweene us. We have some meane understanding of their senses, so have beasts of ours, about the same measure. They flatter and faune upon us, they threat and entreat us, so do we them. Touching other matters, we manifestly perceive that there is a full and perfect communication amongst them, and that not only those of one same kind understand one another, but even such as are of different kindes. Et mutæ pecudes, et denique secla ferarum Dissimilis fuerunt voces variasqe cluere, Cum metus aut dolor est, aut eum tam gaudia gliscunt. -- LUCR. v. 1069. Whole heards (though dumbe) of beasts, both wild and tame, Use diverse voices, diffrent sounds to frame, As joy, or grief, or fear, Upspringing passions bear. By one kind of barking of a dogge, the horse knows he is angrie; by another voice of his, he is nothing dismaid. Even in beasts that have no voice at all, by the reciprocall kindness which we see in them, we easily inferre there is some other meane of entercommunication: their jestures treat, and their motions discourse. Non alia longe ratione atque ipse videtur Protrahere ad gestum, pueros infantia lingua. -- Ibid. 1040. No otherwise, then for they cannot speak, Children are drawne by signes their mindes to breake. And why not, as well as our dumbe men dispute, argue, and tel l histories by signes? I have some so ready and so excellent in it, that (in good sooth) they wanted nothing to have their meaning perfectly understood. Doe we not daily see lovers with the looks and rowling of their eyes, plainly show when they are angrie or pleased, and how they entreat and thanke one another, assigne meetings, and express any passion? E’l silentio ancor suole Haver prieghi e parole. Silence also has a way, Words and prayers to convay. What do we with our hands? Doe we not sue and entreat, promise and performe, call men unto us and discharge them, bid them farewell and be gone, threaten, pray, beseech, deny, refuse, demand, admire, number, confesse, repent, fear, be ashamed, doubt, instruct, command, incite, encourage, sweare, witness, accuse, condemne, absolve, injurie, despise, defie, despight, flatter, applaud, blesse, humble, mocke, reconcile, recommend, exalt, show gladnesse, rejoice, complain, waile, sorrow, discomfort, despair, cry out, forbid, declare silence and astonishment: and what not? with so great variation and amplifying as if they would contend with the tongue. And with our head do we not invite and and call to us, discharge and send away, avow, disavow, honor, worship, disdaine, demand, direct, rejoice, affirme, deny, complain, cherish, blandish, chide, yield, submit, brag, boast, threaten, exhort, warrant, assure, and enquire? What do we with our eye-lids? and with our shoulders? To conclude, there is no motion nor jesture that does not speak, and speaks in a language very easy, and without any teaching to be understood: nay, which is more, it is a language common and public to all: whereby it followeth (seeing the varietie and severall use it has from others) that this must rather he deemed the proper and peculiar speech of humane nature. I omit that which necessitie in time of need does particularly instruct and suddenly teach such as need it; and the alphabets upon fingers, and grammars by jestures; and the sciences which are only exercised and expressed by them: and the nations Plinie reporteth to have no other speech. An Ambassador of the City of Abdera, after he had talked a long time unto Agis, King of Sparta, said thus unto him: ’O King, what answer wilt you that I bear backe unto our citizens?’ ’Thus (answered he) that I have suffered you to speak all you wouldst, and as long as you pleasedst, without ever speaking one word.’ Is not this a kind of speaking silence, and easy to be understood? And as for other matters; what sufficiency is there in us that we must not acknowledge from the industry and labours of beasts? Can there be a more formall and better ordained policy, divided into so severall charges and offices, more constantly entertained, and better maintained, than that of Bees? Shall we imagine their so orderly disposing of their actions, and managing of their vocations, have so proportioned and formall a conduct without discourse, reason, and forecast? His quidam signis atque hoc exempla sequuti, Esse apibus partem divinæ mentis, et haustus Aethereos dixere. --VIRG. Geor. IV. 219. Some by these signes, by these examples moved, Said that in Bees there is and may be proved Some taste of heavenly kind, Part of celestial mind. The Swallowes which, at the approach of springtime, we see to pry, to search, and ferret all the corners of our houses; is it without judgement they seek, or without discretion they chuse from out a thousand places, that which is fittest for them to build their nest andlodging? And in that prety cunning contexture and admirable framing of their houses, would birds rather fit themselves with a round than a square figure, with an obtuse than a right angle, except they knew both the commodities and effects of them? Would they (suppose you) first take water and then clay, unless they guessed that the hardnesse of the one is softened by the moistnesse of the other? Would they floore their palace with mosse or down, except they foresaw that the tender parts of their young ones shall thereby be more soft and easy? Would they shroud and shelter themselves from stormy weather, and build their cabbins towards the East, unless they knew the different conditions of winds, and considered that some are more healthfull and safe for them than some others? Why does the Spider spin her artificiall web thicke in one place and thin in another? And now useth one, and then another knot, except she had an imaginary kind of deliberation, fore- thought, and conclusion? We perceive by the greater part of their workes what excellency beasts have over us, and how weake our art and short our cunning is, if we go about to imitate them. We see, notwithstanding, even in our grosest works, what faculties we employ in them, and how our mind employeth the uttermost of her skill and forces in them: why should we not think as much of them? Wherefore do we attribute the workes which excel whatever we can performe, either by nature or by art, unto a kind of unknown, natural, and servile inclination? Wherein unawares we give them a great advantage over us, to infer that nature, led by a certain loving kindness, leadeth and accompanieth them (as it were by the hand) unto all the actions and commodities of their life; and that she forsaketh and leaveth us to the hazard of fortune; and by art to quest and find out those things that are behovefull and necessarie for our preservation: and therewithall demeth us the means to attaine by any institution and contention of spirit to the natural sufficiency of brute beasts: So that their brutish stupidity does in all commodities exceed whatsoever our divine intelligence can effect. Verily, by this account, we might have just cause and great reason to terme her a most injust and partiall step- dame: But there is no such thing, our policy is not so deformed and disordered. Nature has generally imbraced all her creatures: And there is not any but she has amply stored with all necessary means for the preservation of their being. For the daily plaints, which I often hear men (when the licence of their conceits does sometimes raise them above the clouds, and then headlong tumble them down even to the Antipodes), exclaiming that man is the only forsaken and out-cast creature, naked on the bare earth, fast bound and swathed, having nothing to cover and arm himself withall but the spoile of others; whereas Nature has clad and mantled all other creatures, some with shels, some with huskes, with rindes, with hair, with wooll, with stings, with bristles, with hides, with mosse, with feathers, with skales, with fleeces, and with silke, according as their quality might need or their condition require: And has fenced and armed them with clawes, with talons, with hoofes, with teeth, with stings, and with hornes, both to assaile others and to defend themselves: And has moreover instructed them in everything fit and requisite for them, as to swim, to run, to creepe, to flie, to roare, to bellow, and to sing: whereas man only (Oh, silly, wretched man) can neither go, nor speak, nor shift, nor feed himself, unless it be to whine and weepe only, except he be taught. Tum porro, puer ut sævis projectus ab undis Navila, nudus humi, jacit infans indignus omni Vitali auxilio, cum primum in luminis oras Nexibus ex alvo matris natura profundit, Vagituque locum lugibri complet, et æqum est Cui tantum in vita restet transire malorum: At variæ crescunt pecudes, armenta, feræque, Nec crepitacula eis opus est, nec cuiquam adhibenda est Almæ nutricis blanda atque infracta loquela: Nec varias quærunt vestes pro tempore cæli: Denique non armis opus est, non mænibus altis Qeis sua tutentur quando omnibus omnia large Tellus ipsa parit, naturaque dædata rerum.-- LUCR. v. 222. An infant, like a shipwracke ship-boy cast from seas, Lies naked on the ground and speechlesse, wanting all The helpes of vital spirit, when nature with small ease Of throes, to see first light, from her wombe lets him fall, Then, as is meet, with mournful cries he fils the place, For whom so many ils remaine in his lives race. But diverse herds of tame and wild beasts foreward spring, Nor need they rattles, nor of Nurces cockring-kind The flattering broken speech their lullaby need sing. Nor seek they diverse coats, as diverse seasons bind. Lastly no armour need they, nor high-reared wall Whereby to guard their own, since all things unto all Worke-master nature does produce, And the earth largely to their use. Such complaints are false. There is a greater equality and more uniform relation in the policy of the world. Our skin is as sufficiently provided with hardnesse against the injuries of the weather as theirs. Witness diverse nations which yet never knew the use of clothes. Our ancient Gaules were but slightly apparelled, no more are the Irish-men, our neighbors, in so cold a climate: which we may better judge by ourselves, for all those parts of our body we are pleased to leave bare to winde and wether, are by experience found able to endure it. If there were any weake part in us which in likely-hood should seem to fear cold, it ought to be the stomacke, where digestion is made. Our forefathers used to have it bare, and our ladies (as dainty-nice as they be) are many times seen to go open-breasted, as low as their navill. The handles and swathes about our children are no more necessary: and the mothers of Lacedemonia brought up theirs in all liberty and loosenesse of moving their limbs without swathing or binding. Our whining, our puling, and our weeping is common to most creatures, and diverse of them are often seen to waile and grone a long time after their birth, forasmuch as it is a countenance fitting the weaknesse wherein they feel themselves. As for the use of eating and feeding, it is in us, as in them, natural and without teaching. Sentit enim vim quisque suam quam possit abuti. -- LUCR. v. 1043. For every one soone-understanding is Of his own strength, which he may use amisse. Who will make question that a child having attained the strength to feed himself, could not quest for his meat and shift for his drinke? The earth without - labor or tilling does sufficiently produce and offer him as much as he shall need. And if not at all times, no more does she unto beasts; witness the provision we see the ants and other silly creatures to make against the cold and barren seasons of the yeare. The nations that have lately bin discovered, so plenteously stored with all manner of natural meat and drinke, without care or labor, teach us that bread is not our only food: and that without toyling our common mother nature has with great plentie stored us with whatsoever should be needfull for us, indeed, as it is most likely, more richly and amply than now adaies she does, that we have added so much art unto it. Et tellus nitidas fruges vinetaque læta Sponte sua primum mortalibus creavit, Ipsa dedit dulces foetus, et pabulaa læta, Quæ nunc vix nostro grandescunt aucta labore, Conterimusque boves et vires agricolarum: -- LUCR. ii. 1166 The earth itself at first of the own accord Did men rich Vineyards, and cleane fruit afford. It gave sweet of-springs, food from sweeter soyle Which yet scarse greater grow for all our toyle, Yet tire therein we do, Both Plough-men’s strength and Oxen too. The gluttonous excess and intemperate lavishnesse of our appetite exceeding all the inventions we endeavor to find out wherewith to glut and cloy the same. As for arms and weapons, we have more that be natural unto us than the greatest part of other beasts. We have more severall motions of limbs, and naturally without reaching: we reape more serviceable use of them than they do. Those which are trained up to fight naked, are seen head long to cast themselves into the same hazards and dangers as we do. If some beasts excel us in this advantage, we exceed many others: and the industrie to enable the skill to fortifie and the wit to shelter and cover our body by artificiall means, we have it by a kind of natural intinct and teaching. Which to prove, the elephant does whet and sharpen his teeth. he useth in war (for he has some he only useth for that purpose) which he heedfully spareth and never puts them to other service: When buls prepare themselves to fight, and they raise, scatter, and with their feet cast the dust about them: the wild boare whets his tusks; when the Ichneumon is to grapple with the crocodile, he walloweth his body in the mire, then lets the same drie and harden upon him, which he does so often that at last the same becomes as hard and tough as well as any compact crust, which serveth him in stead of a cuirace. Why shall we not say that it is as natural for us to arm ourselves with wood and yron? As for speech, sure it is that if it be not natural it is not necessary. I believe, nevertheless, that if a child, bred in some uncouth solitarinesse, far from haunt of people (though it were a hard matter to make trial of it) would no doubt have some kind of words to express, and speech to utter his conceits. And it is not to be imagined that nature has refused us that meane and barred us that helpe which she has bestowed upon many and diverse other creatures: for what is that faculty we see in them when they seem to complain, to rejoice, to call one unto another for helpe, and bid one another to loving conjunction (as commonly they do) by the use of their voice, but a kind of speech? And shall not they speak among themselves that speak and utter their mind unto us and we to them? How many waies speak we unto our dogges, and they seem to understand and answer us? With another language and with other names speak we unto and call them than we do our birds, our hogges, our oxen, our horses, and such like; and according to their different kindes we change our idiome. Cosi per entro loco schiera bruna S’ammusa l’una con I’altra formica, Forse a spiar lor via, et lor fortuna. --DANTE. Purgatorio, xxvi. 84. So Ants amidst their sable-coloured band One with another mouth to mouth confer, Haply their way, or state to understand. Me seems that Lactantius does not only attribute speech unto beasts, but also laughing. And the same difference of tongue, which according to the diversitie of countri es is found amongst us, is also found amongst beasts of one same kind. Aristotle to that purpose alleageth the diverse calles or purres of partriges, according to the situation of their place of breeding. ----- variæque volucres Longe alias alio jaciunt in tempore voces, Et partim mutant cum tempestatibus una Raucisonos cantus. -- LUCR. V. 1088. And diverse birds, send forth much diverse sounde At diverse times, and partly change the grounds Of their hoarce-sounding song, As seasons change along. But it would be known what language such a child should speak, and what some report by divination has no great likelyhood. And if against this opinion a man would alleage unto me that such as are naturally deafe, speak not at all: I answer that it is not only because they could not receive the instruction of the world by their ears, but rather inasmuch as the sense of hearing, whereof they are deprived, has some affinity with that of speaking, both which with a natural kind of ligament or seame hold and are fastned together. In such sort as what we speak we must first speak it unto ourselves, and before we utter and send the same forth to strangers we make it inwardly to sound unto our ears. I have said all this to maintaine the coherency and resemblance that is in all humane things, and to bring us unto the general throng. We are neither above nor under the rest: what ever is under the coape of heaven (says the wise man) runneth one law, and followeth one fortune. Indupedita suis fatalibus omnia vinclis. -- Ibid. 885. All things enfolded are, In fatall bonds as fits their share. Some difference there is, there are orders and degrees; but all is under the visage of one same nature, ----- res quaque suo ritu procedit, et omnes Fædere natura certo discrimina servant. -- LUCR. v. 932. All things proceed in their course, natures all Keeps difference, as in their league does fall. Man must be forced and marshalled within the lists of this policy. Miserable man, with all his wit, cannot in effect go beyond it: he is embraced and engaged, and as other creatures of his rank are, he is subjected in like bond, and without any prerogative or essentiall pre-excellencie; and what ever privilege he assume unto himself, he is of very meane condition. That which is given by opinion or fantasie has neither body nor taste. And if it be so that he alone, above all other creatures, has this liberty of imagination and this licence of thoughts which represent unto him both what is and what is not, and what him pleaseth, falsehood and truth; it is an advantage bought at a very high rate, and whereof he has little reason to glory: for thence springs the chiefest source of all the mischiefs that oppresse him, as sinne, sicknesse, irresolution, trouble and despaire. But to come to my purpose, I say therefore, there is no likelyhood, we should imagine, the beasts do the very same things by a natural inclination and forced genuitie, which we do of our freewil and industrie. Of the very same effects we must conclude likewise faculties, and by the richest effects infer the noblest faculites, and consequently acknowledge that the same discourse and way we hold in working, the very same, or perhaps some other better, do beasts hold. Wherefore shall we imagine that natural compulsion in them, that prove no such effect ourselves? Since it is more honorable to be addressed to act, and tyed to work orderly, by and through a natural and unavoideable condition and most approching to Divinitie, than regularly to work and act by and through a casual and rash liberty; and it is safer to leave the reignes of our conduct unto nature than unto ourselves. The vanity of our presumption maketh us rather to be beholding, and as it were endebted unto our own strength, for our sufficiency, than unto her liberalitie; and enrich other creatures with natural gifts, and yield those unto them, that so we may ennoble and honor our selves with gifts purchased, as me thinketh, by a very simple humor: for I would prize graces, and value gifts, that were altogether my own, and natural unto me, as much as I would those, I had begged, and with a long prenticeship, shifted for. It lyeth not in our power to obtaine a greater commendation than to be favoured both of God and Nature. By that reason, the fox, which the inhabitants of Thrace use when they will attempt to march upon the yce of some frozen river, and to that end let her go loose afore them, should we see her running alongst the river side, approch her eare close to the yce, to listen whether by any far or near distance she may hear the noyse or roaring of the water running under the same, and according as she perceiveth the yce thereby to be thicke or thinne, to go either forward or backward; might not we lawfully judge that the same discourse possesseth her head as in like case it would ours? And that it is a kind of debating reason and consequence drawen from natural sense? Whatsoever maketh a noyse moveth, whatsoever moveth is not frozen, whatsoever is not frozen is liquid, whatsoever is liquid yields under any weight? For to impute that only to a quicknesse of the sense of hearing, without discourse or con sequence, is but a foolish conceipt, and cannot enter into my imagination. The like must be judged of so many wiles and inventions wherewith beasts save themselves from the snares and scape the baits we lay to entrap them. And if we will take hold of any advantage tending to that purpose, that it is in our power to seize upon them, to employ them to our service, and to use them at our pleasure; it is but the same oddes we have one upon another. To which purpose we have our slaves or bond- men; and were not the Climacides certain women in Syria, which creeping on al foure upon the ground, served the ladies in steed of footstoles or ladders to get up into their coachs? Where the greater part of free men, for very slight causes, abandon both their life and being to the power of others. The wives and concubines of the Thracians strive and contend which of them shal be chosen to be slain over her husbands or lovers tombe. Have tyrants ever failed to find many men vowed to their devotion? Where some for an overplus or supererogation have added this necessity, that they must necessarily accompany them as well in death as in life. Whole hostes of men have thus tyed themselves unto their captaines. The tenor of the oath ministred unto the schollars that entered and were admitted the rude schoole of Roman Gladiators emplied these promises, which was this: we vow and sweare to suffer ourselves to be enchained, beaten, burned, and killed with the sword, and endure whatsoever any lawfull fenser ought to endure for his master: most religiously engaging both our body and soul to the use of his service: Ure meum, si vis, flamma caput et pete ferro Corpus, et intorto verbere terga seca. -- TIBUL. i. El. ix. 21. Burne tyrant (if you wilt my head with fire, with sword My body strike, my backe cut with hard-twisted cord. Was not this a very strict covenant? Yet were there some years ten thousand found that entered and lost themselves in those schooles. When the Scithians buried their king, they strangled over his dead body first the chiefest and best beloved of his concubines, then his cup-bearer, the master of his horse, his chamberlains, the usher of his chamber, and his master cooke. And in his anniversary killed fiftie horse, mounted with fifty pages, whom before they had slain with thrusting sharpe stakes into their fundament, which, going up along their chine-bone, came out at their throat; whom thus mounted; they set in orderly rankes about the tombe. The men that serve us do it better cheape, and for a less curious and favourable entreating than we use unto birds, unto horses, and unto dogges. What carke and toile apply we not ourselves unto for their sakes? Me thinks the vilest and basest servants will never do that so willingly for their masters which princes are glad to do for their beasts. Diogenes, seeing his kinsfolks to take care how they might redeeme him out of thraldome; ’they are fooles,’ said he, ’for it is my master that governeth, keepeth, feedeth, and serveth me:’ And such as keep or entertaine beasts may rather say they serve them than that they are served of them. And yet they have that natural greater magnanimity, that never lyon was seen to subject himself unto another lyon, nor one horse unto another horse, for want of heart. As we hunt after beasts, so tygers and lyons hunt after men, and have a like exercise one upon another: hounds over the hare; the pike or luce over the tench; the swallowes over the grasse-hoppers) and the sparrow-hawkes over blacke-birds and larkes. ------ serpente ciconia pullos Nutrit, et inventa per devia rura lacerta, Et leporem aut capream famulæ Iovis, et generosæ In saltu venantur aves. -- Juven. Sat. xiv. 74. The storke her young feeds with serpents prey, And lyzarts found somewhere out of the way, Joves servants - Eagles, hawkes of nobler kynde, In forrests hunt, a hare or kid to find, We share the fruits of our prey with our dogges and hawkes, as a meed of their pain and reward of their industry. As about Amphipolis, in Thrace, faulkners and wild hawks divide their game equally: and as about the Mæotide fennes, if fishers do not very honestly leave behind them an even share of their fishings for the woolves that range about those coasts, they presently run and teare their nets. And as we have a kind of fishing rather managed by sleight than strength, As that of hooke and line about our angling-rods, so have beasts amongst themselves. Aristotle reporteth that the cuttle-fish casteth a long gut out of her throat, which like a line she sendeth forth, and at her pleasure pulleth it in again, according as she perceiveth some little fish come near her, who being close hidden in the gravell or stronde, letteth him nible or bite the end of it, and then by little and little draws it in unto her, until the fish be so near that, with a soudaine leape, she may catch it. Touching strength, there is no creature in the world open to so many wrongs and injuries as man: we need not a whale, an elephant, nor a crocodile, nor any such other wild beast, of which one alone is of power to defeat a great number of men; seely lice are able to make Silla give over his Dictatorship: the heart and life of a mighty and triumphant emperor is but the break-fast of a seely little worme. Why say we that skill to discerne and knowledge to make choyce (gotten by art and acquired by discourse) of things good for this life, and availfull against sicknesse, and to distinguish of those which are hurtful, and to know the virtue of reubarb, quality of oake ferne and operation of polipodie, is only peculiar unto man? When we see the Goats of Candia being shot with an arrow to choose from out a million of simples the herb Dittamy or Garden-ginger, and there-with cure themselves; and the Tortoise having eaten of a Viper immediately to seek for Origon or wild Marjoram to purge herself: the Dragon to run and clear his eyes with Fenel: Cranes with their bils to minister glisters of sea-water unto themselves; the Elephants to pull out, not only from themselves and their fellowes, but also from their masters (witness that of King Porus, whom Alexander defeated) such javelins or darts as in fight have been hurled or shot at them, so nimbly and so cunningly as ourselves could never do it so easily and with so little pain: Why say we not likewise that that is science and prudence in them? For, if to depress them some would alleage it is by the only instruction and instinct of Nature they know it, that will not take the name of science and title of prudence from them; it is rather to ascribe it unto them than unto us for the honor of so assured a schoole-mistris. Chrysippus, albeit in other things as disdainfull a judge of the condition of beasts as any other Philosopher, considering the earliest movings of the dog, who coming into a path that led three severall ways in search or quest of his Master, whom he had lost, or in pursuit of some prey that has escaped him, goeth senting first one way and then another, and having assured himself of two, because he findeth not the tracke of what he hunteth for, without more adoe furiously betakes himself to the third; he is enforced to confesse that such a dog must necessarily discourse thus with himself, ’I have followed my Masters footing hitherto, he must of necessity pass by one of these three ways; it is neither this nor that, then consequently he is gone this other.’ And by this conclusion or discourse assuring him self, coming to the third path, he useth his sense no more, nor sounds it any longer, but by the power of reason suffers himself violently to be carried through it. This meere logicall tricke, and this use of divided and conjoyned. propositions, and of the sufficient numbring of parts: is it not as good that the dog know it by him self, as by Trapezuntius his logicke? Yet are not beasts altogether unapt to be instructed after our manner. We teach Blacke-birds, Starlins, Ravens, Piots, and Parots to chat; and that facilitie we perceive in them to lend us their voice so supple and their wind so tractable, that so we may frame and bring it to a certain number of letters and silables, witnesseth they have a kind of inward reason which makes them so docile and willing to learne. I think every man is cloied and wearied with seeing so many apish and mimmike trickes that juglers teach their Dogges, as the dances, where they misse not one cadence of the sounds or notes they hear: Marke but the diverse turnings and severall kinds of motions which by the commandement of their bare words they make them performe: But I wonder not a little at the effect, which is ordinary amongst us; and that is, the dogs which blind men use, both in City and in Country: I have observed how sodainly they will stop when they come before some doores where they are wont to receive alms: how carefully they will avoyd the shocke of Carts and Coaches, even when they have roome enough to pass by themselves. I have seen some going along a Town-ditch leave a plaine and even path and take a worse, that so they might draw their Master from the ditch. How could a man make the dog conceive his charge was only to looke to his masters safetie, and for his service to despise his own commoditie and good? And how should he have the knowledge that such a path would be broade enough for him, but not for a blind man? Can all this he conceived without reason? We must not forget what Plutarke affirmeth to have seen a dog in Rome do before the Emperor Vespasian the father in the Theatre of Marcellus. This Dog served a jugler, who was to play a fiction of many faces and sundry countenances, where he also was to act a part. Amongst other things he was for a long while to counterfeit and faine himself dead, because he had eaten of a certain drug: having swallowed a piece of bread, which was supposed to be the drug, he began sodainly to stagger and shake as if he had been giddie, then stretching and laying himself along as stiffe as if he were stark dead, suffered himself to be dragged and hauled from one place to another, according to the subject and plot of the play, and when he knew his time, first he began fair and softly to stir as if he were roused out of a dead slumber, then lifting up his head he looked and stared so gastly that all the bystanders were amazed. The Oxen, which in the Kings gardens of Susa were taught to water them and to draw water out of deepe wells, turned certain great wheeles, to which were fastned great buckets (as in many places of Languedoke is commonly seen) and being every one appointed to draw just a hundred turnes a day, they were so accustomed to that number as it was impossible by any compulsion to make them draw one more, which taske ended they would suddenly stop. We are grown striplings before we can tell a hundred; and many nations have lately been discovered that never knew what numbers meant. More discourse is required to teach others than to be taught. And omitting what Democritus judged and proved, which is, that beasts have instructed us in most of our Arts: As the Spider to weave and sew, the Swallow to build, the Swan and the Nightingale music, and diverse beasts, by imitating them, the art of Physicke: Aristotle is of opinion that Nightingales teach their young ones to sing, wherein they employ both long time and much care: whence it followeth that those which we keep tame in cages and have not had leisure to go to their parents schoole, lose much grace in their singing. Whereby we may conclude they are much amended by discipline and study. And amongst those that run wild, their song is not all one nor likewise. Each one has learnt either better or worse, according to his capacity. And so jealous are they in their prentiseship, that to excel one another they will so stoutly contend for the mastery that many times such as are vanquished die; their winde and strength sooner failing than their voice. The young ones wil very sadly sit recording their lesson, and are often seen labouring how to imitate certain song-notes: The Scholler listeneth attentively to his Masters lesson, and carefully yieldeth account of it; now one and then another shall hold his peace: Marke but how they endeavor to amend their faults, and how the elder striveth to reprove the youngest. Arrius protesteth to have seen an Elephant who on every thigh had a cimball hanging and one fastned to his truncke, at the sound of which all other Elephants danced in a round, now rising aloft, then lowting full low at certain cadences, even as the instrument directed them, and was much delighted with the harmony. In the great showes of Rome Elephants were ordinarily seen, taught to move and dance at the sound of a voice, certain dances, wherein were many strange shifts, enterchanges, caprings, and cadences, very hard to be learned. Some have been noted to konne and practise their lessons, using much study and care, as being loath to be chidden and beaten of their masters. But the tale of the piot is very strange, which Plutarke confidently witnesseth to have seen: ’This jay was in a Barbers shop of Rome, and was admirable in counterfeiting with her voice whatsoever she heard: It fortuned one day that certain Trumpeters staied before this shop and there sounded a good while; and being gone, all that day and the next after the piot began to be very sad, silent, and melancholy, whereat all men marvelled, and surmized that the noise or clang of the trumpets had thus affrighted and dizzied her, and that with her hearing she had also lost her voice. But at last they found she was but in a deep study and dumpish, retracting into herself, exercising her mind, and preparing her voice to represent the sound, and express the noise of the Trumpets she had heard. And the first voice she uttered was that wherein she perfectly expressed their straines, their closes, and their changes: having by her new prentiship altogether quit, and as it were scorned whatever she could prattle before. I will not omit to alleage another example of a Dogge, which Plutarke also says to have seen (as for any order or method I know very well I do but confound it, which I observe no more in ranging these examples than I do in all the rest of my business), who being in a ship, noted that his Dogge was in great perplexity how to get some Oyle out of a deepe Pitcher, which by reason of its narrow mouth he could not reach with his tongue, got him presently some Pibble stones, and put so many into the jarre that he made the Oyle come up so neare the brimme as he could easily reach and licke some. And what is that but the effect of a very subtill spirit? It is reported that the ravens of Barbary will do the like, when the water they would drinke is too low. This action does somewhat resemble that which Juba, a King of that Nation, relateth of their elephants; that when through the wiles of those that chase them, anyone chanceth to fall into certain deep pits which they prepare for them, and to deceive them they cover over with reeds, shrubs, and boughes, his fellowes will speedily with all diligence bring great store of stones and peeces of timber that so they may helpe to recover him out again. But this beast has in many other effects such affinity with man’s sufficiency, that would I particularly trace out what experience has taught, I should easily get an affirmation of what I so ordinarily maintaine, which is, that there is more difference found betweene such and such a man, than betweene such a beast and such a man. An Elephants keeper in a private house of Syria was wont every meale to steele away halfe of the allowance which was allotted him; it fortuned on a day his master would needs feed him himself, and having poured that just measure of barley which for his allowance he had prescribed for him, into his manger, the elephant, sternely eying his master, with his truncke divided the provender in two equal parts, and laid the one aside, by which he declared the wrong his keeper did him. Another having a keeper, who to encrease the measure of his provender was wont to mingle stones with it, came one day to the pot which with meat in it for his keepers dinner was seething over the fire, and filled it up with ashes. These are but particular effects, but that which all the world has seen, and all men know, which is, that in all the armies that came out of the East, their chiefest strength consisted in their elephants, by whom they reaped, without comparison, far greater effects than now adaies we do by our great ordnance, which in a manner holds their place in a ranged battle (such as have any knowledge in ancient histories may easily guesse it to be true). -----si quidem Tyrio servire solebant Anibali, et nostris ducibus, regique Molosso Horum majores, et dorso ferre cohortes, Partem aliquam belli, et euntem in prælia surriam -- JUV. Sat. xii. 107. Their elders usde great Hannibal to steed Our Leaders, and Molossian Kings at need, And on their backe to bear strong guarding Knights, Part of the war, and troupes addrest to fights. A man must needs rest assured of the confidence they had in these beasts, and of their discourse, yielding the front of a battle unt o them; where the least stay they could have made, by reason of their hugenesse and weight of their bodies, and the least amazement that might have made them turn head upon their own men, had bin sufficient to lose all. And few examples have been noted that ever it fortuned they turned upon their owns troupes, whereas we head-long throng one upon another, and so are put to rout. They had charge given them, not only of one simple moving, but of many and severall parts in the combat. As the Spaniards did to their dogges in their new conquest of the Indias, to whom they gave wages and imparted their booties, which beasts showed as much dexteritie in pursuing and judgement in staying their victory, in charging or retreating, and, as occasion served, in distinguishing their friends from their enemies, as they did earnestnesse and eagerness. We rather admire and consider strange than common things, without which I should never so long have amused my self about this tedious catalogue. For, in my judgement, he that shall meerly check what we ordinarily see in those beasts that live amongst us shall in them flnde as wonderful effects as those which with so much toile are collected in far countries and passed ages. It is one same nature which still does keep her course. He that throughly should judge her present estate might safely conclude both what shall happen and what is past. I have seen amongst us men brought by sea from distant countries, whose language, because we could in no wise understand, and that their fashions, their countenance, and their clothes did altogether differ from ours, who of us did not deem them brutish and savage? Who did not impute their mutenesse into stupidity or beastlines, and to see them ignorant of the French tongue, of our kissing the hands, of our low-lowting courtesys, of our behaviour and carriage, by which without contradiction, humane nature ought to take her patterne? Whatsoever seems strange unto us, and we understand not, we blame and condemne. The like befalleth us in our judging of beasts. They have diverse qualities, which somewhat simbolize witih ours, from which we may comparatively draw some conjecture, but of such as are peculiar unto them what know we what they are? Horses, dogges, oxen, sheepe, birds, and the greater number of sensitive creatures that live amongst us, know our voice, and by it suffer themselves to be directed. So did the lamprey which Crassus had, and came to him when he called it: so do the eeles that breed in Arethusa’s fountains. And my self have seen some fish-ponds where at a certain crie of those that kept them, the fish would presently come to shoare, where they were wont to be fed. ------ nomen habent, et ad magistri Vocem quisque sui venit citatus. -- MART. iv. Epig. XXX. 6. They have their proper Dames, and every one Comes at his master’s voice, as call’d upon. By which we may judge and conclude that elephants have some apprehension of religion, forasmuch as after diverse washings and purifications, they are seen to lift up their truncke as we do our arms, and at certain hours of the day, without any instruction, of their own accord, holding their eyes fixed towards the sunne-rising, fall into a long meditating contemplation; yet, because we see no such appearance in other beasts, may we rightly conclude that they are altogether void of religion, and may not take that ill payment which is hidden from us. As we perceive something in that action which the Philosopher Cleanthes well observed, because it somewhat draws near unto ours. He saw (as himself reporteth) a company of emmets go from their nest, bearing amongst them the body of a dead ant, toward another emmets nest, from which many other ants came, as it were to meet them by the way to parly with them, who after they had continued together awhile, they which came last, returned backe to consult (as you may imagine) with their fellow-citizens, and because they could hardly come to any capitulation, they made two or three voyages to and fro. In the end, the last come brought unto the other a worme from their habitation, as for a ransome of the dead, which worme the first company took upon their backes, and carried it home, leaving the dead body unto the other. See, here the interpretation that Cleanthes gave it: Witnessing thereby that those creatures which have no voice at all, have nevertheless mutual commerce and interchangable communication, whereof if we be not partakers, it is only our fault; and therefore do we fondly to censure it. And they yet produce diverse other effects, far surpassing our capacity, and so far out of the reach of our mutation that even our thoughts are unable to conceive them. Many hold opinion that in the last and famous sea- fight which Antonie lost against Augustus, his admiral-galley was in her course staied by that little fish the Latines call Remora, and the English a Suck-stone, whose property is to stay any ship he can fasten himself unto. And the Emperor Caligula, sailing with a great fleet along the coast of Romania, his own galley was suddenly staied by such a fish, which he caused to be taken sticking fast to the keele, moodily raging that so little a creature had the power to force both sea and winde, and the violence of all his oares, only with her bil sticking to his galley ( for it is a kind of shellfish) and was much more amazed when he perceived the fish being brought aboord his ship to have no longer that powerfull virtue which it had being in the sea. A certain citizen of Cyzicum, whilom purchased unto himself the reputation to be an excellent mathematician, because he had learnt the quality of the hedge-hogge, whose property is to build his hole or denne open diverse waies, and toward severall winds, and fore-seeing rising stormes, he presently stoppeth the holes that way, which thing the foresaid citizen heedfully observing, would in the City foretell any future storm, and what wind should blow. The cameleon taketh the colour of the place wherein he is. The fish called a pourcontrell, or manie-feet, changeth him self into what colour he lists as occasion offereth itself, that so he may hide himself from what he feareth, and catch what he seeketh for. In the cameleon it is a change preceding of passion, but in the pourcontrell a change in action; we ourselves do often change our colour and alter our countenance through sudden fear, choler, shame, and such like violent passions, which are wont to alter the hew of our faces, but it is by the effect of sufferance, as in the cameleon. The jaundise has power to make us yelow, but it is not in the disposition of our wils. The effects we perceive in other creatures, greater than ours, witness some more excellent faculty in them, which is concealed from us; as it is to be supposed diverse others of their conditions and forces are, whereof no appearance or knowledge commeth to us. Of all former predictions, the ancientest and most certain were such as were drawen from the flight of birds; we have nothing equall unto it, nor so admirable. The rule of fluttering, and order of shaking their wings, by which they conjecture the consequences of things to ensue, must necessarily be directed to so noble an operation by some excellent and supernaturall meane. For it is a wresting of the letter to attribute so wondrous effects to any natural decree, without the knowledge, consent, or discourse of him that causeth and produces them, and is a most false opinion, which to prove, the torpedo or cramp-fish has the property to benumme and astonish, not only the limbs of those that touch it, but also theirs that with any long pole or fishing line touch any part thereof, she does transmit and convey a kind of heavy numming into the hands of those that stir or handle the same. Moreover, it is averred that if any matter be cast upon them the astonishment is sensibly felt to gain upward, until it come to the hands, and even through the water it astonisheth the feeling-sence. Is not this a wonderful power? Yet is it not altogether unprofitable for the Cramp-fish, she both knowes and makes use of it: for to catch prey she pursueth, she is seen to hide herself under the mud, that, other fishes swimming over her, strucken and benumbed with her exceeding coldnesse, may fall into her clawes. The Cranes, swallowes, and other wandering birds, changing their abode according to the seasons of the years, show evidently the knowledge they have of their fore-divining faculty, and often put the same in use. Hunters assure us that to chose the best dog, and which they purpose to keep from out a litter of other young whelps, there is no better meane than the damme herself: for, if they be removed from out their kennell, him that she first brings thither again shall alwaies prove the best; or if one but encompasse her kennell with fire, looke which of her whelps she first seeketh to save, is undoubtedly the best; whereby it appeareth they have a certain use of prognosticating that we have not; or else some hidden virtue to judge of their young ones, different and more lively than ours. The manner of all beasts breeding, engendering, nourishing, working, moving, living, and dying, being so near to ours, what ever we abridge from their moving causes, and adde to our condition above theirs can no way depart from our reasons discourse. For a regiment of our health, Physitians propose the example of bats manner of life and proceeding unto us: for this common saying is alwaies in the people’s mouth: Tenez chauds les pieds et la teste, Au demeurant vivez en beste. -- JOUB. Err. Pop. pur. ii. 140. Keep warme (’tis meete) the head and feete: In all the rest, live like a beast. Generation is the chiefest natural action: we have a certain disposition of some members fittest for that purpose; nevertheless, they bid us range ourselves unto a brutish situation and disposition, as most effectuall: ------ more ferarum, Quadrupedumque maqis ritu, plerumque putantur Concipere uxores: quia sic loca sumere possunt, Pectoribus positis, sublatis semina lumbis. -- LUCR. iv. 1256. And reject those indiscreet and insolent motions which women have so luxuriously found out, as hurtful: conforming them to the example and use of beasts of their sex, as more modest and considerate. Nam mulier prohibet se concipere, atgue repugnat, Clunibus ipse viri Venerem si læta retractet, Atque exposato ciet omni pectore fluctus, Et enim sulci recta regione viaque Vomerem, atque locis avertit seminis ictum. -- LUCR. iv. 1260. If it be justice to give every one his due, beasts which serve, love, and defend their benefactors, pursue and outrage strangers, and such as offend them, by so doing they represent some show of our justice, as also in reserving a high kind of equality in dispensing of what they have to their young ones. Touching friendship, without all comparison, they professe it more lively and show it more constantly than men. Hircanus, a dog of Lysimachus the King, his master being dead, without eating or drinking, would never come from off his bed, and when the dead corps was removed thence he followed it, and lastly flung himself into the fire where his master was burned. As did also the dogge of one called Pyrrhus, who after he was dead would never budge from his masters couch, and when he was removed suffered himself to be carried away with him, and at last flung himself into the fire wherein his master was consumed. There are certain inclinations of affection which, without counsell of reason, arise sometimes in us, proceeding of a casual temerity, which some call sympathie: beasts as well as men are capable of it. We see horses take a kind of acquaintance one of another, so that often, traveling by the highway or feeding together, we have much ado to keep them asunder; we see them bend and applie their affections to some of their fellowes colours, as if it were upon a certain visage: and when they meet with any such, with signes of joy and demonstration of good will to joine and accost them, and to hate and shunne some other formes and colours. Beasts as well as we have choice in their loves, and are very nice in chusing of their mates. They are not altogether void of our extreme and unappeasable jealousies. Lustfull desires are either natural and necessary as eating and drinking; or else natural and not necessary, as the acquaintance of males and females; or else neither necessary nor natural: of this last kind are almost all mens, for they are all superfluous and artificiall. It is wonderful to see with how little nature will be satisfied, and how little she has left for us to be desired. The preparations in our kitchens do nothing at al concede her laws. The Stoics say that a man might very well sustain himself with one olive a day. The delicacy of our wines is no part of her lesson, no more is the surcharge and relishing which we adde unto our letcherous appetites. -----neque illa Magno prognatum deposcit console cunnum. -- HOR. Ser. i. Sat. ii. 30. These strange lustfull longings which the ignorance of good, and a false opinion, have possest us with, are in number so infinite that in a manner they expell all those which are natural, even as if there were so many strangers in a city that should either banish and expell all the natural inhabitants thereof, or utterly suppresse their ancient power and authority, and absolutely usurping the same, take possession of it. Brute beastes are much more regulare than we, and with more moderation containe themselves within the compasse which nature has prescribed them; but not so exactly but that they have some coherency with our riotous licenciousnesse. And even as there have been found, certain furious longings and unnaturall desires which have provoked men unto the love of beasts, so have diverse times some of them been drawn to love us, and are possessed with monstrous affections from one kind to another: witness the elephant that in the love of an herb-wife, in the city of Alexandria, was corivall with Aristophanes the Grammarian, who in all offices pertayning to an earnest woer and passionate suiter yielded nothing unto him; for, walking through the fruit-market, he would here and there snatch up some with his truncke, and carry them unto her: as near as might be he would never loose the sight of her, and now and then over her hand put his truncke into her bosome, to feel her breasts. They also report of a dragon that was exceedingly in love with a young maiden, and of a goose in the city of Asope which dearely loved a young child; also of a ram that belonged to the musitian Glausia. Do we not daily see munkies ragingly in love with women, and furiously to pursue them? And certain other beasts given to love the males of their own sex? Oppianus and others report some examples to show the reverence and manifest the awe some beasts in their marriages bear unto their kindred; but experience makes us often see the contrary: -----nec habetur turpe juvencæ Ferre patrem tergo: tua filia coniux: Quasque creavit, init pecudes caper: ipsaque cuius Semine concepta est, ex illo conecepit ales -- OVID. Metam. x. 325. To bear her Sire the Heifer shameth not: The Horse takes his own Fillies maiden-head: The Goat gets t hem with young whom he begot: Birds bred by them, by whom themselves were bred. Touching a subtil pranke and witty tricke, is there any so famous as that of Thales the philosopher’s mule, which, laden with salt, passing through a river chanced to stumble, so that the sacks she carried were all wet, and perceiving the salt (because the water had melted it to grow lighter, ceased not, as seen as she came near any water, together with her load, to plunge herself therein, until her master, being aware of her craft, commanded her to be laden with wooll, which being wet became heavier; the mule finding herself deceived, used her former policy no more. There are many of them that lively represent the visage of our avarice, who with a greedy kind of desire endeavor to surprise whatsoever comes within their reach, and though they reap no commodity, nor have any use of it, to hide the same very curiously. As for husbandry, they exceed us, not only in fore-sight to spare and gather together for times to come, but have also many parts of the skill belonging thereunto. As the ants, when they perceive their corne to grow mustie and graine to be sowre, for fear it should rut and putrifie, spread the same abroad before their nests, that so it may aire and drie. But the caution they use in gnawing, and prevention they employ in paring their graines of wheat, is beyond all imagination of mans wit: Because wheat does not alwaies keep drie nor wholesome, but moisten, melt, and dissolve into a kind of whey, namely, when it beginneth to bud, fearing it should turn to seed, and lose the nature of a storehouse, for their sustenance, the part and gnaw off the end whereat it wonts to bud. As for war, which is the greatest and most glorious of all humane actions, I would faine know if we will use it for an argument of some prerogative, or otherwise for a testimony of our imbecility and imperfection, as in truth the science we use to defeat and kill one another, to spoile and utterly to overthrow our own kind, it seems it has not much to make itself to be wished for in beasts, that have it not. ------ quando leoni Fortior eripuit ritam leo, quo nemore unquam Expirarit aper maioris dentibus apri? -- JUVEN. Sat. xv. 160. When has a greater Lion damnifide A Lions life? in what wood ever di’de, A boare by tusks and gore, Of any greater boare? Yet are not they altogether exempted from it witness the furious encounters of Bees, and the hostile enterprises of the Princes and Leaders of the two contrary Armies. ----- sæpe duobus Regibus incessit magno discordia motu, Continuoque animos vulgi et trepidantia bello Corda licet longe præsciscere. -- VIRG. Georg. iv. 67. Oft-times twixt two so great Kings great dissention With much adoe does set them at contention; The vulgare mindes strait may you see from far, And hearts that tremble at the thought of war. I never marke this divine description but me thinkes I read humane foolishnesse and worldly vanity painted in it. For these motions of war, which out of their horror and astonishment breed this tempest of cries and clang of sounds in us: Fulgur ubi ad cælum se tollit, totaque circum Ære renidescit tellus, subterque virum vi Excitur pedibus sonitus, clamoreque montes Icti rejectant voces ad sidera mundi: -- LUCR. ii. 326. Where lightning raiseth itself to the skies, The earth shines round with armour, soundes do rise By mens force under feet, wounded with noyse The hilles to heav’n reverberate their voice. This horror-causing array of so many thousands of armed men, so great fusion, earnest fervor, and undaunted courage, it would make one laugh to see by how many vain occasions it is raised and set on fire, and by what light means it is again suppressed and extinct. ----- Paridis propter narrator amorem Græcia Barbariæ diro collisa duello. -- HOR. i. Epist. ii. 6. For Paris lustfull love (as Stories tell) All Greece to direfull war with Asia fell. The hatred of one man, a spight, a pleasure, a familiar suspect, or a jealousie, causes which ought not to move two scolding fish-wives to scratch one another, is the soul and motive of all this hurly-burly. Shall we believe them that are the principal authors and causes therof? Let us but hearken unto the greatest and most victorious Emperor that ever, was, how pleasantly he laughs and wittily he plaies at so many battells and bloody fights, hazarded by both sea and land, at the blood and lives of five hundred thousand soules which followed his fortune, and the strength and riches of two parts of the world consumed and drawne drie for the service of his enterprise: Quod futuit Glaphyran Antonius, hanc mihi poenam Fulvia constituit, se quoque uti futuam Fulviam ego ut furuam? quid si me Manius oret Pædicam, faciam? non puto, si sapiam. Aut futue, aut pugnemus, ait: quid si mihi vita Charior est ipsa mentula? Signa canant. -- MART, xi. Epig. xxi. (I use my Latine somewhat boldly, but it is with that leave which you have given me.) This vast huge body has so many faces and severall motion, which seem to threat both heaven and earth. Quam multi Lybico volvuntur marmore fluctus, Sævus ubi Orion hybernis conditur undis. Vel cum sole novo densæ torrentur aristæ, Aut Hermi campo, aut Lyciæ flaventibus arvis, Scuta sonant, pulsuque pedum tremit excita tellus. -- VIRG. Æn. vii. 717. As many waves as rowle in Affricke marble bounds, When fierce Orion hides in Winter waves his head: Or when thicke-ears of Corne are parch’t by Sunne new-spred. In Hermus fruitfull fields, or Lycæs yellow grounds, With noyse of shields and feet, the trembling earth so sounds. ’This many-headed, diverse-armed, and furiously-raging monster, is man, wretched, weake and miserable man; whom, if you consider well, what is he but a crawling and ever- moving ants-nest?’ It nigrum campis agmen: -- VIRG, Æn.. iv. 404. The sable-coloured band, Marches along the Land. A gust of contrary winds, the croking of a flight of Ravens, the false pase of a horse, the casual flight of an Eagle, a dream, a sodaine voice, a false signe, a mornings mist, an evenings fogge, are enough to overthrow, sufficient to overwhelme and able to pull him to the ground. Let the Sunne but shine hot upon his face, he faints and swelters with heat: cast but a little dust in his eyes, as to the Bees mentioned by our Poet, all our ensignes, all our legions, indeed great Pompey himself, in the forefront of them is overthrowne and put to rout. (For as I remember it was he whom Sertorius vanquished in Spain, with all those goodly arms.) This also served Eumenes against Antigonus, and Surena against Crassus: Hi motus animorum, atque hæc certamina tanta, Pulveris exigui jactu compressa quiescent. -- VIRG. Georg. iv. 86, 87. Their stomacke-motions, these contentions great, [Calm’d] with a little dust, strait lose their heat. Let us but uncouple some of our ordinary flies, and let loose a few gnats amongst them, they shall have both the force to scatter and courage to consume him. The Portugals not long since beleagring the City of Tamly, in the territory of Xiatine, the inhabitants thereof brought great store of hives (whereof they have plentie) upon their walls; and with fire drove them so forcible upon their enemies, who, as unable to abide their assaults and endure their stingings, left their enterprize. Thus by this new kind of help was the liberty of the town gained and victory purchased; with so happy success, that in their retreating there was not one townes-man found wanting. The soules of Emperours and Coblers are all cast in one same mould. Considering the importance of Princes actions, and their weight, we persuade ourselves they are brought forth by some weighty and important causes; we are deceived: They are moved, stirred and removed in their motions by the same springs and wards that we are in ours. The same reason that makes us chide and braule and fall out with any of our neighbors, causeth a war to follow betweene Princes; the same reason that makes us whip or beat a lackey maketh a Prince (if he apprehend it) to spoyle and waste a whole Province. They have as easy a will as we, but they can do much more. Alike desires perturbe both a skinne-worme and an Elephant. Touching trust and faithfulnesse, there is no creature in the world so trecherous as man. Our histories report the earnest pursuit and sharpe chase that some dogges have made for the death of their masters. King Pirrhus, finding a dog that watched a dead man, and understanding he had done so three days and nights together, commanded the corps to be enterred and took the dog along with him. It fortuned one day, as Pirrhus was surveying the general musters of his army the dog perceiving in that multitude the man who had murthered his maister, loud-barking and with great rage ran furiously upon him; by which signes he furthered and procured his maisters revenge, which by way of justice was shortly executed. Even so did the dogge belonging to Hesiodus, surnamed the wise, having convicted the children of Canister of Naupactus of the murther committed on his Masters person. Another Dogge being apointed to watch a Temple in Athens, having perceived a sacrilegious theefe to carrie away the fairest jewels therein, barked at him so long as he was able, and seeing he could not awaken the Sextons or temple-keepers, followed the theefe whither-soever he went; daie-light being come, he kept himself a loof-off, but never lost the sight of him: if he offered him meat, he utterly refused it; but if any passenger chanced to come by, on them he fawned, with wagging his tail, and took what-ever they offered him; if the theefe staied to rest himself, he also staied in the same place. The news of this Dogge being come to the Temple-keepers, they as they went along, enquiring of the Dogs hair and colour, pursued his tracke so long that at last they found both the Dog and the theefe in the City of Cromyon, whom they brought backe to Athens, where for his offence he was severely punished. And the judges in acknowledgement of the Dogges good office, at the Cities charge appointed him for his sustenance a certain daily measure of Corne, and enjoyned the Priests of the Temple, carefully to looke unto him. Plutarke affirmeth this story to be most true, and to have hapned in his time. Touching gratitude and thankfulnesse (for me thinks we have need to further this word greatly), this only example shall suffice, of which Appion reporteth to have been a spectator himself. One day (says he) that the Senate of Rome (to please and recreate the common people) causd a great number of wild beasts to be baited, namely huge great Lions, it so fortuned that there was one amongst the rest, who by reason of his furious and stately carriage, of his unmatched strength, of his great limbs, and of his loud and terror-causing roaring, drew all bystanders eyes to gaze upon him. Amongst other slaves, that in sight of all the people were presented to encounter with these beasts, there chanced to be one Androclus of Dacia, who belonged unto a Roman Lord who had been Consull. This huge Lion, having eyed him afar off, first made a suddaine stop, as strucken into a kind of admiration, then with a mild and gentle contenance, as if he would willingly have taken acquaintance of him), fair and softly approached unto him: Which done, and resting, assured he was the man he took him for, begun fawningly to wagge his tail, as dogges do that fawne upon their newfound masters, and licke the poore and miserable slaves hands and thighs, who through fears was almost out of his wits and halfe dead. Androclus at last taking hart of grace, and by reason of the Lions mildness having rouzed up his spirits, and wishly fixing his eyes upon him, to see whether he could call him to remembrance, it was to all beholders a singular pleasure to observe the love, the joy, and blandishments each endevored to enter-show one another. Whereat the people raising a loud crie, and by their shouting and clapping; of hands seeming to be much pleased, the Emperor willed the slave to be brought before him, as desirous to understand of him the cause of so strange and seld-seen an accident, who related this new and wonderful story unto him. My Master (said he) being Proconsull in Affrica, forasmuch as he caused me every day to be most cruelly beaten, and held me in so rigorous bondage, I was constrained, as being wearie of my life, to run away; and safely to scape from so eminent a person, and who had so great authority in the Countrie, I thought it best to get me to the desart and most unfrequented wildernesses of that region, with a full resolution, if I could not compasse the means to sustain my self, to find one way or other, with violence to make myself away. One day the Sunne about noone-tide became extremely hote, and the scorching heat thereof intolerable, I fortuned to come unto a wild unhauted cave, hidden amongst crags and almost inaccessible, and where imagined no footing had ever been; therein I hid myself. I had not long been there but in comes this Lion, with one of his pawes sore hurt, and bloody-goared, wailing for the smart, and groaning for the pain he felt; at whose arrivall I was much dismaied, but he seeing me lie close-cowering in a corner of his den, gently made his approaches unto me, holding forth his goared paw toward me and seemed with shewing the same humbly to sue and suppliantly to beg for help at my hands. I, moved with ruth, taking it into my hand, pulled out a great splint which was gotten into it, and shaking off all fear, first I wrung and crusht his sore, and caused the filth and matter, which therein was gathered, to come forth; then, as gently as for my heart I could, I cleansed, wiped, and dried the same. He feeling some ease in his grief, and his pain to cease, still holding his foot betweene my hands, began to sleep and take some rest. Thence forward he and I lived together the full space of three years in his den, with such meat as he shifted-for; for what beasts he killed, or what prey soever he took, he ever brought home the better part and shared it with me, which for want of fire I rotted in the Sunne, and therewith nourished my self all that while. But at last, wearied with this kind of brutish life, the Lion being one day gone to purchase his wonted prey, I left the place, hoping to mend my fortunes, and having wandred up and down three dayes, I was at last taken by certain soldiers, which from Africa brought me into this City to my Master again, who immediately condemned me to death, and to be devoured by wild beasts. And as I now perceive, the same Lion was also shortly after taken, who as you see has now requited me of the good turn I did him, and the health which by my means he recovered. Behold here the historie Androclus reported unto the Emperor, which after he caused to be declared unto all the people, at whose general request he was forthwith set at liberty, and quit of his punishment, and by the common consent of all had the Lion bestowed upon him. Appion says further, that Androclus was daily seen to lead the Lion up and down the streets of Rome, tied only with a little twine, and walking from taverne to taverne, received such money as was given him, who would gently suffer himself to be handled, touched, decked, and strowed with flowers, all over and over, many saying when they met him: ’Yonder is the Lion that is the mans hoste, and yonder is the man that is the Lions Physitian.’ We often mourne and weepe for the loss of those beasts we love, so do they many times for the loss of us. Post bellator equus positis insiqnibus Æthon It lacrimans, guttisque humectat grandibus ora. -- VIRG. Æn. xi. 89. Next Æthon horse of war, all ornaments laid down, Goes weeping, with great drops bedewes his cheeckes adowne. As some of our nations have wives in common and some in severall, each man keeping himself to his own, so have some beasts; yet some there are that observe their marriage with as great respect as we do ours. Touching the mutual societie and reciprocall confederation which they devise amongst themselves, that so they may be fast combined together, and in times of need help one another, it is apparant that if Oxen, Hogs, and other beasts, being hurt by us, chance to crie, all the heard runnes to aid him, and in his defense will joine all together. The fish, called of the Latines Scarus, having swallowed the fishers hook, his fellowes will presently flocke about him, and nible the line in sunder; and if any of them happen to be taken in a bow-net, some of his fellowes, turning his head away, will put his tail in at the neck of the net, who with his teeth fast-holding the same, never leave him until they have pulled him out. The Barbel fishes, if one of them chance to be engaged, will set the line against their backes, and with a fin they have, toothed like a sharp saw, presently saw and fret the same asunder. Concerning particular offices, which we for the benefit of our life draw one from an other, many like examples are found amongst them. It is assuredly beleeved that the Whale never swimmeth unless she have a little fish going before her as her vantgard; it is in shape like a Gudgeon, and both the Latines and we call it the Whale-guide; for she does ever follow him, suffering herself as easily to be led and turned by him as the ship is directed and turned by a stern: for requitall of which good turn, whereas all things else, be it beast, fish, or vessell, that comes within the horrible Chaos of this monstrous mouth, is presently lost and devoured, this little fish does safety retire himself therein, and there sleepes very quietly, and as long as he sleepes the Whale never stirs; but as soone as he awaketh and goeth his way, wherever he takes his course she alwaies followeth him, and if she fortune to lose him, she wanders here and there, and often striketh upon the rocks, as a ship that has nor mast nor rudder. This Plutarke witnesseth to have seen in the Iland of Anticyra. There is such a like societie betweene the little bird called a Wren and the Crocodill; for the Wren serveth as a sentinell to so great a monster: And if the Ichneumon, which is his mortal enemy, approach to fight with him, the little birdlet, lest he might surprise him whilst he sleepeth, with his singing, and pecking him with his bill, awakens him, and gives him warning of the danger he is in. The bird liveth by the scraps, and feedeth upon the leavings of that monster, who gently receiveth him into his mouth, and suffers him to pecke his jawes and teeth for such mamokes of flesh as sticke betweene them: and if he purpose to close his mouth, he does first warne him to be gone, fair and easy closing it by little and little, without any whit crushing or hurting him. The shell-fish called a nacre liveth even so with the pinnotere, which is a little creature like unto a crabfish, and as his porter or usher waits upon him, attending the opening of the nacre, which he continually keepes gaping until he see some little fish enter in, fit for their turn, then he creepes into the nacre, and leaves not pinching his quick flesh until he makes him close his shell, and so they both together, fast in their hold, devour their prey. In the manner of the tunnies life may be discovered a singular knowledge of the three parts of the mathematikes. First for astrologie, it may well be said that man does learne it of them: for wherever the winter Solstitium does take them, there do they stay themselves, and never stir till the next Equinoctium, and that is the reason why Aristotle does so willingly ascribe that art unto them: then for geometric and arithmetike, they alwaies frame their shole of a cubike figure, every way square: and so form a solid close and well-ranged battalion, encompassed round about of six equall sides. Thus orderly marshaled, they take their course and swim whither their journey tends, as broad and wide behind as before: so that he that seeth and telleth but one rank, may easily number all the troope, forasmuch as the number of the depth is equall unto the bredth, and the bredth unto the length. Touching magnanimity and haughtie courage, it is hard to set it forth more lively, and to produce a rarer patterne than that of the dog which from India was sent unto Alexander: to whom was first presented a stag, then a wild boare, and then a bear, with each of which he should have fought, but he seemed to make no accompt of them, and would not so much as remove out of his place for them; but when he saw a lion, he presently rouzed himself, shewing evidently he meant only so noble a beast worthie to enter combat with him. Concerning repentance and acknowledging of faults committed, it is reported that an elephant, having, through rage of choler, slain his governour, conceived such an extreme inward grief that he would never afterward touch any food, and suffered himself to pine to death. Touching clemencie, it is reported of a tiger (the fiercest and most inhumane beast of all having a kid given her to feed upon, endured the force of gnawing hunger two days together rather than she would hurt him; the third day with main strength she broke the cage wherein she was kept pent, and went elsewhere to shift for feeding; as one unwilling to seize upon the seelie kid, her familiar and guest. And concerning privileges of familiaritie and sympathie caused by conversation, is it not oft seen how some make cats, dogs, and hares so tame, so gentle, and so mild, that, without harming one another, they shall live and continue together? But that which experience teacheth sea-faring men, especially those that come into the seas of Sicilie, of the quality and condition of the Halcyon bird, or as some call it alcedo or kings-fisher, exceeds all mens conceit. In what kinds of creature did ever nature so much prefer both their hatching, sitting, brooding, and birth? Poets faine that the Iland of Delos, being before wandring and fleeting up and down, was for the delivery of Latona made firme and setled; but Gods decree has been that all the watrie wildernesse should be quiet and made calm, without raine, wind, or tempest, during the time the Halcyon sitteth and bringeth forth her young ones, which is much about the winter Solstitium, and shorteest day in the yeare: by whose privilege even in the hart and deadest time of xinter we have seven calme days, and as many nights to saile without any danger. Their hens know no other cocke but their own: they never forsake him all the days of their life; and if the cocke chance to be weake and crazed, the hen will take him upon her neck and carrie him with her wherever she goeth, and serve him even until death. Mans wit could never yet attaine to the full knowledge of that admirable kind of building or structure which the Halcyon useth in contriving of her neast, no, nor devise what it is of. Plutarke, who has seen and handled many of them, thinkes it to be made of certain fish-bones, which she so compacts and conjoyneth together, enterlacing some long and some crosse-waise, adding some foldings and roundings to it, that in the end she frameth a round kind of vessel, readie to float and swim upon the water: which done, she carrieth the same where the sea waves beat most; there the sea gently beating upon it, shewes her how to daube and patch up the parts not well closed, and how to strengthen those places and fashion those ribs that are not fast, but stir with the sea waves: and on the other side, tha t which is closely wrought, the sea beating on it, does so fasten and conjoyne together, that nothing, no, not stone or yron, can any way loosen divide, or break the same except with great violence and what is most to be wondred at is the proportion and figure of the concavitie within; for it is so composed and proportioned that it can receive or admit no manner of thing but the bird that built it; for to all things else it is so impenetrable, close, and hard, that nothing can possibly enter in: no, not so much as the sea water. See here a most plaine description of this building or construction taken from a very good author: yet me thinks it does not fully and sufficiently resolve us of the difficultie in this kind of architecture. Now from what vanity can it proceed, we should so willfully contemne and disdainfully interpret those effects, which we can neither imitate nor conceive? But to follow this equalitie or correspondences betweene us and beasts somewhat further: the privilege whereof our soul vants, to bring to her condition whatsoever it conceiveth, and to despoile what of mortal and corporall qualities belongs unto it, to marshall those things which she deemed worthie her acquaintance, to disrobe and deprive their corruptible conditions, and to make them leave as superfluous and base garments, thicknesses, length, depth, weight, colour, smell, roughnesse, smoothnesse, hardnesse, softnesse, and all sensible accidents else, to fit and appropriate them to her immortall and spirituall condition: so that Rome and Paris, which I have in my soul; Paris which I imagine; indeed, I imagine and conceive the same without reatnesse and place, without stone and morter. and without wood; then say I unto my self, the same privilege seems likewise to be in beasts: for a horse accustomed to hear the sound of trumpets, the noyse of shot, and the clattering of arms, whom we see to snort, to startle, and to neigh in his sleep, as he lies along upon his litter, even as he were in the hurly burly; it is most certain, that in his mind he apprehends the sound of a drum without any noyse, and an army without arms or body. Quippe videbis equos fortes, cum membra jacebunt In somnis, sudare tamen, spirareque sæpe, Et quasi de palma summas contendere vires. -- LUCR. iv. 982. You shall see warlike horses, when in sleep Their limbs lie, yet sweat, and a snorting keep. And stretch their utmost strength, As for a goale at length. That hare which a grey-bound imagineth in his dreame, after whom as he sleepeth we see him bay quest, yelp, and snort, stretch out his tail, shake his legs, and perfectly represent the motions of his course the same is a hare without bones, without hair. Venantumque canes in molli sæpe quiete, Iactant crura tamen subito, vocesque repente Mittunt, et crebras redducunt naribus auras, Ut vestigia si teneant inventa ferarunt Expergefactique, sequuntur inania sæpe, Cervorum simulacra, fugæ quasi dedita cernant: Donec discussis redeant erroribus ad se. -- LUCR. iv. 986 Oft times the hunters dogs in easy rest Stir their legs, suddainly, open, and quest, And send from nosthrils thicke-thicke snuffing sent As if on traile they were of game full-bent: And wakened so, they follow shadowes vain Of Deere in chase, as if they fled amaine: Till, their fault left, they turn to sense again. Those watching-dogs which in their sleep we sometimes see to grumble, and then barking, to startle suddainly out of their slumber, as if they perceived some stranger to arive, that stranger which their mind seems to see is but an imaginarie man, and not perceived, without any dimension, colour, or being: -----Consueta domi catulorum blanda propago Degere, sæpe levem ex oculis volucremque soporem Discutere, et corpus de terra corripere instant Proinde quasi ignotas facies atque ora tuantur. -- Ib. 993. The fawning kind of whelps, at home that liv’s, From eyes to shake light-swift sleepe often striv’s, And from the ground their starting bodies hie, As if some unknown stranger they did spie. Touching corporall beauties before I go any further it were necessarie I know whether we are yet agreed about her description. It is very likely that we know not well what beautie either in nature or in general is, since we give so many and attribute so diverse formes to humane beauties indeed, and to our beautie: Of which if there were any natural or lively description, we should generally know it, as we do the heat of fire. We imagine and faine her formes, as our fantasies lead us. Turpis Romano Belgicus ore color. -- PROPERT. ii. Eleg. xviii. 26. A Dutch-froes colour has no grace, Seen in a Roman Ladies face. The Indians describe it blacks and swarthy, with blabbered-thick lips, with a broad and flat nose, the inward gristle whereof they loade with great gold rings, hanging down to their mouth, and their neather lips with great circlets beset with precious stones, which cover all their chins, deeming it an especiall grace to show their teeth to the roots. In Peru, the greatest ears are ever esteemed the fairest, which with all art and industrie they are continually stretching out; and a man (who yet liveth) sweareth to have seen in a Province of the East Indias the people so careful to make them great, and so to load them with heavy jewels, that with ease he could have thrust his arm through one of their eare-holes. There are other Nations who endeavor to make their teeth as blacke as jeat, and skorne to have them white; and in other places they die them red. Not only in the province of Baske, but in other places, women are accounted fairest when their heads are shaven, and which is strange, in some of the Northerly frozen-countries, as Plinie affirmeth. Those of Mexico esteems the littlenesse of their foreheads as one of the chiefest beauties, and whereas they shave their hair over all their body besides, by artificiall means they labor to nourish and make it grow only in their foreheads; and so love to have great dugs, that they strive to have their children sucke over their shoulders. So would we set forth ilfavordnesse. The Italians proportion it big and plum; the Spaniards spynie and lanke; and amongst us one would have her white, another browne, and soft and delicate, another strong and lustie; some desire wantonnesse and blithnesse, and othersome sturdinesse and majestie to be joined with it. Even as the preheminence in beauties which Plato ascribeth unto the Sphericall figure, the Epicureans refer the same unto the Piramidall or Square; and say they cannot swallow a God made round like a bowle. But however it is, nature has no more privileged us in that than in other things, concerning her common laws. And if we impartially enter into judgement with ourselves, we shall find that if there be any creature or beast less favoured in that than we, there are others (and that in great numbers) to whom nature has been more favourable than to us. A multis animalibus decore vincimur: (SEN. Epist. cxxiv.) ’We are excelled in comelinesse, by many living creatures’: Yea, of terrestriall creatures that live with us. For, concerning those of the Sea, omitting their figure, which no proportion can containe, so much does it differ, both in colour, in neatnesse, in smoothnesse, and in disposition, we must give place unto them: which in all qualities we must likewise do to the eyrie ones. And that prerogative which Poets yield unto our upright stature, looking towards heaven whence her beginning is, Pronaque cum spectent animalia cætera terram, Os homini sublime dedit, cælumque videre Iussit, et erectos ad sidera tollere vultus, -- OVID. Metam. 1. i. 84. Where other creatures on earth looke and lie, A loftie looke God gave man, had him prie On heav’n, rais’d his high countenance to the skie, is meerely poeticall, for there are many little beasts that have their sight dire ctly, fixed towards heaven: I find the Camels and the Estridges necke much more raised and upright than ours. What beasts have not their face aloft and before, and looke not directly opposite as we; and in their natural posture descrie not as much of heaven and earth as man does? And what qualities of our corporall constitution, both in Plato and Cicero, cannot fit and serve a thousand beasts? Such as most resemble man are the vilest and filthiest of all the rout: As for outward apparance and true shape of the visage, it is the Munkie or Ape: Simia quam similis, turpissima bestia, nobis! -- Cic. Nat. Deor. i. Enni. An Ape, a most il-favored beast, How like to us in all the rest? ’ as for inward and vital parts, it is the Hog. Truely, when I consider man all naked (indeed, be it in that sex which seems to have and challenge the greatest share of eye-pleasing beautie) and view his defects, his natural subjection, and manifold imperfections, I find we have had much more reason to hide and cover our nakednesse than any creature else. We may be excused for borrowing those which nature had therein favored more than us, with their beauties to adorn us, and under their spoiles of wooll, of hair, of feathers, and of silke to shroud us. Let us moreover observe, that man is the only creature whose wants offend his own fellowes, and he alone that in natural actions m ust withdraw and sequester himself from those of his own kind. Verely it is an effect worthie consideration, that the skilfullest masters of amorous dalliaunce appoint for a remedie of venierian passions a free and full survay of the body, which one longeth and seeks after: and that to coole the longing and aswage the heat of friendship, one need but perfectly view and thoroughly consider what he loves. Ille quod obscænas in aperto corpore partes Viderat, in cursu qui f uit, ha sit amor. -- OVID. Rem. Am. ii. 33 The love stood still, that ran in full cariere, When bare it saw parts that should not appeare. And although this remedie may perhaps proceed from a squeamish and cold humor, yet it is a wonderful signe of our imbecillitie that the use and knowledge should so make us to be cloyd one of an other. It is not bashfulness so much as art and foresight makes our Ladies so circumspect and unwilling to let us come into their closets before they are fully readie and throughly painted, to come abroad and show themselves: Nec veneres nostras hoc fallit, quo magis ipsæ Omnia summopere hos vitæ post scænia celant, Quos retinere volunt adstrictoque esse in amore. -- LUCR. iv. 1176. Our Mistresses know this, which makes them not disclose Parts to be plaid within, especially from those Whom they would servants hold, and in their love-bands close: Whereas, in other creatures there is nothing but we love and pleaseth our senses: so that even from their excrements and ordure we draw not only dainties to eat, but our richest ornaments and perfumes. This discourse of beautie toucheth only our common order, and is not so sacrilegious as it intendeth or dareth to comprehend those divine, supernaturally and extraordinarie beauties which sometimes are seen to shine amongst as, even as stars under a corporall and terrestriall veile. Moreover, that part of natures favors which we impart unto beasts, is by our own confession much more advantageous unto them. We assume unto ourselves imaginarie and fantastic goods, future and absent goods, which humane capacitie can no way warrant unto herself; or some other, which by the overweening of our own opinion we falsely ascribe unto ourselves; as reason, honor, and knowledge; and to them as their proper share we leave the essentiall, the manageable, and palpable goods, as peace, rest, securitie, innocencie, and health: I say, which is the goodliest and richest present nature can impart unto us. So that even Stoike Philosophie dareth to affirme, that if Heraclitus and Pherecydes could have changed their wisdom with health, and by that means the one to have rid himself of the dropsie and the other of the lowsie-evil, which so sore tormented them, they would surely have done it: whereby they also yield so much more honor unto wisdom by comparing and counterpeizing the same unto health, than they do in this other proposition of theirs, where they say, that if Circe had presented Vlisses with two kinds of drinke, the one to turn a wise man into a foole, the other to change a foole into a wise man, he would rather have accepted that of folly, than have been pleased that Circe should transforme his humane shape into a beaste. And they say that Wisdome herself would thus have spoken unto him: ’Meddle not with me, but leave me rather than then shouldst place me under the shape and body of an Asse.’ What? This great and heavenly wisdom? Are Phylosophers contented then to quit it for a corporall and earthly veile? Why then it is not for reasons sake, nor by discourse and for the soul, we so much excel beasts: it is for the love we bear unto our beautie, unto our fair hew, and goodly disposition of limbs, that we reject and set our understanding at naught, our wisdom, and what else we have. Well, I allow of this ingenious and voluntarie confession surely they knew those parts we so much labor to pamper to be meere fantasies. Suppose beasts had all the virtue, the knowledge, the wisdom and sufficiency of the Stoics, they should still be beasts; nor might they ever be compared unto a miserable, wretched, and senseless man. For, when all is done, whatsoever is not as we are, is not of any worth. And God to be esteemed of us, must (as we will show anon) draw somewhat near it. Whereby it appeareth that it is not long of a true discourse, but of a foolish hardinesse and self-perfuming obstinacy, we prefer ourselves before other creatures, and sequester ourselves from their condition and societie. But to return to our purpose: we have for our part inconstancie, irresolution, uncertaintie, sorrow, superstition, carefulnesse for future things (indeed after our life), ambition, covetousnesse, jelousie, envie, inordinate, mad, untamed appetites, war, falsehood, disloyaltie, detraction, and curiosity. Surely we have strangely overpaid this worthie discourse, whereof we so much glory, and this readinesse to judge, or capacitie to Know, if we have purchased the same with the price of so infinite passions to which we are uncessantly enthralled. If we be not pleased (as Socrates is) to make this noble prerogative over beasts, to be of force, that whereas nature has subscribed them certain seasons and bounds for their natural lust and voluptuousness, she has given us at all howers and occasions the full reines of them. Ut vinum ægrotis, quia prodest raro, nocet sæpissime, melius est non adhibere omnino, quam, spe dubiæ salutis, in apertam perniciem incurrere: Sic, ha ud scio, an melius fuerit humano generi motum motum celerem cogitationis, acumen, solertiam quam rationem vocamus, quoniam pestifera sint multis, admodum paucis salutaria, non dari omnino, quam tam munifice et tam large dari: (CIC. Nat. Deor. iii. c. 27.) ’As it is better not to use wine at all in sicke persons, because it seldom does them good, but many times much hurt, than in hope of doubtfull health to run into undoubted danger; so do I not knowe whether it were better that this swift motion of the thought, this sharpenesse this conceitednesse which we call reason, should not at all be given to mankind (because it is pernicious unto many and healthfull to very few) than that it should be given so plentifully and so largely.’ What good or commoditie may we imagine this far-understanding of so many things brought ever unto Varro and to Aristotle? Did it ever exempt, or could it at any time free them from humane inconveniences? Were they ever discharged of those accidents that incidently follow a seelie labouring man? Could they ever draw any ease for the gout from logike? And howbeit they knew the humor engendering the same to lodge in the joints, have they felt it the less? Did they at any time make a covenant with death, although they knew full well that some nations rejoice at her coming? as also of cuckoldship, because they knew women to be common in some countries? But contrariwise having both held the first rank in knowledge, the one amongst the Romans, the other among the Greeks, indeed, and at such times wherein sciences flourished most, we could never learne they had any speciall exce llencie in their life. We see the Græcian has been put to his plunges in seeking to discharge himself from some notable imputations in his life. Was it ever found that sensualitie and health are more pIeasing unto him that understands Astrologie and Grammar? (Illiterate num minus nervi rigent? -- HOR. Epod. viii. 17. As stiffe unlearned sinnewes stand, As theirs that much more understand.) or shame and povertie less importunate and vexing? Scilicet et morbis, et de bilitate carebis, Et luctum, et curam et tempora vitæ Longa tibi posthæc fato meliore dabuntur. -- JUVEN. Sat. xiv. 166. Thou shall be from disease and weaknesse free, From moan, from care, long time of life to you Shall by more friendly fate affoorded be. I have in my days seen a hundred artificers, and as many labourers, more wise and more happy than some sectors in the Universitie, and whom I would rather resemble. Me thinks learning has a place among st things necessarie for mans life, as glory, noblenesse, dignitie, or at most as riches, and such other qualities, which indeed stead the same; but afar off and more in conceipt than by Nature. We have not much more need of offices, of rules, and laws how to live in our commonwealth than the cranes and ants have in theirs. Which notwithstanding, we see how orderly and without instruction they maintaine themselves. If man were wise he would value everything according to its worth, and as it is either more profitable or more necessarie for life. He that shall number us by our actions and proceedings, shall doubtlesse find many more excellent ones amongst the ignorant than among the wiser sort: I meane in all kind of vertues. My opinion is, that ancient Rome brought forth many men of much more valor and sufficiencie, both for peace and war, than this late learned Rome, which with all her wisdom has overthrowne her erst-flourishing estate. If all the rest were likewise, then should honestie and innocencie at least belong to the ancient, for she was exceedingly well placed with simplicities. But I will shorten this discourse, which perhaps would draw me further than I would willingly follow: yet thus much I will say more, that only humility and submission is able to make a perfect honest man. Every one must not have the knowledge of his dutie referred to his own judgement, but ought rather to have it prescribed unto him, and not be allowed to chose it at his pleasure and free will: otherwise, according to the imbecility of our reasons, and infinite varietie of our opinions, we might perhaps forge and devise such duties unto ourselves, as would induce us (as Epicurus says) to endeavor to destroy and devoure one another. The first law that ever God gave unto man was a law of pure obedience. It was a bare and simple commandement whereof man should enquire and know no further: forasmuch as to obey is the proper dutie of a reasonable soul, acknowledging a heavenly and superiour benefactor. From obeying and yielding unto him proceed all other vertues, even as all sinnes derive from self-overweening. Contrariwise, the first temptation that ever seized on human nature was disobedience, by the devils instigation, whose first poison so far insinuated itself into us, by reason of the promises he made us of wisdom and knowledge: Eritis sicut Dii scientes bonum et malum: (Gen. iii. 5.) ’You shall be like Gods, knowing both good and evil.’ And the Syrens, to deceive Vllysses, and alluring him to fall into their dangerous and confounding snares, offer to give him the full fruition of knowledge. The opinion of wisdom is the plague of man. That is the occasion why ignorance is by our religion recommended unto us as an instrument fitting beleefe and obedience: Cavete, ne quis vos decipiat per Philosophiam et inanessseductiones, secundum elementa mundi: (Col. ii. 8.) ’Take heed lest any man deceive you by Philosophie and vain seducements, according to the rudiments of the world.’ All the Philosophers of all the sects that ever were do generally agree in this point, that the chiefest felicitie, or summum bonum, consisteth in the peace and tranquillitie of the soul and body: but where shall we find it? Ad summum sapiens uno minor est Iove, dives; Liber, honoratus, pulcher, Rex denique Regum: Præcipue sanus, nisi cum pituita molesta est. -- HOR. i. Epist. i. 106. In summe, who wise is known, Is less than Jove alone, Rich, honorable, free, fair, King of Kings, Chiefely in health, but when fleagme trouble brings. It seems verily that nature for the comfort of our miserable and wretched condition has allotted us no other portion but presumption. It is therefore (as Epictetus says) that man has nothing that is properly his own but the use of his opinions. Our hereditarie portion is nothing but smoke and wind. The Gods (as says Philosophie) have health in true essence, and sicknesse in conceipt. Man, cleane contrary, possesseth goods in imagination, and evils essentially. We have had reason to make the powers of our imagination to be of force: for all our facilities are but in conceipt, and as it were in a dreame. Heare but this poore and miserable creature vaunt himself. There is nothing (says Cicero) so delightfull and pleasant as the knowledge of letters; of letters, I say, by whose means the infinitie of things, the incomprehensible greatness of nature, the heavens, the earth, and all the seas of this vast universe, are made known unto us. They have taught us religion, moderation, stowtnesse of courage, and redeemed our soul out of darknesse, to make her see and distinguish of all things, the high as well as the lowe, the first as the last, and those betweene both. It is they that store and supply us with all such things as may make us live happily and well, and instruct us how to pass our time without sorrow or offence. Seemeth not this goodly orator to speak of the Almighties and everliving Gods condition? And touching effects, a thousand poore seelie women in a countrie town have lived and live a life much more reposed, more peaceable, and more constant than ever he did. -----Deus ille fuit Deus, inclyte Memmi, Qui princeps vitæ rationem invenit eam, quæ Nunc appellatur sapienta, quique per artem, Fluctibus e tantis vitam tantisque tenebris, In tam tranquillo et tam clara luce locavit. -- LUCR. v. 8. Good sir, it was God, God it was, first found That course of man’s life, which now is renown’d By name of wisdom; who by art reposed, Our life in so clear light, calme so composde, From so great darknesse, so great waves opposed. Observe what glorious and noble words these be yet but a sleight accident brought this wisemans understanding to a far worse condition than that of a simple shepherd: notwithstanding this divine Teacher, and this heavenly wisdom. Of like impudence is the promise of Democritus his Book, ’I will now speak of all things;’ And that fond title which Aristotle gives us of mortal gods, and that rash judgement of Chrysippus that Dion was as vertuous as God: And my Seneca says he acknowledgeth that God has given him life, but how to live well that he has of himself. Like unto this other: In virtute vere gloriamur, quod non contingeret, si id donum a Deo non a nobis haberemus: (CIC. Nat. Deor. iii.) ’We rightly vaunt us of virtue, which we should not do, if we had it of God, not of ourselves:’ This also is Senecæs, that the wise man has a fortitude like unto Gods; but in humanity weaknesse wherein he excelleth him. There is nothing more common than to meet with such passages of temeritie: There is not any of us that will be so much offended to see himself compared to God as he will deem himself wrong to be depressed in the rank of other creatures. So much are we more jealous of our own interest than of our Creators. But we must tread this foolish vanity under foot, and boldly shake off and lively reject those foolish ridiculous foundations whereon these false opinions are built. So long as man shall be persuaded to have means or power of himself, so long will he denie and never acknowledge what he oweth unto his Master: he shall alwaies (as the common saying is) make shift with his own: He must be stripped unto his shirt. Let us consider some notable example of the effect of Philosophie. Possidonius having long time been grieved with a painfull-lingring diseease which with the smarting pain made him wring his hands and gnash his teeth, thought to scorne grief with exclaiming and crying out against it: ’Doe what you list, yet will I never say that you are evil or pain.’ He feeleth the same passions that my lackey does, but he boasteth himself that at least he conteineth his tongue under the laws of his sect. Re succumbere non oportebat verbis gloriantem; (CIC. Tusc. Qu. ii. c. 25.) ’It was not for him to yield in deeds, who had so braved it in words.’ Arcesilas lying sicke of the gowt, Carneades coming to visit him, and seeing him to frowne, supposing he had been angrie, was going away again, but he called him back, and shewing him his feet and breast, said unto him, ’There is nothing come from thence hither. This has somewhat a better garb;’ for he feeleth himself grieved with sicknesse, and would faine be rid of it, yet is not his heart vanquished or weakned thereby, the other stands upon his stifnesse (as I fear) more verball than essentiall And DionysiusHeracleotes being tormented with a violent smarting in his eyes, was at last persuaded to quit these Stoice resolutions. Be it supposed that Learning and Knowledge should work those effects they speak of, that is, to blunt and abate the sharpnesse of those accidents or mischances that follow and attend us; does she any more than what ignorance effecteth much more evidently and simply? The Philosopher Pyrrho being at sea, and by reason of a violent storme in great danger to be cast away, presented nothing unto those that were with him in the ship to imitate but the securitie of an Hog which was aboard, who, nothing at all dismaied, seemed to behold and outstare the tempest. Philosophie after all her precepts gives us over to the examples of a Wrestler or of a Muletier, in whom we ordinarily perceive much less feeling of death, of pain, of grief, and other conveniences, and more undaunted constancy, than ever Learning or Knowledge could store a man withall, unless he were born and of himself through some natural habitude prepared unto it. What is the cause the ten der members of a child or limbs of a horse are much more easy and with less pain cut and incised than ours, if it be not ignorance? How many, only through the power of imagination, have falne into dangerous diseases? We ordinarily see diverse that will cause themselves to be let blood, purged, and dieted, because they would be cured of diseases they never felt but in conceit; when essentiall and true maladies faile us, then Science and Knowledge lend us hers: This colour or complexion (said she) presageth some rheumatike defluxion will ensue you: This soultring-hot season menaceth you with some febricant commotion; this cutting of the vital line of your left hand warneth you of some notable and approaching indisposition. And at last she will roundly addresse herself unto perfect health; saying this youthly vigor and suddain joy cannot possibly stay in one place, her blood and strength must be abated, for fear it turn you to some mischief. Compare but the life of a man subject to these like imaginations, unto that of a day- laboring swaine, who followes his natural appetites, who measureth all things only by the present sense, and has neither learning nor prognostications, who feeleth no disease but when he has it: whereas the other has often the stone imaginarily before he have it in his reines: as if it were not time enough to endure the sicknesse when it shall come, he does in his fancie prevent the same, and headlong runneth to meet with it. What I speak of Physicke, the same may generally be applied and drawne to all manner of learning. Thence came this ancient opinion of those Philosophers who placed chief felicitie in the knowledge of our judgements weaknesse. My ignorance affords me as much cause of hope as of fear: and having no other regiment for my health than that of other men’s examples, and of the events I see elsewhere in like occasions whereof I find some of all sorts: and rely upon the comparisons that are most favourable unto me. I embrace health with open arms, free, plaine, and full, and prepare my appetite to enjoy it, by how much more it is now less ordinary and more rare unto me: so far is it from me that I, with the bitternesse of some new and forced kind of life, trouble her rest and molest her ease. Beasts do manifestly declare unto us how many infirmities our mindes agitation brings us. That which is told us of those that inhabit Bresill, who die only through age, which some impute to the clearnesse and calmnenesse of their aire, I rather ascribe to the calmenesse and clearnesse of their mindes, void and free from all passions, cares, toiling, and unpleasant labours, as a people that pass their life in a wonderful kind of simplicitie and ignorance, without letters, or laws and without Kings or any Religion. Whenc comes it (as we daily see by experience) that the rudest and grossest clownes are more tough, strong, and more desired in amorous executions; and that the love of a Muletier is often more accepted than that of a perfumed quaint courtier? But because in the latter the agitation of his mind does so distract, trouble, and wearie the force of his body, as it also troubleth and wearieth itself, who does belie, or more commonly cast the same down even into madnesse, but her own promptitude, her point, her agilitie, and, to conclude, her proper force? Whence proceeds the subtilest folly but from the subtilest wisdom? As from the extremest friendships proceed the extremest enmities and from the soundest healths the mortallest diseases, so from the rarest and quickest agitations of our mindes ensue the most distempered and outrageous frenzies. There wants but half a pegs turn to pass from the one to the other. In mad mens actions we see how fitlie folly suteth and meets with the strongest operations of our mind. Who knowes not how unperceivable the neighbourhood between folly with the liveliest elevations of a free mind is, and the effects of a supreme and extraordinarie virtue. Plato affirmeth that melancholy mindes are more excellent and disciplinable; so are there none more inclinable unto folly. Diverse spirits, are seen to be overthrowne by their own force and proper nimblenesse. What a start has one (T ORQUATO T ASSO ) of the most judicious, ingenious, and most fitted under the air of true ancient poesie, lately gotten by his own agitation and self- gladnesse, above all other Italian Poets that have been of a long time? Hath not he wherewith to be beholding unto this his killing vivacitie? unto this clearnesse that has so blinded him? unto his exact and far-reaching apprehension of reasons which has made him voide of reason? unto the curious and laborious pursute of Sciences, that have brought him unto sottishnesse? unto this rare aptitude to the exercises of the mind, which has made him without mind or exercise? I rather spited than pitied him when I saw him at Ferrara, in so piteous a plight, that he survived himself; misacknowledging both himself and his labours, which unwitting to him, and even to his face, have been published both uncorrected and maimed. Will you have a man healthy, will you have him regular, and in constant and safe condition? overwhelme him in the darke pit of idlenesse and dulnesse. We must be besotted ere we can become wise, and dazzled before we can be led. And if a man shall tell me that the commoditie to have the apptite cold to griefes and wallowish to evils, draws this incommoditie after it, it is also consequently the same that makes us less sharpe and greedie to the enjoying of good and of pleasures: It is true but the misery of our condition beareth that we have not so much to enjoy as to shun, and that extreme voluptuousness does not so much pinch us as a light smart: Segnius homines bona quam mala sentiunt: (TIT. LIV. xxx. c. 21.) ’Men have a duller feeling of a good turn than of an ill;’ we have not so sensible a feeIing of perfect health as we have of the least sicknesse, -----pungit In cute vix sumnma violatum plagula corpus Quando valere nihil quemquam movet. Hoc juvat unum Quod me non torquet latus aut pes; cætera quisquam Vix queat aut sanum sese aut sentire valentem. A light stroke that dooth scarce the top-skin wound, Greeves the gall’d body, when in health to be, Does scarce move any: only ease is found. That neither side nor foot tormenteth me: Scarce any in the rest can feel he’s sound. Our being in health is but the privation of being ill. See therefore where the sect of Philosophie that has most preferred sensualitie, has also placed the same but to indolencie or unfeeling of pain. To have no infirmitie at all is the chiefest possession of health that man can hope for (as Ennius said) Nimium boni est, cui nihil est mali. He has but too much good, Whom no ill has withstood. For the same tickling and pricking which a man does feel in some pleasures, and seems beyond simple health and indolencie, this active and moving sensualitie, or as I may terme it, itching and tickling pleasure, aymes but to be free from pain, as her chiefest scope. The lust-full longing which allures us to the acquaintance of women seekes but to expell that pain which an earnest and burning desire does possesse us with, and desires but to allay it thereby to come to rest and be exempted from this fever; and so of others. I say therefore, that if simplicitie directeth us to have no evil, it also addresseth us according to our condition to a most happy estate. Yet ought it not to be imagined so dull and heavy than the altogether senselesse. And Crantor had great reason to withstand the unsensiblenesse of Epicurus, if it were so deeply rooted that the approching and birth of evils might gainsay it. I commend not that unsensiblenesse which is neither possible nor to be desired. I am well pleased not to be sicke, but if I be, I will know that I am so; and if I be cauterized or cut, I will feel it. Verily, he that should root out the knowledge of evil should therewithall extirp the knowledge of voluptuousness, and at last bring man to nothing.Istud nihil dolere, non sine magna mercede contingit immanitatis in animo, stuporis in corpore: (CIC. Tusc. Qu. iii.) ’This very point, not to be offended or grieved with any thing, befals not freely to a man without either inhumanitie in his mind or senselesnesse in his body.’ Sicknesse is not amiss unto man, coming in her turn; nor is he alwaies to shun pain, nor ever to follow sensualitie. It is a great advantage for the honor of ignorance that Science itself throwes us into her arms when she findes her self busie to make us strong against the assaults of evils: she is forced to come to this composition: to yield us the bridle, and give us leave to shrowd ourselves in her lap, and submit ourselves unto her favor, to shelter us against the assaults and injuries of fortune. For what meaneth she else when she perswades us to withdraw our thought from the evils that possesse us, and entertains them with foregon pleasures, and stead us as a comfort of present evils with the remembrance of forepast felicities, and call a vanished content to our help, for to oppose it against that which vexeth us? Levationes, ægritudinum in avocatione a cogitanda molestia, et revocatione ad contemplandas voluptates ponit. (Ibid.)’Eases of grief she reposeth either in calling from the thought of offence, or calling to the contemplations of some pleasures.’ Unless it be that where force fails her, she will use policy and show a tricke of nimblenesse and turn away, where the vigor both of her body and arms shall faile her. For not only to a strict Philosopher, but simply to any setled man, when he by experience feeleth the burning alteration of a hot fever, what currant paiment is it to pay him with the remembrance of the sweetness of Greeke wine? It would rather empaire his bargaine. Che ricordarsi il ben doppia la noia. For to think of our joy, Redoubles our annoy. Of that condition is this other counsell, which Philosophie gives only to keep forepast felicities in memories and thence blot out such griefes as we have felt: as if the skill to forget were in our power: and counsell of which we have much less regard: Suavis est laborum præteritorum memoria. -- CIC. Fin. ii. Eurip. Of labours overpast, Remembrance has sweet taste What? shall Philosophie, which ought to put the weapons into my hands to fight against Fortune; which should harden my courage, to suppress and lay at my feet all humane adversities, will she so faint as to make me like a fearfull cunnie creepe into some lurking- hole, and like a craven to tremble and yield? For memory representeth unto us, not what we chuse, but what pleaseth her. Nay, there is nothing so deeply imprinteth anything in our remembrance as the desire to forget the same: it is a good way to commend to the keeping, and imprinteth anything in our mind, to solicit her to lose the same. And that is false, Est situm in nobis, ut et adversa quasi perpetua oblivione obruamus, et secunda jucunde et suaviter meminerimus: (CIC. Fin. Bon. i.) ’This is engraffed in us, or at least in our power, that we both burie in perpetuall oblivion things past against us, and record with pleasure and delight what soever was for us.’ And this is true, Memini etiam quæ nolo; oblivisci non possum quæ volo: (Plu. In vita Them.) ’I remember even those things I would not; and can not forget what I would.’ And whose counsell is this? his, Qui se unus sapientem profiteri sit ausus: ’Who only durst professe himself a wise man’ Qui genus humanum ingenio superavit, et omnes Præstrinæit stellas, exortas uti ætheriusSol. -- LUCR. iii. 1086 Who from all mankind bare for wit the prize, And dim’d the stars as when skies Sunne does rise. To empty and diminish the memory, is it not the readie and only way to ignorance? Iners malorum remedium ignorantia est. -- SEN. Oed. act iii. sc. 1. Of ills a remedie by chance, And very dull is ignorance. We see diverse like precepts, by which we are permitted to borrow frivolous appearances from the vulgar sort, where lively and strong reason is not of force sufficient: alwaies provided they bring us content and comfort. Where they can not cure a sore they are pleased to stupifie and hide the same. I am persuaded they will not denie me this, that if, they could possibly add any order or constancy to a mans life, that it might thereby be still maintained in pleasure and tranquillitie, by or through any weaknesse or infirmitie of judgement, but they would accept it. ------ potare, et spargere flores Incipiam, patiarque vel inconsultus haberi. -- HOR. i. Epist. v. 14. I will begin to strew flowers, and drinke free, And suffer witlesse, thriftlesse, held to be. There should many Philosophers be found of Lycas his opinion: This man in all other things being very temperate and orderly in his demeanors, living quietly and contentedly with his families wanting of no dutie or office both towards his own houshold and strangers, very carefully preserving himself from all hurtful things: notwithstanding through some alteration of his senses or spirits, he was so possessed with this fantastic conceipt or obstinate humor that he ever and continually thought to be amongst the Theatres, where he still saw all manner of spectacles, pastimes, sports and the best Comedies of the world. But being at last by the skill of Physitians cured of this maladie, and his offending humor Purged, he could hardly be held from putting them in suite, to the end they might restore him to the former pleasures and contents of his imagination. ----- pol me occidistis amici, Non servastis, ait, cui sic extorta voluptas, Et demptus per vim menti gratissimus error. -- HOR. i. Epist. ii. 138. You have not sav’d me, friends, but slain me quite, (Quoth he) from whom so reft is my delight; And error purg’d, which best did please my spright. Of a raving like unto that of Thrasilaus, son unto Pythodorus, who verily beleeved that all the ships that went out from the haven of Pyræus, indeed all such as came into it, did only travell about his business, rejoycing when any of them had made a fortunate voyage, and welcommed them with great gladnesse: His brother Crito, having caused him to be cured and restored to his better senses, he much bewailed and grieved of the condition wherein he had formerly lived in, such joy, and so void of all care and grief. It is that which that ancient Greeke verse says: That not to be so advised brings many commodities with it: ’Εν τω φρονειν γαρ ηδεν ηδιοτος βιος -- SOPH. Aia. Flag. The sweetest life I wis, In knowing nothing is. And as Ecclesiastes witnesseth: ’In much wisdom is much sorrow. And who getteth knowledge purchaseth sorrow and grief’ Even that which Philosophy does in general tearmes allow, this last remedy which she ordaineth for all manner of necessities; that is, to make an end of that life which we cannot endure. Placet? pare: placet? quacunque vis exi. Pungit dolor? vel fodiat sane: si nudus es, da jugulum: sin tectus armis vulcaniis, id est, fortitudine, resiste: (CIC. Tusc. Qu. 1. ii.) ’Does it like you? obey: does it not like you? get out as you will; does grief pricke you? and let it pierce you too: if you be naked, yield your throat: but if you be covered with the armour of Vulcan, that is, with fortitude, resist.’ And that saving, used of the Græcians in their banquets, which they aply unto it, Aut bibat, aut abeat: (CIC. Ib. v.) ’Either let him carouse, or carry him out of the house:’ which rather fitteth the mouth of a Gascoine, who very easily does change the letter B into V, than that of Cicero: Vivere si recte nescis, discede peritis: Lusisti satis, edisti satis, atque bibisti: Tempus abire tibi est, largius æquo Ridat, et pulset lascivia descentius ætas: -- HOR. ii. Epist. ii. ult. Live well you cannot, them that can, give place; Well have you sported, eaten well, drunke well: ’Tis time you part; lest wanton youth with grace Laugh at, and knock you that with swilling dwell. what is it but a confession of his insufficiency, and a sending one backe not only to ignorance, there to be shrowded, but unto stupidity itself, unto unsensiblenesse and not being? ------ Democritum postquam matura vetustas Admonuit memorem, motus lanquescere mentis. Sponte sua letho caput obvius obtu lit ipse. -- LUCR. iii. 1083. When ripe age put Democritus in mind, That his mindes motions fainted, he to find His death went willing, and his life resign’d. It is that which Anthisthenes said, that a man must provide himself either of wit to understand or of a halter to hang himself: And that which Chrysippus alleged upon the speech of the Poet Tyrtaius, De la virtue, ou de mort approcher. -- PLUT. in Solon’s Life. Or virtue to approch, Or else let death incroch. And Crates said that love was cured with hunger, if not by time; and in him that liked not these two means, by the halter. That Sextius, to whom Seneca and Plutarke give so much commendation, having given over all things else and betaken himself to the study of Philosophy, seeing the progress of his studies so tedious and slow, purposed to cast himself into the Sea; Ranne unto death for want of knowledge: Reade here what the law says upon the subject. If perhaps any great inconvenience happen, which cannot be remedied, the haven is not far-off, and by swimming may a man save himself out of his body, as out of a leaking boat: for it is fear to die, and not desire to live, which keepes a foole ioyned to his body. As life through simplicity becommmeth more pleasant, so (as I erewhile began to say) becomes it more innocent and better. The simple and the ignorant (says St. Paul) raise themselves up to heaven, and take possession of it; whereas we, with all the knowledge we have plunge ourselves down to the pit of hell. I rely neither upon Valentian (a professed enemy to knowledge and learning), nor upon Licinius (both Roman Emperours), who named them the venime and plague of all politike estates: Nor on Mahomet, who, as I have heard, does utterly interdict all manner of learning to his subjects. But the example of that great Lycurgus and his authority, ought to bear chief sway and the reverence of that divine Lacedemonian policy, so great, so admirable, and so long time flourishing in all virtue and felicity without any institution or exercise at all of letters. Those who return from that new world which of late has been discovered by the Spaniards, can witness unto us how those nations, being without Magistrates or law, live much more regularly and formally than we, who have amongst us more officers and laws than men of other professions or actions. Di citatorie piene e di libelli, D’essamine, e di carte, di procure Hanno mani e il seno, e gran fastelli Di chiose, di consioli e di letture, Per cui le faculta de’ poverelli Non sono mai ne le citta sicure, Hanno dietro e dinanzi e d’ambi i lati, Notai, pro curatori, e advocate. -- ARIOSTO, cant. xiv. stan. 84. Their hands and bosoms with writs and citations, With papers, libels, proxies, full they bear, And bundels great of strict examiunations, Of glosses, counsels, readings here and there. Whereby in townes poore men of occupations Possesse not their small goods secure from fear, Before, behind, on each sides Advocates, Proctors, and Notaries hold up debates. It was that which a Roman Senator said, that ’their predecessors had their breath stinking of garlike, and their stomacke perfumed with a good, conscience:’ and contrary, the men of his time outwardly smelt of nothing but sweet odours, but inwardly they stunke of all vices: which, in mine opinion, is as much to say they had much knowledge and sufficiency, but great want of honesty. Incivility, ignorance, simplicity, and rudenesse are commonly joined with innocency. Curiosity, subtility, and knowledge are ever followed with malice: Humility, fear, obedience, and honesty (which are the principal instruments for the preservation of humane society) require a single docile soul and which presumeth little of herself: Christians have a peculiar knowledge how curiosity is in a man a natural and originall infirmity. The care to increase in wisdom and knowledge was the first overthrow of man-kind: is the way whereby man hat h headlong cast himself down into eternall damnation. Pride is his loss and corruption: it is pride that misleadeth him from common waies; that makes him to embrace all new fangles, and rather chuse to be chief of a straggling troupe and in the path of perdition, and be regent of some erroneous sect, and a teacher of falsehood, than a disciple in the schoole of truth, and suffer himself to be led and directed by the hand of others in the ready beaten highway. It is perhaps that which the ancient Greeke proverb implieth η δειοιδαιονια, χαθαπερ παερι τω τυφω πειθεται, ’Superstition obaieth pride as a father.’ Oh overweaning, how much doest you hinder us? Socrates being advertised that the God of wisdom had attributed the name of wise unto him, was thereat much astonished, and diligently searching and rouzing up himself, and ransacking the very secrets of his heart, found no foundation or ground for this divine sentence. He knew some that were as just, as temperate, as valiant and as wise as he, and more eloquent, more fair and more profitable to their country. In fine he resolved that he was distinguished from others, and reputed wise, only because he did not so esteeme himself: And that his God deemed the opinion of science and wisdom a singular sottishnes in man; and that his best doctrine was the doctrine of ignorance, and simplicitie his greatest wisdom. The sacred wrote pronounceth them to be miserable in this world that esteeme themselves. ’Dust and ashes,’ says he, ’what is there in you you should so much glory of?’ And in another place God has made man like unto a shadowe, of which who shall judge when, the light being gone, it shall vanish away? Man is a thing of nothing. So far are our faculties from conceiving that high Deitie, that of our Creators works, those bear his marke best, and are most his own, which we understand least. It is an occasion to induce Christians to believe, when they chance to meet with any incredible thing, that it is so much the more according unto reason, by how much more it is against humane reason. If it were according unto reason, it were no more a wonder; and were it to be matched, it were no more singular. Melius scitur Deus nesciendo, ’God is better knowen by our not knowing him,’ says S. Augustine: and Tacitus, Sanctius est ac reverentius de actis deorum credere quam scire: ’It is a course of more holinesse and reverence to hold beleefe than to have knowledge of Gods actions.’ And Plato deemes it to be a vice of impiety overcuriously to enquire after God, after the world, and after the first causes of things. Atque illum quidem parentem hujus universitatis invenire, difficile; et quum jam inveneris, indicare in vulgus, nefas:/2 ’Both it is difficult to find out the father of this universe, and when you have found him, it is unlawfull to reveale Him to the vulgar,’ says Cicero. We easily pronounce puissance, truth, and justice; they be words importing some great matter, but that thing we neither see nor conceive. We say that God feareth, that God will be angry, and that God loves. Immortalia mortali sermone notantes, -- LUCR. v. 122. Who with tearmes of mortality Note things of immortality. They be all agitations and motions, which according to our forms can have no place in God, nor we imagine them according to his. It only belongs to God to know himself and interpret his own workes; and in our tongues he does it improperly, to descend and come down to us, that are and lie groveling on the ground. How can wisdom (which is the choice betweene good and evil) beseeme him, seeing no evil does touch him? How reason and intelligence, which we use to come from obscure to apparant things, seeing there is no obscure thing in God? Justice, which distributeth unto every man what belongs unto him, created for the society and conversation of man, how is she in God? How, temperance, which is the moderation of corporall sensualities, which have no place at all in his God-head? Fortitude patiently to endure sorrowes, and labours and dangers, appertaineth little unto him, these three things no way approaching him, having no accesse unto him. And therefore Aristotle holds him to be equally exempted from virtue and from vice. Neque gratia, neque ira teneri pote st, quod quæ talia essent, imbecilla essent omnia: (CIC. Nat. Deor. i.) ’Nor can he be possessed with favor and anger; for, all that is so is but weake.’ The participation which we have of the knowledge, of truth, what soever she is, it is not by our own strength we have gotten it; God has sufficiently taught it us in that he has made choice of the simple, common, and ignorant to teach us His wonderful secrets. Our faith has not been purchased by us: it is a gift proceeding from the liberality of others. It is not by our discourse or understanding that we have received our religion, it is by a forreine authority and commandement. The weaknesse of our judgement helps us more than our strength to compasse the same, and our blindnesse more than our clear- sighted eyes. It is more by the means of our ignorance than of our skill that we are wise in heavenly knowledge. It is no marvell if our natural and terrestriall means cannot conceive the supernaturall or apprehend the celestial knowledge. Let us adde nothing of our own unto it but obedience and subjection: for (as it is written) ’I will confound the wisdom of the wise, and destroy the understanding of the prudent. Where is the wise? where is the scribe, where is the disputer of this world? (1 COR. i. 19-21.) has not God made the wisdom of this world foolishuesse? For seeing the world by wisdom knew not God, in the wisdom of God, it has pleased Him, by the vanity of preaching, to save them that believe.’ Yet must I see at last whether it be in mans power to find what he seekes for: and if this long search, wherein he has continued so many ages, has enriched him with any new strength or solid truth: I am persuaded, if be speak in conscience, he will confesse that all the benefit he has gotten by so tedious a pursuit has been that he has learned to know his own weaknesse. That ignorance which in us was natural, we have with long study confirmed and averred. It has happened unto those that are truly learned, as it happens unto ears of corne, which as long as they are empty, grow and raise their head aloft, upright and stout; but if they once become full and big with ripe corne, they begin to humble and droope downeward. So men having tried and sounded all, and in all this chaos and huge heape of learning and provision of so infinite different things, found nothing that is substantiall, firme, and steadie, but all vanity, have reno unced their presumption, and too late known their natural condition. It is that which Velleius upbraids Cotta and Cicero withall, that they have learnt of Philo to have learned nothing. Pherecydes, one of the seven wise men, writing to Thales even as he was yielding up the ghost, ’I have,’ says he, ’appoynted my friends, as soon as I shal be layed in my grave, to bring you all my writings. If they please you and the other sages, publish them; if not, conceal them. They containe no certainties nor do they any whit satisfie me. My profession is not to know the truth nor to attaine it. I rather open than discover things.’ The wisest that ever was, being demanded what he knew, answered, he knew that he knew nothing. He verified what some say, that the greatest part of what we know is the least part of what we know not: that is, that that which we think to know is but a parcel, indeed, and a small particle, of our ignorance. ’We know things in a dreame’ says Plato, ’and we are ignorant of them in truth.’ Omnes pene veteres nihil cognosci, nihil percipi, nihil sciri posse dixerunt angustos sensus, imbecilles animos, brevia curricula vitæ: (CIC. Acad. q. i.) ’Almost all the ancients affirmed nothing may be knowen, nothing perceived, nothing understood: that our senses, are narrow, our mindes are weake, and the race of our life is short.’ Cicero himself, who ought all he had unto learning, Valerius says, that in his age he begun to disesteeme letters: and whilst he practised them, it was without bond to any speciall body, following what seemed probable unto him, now in the one and now in the other sect; ever holding himself under the Academies doubtfulnesse. Dicendum est, sed ita ut nihil affirmem; quæram omnia, dubitans plerumque, et mihi diffidens: (CIC. Divin. i.) ’Speake I must, but so as I avouch nothing, question all things, for the most part in doubt and distrust of my self.’ I should have too much a do if I would consider man after his own fashion, and in grose: which I might do by his own rule, who is wont to judge of truth, not by the weight or value of voices, but by the number. But leave we the common people, Qui vigilans stertit, -- LUCR. iii. 1091. Who snoare while they are awake. Mortua cui vita est, prope jam vivo atque videnti: -- Ib. 1089. Whose life is dead while yet they see, And in a manner living be. Who feeleth not himself, who judgeth not himself, who leaves the greatest part of his natural parts idle. I will take man even in his highest estate. Let us consider him in this small number of excellent and choice men, who having naturally been endowed with a peculiar and exquisite wit, have also fostred and sharpened the same with care, with study and with art, and have brought and strained unto the highest pitch of wisdom it may possibly reach unto. They have fitted their soul unto all senses, and squared the same to all byases; they have strengthned and under-propped it with all foraine helpes, that might any way fit or stead her, and have enriched and adorned her with whatsoever they have been able to borrow, either within or without the world for her avail: It is in them that the extreme height of humane nature does lodge. They have reformed the world with policies and laws. They have instructed the same with arts and sciences, as also by example of their wonderful manners and life. I will but make accompt of such people, of their witness and of their experience. Let us see how far they have gone, and what holdfast they have held by. The maladies and defects which we shall find in that college, the world may boldly allow them to be his. Whosoever seekes for any thing, commeth at last to this conclusion and says, that either he has found it, or that it cannot be found, or that he is still in pursuit after it. All philosophy is divided into these three kindes. Her purpose is to seek out the truth, the knowledge and the certainty. The Peripatetike, the Epicureans, the Stoics and others have thought they had found it. These have established the sciences that we have, and as of certain knowledges have treated of them; Clitomachus, Carneades, and the Academikes have despaired the finding of it, and judged that truth could not be conceived by our means. The end of these is weaknesse and ignorance. The former had more followers and the worthiest sectaries. Pyrrho and other sceptikes, or epechistes, whose doctrine or manner of teaching many auncient learned men have thought to have been drawne from Homer, from the seaven wise men, from Archilochus and Euripides, to whom they join Zeno, Democritus, and Xenophanes, say that they are still seeking after truth. These judge that those are infinitely deceived who imagine they have found it, and that the second degree is over boldly vain in affirming that mans power is altogether unable to attaine unto it. For to establish the measure of our strength to know and distinguish of the difficulty of things is a great, a notable and extreme science, which they doubt whether man be capable thereof or no. Nil sciri quisquis putat, id quoque nescit, An sciri possit, quo se nil scire fatetur. -- LUCR. iv. 471. Who thinks nothing is known, knowes not that Whereby he Grauntes he knowes nothing if it known may be. That ignorance which knows, judgeth, and condemneth itself, is not an absolute ignorance: for to be so, she must altogether be ignorant of herself. So that the profession of the Pyrrhonians is ever to waver, to doubt, and to enquire; never to be assured of any thing, nor to take any warrant of himself. Of the three actions or faculties of the soul, that is to say, the imaginative, the concupiscible, and the consenting, they allow and conceive the two former: the last they hold and defend to be ambiguous, without inclination or approbation either of one or other side, be it never so light. Zeno in jesture painted forth his imagination upon this division of the soules faculties: the open and outstretched hand was apparance; the hand halfe-shut, and fingers somewhat bending, consent; the fist closed, comprehension: if the fist of the left hand were closely clinched together, it signified Science. Now this situation of their judgement, straight and inflexible, receiving all objects with application or consent, leads them unto their Ataraxie, which is the condition of a quiet and settled life, exempted from the agitations which we receive by the impression of the opinion and knowledge we imagine to have of things; whence proceed fear, avarice, envie, immoderate desires, ambition, pride, superstition, love of novelties, rebellion, disobedience, obstinacy, and the greatest number of corporall evils: indeed, by that meane they are exempted from the jealousie of their own discipline, for they contend but faintly: they fear nor revenge nor contradiction in the disputations. When they say that heavy things descend downward, they would be loth to be beleeved, but desire to be contradicted, thereby to engender doubt and suspence of judgement, which is their end and drift. They put forth their propositions but to contend with those they imagine we hold in our conceipt. If you take theirs, then will they undertake to maintaine the contrary all is one to them, nor will they give a penny to chuse. If you propose that snow is blacke, they will argue on the other side that it is white. lf you say it is neither one nor other, they will maintaine it to be both. If by a certain judgement you say that you cannot tell, they will maintaine that you can tell. Nay, if by an affirmative axiome you swear that you stand in some doubt, they will dupute that you doubt not of it, or that you cannot judge or maintaine that you are in doubt. And by this extremity of doubt, which staggereth itself, they separate and divide themselves from many opinions, indeed from those which diverse ways have maintained both the doubt and the ignorance. Why shall it not be granted then (say they) as to Dogmatists, or Doctrine-teachers, for one to say greene and another yellow, so for them to doubt? Is there any thing can be proposed unto you, either to allow or refuse which may not lawfully be considered as ambiguous and doubtfull? And whereas others be carried either by the custom of their countries or by the institution of their parents, or by chance, as by a tempest, without choyce or judgement, indeed sometimes before the age of discretion, to such and such another opinion, to the Stoike or Epicurean Sect, to which they find themselves more engaged, subjected, or fast tyed, as to a prize they cannot let go: Ad quamcunque disciplinam, velut Te mpestate, delati, ad eam tanquam ad saxum adhærescunt: (CIC. Acad. Qu. x.) ’Being carried as it were by a Tempest to any kind of doctrine, they sticke close to it as it were to a rocke.’ Why shall not these likewise be permitted to maintaine their liberty and consider of things without dutie or compulsion? Hoc liberiores et solutiores, quod integra illis, est judicandi potestatas: (Ibid.) ’They are so much the freer and at liberty, for that their power of judgement is kept entire.’ Is it not some advantage for one to find himself disengaged from necessitie which brideleth others: Is it not better to remaine in suspence than to entangle himself in so many errours that humane fantasia has brought forth? Is it not better for a man to suspend his own persuasion than to meddle with these sedicious and quarrellous divisions? What shall I chuse? Mary, what you list, so you chuse. A very foolish answer: to which it seems nevertheless that all Dogmatisme arriveth; by which it is not lawfull for you to be ignorant of that we know not. Take the best and strongest side, it shall never be so sure but you shall have occasion to defend the same, to close and combat a hundred and a hundred sides? Is it not better to keep out of this confusion? You are suffered to embrace as your honor and life Aristotles opinion upon the eternitie of the Soule, and to belie and contradict whatsoever Plato says concerning that; and shall they be interdicted to doubt of it? If it be lawfull for Panæcius to maintaine his judgement about auspices, dreames, oracles, and prophecies, whereof the Stoics make no doubt at all: wherfore shall not a wise man dare that in all things which this man dareth in such as he has learned of his masters, confirmed and established by the general consent of the schoole whereof he is a sectary and a professor? If it be a child that judgeth, he wots not what it is; if a learned man, he is forestalled. They have reserved a great advantage for themselves in the combat, having discharged themselves of the care how to shroud themselves. They care not to be beaten, so they may strike again: and all is fish that comes to net with them. If they overcome, your proposition halteth; if you, theirs is lame; if they faile, they verifie ignorance; if you, she is verified by you; if they prove that nothing is knowen, it is very well; if they cannot prove it, it is good likewise: Vt quum in eadem re paria contrariis in partibus momenta inveniuntur, facilius ab utraque parte assertio sustineatur; (CIC. Ibid.) ’So as when the same matter the like weight and moment is found on diverse parts, we may the more easily hold with avouching on both parts.’ And they suppose to find out more easily why a thing is false than true, and that which is not than that which is: and what they believe not, than that what they believe. Their manner of speech is, ’I confirme nothing.’ It is no more so than thus, or neither: I conceive it not; apparances are every where likewise. The law of speaking pro or contra is all one. ’Nothing seems true that may not seem false.’ Their sacramental word is επεχω; which is as much to say as I hold and stir not. Behold the burdens of their songs and other such like. Theyr effects is a pure, entire, and absolute surceasing and suspence of judgement. They use their reason to enquire and to debate, and not to stay and choose. Whosoever shall imagine a perpetuall confession of ignorance, and a judgement upright and without staggering, to what occasion soever may chance, that man conceives the true Pyrrhonisme. I expound this fantazy as plaine as I can, because many deem it hard to be conceived: and the authors themselves represent it somewhat obscurely and diversly. Touching the actions of life, in that they are after the common sort, they are lent and applied to natural inclinations, to the impulsion and constraint of passions, to the constitutiones of laws and customs, and to the tradition of arts: Non enim nos Deus ista scire, sed tantummodo uti voluit: (Cic. Divin. i.) ’For God would not have us know these things, but only use them.’ By such means they suffer their common actions to be directed without any conceit or judgement, which is the reason that I cannot well sort unto this discourse what is said of Pyrrho. They faine him to be stupide and unmovable, leading a kind of wild and unsociable life, not shunning to be hit with carts, presenting himself unto downefalls, refusing to conforme himself to the laws. It is an endearing of his discipline. He would not make himself a stone or a blocke, but a living, discoursing, and reasoning man, enjoying all pleasures and natural commodities, busying himself with and using all his corporall and spirituall parts in rule and right. The fantastic and imaginary and false privileges which man has usurped unto himself to sway, to appoint, and to establish, he has absolutely renounced and quit them. Yet is there no Sect but is enforced to allow her wise Sectary, in chief to follow diverse things nor comprehended, nor perceived, nor allowed, if he will live. And if he take shipping, he follows his purpose, not knowing whether it shall be profitable or no: and yieldes to this, that the ship is good, the pilote is skilfull, and that the season is fit, circumstances only probable. After which he is bound to go and suffer himself to be removed by apparances, alwaies provided they have no express contrariety in them. He has a body, he has a soul, his senses urge him forward, his mind moveth him. Although he find not this proper and singular marke of judging in himself, and that he perceive he should not engage his consent seeing some falsehood may be like unto this truth: he ceaseth not to conduct the offices of his life fully and commodiously. How many arts are there which professe to consist more in conjecture than in the science; that distinguish not betweene truth and falsehood, but only follow seeming? There is both true and false (say they), and there are means in us to seek it out, but not to stay it when we touch it. It is better for us to suffer the order of the world to manage us without further inquisition. A mind warranted from prejudice has a marvellous preferment to tranquillity. Men that sensure and controule their judges do never duly submit unto them. How much more docile and tractable are simple and uncurious mindes found both towards the laws of religion and Politike decrees, than these over-vigilant and nice wits, teachers of divine and humane causes? There is nothing in mans invention wherein is so much likelyhood, possibilities and profit. This representeth man bare and naked, acknowledging his natural weaknesse, apt to receive from above some strange power, disfurnished of all humane knowledge, and so much the more fitte to harbour divine understanding, disannulling his judgement, that so he may give more place unto faith. Neither misbeleeving nor establishing any doctrine or opinion repugnant unto common laws and observances, humble, obedient, disciplinable and studious; a sworne enemy to Heresie, and by consequence exempting himself from all vain and irreligious opinions, invented and brought up by false Sects. It is a white sheet prepared to take from the finger of God what form so ever it shall please him to imprint therein. The more we addresse and commit ourselves to God, and reject ourselves, the better it is for us. Accept (says Ecclesiastes) in good part things both in show and taste, as from day to day they are presented unto you, the rest is beyond your knowledge. Dominus novit cogitationes hominum, quoniam vanæ sunt: (Psal. xciii. 11.) ’The Lord knowes the thoughts of men, that they are vayne.’ See how of three general Sects of Philosophie, two make express profession of doubt and ignorance and in the third, which is the Dogmatists, it is easy to be discerned that the greatest number have taken the face of assurance; only because they could set a better countenance on the matter. They have not so much gone about to establish any certainty in us, as to show how far they had waded in seeking out the truth. Quam docti fingunt magis quam norunt: ’Which the learned do rather conceit than know.’ Timæus, being to instruct Socrates of what he knowes of the Gods, of the world, and of men, purposeth to speak of it as one man to another; and that it sufficeth, if his reasons be as probable as another mans. For exact reasons are neither in his hands, nor in any mortal man; which one of his Sectaries has thus imitated: Vt potero, explicabo: nec tamen, ut Pythius Apollo, certa ut sint et fixa quæ dixero; sed ut homunculus, probabilia conjectura sequens: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’As I can, I will explaine them; yet not as Apollo giving oracles, that all should be certain and set down, that I say but as a meane man who followes likelihood by his conjecture.’ And that upon the discourse of the contempt of death; a natural and popular discourse. Elsewhere he has translated it, upon Platoes very words: Si forte, de Deorum natura ortuque mundi disserentes, minus id quod habemus in animo consequimur, haud erit mirum. Æquum est enim meminisse, et me, qui disseram, hominem esse, et vos qui judicetis: ut, si probabilia dicentur, nihil ultra requiratis (Cic. Univers.) ’It will be no marvell if arguing of the nature of Gods and originall of the world, we scarcely reach to that which in our mind we comprehend; for it is meet we remember that both I am a man who am to argue, and you who are to judge, so as you seek no further, if I speak but things likely.’ Aristotle ordinarily hoardeth us up a number of other opinions and other beleefes, that so he may compare his unto it, and make us see how far he has gone further, and how near he comes unto true-likelyhood. For truth is not judged by authorities nor by others testimony. And therefore did Epicurus religiously avoyd to aleadge any in his compositions. He is the Prince of Dogmatists, and yet we learne of him that, to know much breedes an occasion to doubt more. He is often seen seriously to shelter himself under so inextricable obscurities that his meaning cannot be perceived. In effect, it is a Pyrrhonisme under a resolving form. Listen to Ciceroes protestation, who does declare us others fantasies by his own. Qui requirunt, quid de quaque re ipsi sentiamus; curiosius id faciunt, quam necesse est. Hæc in Philosophia ratio contra omnia disserendi, nullamque rem aperte judicandi, profecta a Socrate, repetita ab Arcesila, confirmata a Carneade, usque ad nostram viget ætatem. Hi sumus, qui omnibus veris falsa quædam adiuncta esse di camus, tanta similitudine, ut in iis nulla insit certe judicandi et assentiendi nota: (Cic. Nat. Deo. i.) ’They that would know what we conceit of everything, use more curiosity than needs. This course in Philosophy to dispute against all things, to judge eexpressly of nothing, derived from Socrates, renewed by Arcesilas, confirmed by Carneades, is in force till our time: we are those that aver some falsehood entermixt with every truth, and that with such likenesses as there is no set note in those things for any a ssuredly to give judgement or assent.’ Why has not Aristotle alone, but the greatest number of Philosophers, affected difficulty, unless it be to make the vanity of the subject to prevaile, and to ammuse the curiosity of our mind, seeking to feed it by gnawing so raw and bare a bone? Clytomachus affirmed that he could never understand by the writings of Carneades, what opinion he was of. Why has Epicurus interdicted facility unto his Sectaries? And why has Heraclitus been surnamed οχοτεινος ’a darke mysty clowded fellow’? Difficulty is a coine that wise men make use of, as juglers do with pass and repasse, because they will not display the vanity of their art, and wherewith humane foolishnesse is easily apaid. Clarus ob obscuram linguam, magis inter inanes, Omnia enim stolidi magis admirantur amantgue. Inversis quæ sub verbi; latitantia cernunt. -- Lucr. i. 656. For his darke speech much prais’d, but of the unwise; For fooles do all still more admire and prize That under words turn’d topsie-turvie lies. Cicero reproveth some of his friends because they were wont to bestow more time about astrology, law, logike, and geometry, than such arts could deserve; and diverted them from the devoirs of their life, more profitable and more honest. The Cyrenaike philosophers equally contemned natural philosophy and logicke. Zeno in the beginning of his bookes of the Commonwealth declared all the liberall sciences to be unprofitable. Chrysippussaid, that which Plato and Aristotle had written of logike, they had written the same in jest and for exercise sake, and could not believe that ever they spake in good earnest of so vain and idle a subject. Plutarke says the same of the metaphysikes: Epicurus would have said it of rhetorike, of grammar, of poesie, of the mathematikes, and (except natural philosophy of all other sciences: and Socrates of all, but of the art of civill manners and life. Whatsoever he was demanded of any man, he would ever first enquire of him to give an accompt of his life, both present and past, which he would seriously examine and judge of; deeming all other apprentiships as subsequents and of supererogation in regard of that. Parum mihi placeant ex literæ quæ ad virtutem doctoribus nihil profuerunt: ’That learning pleaseth me but a little, which nothing profiteth the teachers of it unto virtue.’ Most of the arts have thus been contemned by knowledge itself, for they thought it not amisse to exercise their mindes in matters wherein was no profitable solidity. As for the rest, some have judged Plato a dogmatist, others a doubter; some a dogmatist in one thing, and some a doubter in another. Socrates, the fore-man of his Dialogues does ever aske and propose his disputation; yet never concluding, nor ever satisfying, and says he has no other science but that of opposing. Their author, Homer, has equally grounded the foundations of all sects of philosophy, thereby to show how indifferent he was which way he went. Some say that of Plato arose ten diverse sects. And as I think, never was instruction wavering and nothing avouching if his be not. Socrates was wont to say that when midwives begin once to put in practice the trade to make other women bring forth children, themselves become barren. That be, by the title of wise, which the gods had conferred upon him, had also in his man-like and mentall love shaken off the faculty of begetting: Being well pleased to afford all helpe and favor to such as were engenderers; to open their nature, to suple their passages, to ease the issue of their child-bearing, to judge thereof, to baptise the same, to foster it, to strengthen it, to swathe it, and to circumcise it, exercising and handling his instrument at the perill and fortune of others. So is it with most authors of this third kind, as the ancients have well noted by the writings of Anaxagoras, Democritus, Parmenides, Xenophanes, and others. They have a manner of writing doubtfull both in substance and intent, rather enquiring than instructing: albeit here and there they enterlace their stile with dogmaticall cadences. And is not that as well seen in Seneca and in Plutarke? How much do they speak sometimes of one face and sometimes of another, for such as looke near unto it? Those who reconcile lawyers, ought first to have reconciled them every one unto himself. Plato has (in my seeming) loved this manner of philosophying dialogue wise in good earnest, that thereby he might more decently place in sundry mouthes the diversity and variation of his own conceits. Diversly to treat of matters is as good and better as to treat them conformably; that is to say, more copiously and more profitably. Let us take example by ourselves. Definite sentences make the last period of dogmaticall and resolving speech; yet see we that those which our Parliaments present unto our people as the most exemplare and fittest to nourish in them the reverence they owe unto this dignitie, especially by reason of the sufficiencie of those persons which exercise the same, taking their glory, not by the conclusion, which to them is dayly, and is common to al judges as much as the debating of diverse and agitations of contrary reasonings of law causes will admit. And the largest scope for reprehensions of some Philosophers against others, draweth contradictions and diversities with it, wherein every one of them findeth himself so entangled, either by intent to show the wavering of mans mind above all matters, or ignorantly forced by the volubilitie and incomprehensiblenesse of all matters: What meaneth this burden? In a slippery and gliding place let us suspend our beliefe. For as Euripides says, Les oeuvres de Dieu en diverses Facons, nous donnent des traverses. Gods workes do travers our imaginations, And crosse our workers in diverse different fashions. Like unto that which Empedocles was wont often to scatter amongst his bookes, as moved by a divine fury and forced by truth. No, no, we feel nothing, we see nothing; all things are hid from us; there is not one that we may establish, how and what it is. But returning to this holy word, Cogitationes mortalium timidæ, et incertæ ad inventiones nostræ, et providentiæ (Wisd. c. ix. 14.) ’The thoughts of mortal men are feareful, our devices and foresights are uncertaine.’ It must not be thought strange if men disparing of the goale have yet taken pleasure in the chase of it; studie being in itself a pleasing occupation, indeed so pleasing that amid sensualities the Stoics forbid also that which comes from the exercise of the mind, and require a bridle to it, and find intemperance in over much knowledge. Democritus having at his table eaten some figges that tasted of hony, began presently in his mind to seek out whence this unusuall sweetness in them might proceed; and to be resolved, rose from the board, to view the place where those figges had been gathered. His maide servant noting this alteration in her master, smilingly said unto him, that he should no more busie himself about it; the reason was, she had laide them in a vessell where hony had been; whereat he seemed to be wroth in that she had deprived him of the occasion of his intended search, and robbed his curiosity of matter to work upon. ’Away,’ quoth he unto her, ’you hast much offended me; yet will I not omit to find out the cause, as if it were naturally so.’ Who perhaps would not have missed to find some likely or true reason for a false and supposed effect. This story of a famous and great Philosopher does evidently represent unto us this studious passion, which so does ammuse us in pursuit of things, of whose obtaining we despaire. Plutarke reporteth a like example of one who would not be resolved of what he doubted, because he would not lose the pleasure he had in seeking it: As another, that would not have his Physitian remove the thirst he felt in his ague, because he would not lose the pleasure he took in quenching the same with drinking. Satius est supervacua discere, quam nihil: (Sen. Epist. 89. f.) ’It is better to learne more than we need than nothing at all.’ Even as in all feeding, pleasure is alwayes alone and single and all we take that is pleasant is not ever nourishing and wholesome: So likewise, what our mind draws from learning leaveth not to be voluptuous, although it neither nourish nor be wholesome. Note what their saying is: ’The consideration of nature is a food proper for our mindes, it raiseth and puffeth us up, it makes us by the comparison, of heavenly and high things to disdaine base an d low matters. The search of hidden and great causes is very pleasant, indeed unto him that attaines nought but the reverence and fear to judge of them.’ These are the very words of their profession. The vain image of this crazed curiosity is more manifestly seen in this other example, which they for honor-sake have so often in their mouths. Eudoxus wished, and praid to the Gods, that he might once view the Sunne near at hand, to comprehend his form, his greatness and his beautie: on condition he might immediately be burnt and consumed by it. Thus with the price of his own life would he attaine a Science, whereof both use and possession shall therewith be taken from him; and for so sudden and fleeting knowledge lose and forgoe all the knowledges he either now has, or ever hereafter may have. I can not easily be persuaded that Epicurus, Plato, or Pythagoras have sold us their atomes, their ideas and their numbers for ready payment. They were over wise to establish their articles of faith upon things so uncertaine and disputable. But in this obscuritie and ignorance of the world, each of these notable men has endeavoured to bring some kind of show or image of light; and have busied their mindes about inventions that might at least have a pleasing and wilie apparance, provided (notwithstanding it were false) it might be maintained against contrary oppositions: Vnicuiquæ ista pro ingenio finguntur, non ex Scientiæ vi: ’These things are conceited by every man as his wit serves, not as his knowledge stretches and reaches.’ An ancient Phylosopher being blamed for professing that Philosophie, whereof in his judgement he made no esteeme; answered, that that was true Philosophizing. They have gone about to consider all, to balance all, and have found that it was an occupation fitting the natural curiosity which is in us. Some things they have written for the behoofe of common societie, as their religions: And for this consideration was it reasonable that they would not throughly unfold common opinions, that so they might not breed trouble in the obedience of laws and customs of their countries. Plato treateth this mysterie in a very manifest kind of sport. For, where he writeth according to himself, he prescribeth nothing for certaintie: When he institutes a Law giver, he borroweth a very swaying and avouching kind of stile: Wherein he boldly entermingleth his most fantastic opinions; as profitable to persuade the common sort, as ridiculous to persuade himself: Knowing how apt we are to receive all impressions, and chiefly the most wicked and enormous. And therefore is he very careful in his laws that nothing be sung in public but Poesies the fabulous fictions of which tend to some profitable end: being so apt to imprint all manner of illusion in man’s mind, that it is injustice not to feed them rather with commodious lies, than with lies either unprofitable or damageable. He flatly says in his Common-wealth that for the benefit of men, it is often necessarie to deceive them. It is easy to distinguish how some Sects have rather followed truth, and some profit; by which the latter have gained credit. It is the misery of our condition that often what offers itself unto our imagination for the likelyst, presents not itself unto it for the most beneficiall unto our life. The boldest sects, both Epicurean, Pirrhonian and new Academike, when they have cast their accompt are compelled to stoop to the civill law. There are other subjects which they have tossed, some on the left and some on the right hand, each one labouring and striving to give it some semblance, were it right or wrong: For, having found nothing so secret, whereof they have not attempted to speak, they are many times forced to forge diverse feeble and foolish conjectures : Not that themselves took them for a ground-work, not to establish a truth, but for an exercise of their studie. Non tam id sensisse, quod dicerent, quam exercere ingenia materiæ difficultate videntur voluisse. ’They seem not so much to have thought as they said, as rather willing to exercise their wits in the difficulty of the matter.’ And if it were not so taken, how should we cloke so great an inconstancie, varietie and vanity of opinions, which we see to have been produced by these excellent and admirable spirits? As for example, What greater vanity can there be than to go about by our proportions and conjectures to guess at God? And to governe both him and the world according to our capacitie and laws? And to use this small scantlin of sufficiencie, which he has pleased to impart unto our natural condition, at the cost and charges or divinitie? And because we cannot extend our sight so far as his glorious throne, to have removed him down to our corruption and miseries? Of all humane and ancient opinions concerning religion, I think that to have had more likelyhood and excuse, which knowledged and confessed God to be an incomprehensible power, chief beginning and preserver of all things; all goodness, all perfection; accepting in good part the honor and reverence which mortal men did yield him, under what usage, name and manner soever it was. Jupiter omnipotens rerum, regumque, Deumque, Progenitor, genitrixque. Almightie love is parent said to be Of things, of Kings, of Gods, both he and she. This zeale has universally been regarded of heaven with a gentle and gracious eye. All policies have reaped some fruit by their devotion; Men and impious actions have every where had correspondent events. Heathen histories acknowledge dignitie, order, justice, prodigies, and oracles, employed for their benefit and instruction in their fabulous religion: God of his mercy daining, perhaps, to foster by his temporal blessings the budding and tender beginnings of such brute knowledge as natural reason gave them of him athwart the false images of their deluding dreames: Not only false but impious and injurious are those which man has forged and devised by his own invention. And of all religions Saint Paul found in credit at Athens, that which they had consecrated onto a certain hidden and unknown divinitie seemed to be most excusable. Pythagoras shadowed the truth some what nearer, judgeing that the knowledge of this first cause and Ens entium must be undefined, without any prescription or declaration. That it was nothing else but the extreme indevour of our imagination toward perfection, every one amplifying the idea thereof according to his capacitie. But if Numa undertook to conforme the devotion of his people to this project, to join the same to a religion meerely mental without any prefixt object or materiall mixture, he undertook a matter to no use. Mans mind could never be maintained if it were still floting up and down in this infinite deepe of shapeles conceits. They must be framed onto her to some image according to her model. The majesty of God has in some sort suffered itself to be circumscribed to corporall limits: His supernaturall and celestiall Sacraments bear signes of our terrestriall condition. His adoration is exprest by offices and sensible words; for it is man that beleeveth and praieth. I omit other arguments that are employed about this subject. But I could hardly be made believe that the sight of our Crucifixes and pictures of that pittiful torment, that the ornaments and ceremonious motions in our Churches, that the voyces accomodated and suted to our thoughts-devotions, and this stirring of our senses, does not greatly inflame the peoples soules with a religious passion of wonderous beneficiall good. Of those to which they have given bodies, as necessity required amid this general blindnesse, as for me; I should rather have taken part with those who worshipped the Sunne. -----la lumiere comnune, L’ail du monde; et si Dieu au chef porte des yeux, Les rayons du Soleil sont ses yeux radieux Qui donnent vie a tous, nous maintiennent et gardent, Et les faicts des humains en ce monde regardent: Ce beau, ce grand Soleil, qui nous fait les saysons, Selon qu’il entre ou sort de ses douze maysons: Qui remplit l’univers de ses vertus cognues, Qui d’un traict de ses yeux nous dissipe les nues: L’espirit, l’ame du monde, ardent et flamboyant, En la course d’un iour tout le Ciel tournoyant, Plein d’immense grandeur, rond, vagabond et ferme: Lequel tient dessoubs luy tout le monde pour terme, En repos sans repos, oysif, et sans seiour, Fils aisne de Nature, et le Pere du iour. The common light, The worlds eye: and if God bear eyes in his cheefe head, His most resplendent eyes the Sunne-beames may be said, Which unto all give life, which us maintaine and guard, And in this world of men, the workes of men regard: This great, this beauteous Sunne, which us our seasons makes, As in twelve houses ee ingresse or egresse takes; Who with his Vertues known, does fill this universe, With one cast of his eyes does us all clowds disperse: The spirit, and the soul of this world, flaming, burning, Round about heav’n in course of one dayes journey turning. Of endlesse greatness full, round, moveable and fast: Who all the world for bounds beneath himself has pla’st: In rest, without rest, and still more stayed, without stay, Of Nature the eldest Childe, and Father of the day. Forasmuch as besides this greatness and matchlesse beautie of his, it is the only glorious piece of this vaste worlds frame, which we perceive to be furthest from us: And by that meane so little known as they are pardonable, they entered into admiration and reverence of it. Thales, who was the first to enquire and find out this matter, esteemed God to be a spirit who made all things of water. Anaximander thought the Gods did dy, and were new borne at diverse seasons, and that the worlds were infinite in number. Anaximenes deemed the air to be a God, which was created immense and always moving. Anaxagoras was the first that held the description and manner of all things to be directed by the power and reason of a spirit infinite. Alcmæon has ascribed divinity unto the Sunne, unto the Moone, unto Stars, and unto the Soule. Pythagoras has made God a spirit dispersed through the Nature of all things, whence our soules are derived. Parmenides, a circle circumpassing the heavens, and by the heat of light maintaining the world. Empedocles said the four Natures, whereof all things are made, to be Gods. Protagoras, that he had nothing to say whether they were or were not, or what they were. Democritus would sometimes say that the images and their circuitions were Gods, and othertimes this Nature, which disperseth these images, and then our knowledge and intelligence. Plato scattereth his beliefe after diverse semblances. In his Timæus he says that the worlds father could not be named. In his Lawes that his being must not be enquired after. And elsewhere in the said bookes he maketh the world, the heaven, the starres, the earth, and our soules, to be Gods; and besides, admitteth those that by ancient institutions have been received in every commonwealth. Xenophon reporteth a like difference of Socrates his discipline. Sometimes that Gods form ought not to be inquired after; then he makes him infer that the Sunne is a God, and the Soule a God; othertimes that there is but one, and then more. Speusippus, Nephew unto Plato, makes God to be a certain power, governing all things, and having a soul. Aristotle says sometimes that it is the spirit, and sometimes the world; othertimes he appoynteth another ruler over this world, and sometimes he makes God to be the heat of heaven. Xenocrates makes eight; five named amongst the planets, the sixth composed of all the fixed starres, as of his own members; the seaventh and eighth the Sunne and the Moone. Heraclides Ponticus does but roame among his opinions, and in fine depriveth God of sense, and maks him remove and transchange himself from one form to another; and then says that is both heaven and earth. Theophrastus in all his fantasies wandereth still in like irresolutions, attributing the worlds superintendency now to the intelligence, now to the heaven, and now to the starres. Strabo, that it is Nature having power to engender, to augment and to diminish, without form or sense. Zeno, the natural Law, commanding the good and prohibiting the evil; which Lawe is a breathing creature, and removeth the accustomed Gods, Jupiter, Iuno, and Vesta. Diogenes Apolloniates, that it is Age. Xenophanes makes God round, seeing, hearing not breathing, and having nothing common with humane Nature. Aristo deemeth the form of God to be incomprehensible, and depriveth him of senses, and wotteth not certainely whether he be a breathing soul or something else. Cleanthes, sometimes reason, othertimes the World; now the soul of Nature, and other-while the supreme heat, enfoulding and containing all. Perseus, Zenoes disciple, has been of opinion that they were surnamed Gods who had brought some notable good or benefit unto humane life, or had invented profitable things. Chrysippus made a confused huddle of all the foresaid sentences, and amongst a thousand formes of the Gods which he faineth, he also accompteth those men that are immortalized. Diagoras and Theodorus flatly denied that there were anie Gods: Epicurus makes the Gods bright-shining, transparent, and perflable, placed as it were betweene two Forts, betweene two Worlds, safely sheltered from all blowes, invested with a humane shape, and with our members, which unto them are of no use. Ego Deum genus esse semper duxi, et dicam cælitum, Sed eos non curare opinor, quid agat humanum genus. -- ENN. in CIC. De Div. ii. I still thought and wil say, of Gods there is a kind; But what Our mankinde does, I think they nothing mind. Trust to your Philosophie, boast to have hit the naile on the head; or to have found out the beane of this cake, to see this coile and hurly-burly of so many Philosophical wits. The trouble or confusion of worldly shapes and formes has gotten this of me, that customs and conceipts differing from mine do not so much dislike me as instruct me; and at what time I conferre or compare them together, they do not so much puffe me up with pride as humble me with lowlinesse. And each other choyce, except that which commeth from the express hand of God, seems to me a choyce of small prerogative or consequence. The worlds policies are no less contrary one to another in this subject than the schooles whereby we may learne that Fortune herself is no more diverse, changing, and variable, than our reason, nor more blinde and inconsiderat. Things most unknown are fittest to be deified. Wherefore to make Gods of ourselves (as antiquitie has done), it exceeds the extreme weaknesse of discourse. I would rather have followed those that worshipped the Serpent, the Dogge, and the Ox, forasmuch as their Nature and being is least known to us, and we may more lawfully imagine what we list of those beasts, and ascribe extraordinarie faculties unto them. But to have made Gods of our conditions, whose imperfections we should know, and to have attributed desire, choler, revenge, marriages, generation, alliances, love, and jealousie, our limbs and our bones, our infirmities, our pleasures, our deaths, and our sepulchres unto them has of necessity proceeded from a meere and egregious sottishness or drunkennesse of mans wit. Quæ procul usque adeo divino ab numine distant. Inque Deum numero quæ sint indigna videri. -- LUCR. v. 123. Which from Divinity so distant are, To stand in ranks of Gods unworthy far. Formæ, ætates, vestitus ornatus noti sunt: genera, conjugia, cognationes, omniaque traducta ad similitudinem imbecillitatis humanæ: nam et perturbatis animis inducuntur; accipimus enim Deorum cupiditates ægritudines, iracundias: ’Their shapes, their ages, their aparrell, their furnitures are knowen; their kindes, their marriages, their kindred, and all translated to the likenesse of man’s weaknesse: For they are also brought in with mindes much troubled; for we read of the lustfulnesse, the grievings, the angrinesse of the Gods.’ As to have ascribed Divinity, not only unto faith, virtue, honor, concord, liberty, victory and piety; but also unto voluptuousness, fraud, death, envy, age and misery; indeed unto fear, unto ague, and unto evil fortune, and such other industries and wrongs to our fraile and transitory life: Quid juvat hoc, templis nostros inducere mores? O curvæ in terris animæ et cælestium inanes! -- PERS. Sat. ii. 62, 61. What boots it, into Temples to bring manners of our kindes? O crooked soules on earth, and void of heavenly mindes. The Egyptians, with an impudent wisdom forbad, upon a of hanging, that no man should dare to say that Serapis and Isis, their Gods, had whilome been but men, when all knew they had been so. And their images or pictures drawne with a finger acrosse their mouth imported (as Varro says) this misterious rule unto their priests, to conceal their mortal off-spring, which by necessary reason disannuled all their veneration. Since man desired so much to equall himself to God, it had been better for him (says Cicero) to draw those divine conditions unto himself, and bring them down to earth, than to send his corruption and place his misery above in heaven; but to take him aright, he has diverse ways, and with like vanity of opinion, does both the one and other. When Philosophers blazon and display the Hierarchy of their gods, and to the utmost of their skill endeavor to distinguish their aliances, their charges, and their powers; I cannot believe they speak in good earnest. When Plato decyphreth unto us the orchard of Pluto, and the commodities or corporall paines which even after the ruine and consumption of our body waite for us, and applyeth them to the apprehension or feeling we have in this life; Secreti celant colles, et myrtea circum Sylva tegit, curæ non ipsa in morte relinquunt; -- Virg. Æn. vi. 443. Them paths aside conceal, a mirtle grove Shades them round; cares in death do not remove; when Mahomet promiseth unto his followers a paradise all tapestried, adorned with gold and precious stones, peopled with exceeding beauteous damsels, stored with wines and singular cates: I well perceive they are but scoffers which sute and apply themselves unto our foolishness, thereby to enhonny and allure us to these opinions and hopes fitting our mortal appetite. Even so are some of our men falne into like errours by promising unto themselves after their resurrection a terrestriall and temporal life accompanied with all sorts of pleasures and worldly commodities. Shall we think that Plato, who had so heavenly conceptions and was so well acquainted with Divinity as of most he purchased the surname of Divine, was ever of opinion that man (this seely and wretched creature man) had any one thing in him which might in any sort he applied and suted to this incomprehensible and unspeakable power? or ever imagined that our languishing hold- fasts were capable, or the virtue of our understanding of force, to participate or be partakers either of the blessednesse or eternal punishment? He ought in the behalfe of humane reasoned he answered: If the pleasures you promisest us in the other life are such as I have felt here below, they have nothing in them common with infinity. if all my five natural senses were even surcharged with joy and gladnesse, and my soul possessed with all the contents and delights it could possibly desire or hope for (and we know what it either can wish or hope for) yet were it nothing. If there be any thing that is mine, then is there nothing that is Divine; if it be nothing else but what may appertaine unto this our present condition, it may n ot be accounted of. All mortal mens contentment is mortal. The acknowledging of our parents, of our children and of our friends, if it cannot touch, move or tickle us in the other world, if we still take hold of such a pleasure, we continue in terrestrial and transitorie commodities. We can not worthily conceive of these high, mysterious, and divine promises, if we can but in any sort conceive them, and so imagine them aright; they must be thought to be immaginable, unspeakeable and incomprehensible, and absolutely and perfectly other than those of our miserable experience. ’No eye can behold (says Saint Paul) the hap that God prepareth for his elect, nor can it possibly enter the heart of man. (1 Cor. ii. 9.) And if to make us capable of it (as you saist, Plato, by your purifications), our being is reformed and essence changed, it must be by so extreme and universall a change that, according to philosophicall doctrine, we shall be no more ourselves: Hector erat tunc cum belle certabat , at ille Tractus ab Æmonio non erat Hector equo. -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. xi. 27. Hector he was, when he in fight us’d force; Hector he was not, drawne by th’enemies horse, it shall be some other thing that shall receive these recompences. -----quod mutatur, dissolvitur; interit ergo: Trajiciuntur enim partes atque ordine migrant. -- Lucr. iii. 781. What is chang’d is dissolved, therefore dies: Translated parts in order fall and rise. For in the Metempsychosis or transmigration of soules of Pythagoras, and the change of habitation which he imagined the soules to make, shall we think that the lion in whom abideth the soul of Cæsar, does wed the passions which concerned Cæsar, or that it is he? And if it were he, those had some reason who, debating this opinion against Plato, object that the son might one day be found committing with his mother under the shape of a Mules body, and such like absurdities. And shall we imagine that in the transmigrations which are made from the bodies of some creatures into others of the same kind, the new succeeding ones are not other than their predecessors were? Of a Phenixes cinders, first (as they say) is engendred a worme and then another Phenix: who can imagine that this second Phenix be no other and different from the first? Our Silk-wormes are seen to dye and then to wither drie, and of that body breedeth a Butter-flie, and of that a worme, were it not ridiculous to think the same to be the first Silkeworm? what has once lost its being is no more. Nec si materiam nostram collegerit ætas Post obitum, rursumque redegerit, ut sita nunc est, Atque iterum nobis fuerint data lumina vitæ, Pertineat quidquam tamen ad nos id quoque factum, Interrupta semel cum sit repetentia nostra. -- Ibid. 890. If time sho uld recollect, when life is past, Our stuffe, and it replace, as now ’tis plac’t, And light of life were granted us again, Yet nothing would that deed to us pertaine, When interrupted were our turn again. And Plato, when in another place you saist that it shall be the spirituall part of man that shall enjoy the recompences of the other life, you tellest of things of as small likely-hood. Scilicet avulsus radicibus ut nequit ullam Dispicere ipse oculus rem, seorsum corpore toto. -- Ibid. 580. Ev’n as no eye, by the root’s pull’d out, can see Ought in whole body severall to be. For by this reckoning it shall no longer be man, nor consequently us, to whom this enjoyment shall appertaine; for we are built of two principal essential parts, the separation of which is the death and consummation of our being. Inter enim jecta est vitai pausa vageque Deerrarunt passim motus ab sensibus omnes. -- Ibid. 903. A pause of life is interpos’d; from sense All motions straied are, far wandring thence. We do not say that man suffereth when the wormes gnaw his body and limbs whereby he lived, and that the earth consumeth them: Et nihil hoc ad nos, qui coitu conjugioque Corporis atque animæ consistimus uniter apti. -- -- Ibid. 888. This nought concerns us, who consist of union Of mind and body joyn’d in meet communion. Moreover, upon what ground of their justice can the Gods reward man and be thankfull unto him after his death, for his good and vertuous actions, since themselves addressed and bred them in him? And why are they offended and revenge his vicious deeds, when themselves have created him with so defective a condition, and that but with one twinkling of their will they may hinder him from sinning? Might not Epicurus with some show of humane reason object that unto Plato, if he did not often shrowd himself under this sentence, that it is impossible by mortal nature to establish any certainty of the immortall? Shee is ever straying but especially when she meddles with divine matters. Who feeles it more evidently than we? For, although we have ascribed unto her assured and infallible Principles, albeit we enlighten her steps with the holy lampe of that truth which God has been pleased to impart unto us, we notwithstanding see daily, how little soever she stray from the ordinary path that she start or stragle out of the way traced and measured out by the Church, how soone she loses, entangleth and confoundeth herself; turning, tossing and floating up and down in this vast, troublesome and tempestuous sea of mans opinions without restraint or scope. So soone as she loses this high and common way, she divideth and scattereth herself a thousand diverse ways. Man can be no other than he is, nor imagine but according to his capacity. It is greater presumption (says Plutarch in them that are but men, to attempt to reason and discourse of Gods and of demi- Gods, than in a man meerly ignorant of music to judge of those that sing; or for a man that was never in wars to dispute of, Armes and war, presuming by some light conjecture to comprehend the effects of an art altogether beyond his skill. As I think, Antiquity imagined it did something for divine Majesty when she compared the same unto man, attiring her with his faculties, and enriching her with his strange humors and most shamefull necessities: offering her some of our cates to feed upon, and some of our dances, mummeries, and enterludes to make her merry, with our clothes to apparrell her, and our houses to lodge her, cherishing her with the sweet odors of incense, and sounds of music, adorning her with garlands and flowers, and to draw her to our vicious passion, t o flatter her justice with an inhuman revenge, gladding her with the ruine and dissipation of things created and preserved by her. As Tiberius Sempronius, who for a sacrifice to Vulcan caused the rich spoiles and arms which he had gotten of his enemies in Sardinia to be burned: And Paulus Emilius, those he had obtained in Macedonia, to Mars and Minerva. And Alexander, coming to the Ocean of India, cast in favor of Thetis many great rich vessels of gold into the Sea, replenishing, moreover, her Altars with a butcherly slaughter, not only of innocent beasts, but of men, as diverse Nations, and amongst the rest, ours were wont to do. And I think none has been exempted from shewing the like Essayes. -----Sul mone creatos Quatuor hic juvenes, totidem, quos educat Usens, Viventes rapit, inferias quos immolet umbris. -- Virg. Æn. x. 517. Foure young-men borne of Sulmo, and foure more Whom Usens bred, he living over-bore, Whom he to his dead friend A sacrifice might send. The Getes deem themselves immortall, and their death but the beginning of a journey to their God Zamolxis. From five to five years they dispatch some one among themselves toward him, to require of him necessarie things. This deputy of theirs is chosen by lots; and the manner to dispatch him, after they have by word of mouth instructed him of his charge, is that amongst those which assist his election, three hold so many javelins upright, upon which the others, by meere strength of arms, throw him; if he chance to sticke upon them in any mortal place, and that he dye suddenly, it is to them an assured argument of divine favor; but if he escape, they deem him a wicked and execrable man, and then chuse another. Amestris, mother unto Xerxes, being become aged, caused at one time fourteen young striplings of the noblest houses of Persia (following the religion of her countrie) to be buried all alive, thereby to gratifie some God of under earth. Even at this day the Idols of Temixitan are cemented with the blood of young children, and love no sacrifice but of such infant and pure soules: Oh justice, greedy of the blood of innocencie. Tantum religio portuit suadere malorum. -- Lucr. i. 102. Religion so much mischeefe could Perswade, where it much better should. The Carthaginians were wont to sacrifice their own children unto Saturne, and who had none was faine to buy some: and their fathers and mothers were enforced in their proper persons, with cheerful and pleasant countenance to assist that office. It was a strange conceit, with our own affliction to go about to please and appay divine goodnesse: As the Lacedemonians, who flattered and wantonized their Diana by torturing of young boys, whom often in favor of her they caused to be whipped to death. It was a savage kind of humor to think to gratifie the Architect with the subversion of his Architecture, and to cancel the punishment due unto the guiltie by punishing the guiltles, and to imagine that poore Iphigenia, in the port of Aulis, should by her death and sacrifice discharge and expiate towards God, the Greeks army of the offences which they had committed. Et casta inceste nubendi tempore in ipso Hostia concideret mactatu mæsta parentis. -- Ibid. 99. She, a chaste offring, griev’d incestuously By fathers stroke, when she should wed, to dye. And those two noble and generous soules of the Decii, father and son, to reconcile and appease the favor of the Gods towards the Romanes affairs, should headlong cast their bodies athwart the thickest throng of their enemies. Quæ fuit tanta Deorum iniquitas, ut placari populo Romano non possint, nisi tales viri occidissent? ’What injustice of the Gods was so great as they could not be appeased unless such men perished?’ Considering that it lies not in the offender to cause himself to be whipped, how and when he list, but in the judge, who accompteth nothing a right punishment except the torture he appointeth and cannot impute that unto punishment which is in the free choice of him that suffereth. The divine vengeance presupposeth our full dissent, for his justice and our pain. And ridiculous was that humor of Polycrates, the Tyrant of Samos, who, to interrupt the course of his continuall happinesse, and to recompence it, cast the richest and most precious jewell he had into the Sea, deeming that by this purposed mishap he should satisfie the revolution and vicissitude of fortune; which, to deride his folly, caused, the very same jewel, being found in a fishes belly, to return to his hands again. And to what purpose are the manglings and dismembrings of the Corybantes, of the Mænades, and now a dayes of the Mahumetans, who skar and gash their faces, their stomacke and their limbes, to gratifie their prophet: seeing the offence consisteth in the will not in the breast, nor eyes, nor in the genitories, health, shoulders, or throat? Tantus est perturbatæ mentis et sedibus suis pulsæ furor, ut sic Dii placentur, quemadmodum ne homines quidem sæviunt: (AUG. Civ. Dei. vi. c. 10.) ’So great is the fury of a troubled mind put from the state it should be in, as the Gods must be so pacified, as even men would not be so outrageous.’ This natural contexture does by her use not only respect us, but also the service of God and other mens: it is injustice to make it miscarie at our pleasure, as under what pretence soever it be to kill ourselves. It seems to be a great cowardise and manifest treason to abuse the stupide and corrupt the servile functions of the body, to spare the diligence unto the soul how to direct them according unto reason. Vbi iratos Deos timent , qui sic propitios habere merentur. In regiæ libidinis voluptatem castrate sunt quidam; sed nemo sibi, ne vir esset, jubente Domino manus intulit: (Ibid. e Senec.) ’Where are they afeard of Gods anger, who in such sort deserve to have his favor; some have been guelded for Princes lustfull pleasure; but no man at the Lords command has laid hands on himself to be less than a man.’ Thus did they replenish their religion and stuffe it with diverse bad effects. -----sæpius olim Religio peperit scelerosa atque impia facta. -- Lucr. i. 82. Religion has oft times in former times Bred execrable facts, ungodly crimes, Now can nothing of ours, in what manner soever, be either compared or referred unto divine nature, that does not blemish and defile the same with as much imperfection. How can this infinite beauty, power, and goodnes admit any correspondencie or similitude with a thing so base and abject as we are, without extreme interest, and manifest derogation from his divine greatness? Infirmum Dei fortius est hominibus; et stultum Dei sapientius est hominibus: (1 Cor. i. 25.) ’The weaknesse of God is stronger than man; and the foolishnesse of God is wiser than men.’ Stilpo the Philosopher being demanded whether the Gods rejoice at our honors and sacrifices; you are indiscreet (said he), let us withdraw ourselves apart if you speak of such matters. Notwithstanding we prescribe him limits, we lay continuall siege unto his power by our reasons. (I call our dreames and our vanities reason, with the dispensation of Philosophy, which says that both the foole and the wicked do rave and dote by reason, but that it is a reason of severall and particular form.) We will subject him to the vain and weake apparances of our understanding: him who has made both us and our knowledge. Because nothing is made of nothing: God was not able to frame the world without matter. What? has God delivered into our hands the keyes, and the strongest wards of his infinit puissance? Hath he obliged himself not to exceed the bounds of our knowledge? Suppose, oh man, that herein you hast been able to marke some signes of his effects. Thinkest you he has therein employed all he was able to do, and that he has placed all his formes and ideas in this peece of work? Thou seest but the order and policy of this little cell wherein you are placed. The question is, whether you seest it. His divinitie has an infinit jurisdiction far beyond that. This peece is nothing in respect of the whole. -----omnia cum cælo terraque marique, Nil sunt ad summam summai totius omnem. -- Lucr. vi. 675. All things that are, with heav’n, with sea, and land, To the whole summe of the whole summe as nothing stand. This law you aleagest is but a municipall law, and you knowest not what the universall is: tie your self unto that whereto you are subject, but tie not him: he is neither your companion, nor your brother, nor your fellow citizen, nor your copesmate. If lie in any sort have communicated himself unto you, it is not to debase himself, or stoop to your smalnesse, nor to give you the controulment of his power. Mans body cannot soare up into the clouds, this is for you. The sunne uncessantly goeth his ordinary course the bounds of the seas and of the earth cannot be confounded: the water is ever fleeting, wavering, and without firmnesse: a wall without breach or flaw, impenetrable unto a solid body: man cannot preserve his life amidst the flames, he cannot corporally be both in heaven and on earth, and in a thousand places together and at once. It is for you that he has made these rules: it is you they take hold of. He has testified unto Christians that when ever it has pleased him he has out gone them all. And in truth, omnipotent as he is, why should he have restrained his forces unto a limited measure? In favor of whom should be have renounced his privilege? Thy reason has in no one other thing more likely- hood and foundation, than in that which perswadeth you a plurality of words. Terramque et solem, lunam, mare, cætera quæ sunt, Non esse unica, sed numero magis innumerali. -- Ibid. ii. 1094. The earth, the sunne, the moone, the sea and all In number numberlesse, not one they call. The famousest wits of former ages have beleeved it, indeed some of our modern, as forced thereunto by the apparance of humane reason. For as much as whatsoever eye see in this vast worlds frame, there is no one thing alone, single and one. ---- cum in summa res nulla sit una, Unica quæ gignatur, et unica solaque crescat: - Ibid. 1086. Whereas in general summe, nothing is one, To be bred only one, grow only one. And that all severall kindes are multiplied in some number: whereby it seems unlikely that God has framed this peece of work alone without a fellow: and that the matter of this form has wholy been spent in this only Individuum. Quare etiam atqæ etiam tales fateare necesse est, Esse alios alibi congressus matiriæ, Qualis hic est avidi complexu quem tenet Æther. -- Ibid. 1073. Wherefore you must confesse, again again, Of matters such like meetings elsewhere raigne As this, these skies in greedy gripe containe. Namely, if it be a breathing creature, as its motions make it so likely, that Plato assureth it, and diverse of ours either affirme it, or dare not impugne it; no more than this old opinion, that the heaven, the starres, and other members of the world, are creatures composed both of body and soul; mortal in respect of their composition, but immortall by the Creators decree. Now if there be diverse worlds, as Democritus, Epicurus, and well near all Philosophy has thought; what know we whether the principles and the rules of this one concerns or touch likewise the others? Haply they have another semblance and another policy. Epicurus imagineth them either like or unlike. We see an infinite difference and varietie in this world only by the distance of places. There is neither corne nor wine, no nor any of our beasts seen in that new corner of the world which our fathers have lately discovered: all things differ from ours. And in the old time, marke but in how many parts of the world they had never knowledge nor of Bacchus nor of Ceres. If any credit may be given unto Plinie or to Herodotus, there is in some places a kind of men that have very little or no resemblance at all with ours. And there be mungrell and ambiguous shapes betweene a humane and brutish nature. Some countries there are where men are borne headlesse, with eyes and mouths in their breasts; where all are Hermaphrodites; where they creepe on all foure; where they have but one eye in their forehead, and heads more like unto a dog than ours; where from the navill downewards they are half fish and live in the water; where women are brought a bed at five years of age, and live but eight; where their heads and the skin of their browes are so hard that no yron can pierce them, but will rather turn edge; where men never have beards. Other nations there are that never have use of fire; others whose sperme is of a blacke colour. What shall we speak of them who natarally change themselves into woolves, into coults, and then into men again? And if it be (as Plutark says) that in some part of the Indiæs there are men without mouthes, and who live only by the smell of certain sweet odours; how many of our descriptions be then false ? He is no more risible, nor perhaps capable of reason and societie. The direction and cause of our inward frame should for the most part be to no purpose. Moreover, how many things are there in our knowledge that oppugne these goodly rules which we have allotted and prescribed unto Nature? And we undertake to join God himself unto her. How many things do we name miraculous and against Nature? Each man and every nation does it according to the measure of his ignorance. How many hidden proprieties and quintessences do we daily discover? For us to go according to Nature, is but to follow according to our understanding, as far as it can follow, and as much as we can perceive in it. Whatsoever is beyond it, is monstrous and disordered. By this accompt all shall then be monstrous, to the wisest and most sufficient; for even to such humane reason has persuaded that she had neither ground nor footing, no not so much as to warrant snow to be white: and Anaxagoras said it was blacke. W hether there be anything or nothing; whether there be knowledge or ignorance, which Metrodorus Chius denied that any man might say; or whether we live, as Euripides seems to doubt and call in question; whether the life we live be a life or no, or whether that which we call death be a life: Τις δ οιδεν ει ζην τουθ’ ο κεκληται θανειν, Το ζην οε θνηοκειν εοτι; -- Plat. Gorg. ex Eurip. Who knowes if thus to live, be called death, And if it be to dye, thus to draw breath; And not without apparance. For why do we from that instant take a title of being, which is but a twinkling in the infinit course of an eternall night, and so short an interruption of our perpetuall and natural condition? Death possessing what ever is before and behind this moment, and also a good part of this moment. Some others affirme there is no motion, and that nothing stirreth; namely, those which follow Melissus. For if there be but one, neither can this sphericall motion serve him, nor the moving from one place to another, as Plato proveth, that there is neither generation nor corruption in nature. Protagoras says there is nothing in nature but doubt: that a man may equally dispute of all things: and of that also, whether all things may equally be disputed of: Nausiphanes said, that of things which seem to be, no one thing is nno more than it is not. That nothing is certain but uncertainty. Parmenides, that of that which seems there is no one thing in general. That there is but one Zeno, that one self same is not: and that there is nothing. If one were, he should either be in another, or in himself: if he be in another, then are they two: if he be in himself, they are also two, the comprising and the comprised. According to these rules or doctrines, the Nature of things is but a false or vain shadow. I have ever thought this manner of speech in a Christian is full of indiscretion and irreverence; God cannot dye, God cannot gain-say himself, God cannot do this or that. I cannot allow a man should so bound Gods heavenly power under the Lawes of our word. And that apparence, which in these propositions offers itself unto us, ought to be represented more reverently and more religiously. Our speech has his infirmities and defects, as all things else have. Most of the occasions of this worlds troubles are Grammaticall. Our suits and processes proceed but from the canvasing and debating the interpretation of the Lawes, and most of our wars from the want of knowledge in State-counsellors, that could not cleerely distinguish and fully express the Covenants and Conditions of accords betweene Prince and Prince. How many weighty strifes and important quarels has the doubt of this one sillable, hoc, brought forth in the world? Examine the plainest sentence that Logike itself can present unto us. If you say, it is fair weather, and in so saying, say true, it is fair weather then. Is not this a certain form of speech? Yet will it deceive us: That it is so, let us follow the example: If you say, I lie, and in that you should say true, you lie then. The Art, the reason, the force of the conclusion of this last, are like unto the other; notwithstanding we are entangled. I see the Pyrrhonian philosophers, who can by no manner of speech express their general conceit: for they had need of a new language. Ours is altogether composed of affirmative propositions, which are directly against them. So that when they say I doubt, you have them fast by the throat to make them avow that at least you are assured and know that they doubt. So have they been compelled to save themselves by this comparison of Physicke, without which their conceit would be inexplicable and intricate. When they pronounce, I know not, or I doubt, they say that this proposition transportes itself together with the rest, even as the Rewbarbe doeth, which scowred ill humors away, and therewith is carried away himself. This conceipt is more certainly conceived by an interrogation: What can I tell? As I bear it in an Imprese of a pair of ballances. Note how some prevaile with this kind of unreverent and unhallowed speech. In the disputations that are nowadayes in our religion, if you overmuch urge the adversaries, they will roundly tell you that it lieth not in the power of God to make his body at once to be in Paradise and on earth, and in many other places together. And how that ancient skoffer made profitable use of it. At least (says he) it is no small comfort unto man to see that God cannot do all things; for he cannot kill himself if he would, which is the greatest benefit we have in our condition; he cannot make mortal men immortall nor raise the dead to life again, nor make him that has lived never to have lives, and him who has h ad honors not to have had them, having no other right over what is past, but of forgetfulnesse. And that this society betweene God and Man may also be combined with some pleasant examples, he cannot make twice ten not to be twenty. See what, he says, and which a Christian ought to abhor, that ever such and so profane words should pass his mouth: Whereas, on the contrary part, it seems that foolish men endeavor to find out this foolish-boldness of speech, that so they may turn and winde God almighty according to their measure. -----cras vel atra Nube polum pater occupato, Vel sole puro, non tamen irritum Quodcumque retro est efficiet, neque Diffinget effectumque reddet Quod fugiens semel hora vexit. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. xxix. 43. To morrow let our father fill the skie, With darke cloud, or with clear Sunne, he thereby Shall not make voyd what once is overpast: Nor shall he undoe, or in new mold cast, What time has once caught, that flyeth hence so fast. When we say that the infinite of ages, as well past as to come, is but one instant with God; that his wisdom, goodnesse and power, are one self-same thing with his essence; our tongue speaks it, but our understanding can no whit apprehend it. Yet will our self overweening sift his divinitie through our sieve: whence are engendered all the vanities and errours wherewith this world is so full-fraught, reducing and weighing with his uncertaine balance a thing so far from his reach, and so distant from his weight. Mirum quo procedat improbitas cordis humani, parvulo aliquo invitata successu. (Plin. Nast. Hist. ii. c. 23.) ’It is a wonder whither the perverse wickednesse of mans heart will proceed, if it be but called-on with any little success.’ How insolently do the Stoics charge Epicurus, because he holds that to be perfectly good and absolutely happy belongs but only unto God; and that the wise man has but a shadow and similitude thereof? How rashly have they joined God unto destiny? (Which at my request, let none that beareth the surname of a Christian do at this day.) And Thales, Plato, and Pythagoras have subjected him unto necessities. This over-boldness, or rather bold-fiercenesse, to seek to discover God by and with our eyes, has been the cause that a notable man of our times has attributed a corporall form unto divinitie, and is the cause of that which daily happens unto us, which is by a particular assignation to impute all important events to God: which because they touch us, it seems they also touch him, and that he regardeth them with more care and attention than those that are but slight and ordinary unto us. Magna dii curant, parva negligunt: (Cic. Nat. Deor. ii.) ’The Gods take some care for great things, but none for little.’ Note his example; he will enlighten you with his reason. Nec in regnis quidem reges omnia minima curant: (Cic. Ibid. ii.) ’Nor do Kings in their Kingdomes much care for the least matters.’ As if it were all one to that King, either to remove an Empire or a leafe of a tree: and if his providence were otherwise exercised, inclining or regarding no more the success of a battle than the skip of a flea. The hand of his government affords itself to all things after a like tenure, fashion and order; our interest addeth nothing unto it: our motions and our measures concerne him nothing and move him no whit. Deus ita artifex magnus in magnis, ut minor non sit in parvis: ’God is so great a workman in great things, as he is no less in small things.’ Our arrogancie setteth ever before us this blasphemous equality, because our occupations charge us. Strato has presented the Gods with all immunitie of offices, as are their Priests. He maketh nature to produce and preserve al l things, and by her weights and motions to compact all parts of the world, discharging humane nature from the fear of divine judgments. Quod beatum æternumque sit, id nec habere, negotii quicquam, nec exhibere alteri; (Cic. Ibid. i.) ’That which is blessed and eternall, nor is troubled itself, nor troubleth others.’ Nature wills that in all things likewise there be also like relation. Then the infinite number of mortal men concludeth a like number of immortall: The infinite things that kill and destroy presuppose as many that preserve and profit. As the soules of the Gods, sanse tougues, sanse eyes, and sanse ears, have each one, in themselves a feeling of that which the other feel, and judge of our thoughts; so mens soules, when they are free and severed from the body, either by sleepe or any distraction, divine, prognosticate and see things, which being conjoyned to their bodies, they could not see. Men, says Saint Paul, when they professed themselves to be wise, they became fooles, for the y turned the glory of the incorruptible God to the similitude of the image of a corruptible man (Rom. i. 22,23.). Marke, I pray you, a little the iugling of ancient Deifications. After the great, solemn and prowd pompe of funerals, when the fire began to burne the top of the Pyramis, and to take hold of the bed or hearce wherein the dead corps lay, even at that instant they let fly an Eagle, which taking her flight aloft upward, signified that the soul went directly to Paradise. We have yet a thousand medailes and monuments, namely, of that honest woman Faustina, wherein that Eagle is represented carrying a cocke-horse up towards heaven those deified soules. It is pity we should so deceive ourselves with our own foolish devises and apish inventions, Quod finxere timent, -- Lucan. i. 484. Of that they stand in fear, Which they in fancie bear, as children will be afeard of their fellowes visage, which themselves have besmeared and blackt. Quasi quicquam infælicius sit homine, cui sua figmenta dominantur: ’As though any thing were more wretched than man over whom his own imaginations bear sway and domineere.’ To honor him whom we have made is far from honouring him that has made us. Augustus had as many Temples as Jupiter and served with as much religion and opinion of miracles. The Thracians, in requitall of the benefits they had received of Agesilaus, came to tell him how they had canonized him. ’Hath your Nation,’ said he, ’the power to make those whom it pleaseth Gods? Then first (for example sake) make one of yourselves, and when I shall have seen what good he shall have thereby, I will then thanke you for your offer.’ Oh sencelesse man, who cannot possibly make a worme, and yet will make Gods by dozens. Listen to Trismegistus when he praises our sufficiencie: For man to find out divine nature, and to make it, has surmounted the admiration of all admirable things. See here arguments out of Philosophies schooles itself. Noscere cui Divos et coeli numina soli, Aut soli nescire datum. -- Lucan. i. 452. Only to whom heav’ns Deities to know, Only to whom is giv’n, them not to know. If God be, he is a living creature; if he be a living creature, he has sense; and if he have sense, he is subject to corruption. If he be without a body, he is without a soul, and consequently without action: and if he have a body, he is corruptible. Is not this brave? We are incapable to have made the world, then is there some more excellent nature that has set her helping hand unto it. Were it not a sottish arrogancie that we should think ourselves to be the perfectest thing of this universe? Then sure there is some better thing. And that is God. When you see a rich and stately mansion house, although you know not who is owner of it , yet will you not say that it was built for rats. And this more than humane frame and divine composition, which we see, of heavens pallace, must we not deem it to be the mansion of some Lord greater than ourselves? Is not the highest ever the most worthy? And we are seated in the lowest place. Nothing that is without a soul and void of reason is able to bring forth a living soul capable of reason. The world does bring us forth, then the world has both soul and reason. Each part of us is less than ourselves, we are part of the world, then the world is stored with wisdom and with reason, and that more plenteously than we are. It is a goodly thing to have a great government. Then the worlds government belongeth to some blessed and happy nature. The Starres annoy us not, then the Starres are full of goodnesse. We have need of nourishment, then so have the Gods, and feed themselves with the vapours arising here below. Worldly goods are not goods unto God. Then are not they goods unto us. To offend and to be offended are equall witnesses of imbecility: Then it is folly to, fear God. God is good by his own nature, man by his industry: which is more? Divine wisdom and mans wisdom have no other distinction but that the first is eternall. Now lastingnesse is an accession unto wisdom. Therefore are we fellowes. We have life reason, and liberty, we esteeme goodnesse, charitie and justice; these qualities are then in him. In conclusion, the building and destroying the conditions of divinity are forged by man according to the relation to himself. Oh what a patterne, and what a model! Let us raise and let us amplifie humane qualities as much as we please. Puffe-up your self poore man, indeed swell and swell again. ------ non si te ruperis, inquit. -- Hor. Serm. ii. Sat. iii. 324. Swell till you breake, you shall not be, Equall to that great one, quoth he. Profecto non teum, quem cogitare non possunt, sed semetipsos pro illo cogitantes, non illum, sed seipsos, non illi, sed sibi comparant. ’Of a truth, they conceiting not God, whom they cannot conceive, but themselves instead of God, do not compare him, but themselves, not to him but themseves.’ In natural things the effects do but halfe refer their causes. What this? It is above natures order, its condition is too high, too far out of reach, and overswaying to endure, that our conclusions should seize upon or fetter the same. It is not by our means we reach unto it, this traine is too low. We are no nerer heaven on the top of Sina mount than in the bottome of the deepest sea: Consider of it that you may see with your Astrolabe. They bring God even to the carnall acquaintance of women, to a prefixed number of times, and to how many generations. Paulina, wife unto Saturnius, a matron of great reputation in Rome, supposing to lie with the God Serapis, by the maquerelage of the priests of that Temple, found herself in the arms of a wanton lover of hers. Varro, the most subtill and wisest Latine Author, in his bookes of divinitie writeth that Hercules his Sextaine, with one hand casting lots for himself, and with the other for Hercules, gaged a supper and a wench against him: if he won, at the charge of his offerings, but if he lost, at his own cost. He lost, and paid for a supper and a wench: her name was Laurentina: who by the night saw that God in her arms, saying moreover unto her that the next day the first man she met withall should heavenly pay her her wages. It was fortuned to be one Taruncius, a very rich young man, who took her home with him, and in time left her absolute heir of all he had. And she, when it came to her turn, hoping to do that God some acceptable service, left the Roman people heir general or all her wealth. And therefore she had divine honors attributed unto her. As if it were not sufficient for Plato to descend originally from the Gods by a twofold line, and to have Neptune for the common author of his race. It was certainly beleeved at Athens that Ariston, desiring to enjoy fair Perictyone, he could not, and that in his dreame he was warned by God Apollo to leave her untoucht and unpolluted until such time as she were brought a bed. And these were the father and mother of Plato. How many such-like cuckoldries are there in histories, procured by the Gods against seely mortal men? And husbands most injuriously blazoned in favor of their children? In Mahomets religion, by the easy beleefe of that people are many Merlins found, that is to say, fatherless children: spirituall children, conceived and borne divinely in the wombs of virgins, and that in their language bear names importing as much. We must note that nothing is more dear and precious to any thing than its own being (the Lyon, the Eagle and the Dolphin esteeme nothing above their kind), each thing referreth the qualities of all other things unto her own conditions, which we may either amplifie or shorten; but that is all: for besides this principle, and out of this reference, our imagination cannot go, and guesse further: and it is unpossible it should exceed that, or go beyond it. Whence arise these ancient conclusions. Of all formes, that of man is the fairest: then God is of this form. No man can be happy without virtue, nor can virtue be without reason; and no reason can lodge but in a humane shape: God is then invested with a humane figure. Ita est informatum anticipatum mentibus nostris, ut homini, quum de Deo cogitet, forma occurrat humana: (Cic. Nat. Deo. i.) ’The prejudice forestaled in our mindes is so framed as the form of man comes to mans mind when he is thinking of God.’ Therefore Xenophanes said presently, that if beasts frame any Gods unto themselves, as likely it is they do, they surely frame them like unto themselves,and glorifle themselves as we do. For why may not a goose say thus? All parts of the world behold me, the earth serveth me to tread upon, the Sunne to give me light, the Starres to inspire me with influence; this commoditie I have of the wind, and this benefit of the waters: there is nothing that this worlds-vault does so favourably look upon as me self; I am the favorite of nature; is it not man that careth for me, that keepeth me, lodgeth me, and serveth me? For me it is he soweth, reapeth, and grindeth: if he eat me, so does man feed on his fellow and so do I on the wormes that consume and eat him. As much might a Crane say, indeed more boldly, by reason of her flights liberty, and the possession of this goodly and high-bownding region. Tam blanda conciliatrix, et tam sui est lena ipsa natura: (Cic. Nat. Deo. ibid.) ’So flattring a broker and bawd (as it were) is nature to itself.’ Now by the same consequence the destinies are for us, the world is for us; it shineth, and thundreth for us: both the creator and the creatures are for us: it is the marke and point whereat the universitie of things aymeth. Survay but the register which Philosophy has kept these two thousand years and more, of heavenly affairs. The Gods never acted, and never spake, but for man: She ascribeth no other consultation, nor imputeth other vacation unto them. See how they are up in arms against us. -----domitosque Herculea manu Telluris iuvenes, unde periculum Fulgens contremuit domus Saturni veteris. -- Hor. Car. ii. Od. xii. 6. And young earth-gallants tamed by the hand Of Hercules, whereby the habitation Of old Saturnus did in perill stand, And, shyn’d it ne’er so bright, yet fear’d invasion. See how they are partakers of our troubles, that so they may be even with us, forasmuch as so many times we tire partakers of theirs. Neptunus muros magnogue emota tridenti Fundamenta quatit, totamque a sedibus urbem Eruit: hic Iuno Scæas saavissima portas Prima tenet. -- Virg. Æn.ii. 160. Neptunas with his great three-forked mace Shaks the weake wall, and tottering foundation, And from the site the Cittie does displace, Fierce Juno first holds ope the gates t’invasion. The Caunians, for the jelousie of their own Gods dominations upon their devotion day arm themselves, and running up and down, brandishing and striking the air with their glaives, and in this earnest manner they expell all foraine and banish all strange Gods from out their territories. Their powers are limited according to our necessitie. Some heale horses, some cure men, some the plague, some the scald, some the cough, some one kind of scab, and some another: Adeo minimis etiam rebus prava religio inserit Deos: ’This corrupt religion engageth and inserteth Gods even in the least matters:’ some make grapes to growe, and some garlike; some have the charge of bawdrie and uncleanesse, and some of merchandise: to every kind of trades-man a God. Some one has his province and credit in the East, and some in the West: -----hic illius arma Hic currus fuit. -- Virg. Æn.i. 20. His armor here His chariots there appeare. O sancte Apollo, qui umbilicum certum terrarum obtines. -- Cic. Div. ii. Sacred Apollo, who enfoldest The earths set navell, and it holdest. Pallada Cecropiæ, Minoia Creta Dianam, Vulcanum tellus Hipsi illa colit. Iunonem Sparte, Pelopeiadesque Mycena, Pinigerum Fauni Mænalis ora caput: Mars Latio venerandus. -- Ovid. Fast. iii. 81. Besmeared with blood and goare. Th’Athenians Pallas; Minos-Candy coast Diana, Lemnos Vulcan honors most; Mycene and Sparta, Juno think divine; The coast of Mænalus Faune crown’d with pine; Latium does Mars adore. Some has but one borough or family in his possession: some lodgeth alone, and some in company, either voluntarily or necessarily. Iunctaque sunt magno templa nepotis avo. -- i. 294. To the great grand-sires shrine, The nephews temples do combine. Some there are so seely and popular (for their number amounteth to six and thirty thousand) that five or six of them must be shufled up together to produce an eare of corne, and thereof they take their severall names. Three to a doore, one to be the boards, one to be the hinges, and the third to be the threshold. Foure to a child, as protectors of his bandels, of his drinke, of his meat, and of his sucking. Some are certain, others uncertaine, some doubtfull, and some that come not yet into paradise. Quos, quoniam coeli nondum dignamur honore, Quas dedimus certe terras habitare sinamus. -- Ovid. Metam. i. 194. Whom for as yet with heav’n we have not graced, Let them on earth by our good grant be placed. There are some Philosophicall, some poeticall, and some civill, some of a meane condition, betweene divine and humane nature, mediators and spokes-men betweene us and God: worshipped in a kind of second or diminutive order of adoration: infinite in titles and offices: some good, some bad, som e old and crazed, and some mortal. For Chrysippus thought that in the last conflagration or burning of the world, all the Gods should have an end, except Jupiter. Man faineth a thousand pleasant societies betweene God and him. Nay, is he not his countrieman? -----Iovis incunabula Creten. -- Ovid. Met. viii. 99. The Ile of famous Creet, For Jove a cradle meet. Behold the excuse that Scævola, chief Bishop, and Varro, a great Divine, in their dayes, give us upon the consideration of this subject. It is necessary (say they) that man be altogether ignorant of true things, and believe many false. Quum veritatem qua liberetur, inquirat; credatur ei expedite, quod fallitur: ’Since they seek the truth, whereby they may be free, let us believe it is expedient for them to be deceived.’ Mans eye cannotr perceive things but by the formes of his knowledge. And we remember not the downfall of miserable Phæton, forasmuch as he undertook to guide the reins of his fathers steeds with a mortal hand. Our mind does still relapse into the same depth, and by her own temeritie does dissipate and bruise itself. If you enquire of Philosophy what matter the Sun is composed of, what will it answer? but of yron and stone, or other stuffe for his use. Demand of Zeno what Nature is? A fire (says he), an Artist fit to engender and proceeding orderly. Archimedes, master of this Science, and who in truth and certaintie assumeth unto himself a precedencie above all others, says the Sunne is a God of enflamed yron. Is not this a quaint imagination, produced by the inevitable necessitie of Geometricall demonstrations? Yet not so unavoidable and beneficiall, but Socrates has been of opinion that it sufficed to know so much of it as that a man might measure out the land he either demized or took to rent: and that Polyænus, who therein had been a famous and principal Doctor after he had tasted the sweet fruits of the lazie, idle and delicious gardens of Epicurus, did not contemne them as full of falsehood and apparent vanity. Socrates, in Xenophon, upon this point of Anaxagoras, allowed and esteemed of antiquitie, well seen and expert above all others in heavenly and divine matters, says, that he weakened his braines much, as all men do, who over nicely and greedily will search out those knowledges which hang not for their mowing nor pertaine unto them. When he would needs have the sunn to be a burning stone, he remembered not that stone does not shine in the fire; and which is more, that it consumes therein. And when he made the Sunne and fire to be all one, he forgot that fire does not tan and black those he looketh upon; that we fixly looke upon the fire, and that fire consumeth and killeth all plants and herbs. According to the advice of Socrates and mine, ’The wisest judging of heaven is not to judge of it at all.’ Plato in his Timeus, being to speak of Dæmons and spirits, says it is an enterprise far exceeding my skill and ability: we must believe what those ancient forefathers has said of them, who have said to have been engendred by them. It is against reason not to give credit unto the children of the Gods, although their sayings be neither grounded upon necessary nor likely reasons, since they tell us that they speak of familiar and household matters. Let us see whether we have a little more insight in the knowledge of humane and natural things. Is it not a foolish enterprise to those unto which, by our own confession, our learning cannot possibly attaine, to devise and forge them another body, and of our own invention to give them a false form? as is seen in the planetary motions, unto which because our mind cannot reach, nor imagine their natural conduct, we lend them something of ours, that is to say, materiall, grose, and corporall springs and wards: ----- temo aureus, aurea summæ Curvatura rota, radiorum argenteus ordo. -- Ovid. Met. ii. 107. The Axe-tree gold, the wheeles whole circle gold, The rank of raies did all of silver hold. You would say, we have the Coach-makers, Carpenters, and Painters, who have gone up thither, and there have placed engines with diverse motions, and ranged the wheelings, the windings and enterlacements of the celestial bodies diapred in colours, according to Plato, about the spindle of necessity. Mundus domus est maximna rerum, Quam quinque altitonæ fragmine zonæ Cingunt, per quam limbus pictus bis sex signis, Stellimicantibus, altus, in obliquo æthere, Lunæ Bigas acceptat. The world, of things the greatest habitation, Which five high-thundring Zones by separation Engird, through which a scarfe depainted fair With twice six signes star-shining in the aire. Obliquely raisde, the waine O’ the Moone does entertaine. They are all dreames, and mad follies. Why will not nature one day be pleased to open her bosome to us, and make us perfectly see the means and conduct of her motions, and enable our eyes to judge of them? Oh, good God, what abuses, and what distractions should we find in our poor understanding and weake knowledge! I am deceived if she hold one thing directly in its point, and I shall part hence more ignorant of all other things than mine ignorance. Have I not seen this divine saying in Plato, that Nature is nothing but an ænigmaticall poesie? As a man might say, an overshadowed and darke picture, enter-shining with an infinite varietie of false lights, to exercise our conjectures: Latent ista omnia crassis occultata et circumfusa tenebris: ut nulla acies humani ingenii tanta sit, quæ pene trare incælum, terram intrare possit: (Cic. Acad. Q. iv.) ’All these things lie hid so veiled and environed with misty darknesse, as no edge of man is so piersant as it can pass into heaven or dive into the earth.’ And truly Philosophy is nothing else but a sophisticated poesie: whence have these ancient authors all their authorities but from poets? And the first were poets themselves, and in their art treated the same. Plato is but a loose poet. All high and more than humane sciences are decked and enrobed with a poeticall style. Even as women, when their natural teeth faile them, use some of yuorie and in stead of a true beauties or lively colour, lay on some artificiall hew; and as they make trunk sleeves of wire, and whale-bone bodies, backes of lathes, and stiffe bombasted verdugals, and to the open-view of all men paint and embellish themselves with counterfeit and borrowed beauties; so does learning (and our law has, as some say, certain lawfull fictions, on which it groundeth the truth of justice) which in liew of currant payment and presupposition, delivereth us those things, which she herself teacheth us to be meere inventions: for these Epicycles Excentriques, and Concentriques, which Astrology useth to direct the state and motions of her starres, she gives them unto us, as the best she could ever invent, to fit and sute unto this subject: as in all things else, Philosophy presenteth unto us, not that which is or she beleeveth, but what she inventeth as having most apparence, likelihood, or comelinesse. Plato upon the discourse of our bodies estate and of that of beasts: that what we have said is true we would be assured of it had we but the confirmation of some oracle to confirme it. This only we warrant, that it is the likeliest we could say. It is not to heaven alone that she sendeth her cordages, her engines, and her wheeles. Let us but somewhat consider what she says of ourselves and of our contexture. There is no more retrogradation, trepidation, augmentation, recoyling, and violence in the starres and celestiall bodies than they have feigned and devised in this, poor seeley little body of man. Verily they have thence had reason to name it Microcosmos, or little world, so many severall parts and visages have they imploied to fashion and frame the same. To accommodate the motions which they see in man, the diverse functions and faculties that we feel in ourselves. Into how many severall parts have they divided our soul? Into how many seats have they placed her? Into how many orders, stages, and stations have they divided this wretched man, beside the natural and perceptible? and to how many distinct offices and vocations? They make a public imaginarie thing of it. It is a subject which they hold and handle: they have all power granted them to rip him, to sever him, to range him, to join and reunite him together again, and to stuffe him every one according to his fantasia; and yet they neither have nor possess him. They cannot so order or rule him, not in truth only, but in imagination, but still some cadence or sound is discovered which escapeth their architecture, bad as it is, and botched together with a thousand false patches and fantastic peeces. And they have no reason to be excused: for to painters when they portray the heaven, the earth, the seas, the hills, the scattered Ilands, we pardon them if they but represent us with some slight apparence of them; and as of things unknown we are contented with such feigned shadows. But when they draw us, or any other subject that is familiarly known unto us, to the life, then seek we to draw from them a perfect and exact representation of their or our true lineaments or colours, and scorne if they misse never so little. I commend the Milesian wench, who seeing Thales the Philosopher continually amusing himself in the contemplation of heavens w ide-bounding vault, and ever holding his eyes aloft, laid something in his way to make him stumble, thereby to warne and put him in mind that he should not amuse his thoughts about matters above the clouds before he had provided for and well considered those at his feet. Verily she advised him well, and it better became him rather to looke to himself than to gaze on heaven; for, as Democritus by the mouth of Cicero says, Quod este ante pedes, nemo spectat; coli scrutantur plagas -- Cic. Div. ii. No man looks what before his feet does lie, They seek and search the climates of the skie. But our condition beareth that the knowledge of what we touch with our hands and have amongst us, is as far from us and above the clouds as that of the stars. As says Socrates in Plato, that one may justly say to him who meddles with Philosophy, as the woman said to Thales, which is, he seeth nothing of th at which is before him. For every Philosopher is ignorant of what his neighbour does; indeed, he knowes not what himself does, and wots not what both are, whether beasts or men. These people who think Sebondes reasons to be weake and lame, who know nothing themselves, and yet will take upon them to governe the world and know all: Quæ mare compescant causæ, quid temperet annum, Stellæ sponte sua, jussæve vagentur et errent: Quid premat obscuræ Lunæ, quid profer at orbem, Quid velit et possit rerum concordia discors. -- Hor. i. Epist. xii. 16. What cause does calm the Sea, what cleares the yeare, Whether Stars force’t, or of self-will appeares; What makes the Moones darke Orbe to wax or wane, What friendly fewd of things both will and can. Did they never sound amid their books the difficulties that present themselves to them to know their own being? We see very well that our finger stirreth and our foot moveth, that some parts of our body move of themselves without our leave, and other some that stirr but at our pleasure: and we see that certain apprehensions engender a blushing-red colour, others a palenesse; that some imagination does only work in the milt, another in the braine; some one enduceth us to laugh, another causeth us to weep; some astonisheth and stupifieth all our senses, and staieth the motion of all our limbs; at some object the stomake riseth, and at some other the lower parts. But how a spirituall impression causeth or worketh such a dent or flaw in a massie and solid body or subject, and the nature of the conjoyning and compacting of these admirable springs and wards, man yet never knew: Omnia incerta ratione, et in naturæ majestate abdita: (Plin.) ’All uncertaine in reason, and hid in the majesty of nature.’ Saith Plinie and Saint Augustine: Modus, quo corporibus adhærent spiritus, omnino mirus est nec comprehendi ab homine potent, et hoc ipso homo est: (Aug. De Spir. et Anim.) ’The meane is clearely wonderful whereby spirits cleave to our bodies, nor can it be comprehended by man, and that is very man.’ Yet is there no doubt made of him: for mens opinions are received after ancient beliefs by authority and upon credit; as if it were a religion and a law. What is commonly held of it, is received as a gibrish or fustian tongue. This trueth, with all her framing of arguments and proporcioning of proofes, is received as a firme and solid body which is no more shaken, which is no more judged. On the other side, every one the best he can patcheth up and comforteth this received beliefe with all the means his reason can afford him, which is an instrument very supple, pliable, and yielding to all shapes. ’Thus is the world filled with toyes, and overwhelmed in lies and leasings.’ The reason that men doubt not much of things is that common impressions are never throughly tride and sifted, their ground is not sounded, nor where the fault and weaknes lieth. Men only debate and question of the branch, not of the tree: they aske not whether a thing be true, but whether it was understood or meant thus and thus. They enquire not whether Galen has spoken any thing of worth, but whether thus, or so, or otherwise. Truly there was some reason this bridle or restraint of our judgements liberty, and this tyranny over our beliefs should extend itself even to schooles and arts. The God of scholasticall learning is Aristotle: It is religion to debate of his ordinances, as those of Lycurgus in Sparta. His doctrine is to us as a canon law, which perhaps is as false as another. I know not why I should or might not, as soone and as easy accept either Platoes Ideas, or Epicurus his atomes and indivisible things, or the fulnesse and emptines of Leucippus and Democritus, or the water of Thales, or Anaximanders infinite of nature, or the aire of Diogenes, or the numbers or proportion of Pythagoras, or the infinite of Parmenides, or the single-one of Musæus, or the water and fire of Apollodorus, or the similarie and resembling parts of Anaxagoras, or the discord and concord of Empedocles, or the fire of Heraclitus, or an other opinion (of this infinit confusion of opinions and sentences which this goodly humane reason, by her certainty and clear-sighted vigilancie brings forth in what soever it meddles withal) as I should of Aristotle’s conceit, touching this subject of the principles of natural things, which he frameth of three parts; that is to say, matter, form, and privation. And what greater vanity can there be than to make inanitie itself the cause of the production of things? Privation is a negative: with what humor could he make it the cause and beginning of things that are? Yet durst no man move that but for an exercise of logike: wherein nothing is disputed to put it in doubt, but to defend the author of the schoole from strange objections. His authority is the marke beyond which it is not lawfull to enquire. It is easy to frame what one list upon allowed foundations: for, according to the law and ordinance of this positive beginning, the other parts of the frame are easily directed without crack or danger. By which way we find our reason well grounded, and we discourse without rub or let in the way: For our masters preoccupate and gains afore-hand as much place in our beleefe as they need to conclude afterward what they please, as geometricians do by their graunted questions: the consent and approbation which we lend them, giving them wherewith to draw us, either on the right or left hand, and at their pleasure to winde and turn us. Whosoever is beleeved in his presuppositions, he is our master, and our God. He will lay the plot of his foundations so ample and easy, that, if he list, he will carrie us up, even unto the clouds. In this practice or negotiation of learning, we have taken the saying of Pythagoras for currant payment; which is, that every expert man ought to be bielieved in his own trade. The logitian referreth himself to the grammarian for the Signification of words. The rhetoritian borroweth the places of arguments from the logitian; the poet his measures from the musician; the geometrician his proportions from the arithmetician; the metaphisikes take the conjectures of the physikes for a ground, for every art has her presupposed principles by which mans judgment is bridled on all parts. If you come to the shocke or front of this barre, in which consists the principal error, they immediately pronounce this sentence: that there is no disputing against such as deny principles. There can be no principles in men, except divinitie has revealed them unto them: all the rest, both beginning, middle, and end, is but a dreame and a vapor. Those that argue by presupposition, we must presuppose against them the very same axiome which is disputed of. For, each humane presupposition, and every invention, unless reason make a difference of it, has as much authority as another. So must they all be equally balanced, and first the general and those that tyrannize us. A persuasion of certaintie is a manifest testimony of foolishnesse, and of extreme uncertaintie. And no people are less philosophers and more foolish than Platoe’s Philodoxes, or lovers of their own opinions. We must know whether fire be hot, whether snow be white, whether, in our knowledge, there be anything hard or soft. And touching the answers, whereof they tell old tales, as to him who made a doubt of heat, to whom one replied, that to trie he should caste himself into the fire; to him that denied the yce to be cold, that he should put some in his bosome; they are most unworthy the profession of a philosophers. If they had left us in our own natural estate, admitting of strange apparences as they present themselves unto us by our senses, and had suffered us to follow our natural appetites, directed by the condition of our birth, they should then have reason to speak so. But from them it is that we have learnt to become judges of the world; it is from them we hold this conceit, that mans reason is the general controuler of all that is, both without and within heavens-vault, which imbraceth all and can do all, by means whereof all things are known and discerned. This answer were good among the canibals, who without any of Aristotles precepts, or so much as knowing the name of natural philosophy, enjoy most happily a long, a quiet, and a peaceable life. This answer might perhaps avail more, and be of more force, than all those they can borrow from their reason and invention. All living creatures, indeed, beasts and all, where the commandment of the natural law is yet pure and simple, might with us be capable of this answer, but they have renounced it. They shall not need to tell me it is true, for you both hear and see it is so. They must tell me if what I think I feel, I feel the same in effect; and if I feel it, then let them tell me why I feel it, and how and what. Let them tell me the name, the beginning, the tennons, and the abuttings of heat and of cold, with the qualities of him that is agent, or of the patient: or let them quit me their profession, which is neither to admit nor approve anything by way of reason. It is their touchstone to try all kinds of essayes. But surely it is a touchstone full of falsehood, errors, imperefection and weakenesse: which way can we better make trial of it than by itself? If she may not be credited speaking of herself, I hardly can she be fit to judge of strange matters. If she know anything, it can be but her being and domicile. She is in the soul, and either a part or effect of the same. For the true and essential reason ( whose name we steal by false signes) lodgeth in Gods bosome. There is her home, and there is her retreat, thence she takes her flight when Gods pleasure is that we shall see some glimps of it: even as Pallas issued out of her fathers head, to communicate and empart herself unto the world. Now let us see what mans reason has taught us of herself and of the soul: not of the soul in general, whereof well nigh all philosophy maketh both the celestiall and first bodies partakers; not of that which Thales attributed even unto things that are reputed without soul or life, drawne thereunto by the consideration of the Adamant stone: but of that which appertaineth to us, and which we should know best. Iqnoratur enim quæ, sit natura animai, Nata sit, an contra nascentibus insinuetur, Et simul intereat nobiscum morte dirempta, An tenebras orci visat, vastasque lacunas, An pecudes alias di vinitus insinuet se. -- Lucr. i. 113. What the soules nature is, we do not know: If it be bred, or put in those are bred, Whether by death divorst with us it go, Or see the darke vast lakes of hell below, Or into other creatures turn the head. To Crates and Dicæarchus it seemed that there was none at all; but that the body stirred thus with and by a natural motion: to Plato, that it was a substance moving of itself; to Thales, a Nature without rest; to Asclepiades, an exercitation of the senses; to Hesiodus and Anaximander, a thing composed of earth and water; to Parmenides; of earth and fire; to Empedocles, of blood: Sanguineam vomit ille animam. -- Virg. Æn. ix. 349. His soul of purple-blood he vomits out. To Possidoinus, Cleanthes, and Galen, a heat, or hot complexion: Igneus est ollis vigor, et coelestis origo: -- vi. 730. A firy vigor and celestiall spring, In their originall they strangely bring. To Hyppocrates, a spirit dispersed through the body; to Varro, an air received in at the mouth, heated in the lungs, tempered in the heart, and dispersed through all parts of the body; to Zeno, the quintessence of the foure elements; to Heraclides Ponticus, the light; to Xenocrates and to the Egyptians, a moving number; to the Chaldeans, a virtue without any determinate form. -----Habitum quemdam vitalem corporis esse, Harmoniam Gæci quam dicunt. -- Lucr. iii. 100. There of the body is a vital frame, The which the Greeks a harmony do name. And not forgetting Aristotle, that which naturally causeth the body to move, who calleth it Entelechy, or perfection moving of itself (as cold an invention as any other), for he neither speaks of the essence, nor of the beginning nor of the soules nature, but only noteth the effects of it: Lactantius, Seneca, and the better part amongst the Dogmatists, have confessed they never understood what it was: and after all this rable of opinions. Harum sententiarum quæ vera sit, Deus aliquis viderit: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’Which of these opinions is true, let some God looke unto it,’ says Cicero. I know by myself, quoth Saint Bernard, how God is incomprehensible, since I am not able to comprehend the parts of my own being: Heraclitus, who held that every place was full of Soules and Demons, maintained nevertheless that a man could never go so far towards the knowledge of the soul as that he could come unto it; so deep and mysterious was her essence. There is no less dissention nor disputing about the place where she should be seated. Hypocrates and Herophilus place it in the ventricle of the brain: Democritus and Aristotle, through all the body: Ut bona scope valetudo cum dicitur esse Corporis, et non est tanten hæc pars ulla valentis. -- Lucr. iii. 103. As health is of the body said to be, Yet is no part of him in health we see. Epicurus in the stomacke. Hic exultat enim pavor ac metus, hæc loca circum Lætitiæ mulcent. -- 142. For in these places fear does domineere, And near these places joy keepes merry cheere. The Stoices, within and about the heart; Erasistratus, joyning the membrane of the Epicranium: Empedocles, in the blood: as also Moses, which was the cause he forbade the eating of beasts blood, unto which their soul is commixed: Galen thought that every part of the body had his soul: Strato has placed it betweene the two upper eyelids: Qua facie quidem sit animus aut ubi habitet, nec quærendum quidem est: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’We must not so much as enquire what face the mind bears, or where it dwells,’ says Cicero. I am well pleased to let this man use his own words: for why should I alter the speech of eloquence itself? since there is small gain in stealing matter from his inventions: They are both little used, not very forcible, and little unknown. But the reason why Chrysippus and those of his sect will prove the soul to be about the heart, is not to be forgotten. It is (says he) because when we will affirme or swear anything, we lay our hand upon the stomacke; and when we will pronounce εγω, which signifieth my self, we put down our chin towards the stomacke. This passage ought not to be past-over without noting the vanity of so great a personage: for, besides that his considerations are of themselves very slight, the latter proveth but to the Græcians that they have their soul in that place. No humane judgement is so vigilant or Argoes-eied, but sometimes shall fall asleep or slumber. What shall we fear to say? Behold the Stoices, fathers of humane wisdom, who devise that the soul of man, overwhelmed with any ruine, laboureth and panteth a long time to get out, unable to free herself from that charge, even as a mouse taken in a trap. Some are of opinion that the world was made to give a body, in lieu of punishment, unto the spirits, which through their fault were fallen from the puritie wherein they were created: the first creation having been incorporeall. And that according as they have more or less removed themselves their spirituality, so are they more or less merily and giovally or rudely and saturnally incorporated: whence proceedeth the infinite variety of so much matter created. But the spirit, who for his chastizement was invested with the body of the Sunne, must of necessitie have a very rare and particular measure of alteration. The extremities of our curious search turn to a glimmering and all to a dazeling. As Plutarke says of the off-spring of histories, that after the manner of cards or maps, the utmost limits of known countries are set down to be full of thicke marrish grounds, shady forrests, desart and uncouth places. See here why the grosest and most childish dotings are more commonly found in these which treat of highest and fnrthest matters; even confounding and overwhelming themselves in their own curiosity and presumption. The end and beginning of learning are equally accompted foolish. Marke but how Plato talketh and raiseth his flight aloft in his Poeticall clouds, or cloudy Poesies. Behold and read in him the gibbrish of the Gods. But what dreamed or doted he on when he defined man to be a creature with two feet, and without feathers; giving them that were disposed to mocke at him a pleasant and scopefull occasion to do it? For, having plucked-off the feathers of a live capon, they named him the man of Plato. And by what simplicitie did the Epicureans first imagine that the Atomes or Motes, which they termed to be bodies, having some weight and a natural moving downeward, had framed the world; until such time as they were advised by their adversaries that by this description it was not possible they should join and take hold one of another; their fall being so down-right and perpendicular, and every way engendring parallel lines? And therefore was it necessarie they should afterward adde a causall moving sideling unto them: And moreover to give their Atomes crooked and forked tailes, that so they might take hold of any thing and claspe themselves. And even then those that pursue them with this other consideration, do they not much trouble them? If Atomes have by chance formed so many sorts of figures, why did they never meet together to frame a house or make a shooe? Why should we not likewise believe that an infinit number of Greek letters, confusedly scattered in some open place, might one day meet and join together to the contexture of the Iliads? That which is capable of reason (says Zeno) is better than that which is not. There is nothing better than the world: then the world is capable of reason. By the same arguing Cotta maketh the world a Mathematician, and by this other arguing of Zeno, he makes him a Musitian and an Organist. The whole is more than the part: we are capable of wisdom, and we are part of the world: then the world is wise. There are infinit like examples seen, not only of false, but foolish arguments, which cannot hold, and which accuse their authors not so much of ignorance as of folly, in the reproaches that Philosophers charge one another with, about the disagreeings in their opinions and sects. He that should fardle-up a bundle or huddle of the fooleries of mans wisdom, might recount wonders. I willingly assemble some (as a show or patterns) by some means or byase, no less profitable than the most moderate instructions. Let us by that judge what we are to esteeme of man, of his sense, and of his reason; since in these great men, and who have raised mans sufficiencie so high, there are found so grose errors and so apparant defects. As for me, I would rather believe that they have thus casually treated learning even as a sporting childs baby, and have sported themselves with reason, as of a vain and frivolous instrument, setting forth all sorts of inventions, devices, and fantasies, sometimes more outstretched, and sometimes more loose. The same Plato, who defineth man like unto a Capon, says elsewhere, after Socrates, that in good sooth he knows not what man is; and that of all parts of the world there is none so hard to be known. By this varietie of conceits and instabilitie of opinions, they, as it were, leade us closely by the hand to this resolution of their irresolution. They make a profession not alwayes to present their advice manifest and unmasked: they have oft concealed the same under the fabulous shadows of Poesie, and sometimes under other vizards. For our imperfection admitteth this also, that raw meats are not alwayes good for our stomacks: but they must be dried, altred, and corrupted, and so do they who sometimes shadow their simple opinions and judgements; and that they may the better sute themselves unto common use, they many times falsifie them. They will not make open profession of ignorance, and of the imbecility of mans reason, because they will not make children afraid, but they manifestly declare the same unto us under the show of a troubled Science and unconstant learning. I persuaded somebody in Italy, who laboured very much to speak Italian, that always provided he desired but to be understood, and not to seek to excel others therein, he should only employ and use such words as came first to his mouth, whether they were Latine, French, Spanish, or Gascoine, and that adding the Italian terminations unto them, he should never misse to fall upon some idiome of the countrie, either Tuscan, Roman, Venetian, Piemontoise, or Neapolitan; and amongst so many severall formes of speech to take hold of one. The very same I say of Philosophy. She has so many faces and so much varietie, and has said so much, that all our dreames and devices are found in her. The fantasie of man can conceive or imagine nothing, be it good or evil, that is not to be found in her: Nihil tam absurde dici potest, quod non dicatur ab aliquo Philosophorum (Cic. Div. ii.) ’Nothing may be spoken so absurdly, but that it is spoken by some of the Philosophers.’ And therefore do I suffer my humors or caprices more freely to pass in public; forasmuch as though they are borne with, and of me, and without any patterne, well I wot they will be found to have relation to some ancient humor, and some shall be found that will both know and tell whence and of whom I have borrowed them. My customs are natural; when I contrived them, I called not for the helpe of any discipline: and weake and faint as they were, when I have had a desire to express them, and to make them appear to the world a little more comely and decent, I have somewhat endevoured to aid them with discourse, and assist them with examples, I have wondred at my self that by meere chance I have met with them, agreeing and suitable to so many ancient examples and Philosophicall discourses. What regiment my life was of, I never knew nor learned but after it was much worne, and spent. A new figure: an unpremeditated philosopher and a casual. But to return unto our soul, where Plato has seated reason in the braine; anger in the heart; lust in the liver; it is very likely that it was rather an interpretation of the soules motions than any division or separation he meant to make of it, as of a body into many members. And the likeliest of their opinion is that it is alwayes a soul, which by her rationall faculty remembreth her self, comprehendeth, judgeth, desires, and exerciseth all her other functions by diverse instruments of the body, as the pilote ruleth and directeth his ship according to the experience he has of it; now stretching, haling, or loosing a cable, sometimes hoysing the mainyard, removing an oar, or stirring the rudder, causing severall effects with one only power; and that she abideth in the braine, appeareth by this, that the hurts and accidents which touch that part do presently offend the faculties of the soul, whence she may without inconvenience descend and glide through other parts of the body: ----- medium non deserit unquam Coeli Phoebus iter: radus tamen omnia lustrat: -- Claud. vi. Hon. Cons. Pan. 411. Never the Sunne forsakes heav’ns middle ways, Yet with his rayes he lights all, all survayes: As the sunne spreadeth his light, and infuseth his power from heaven, and therewith filleth the whole world. Cætera pars animæ per totum dissita corpus Paret, et ad numen mentis nomenque movetur. -- Lucr. iii. 144. Th’ other part of the soul through all the body sent Obeyes, and moved is, by the mindes government. Some have said that there was a general soul, like unto a great body, from which all particular, soules were extracted, and returned thither; alwayes reconjoyning and entermingling themselves unto that universall matter: -----Deum namque ire per omnes Terrasque tractusque maris coelumque profundum: Hinc pecudes, armenta, viros, genus omne ferarum, Quemque sibi tenues nascentem arcessere vitas, Scilicet huc reddi deinde, ac resoluta referri Omnia: nec morti esse locum. -- Virg. Georg. iv. Ge. 222. For God through all the earth to pass is found, Through all Sea currents, through the heav’n profound. Here hence men, heards, and all wild beasts that are, Short life in birth each to themselves do share. All things resolved to this point restor’d Returne, nor any place to death affoord. Others, that they did but reconjoyne and fasten themselves to it again: others, that they were produced by the divine substance: others, by the angels, of fire and aire: some from the beginning of the world, and some even at the time of need: others make them to descend from the round of the moone, and that they return to it again. The common sort of antiquities that they are begotten from father to son, after the same manner and production that all other natural things are; arguing so by the resemblances which are betweene fathers and children. Instillata patris virtus tibi, --- Thy Fathers vertues be Instilled into you. Fortes creantur fortibus et bonis, -- Hor. Car. iv. Od. iv. 29. Of valiant Sires and good, There comes a valiant brood, and that from fathers we see descend unto children, not only the marks of their bodies, but also a resemblance of humors, of complexions, and inclinations of the soul. Denique cur acrum violentia triste Leonum Seminum sequitur, dolus Vulpibus, et fuga Cervis A patribus datur, et patrius pavor incitat Artus, Si non certa suo quia semine seminioque Vis animi pariter crescit cum corpore toto? -- Lucr. iii. 766,771. Why followes violence the savage Lyons race? Why craft the Foxes? Why, to Deere to flye apace? By parents is it given, when parents fear incites, Unless because a certain force of inward spirits With all the body growes, As seed and seed-spring goes? That divine justice is grounded thereupon, punishing the fathers offences upon the children; forasmuch as the contagion of the fathers vices is in some sort printed in childrens soules, and that the misgovernment of their will toucheth them. Moreover, that if the soules came from any other place, then by a natural consequence, and that out of the body they should have been some other thing, they should have some remembrance of their first being: considering the natural faculties which are proper unto him, to discourse, to reason, and to remember. ------ Si in corpus nascentibits insinuatur, Cur super anteactam ætatem meminisse nequimus, Nec vestigia gesta-um rerum ulla tenemus. -- Lucr. iii. 692. If our soul at our birth be in our body cast, Why can we not remember ages over-past, Nor any markes retaine of things done first or last? For, to make our soules condition to be of that worth we would, they must all be presupposed wise, even when they are in their natural simplicitie and genuine puritie. So should they have been such, being freed from the corporall prison, as well before they entered the same, as we hope they shall be when they shall be out of it. And it were necessarie they should (being yet in the body) remember the said knowledge (as Plato said) that what we learnt was but a new remembring of that which we had known before: a thing that any man may by experience maintaine to be false and erroneous. First, because we do not precisely remember what we are tanght, and that if memory did meerely execute her functions she would at least suggest us with something besides our learning. Secondly, what she knew being in her puritie, was a true understanding, knowing things as they are by her divine intelligence: whereas here, if she be instructed, she is made to receive lies and apprehend vice, wherein she cannot employ her memory; this image and conception having never had place in her. To say that the corporall prison does so suppresse her natural faculties, that they are altogether extinct in her: first, is cleane contrary to this other beleefe, to knowledge her forces so great, and the operations which men in this transitorie life feel of it, so wonderful, as to have thereby concluded this divinitie, and fore-past eternitie, and the immortalitie to come: Nam si tantopere est animi mutata potestas, Omnis ut actarum excident retinentia rerum, Non ut opinor ea ab letho jam longior errat. -- 695. If of our mind the Power he so much altered, As of things done all hold, all memory is fled, Then (as I guesse) it is not far from being dead. Moreover, it is here with us, and no where else, that the soules powers and effects are to be considered; all the rest of her perfections are vain and unprofitable unto her: it is by her present condition that all her immortalitie must be rewarded and paid, and she is only accomptable for the life of man: it were injustice to have abridged her of her means and faculties, and to have disarmed her against the time of her captivitie and prison, for her weaknesse and sicknesse, of the time and season where she had been forced and compelled to draw the judgement and condemnation of infinite and endlesse continuance, and to relye upon the consideration of so short a time, which is perhaps of one or two hours, or, if the worst happen, of an age (which have no more proportion with infinitie than a moment) definitively to appoint and establish of all her being by that instant of space. It were an impious disproportion to wrest an eternall reward in consequence of so short a life. Plato, to save himself from this inconvenience, would have future payments limited to a hundred years continuance, relatively unto a humane continuance: and many of ours have given them temporall limits. By this they judged that her generation followed the common condition of humane things: as also her life, by the opinion of Epicurus and Democritus, which has most been received; following these goodly apparences. That her birth was seen when the body was capable of her; her virtue and strength was perceived as the corporall encreased; in her infancie might her weaknesse be discerned, and in time her vigor and ripenesse, then her decay and age, and in the end her decrepitude. ------ gigni pariter cum corpore, et una Crescere sentimus, pariterque senescere mentem. -- Ibid. 450. The mind is with the body bred, we do behold, It jointly growes with it, with it it waxeth old. They perceived her to be capable of diverse passions, and agitated by many languishing and painfull motions, wherethrough she fell into wearinesse and grief, capable of alteration and change of joy, stupefaction, and languishment, subject to her infirmities, diseases, and offences, even as the stomacke or the foot; -----mentem sanari, corpus ut ægrum Cernimus, et flecti medicine posse videmus: -- Ibid. 517. We see as bodies sicke are cur’d, so is the mind, We see, how Physicke can it each way turn and winde, dazled and troubled by the force of wine; removed from her seat by the vapors of a burning feaver; drowzie and sleepy by the application of some medicaments, and rouzed up again by the virtue of some others. -----corpoream naturam animi esse necesse est, Corporeis quoniam telis ictuque laborat. -- Ibid. 176. The nature of the mind must ne eds corporeall be, For with corporeall darts and strokes it’s griev’d we see. She was seen to dismay and confound all her faculties by the only biting of a sicke dog, and to containe no great constancy of discourse, no sufficiencie, no virtue, no philosophicall resolution, no contention of her forces that might exempt her from the subjection of these accidents: the spittle or slavering of a mastive dog shed upon Socrates his hands, to trouble all his wisdom, to distemper his great and regular imagination, and so to vanquish and annull them that no signe or show of his former knowledge was left in him: ------ vis animai Conturbatur, ----et divisa seorsum Disjectatur eodem illo distracta veneno. -- Ibid. 501. The soules force is disturbed, separated, Distraught by that same poison, alienated. And the said venome to find no more resistance in his soul than in that of a child of foure years old, a venome able to make all Philosophy (were she incarnate) become furious and mad: so that Cato, who scorned both death and fortune, could not abide the sight of a looking glasse or of water; overcome with horrour, and quelled with amazement, if by the contagion of a mad dog he had fallen into that sicknesse which physicians call hydrophobia, or fear of waters. ------ vis morbi distracta per artus Turbat agens animam, spumantes æquore salso Ventorum ut validis fervescunt viribus undæ. -- Ibid. 495. The force of the disease disperst through joints offends, Driving the soul, as in salt Seas the wave ascends, Foming by furious force which the wind raging lends. Now, concerning this point. Philosophy has indeed armed man for the endurng’ of all other accidents, whether with patience, or if it be overcostly to be found, with an infallible defeat in conveying herself altogether from the sense: but they are means which serve a soul that is her own, and in her proper force capable of discourse and deliberation: not serving to this inconvenience wherewith a Philosopher, a soul becomes the soul of a foole, troubled, vanquished and lost. Which diverse occasions may produce, as in an over- violent agitation, which by some vehement passion the soul may beget in herself: or a hurt in some part of the body, or an exhalation from the stomacke, casting as into some astonishment, dazling, or giddinesse of the head: -----morbis in corporis avius errat Sæpe animus, dementit enim, deliraque fatur, Interdumque gravi Lethargo fertur in altum Æternumque soporem, oculis nutuque cadenti. Ibid. 467. The mind in bodies sicknesse often wandring strayes; For it enraged rave s, and idle talk outbrayes; Brought by sharpe Lethargy sometime to more than deepe, While eyes and eye-lids fall into eternall sleepe. Philosophers have, in mine opinion, but slightly harpt upon this string, no more than other of like consequence. They have ever this Dilemma in their mouth to comfort our mortal condition: ’The soul is either mortal or immortall: if mortal, she shall be without pain: if immortall, she shall mend.’ They never touch the other branch: what if she empaire and be worse? and leave the menaces of future paines to Poets. But thereby they deal themselves a good game. These are two omissions which in their discourses do often offer themselves unto me. I come to the first again: the soul loses the use of that Stoicall chief felicitie, so constant and so firme. Our goodly wisdom must necessarily in this place yielde herself and quit her weapons. As for other matters, they also considered by the vanity of mans reason, that the admixture and societie of two so different parts as is the mortal and the immortall is unimaginable: Quippe etenim mortale æterno jungere, et una Consentire putare, et fungi mutua posse, Desipere est. Quid enim diversius esse putandum est, Aut magis inter se disjuncture discrepitansque, Quam mortale quod est, immortali atque perenni Iunctum in concilio sævas tolerare procellas? --Ibid. 831. For what immortall is, mortal to join unto, And think they can agree, and mutual duties do, Is to be foolish: for what think we stranger is, More disagreenble or more disjoyn’d than this, That mortal with immortall endlesse joyn’d in union, Can most outrageous stormes endure in their communion? Moreover they felt their soul to be engaged in death as well as the body. ----- simul ævo fessa fatiscit, -- Ibid. 463. It faints in one, Wearied as age is gone. Which thing (according to Zeno) the image of sleep does manifestly show unto us. For he esteemeth that it is a fainting and declination of the soul as well as of the body: Contrahi animum, et quasi labi putat atque decidere: (Cic. Div. ii.) ’He thinks the mind is contracted, and does as it were slide and fall down.’ And that (which is perceived in some) its force and vigor maintaineth itself even in the end of life, they referred and imputed the same to the diversitie of diseases, as men are seen in that extremity to maintaine some one sense and some another, some their hearing and some their smelling, without any alteration; and there is no weaknesse or decay seen so universall but some entire and vigorous parts will remaine. Non alio pacto quam sipes cum dolet ægri, In nullo caput interea sit forte dolore. -- Lucr. iii. 111. No otherwise than if, when sick-mans foote does ake, Meane time perhaps his head no fellow-feeling take. Our judgements sight referreth itself unto truth, as does the owles eyes unto the shining of the sunne, as says Aristotle. How should we better convince him than by so grosse blindnesse in so apparent a light? For the contrary opinion of the soules immortalitie, which Cicero says to have first been brought in ( at least by the testimony of books) by Pherecydes Syrius in the time of King Tullus (others ascribe the invention thereof to Thales, and other to others) it is the part of humane knowledge treated most sparingly and with more doubt. The most constant Dogmatists (namely in this point) are enforced to cast themselves under the shelter of the Academikes wings. No man knowes what Aristotle has established upon this subject no more than all the ancients in general, who handle the same with a very wavering beliefe: Rem gratissimam promittentium magis quam probantium: ’Who rather promise than approve a thing most acceptable.’ He has hidden himself under the clouds of intricat and ambiguous words and unintelligible senses, and has left his Sectaries as much cause to dispute upon his judgement as upon the matter. Two things made this his opinion plausible to them: the one, that without the immortality of soules there should no means be left to ground or settle the vain hopes of glory; a consideration of wonderful credit in the world: the other (as Plato says) that it is a most profitable impression, that vices, when they steal away from out the sight and knowledge of humane justice, remaine ever as a blancke before divine justice, which even after the death of the guilty will severely pursue them. Man is ever possessed with an extreme desire to prolong his being, and has to the uttermost of his skill provided for it. Toombs and Monuments are for the preservation of his body, and glory for the continuance of his name. He has employed all his wit to frame him self anew (as impatient of his fortune) and to underprop or uphold himself by his inventions. The soul by reason of her trouble and imbecility, as unable to subsist of herself, is ever and in all places questing and searching comforts, hopes, foundations and forraine circumstances, on which she may take hold and settle herself. And how light and fantastic soever his invention does frame them unto him, he notwithstanding relieth more surely upon them and more willingly than upon himself: But it is a wonder to see how the most obstinat in this so just and manifest persuasion of our spirits immortalitie have found themselves short and unable to establish the same by their humane forces. Somnia sunt non docentis sed optantis: ’These are dreames not of one that teacheth, but wisheth what he would have:’ said an ancient Writer. Man may by his own testimony know that the truth he alone discovereth, the same he oweth unto fortune and chance, since even when she is falne into his hands, he wanteth wherwith to lay hold on her and keep her; and that this reason has not the power to prevaile with it. All things produced by our own discourse and sufficiencie, as well true as false, are subject to uncertaintie and disputation. It is for the punishment of our temeritie and instruction of our misery and incapacitie, that God caused the trouble, downefall and confusion of Babels Tower. Whatsoever we attempt without his assistance, whatever we see without the lampe of his grace, is but vanity and folly: With our weaknes we corrupt and adulterate the very essence of truth (which is uniform and constant when fortune gives us the possession of it. What course soever man taketh of himself, it is Gods permission that he ever commeth to that confusion whose image he so lively representeth unto us by the just punishment, wherewith he framed the presumptuous overweening of Nembroth, and brought to nothing the frivolous enterprises of the building of his high-towring Pyramis or Heaven-menacing tower. Perdam sapientiam sapientium et prudentiam prudentium reprobabo: (1 Cor. i. 19.) ’I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and reprove the providence of them that are most prudent.’ The diversitie of tongues and languages wherewith he disturbed that work and overthrew that proudly-raisd Pile; what else is it but this infinit altercation and perpetual discordance of opinions and reasons which accompanieth and entangleth the frivolous frame of mans learning, or vain building of human science? Which he does most profitably. Who might containe us, had we but one graine of knowledge? This Saint has done me much pleasure: Ipsa Veritatis occultatio, aut humilitatis exercitatio est, out elationis attritio: ’The very concealing of the profit is either an exercise of humility or a beating down of arrogancie.’ Unto what point of presumption and insolencie do we not carry our blindnesse and foolishnesse? But to return to my purpose: Verily there was great reason that we should be beholding to God alone, and to the benefit of his grace, for the truth of so noble a beliefe, since from his liberalitie alone we receive the fruit of immortalitie, which consisteth in enjoying of eternall blessednesse. Let us ingenuously confesse that only God and Faith has told it us: for it is no lesson of Nature, nor coming from our reason. And he that shall both within and without narrowly sift and curiously sound his being and his forces without this divine privilege, he that shall view and consider man without flattering him, shall nor find nor see either efficacie or facultie in him that tasteth of any other thing but death and earth. The more we give, the more we owe: and the more we yield unto God, the more Christian-like do we. That which the Stoike Philosopher said he held by the casual consent of the peoples voice, had it not been better he had held it of God? Cum de animorum æternitate disserimus, non leue momentum apud nos habet Consensus hominum, aut timentium inferos aut colentium. Vtor hac publica persuasione: (Sen. Epist. 117.) ’When we discourse of the immortalitie of soules, in my conceit the consent of those men is of no small authority, who either fear or adore the infernall powers. This public persuasion I make use of.’ Now the weaknes of human arguments on this subject is very manifestly known by the fabulous circumstances they have added unto the traine of this opinion, to find out what condition this our immortalitie was of. Let us omit the Stoices. Usuram nobis largiuntur, tanquam cornicibus: diu mansuros aiunt animos, semper, negant. (Cic. Tusc. Qu. i.) ’They grant us use of life, as is unto Ravens: they say our soules shall long continue, but they deny they shall last ever.’ Who gives unto soules a life beyond this but finite. The most universall and received fantasie, and which endureth to this day, has been that whereof Pythagoras is made Author, not that he was the first inventor of it, but because it received much force and credit by the authority of his approbation; which is, that soules, at their departure from us did but pass and roule from one to another body, from a Lyon to a Horse, from a Horse to a King, uncessantly wandring up and down from House to Mansion. And himself said that he remembred to have been Æthalides, then Euphorbus, afterward Hermotimus, at last from Pyrrhus to have passed into Pythagoras; having memory of himself the space of two hundred and six years: some added more, that the same soules do sometimes ascend up to heaven and come down again: O Pater anne aliquas ad coelum hinc ire putandum est Sublimes animas, interumque ad tarda reverti Corpora? Quæ lucis miseris tam dira cupido? Virg. Æn. vi. 739. Must we think (Father) some soules hence do go, Raised to heav’n, thence turn to bodies slow? Whence does so dyre desire of light on wretches grow? Origen makes them eternally to go and come from a good to a bad estate. The opinion that Varro reporteth is, that in the revolution of foure hundred and forty years they reconjoyned themselves unto their first bodies. Chrysippus, that that must come to pass after a certain space of time unknown and not limited. Plato (who says that he holds this opinion from Pindarus and from ancient Poesie) of infinite vicissitudes of alteration to which the soul is prepared, having no wearines nor rewards in the other world but temporall, as her life in this is but temporall, concludeth in her a singular knowledge of the affairs of Heaven, of Hell, and here below, where she has passed, repassed, and sojourned in many voyages, a matter in his remembrance. Beholde her progresse elsewhere: he that has lived well reconjoyneth himself unto that Star or Planet to which he is assigned: who evil, passeth into a woman: and if then he amend not himself, he trans-changeth himself into a beast of condition agreeing to his vicious customs, and shall never see an end of his punishments until he return to his natural condition, and by virtue of reason he have deprived himself of those grose, stupide, and elementarie qualities that were in him. But I will not forget the objection which the Epicureans make unto this transmigration from one body to another: which is very pleasant. They demand what order there should be if the throng of the dying should be greater than that of such as be borne. For the soules removed from their abode would throng and strive together who should get the best seat in this new case: and demand besides what they would pass their time about, whilst they should stay until any other mansion were made ready for them: Or contrary-wise, if more creatures were borne than should dye, they say bodies shall be in an ill taking, expecting the infusion of their soul, and it would come to pass that some of them should dye before they had ever been living. Denique connubia ad veneris, partusque ferarunt, Esse animas præsto deridiculum esse videtur, Et spectare immortales mortalia membra Innumero numero, certareque præpro peranter Inter se, quæ prima potissimaque insinuetur. - Lucr. iii. 802. Lastly, ridiculous it is, soules should be prest To Venus meetings, and begetting of a beast: That they to mortal lims immortall be addrest In number numberlesse, and over-hasty strive, Which of them first and chief should get in there to live. Others have stayed the soul in the deceased bodies, therewith to animate serpents, wormes, and other beasts, which are said to engender from the corruption of our members, indeed, and from our ashes: others divide it in two parts, one mortal, another immortall: others make it corporeall, and yet notwithstanding immortall: others make it immortall, without any science or knowledge. Nay, there are some of ours who have deemed that of condemned mens souls divels were made: as Plutarke thinks, that Gods are made of those soules which are saved: for there be few things that this author does more resolutely averre then this; holding every where else an ambiguous and doubtfull kind of speech. It is to be imagined and firmlie believed (says he) that the soules of men, vertuous both according unto nature and divine justice, become of Men, Saints, and of Saints, Demi-Gods, and after they are once perfectly, as in sacrifices of purgation, cleansed and purified being delivered from all possibility and mortalitie, become, of Demi-Gods (not by any civill ordinance, but in good truth, and according to manifest reason) perfect and very very Gods; receiving a most blessed and thrice glorious end. But whosoever shall see him who is notwithstanding one of the most sparing and moderate of that faction, so undantedly to skirmish, and will bear him relate his wonders upon this subject, him I refer to his discourse of the Moone, and of Socrates his Dæmon; where as evidently as in any other place, may be averred that the mysteries of Philosophy have many strange conceits, common with those of Poesie; mans understanding losing itself once goes about to sound and controule all things to the utmost ende; as, tired and troubled by a long and wearisome course of our life, we return to a kind of doting childhood. Note here the goodly and certain instructions which concerning our soules-subject we drawe from humane knowledge. There is no less rashnesse in that which she teacheth us touching our corporall parts. Let us make choyce but of one or two examples, else should we lose ourselves in this troublesome and vaste Ocean of Physicall errours. Let us know whether they agree but in this one, that is to say, of what matter men are derived and produced one from another. For, touching their first production, it is no marvell if in a thing so high and so ancient mans wit is troubled and confounded. Archelaus, the Physitian, to whom (as Aristoxenus affirmeth) Socrates was disciple and Minion, assevered that both men and beasts had been made of milkie slime or mudde, expressed by the heate of the earth. Pythagoras says that our seed is the scumme or froth of our best blood: Plato, the distilling of the marrow in the back-bone, which he argueth thus because that place feeleth first the wearinesse which followeth the generative business. Alcmæon, a part of the braine substance, which to prove he says their eyes are ever most troubled that over-intemperately addict themselves to that exercise. Democritus, a substance extracted from all parts of this corporall Masse. Epicurus, extracted from the last soul and the body. Aristotle, an excrement drawne from the nourishment of the blood, the last scattereth itself in our severall members; others, blood, concocted and digested by the heate of the genitories, which they judge because in the extreme, earnest, and forced labours, many shed drops of pure blood; wherein some appearance seems to be, if from so infinit a confusion a ny likelihood may be drawne. But to bring this seed to effect, how many contrary opinions make they of it? Aristotle and Democritus hold that women have no sperme, that it is but a sweate, which by reason of the pleasure and frication they cast forth, and availeth nothing in generation. Galen and his adherents contrariwise, affirme that there can be no generation except two seeds meete together. Behold the Physitians, the Philosophers, the Lawyers, and the Divines pell-mell together by the ears with our women about the question and disputation how long women bear their fruite in their wombe. And as for me, by my own example, I take their part that maintaine a woman may go eleven months with child. The worlde is framed of this experience, there is no meane woman so simple that cannot give her censure upon all these contestations, although we could not agree. This is sufficient to verifie that in the corporall part man is no more instructed of himself than in the spirituall. We have proposed himself to himself, and his reason to reason, to see what she shall tell us of it. Mee thinkes I have sufficiently declared how little understanding she has of herself. And he who has no understanding of himself, what can he have understanding of? Quasi vero mensuram ullius rei possit agere qui sui nesciat: (Plin. Nat. Hist. ii. cap. 1.) ’As though he could take measure of any thing that knowes not his own measure.’ Truely Protagoras told us prettie tales, when he makes a man the measure of all things, who never knew so much as his own. If it be not he, his dignitie will never suffer any other creature to have this advantage over him. Now he being so contrary in himself, and one judgement so uncessantly subverting another, this favorable proposition was but a jest, which induced us necessarily to conclude the nullity of the Compasse and the Compasser. When Thales judgeth the knowledge of man very hard unto man, he teacheth him the knowledge of all other things to be impossible unto him. You for whom I have taken the paines to enlarge so long a work (against my custom) will not shun to maintaine your Sebond with the ordinary form of arguing, whereof you are daily instructed, and will therein exercise both your mind and study; for this last trick of sense must not be employed but as an extreme remedy. It is a desperate thrust, gainst which you must forsake your weapons, to force your adversary to renounce his, and a secret slight, which must seldom and very sparingly be put in practice. It is a great foolish hardnesse to lose our self for the loss of another. A man must not be willing to die to revenge himself, as Gobrias was: who being close by the ears with a Lord of Persia, Darius chanced to come in with his sword in his hand, and fearing to strike for fear he should hurt Gobrias, he called unto him, and bade him smite boldly, although he should smite through both. I have heard arms and conditions of single combates being desperate, and in which he that offered them put not himself and his enemy in danger of an end inevitable to both, reproved as unjust, and condemned as unlawfull. The Portugals took once certain Turkes prisoners in the Indian Seas, who, impatient of their capacity, resolved with themselves (and their resolution succeeded) by rubbing of Ship-nailes one against another, and causing sparkes of fire to fall amongst the barrels of powder (which lay not far from them) with intent to consume both themselves, their masters, and the ship. We but touch at the skirts, and glance at the last closings of the Sciences, wherein extremity, as well as in virtue, is vicious. Keepe yourselves in the common path, it is not good to be so subtil and so curious. Remember what the Italian proverbe says, Chi troppo s’ assottiglia, si scavezza. -- Petr. p. i. canz. xiii. 48. Who makes himself too fine, Does break himself in fine. I persuade you, in your opinions and discourses, as much as in your customs, and in every other thing to use moderation and temperance, and avoide all newfangled inventions and strangenesse. All extravagant waies displease me. You, who by the authority and preheminence which your greatness has laied upon you, and more by the advantages which the qualities that are most your own, bestow on you, may with a nod command whom you please, should have laied this charge upon some one that had made profession of learning, who might otherwise have disposed and enriched this fantasie. Notwithstanding here you have enough to supply your wants of it. Epicurus said of the laws that the worst were so necessary unto us, that without them men would enterdevour one another. And Plato verifieth that without laws we should live like beasts. Our spirit is a vagabond, a d angerous and foolhardy implement; it is very harde to join order and measure to it. In my time, such as have any rare excellency above others, or extraordinary vivacity, we see them almost all so lavish and unbridled in licence of opinions and manners, as it may be counted a wonder to find any one settled and sociable. There is great reason why the spirit of man should be so strictly embarred. In his study, as in all things else, he must have his steps numbered and ordered. The limits of his pursuite must be cut out by art. He is bridled and fettered with and by religions, laws, customs, knowledge, precepts, paines, and recompences, both mortal and immortall; yet we see him, by means of his volubility and dissolution, escape all these bonds. It is a vain body that has no way about him to be seized on or cut off: a diverse and deformed body, on which neither knot nor hold may be fastened. Verily there are few soules so orderly, so constante and so well borne as may be trusted with their own conduct, and may not with moderation, and without rashnes, faile in the liberty of their judgements beyond common opinions. It is more expedient to give some body the charge and tuition of them. The spirit is an outrageous glaive, indeed even to his own possessor, except he have the grace very orderly and discreetly to arm himself therewith. And there is no beast to whom one may more justly apply a blinding bord, to keep her sight in and force her to her footing, and keep from straying here and there, without the tracke which use and laws trace her out. Therefore shall it be better for you to close and bound yourselves in the accustomed path, however it be, than to take your flight to this unbridled licence. But if any one of these new doctors shall undertake to play the wise or ingenious before you, at the charge of his and your health: to rid you out of this dangerous plague, which daily more and more spreds itself in your Courts this preservative will in any extreme necessity, be a let, that the contagion of this venome shall neither offend you nor your assistance. The liberty then, and the jollity of their ancient spirits brought forth many different Sects of opinions, in Philosophy and humane Sciences: every one undertaking to judge and chuse, so he might raise a faction. But now that men walke all one way: Qui certis quibusdam destinatisque sententiis addicti et consecrate sunt, ut etiam quæ non pr obant, cogantur defendere: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ii.) ’Who are addicted and consecrated to certain set and fore- decreed opinions, so as they are enforced to maintaine those things which they prove or approve not:’ And that we receive Arts by civill authority and appointment: so that Schooles have but one patterne, likewise circumscribed discipline and institution; no man regardeth more what coines weigh and are worth; but every man in his turn receiveth them according to the value that common approbation and succession allotteth them: Men dispute no longer of the alloy, but of the use. So are all things spent and vented like. Physike is received as Geometry: and jugling tricks, enchantments, bonds, the commerce of deceased spirits, prognostications, domifications, indeed even this ridiculous wit and wealth-consuming pursuite of the Philosophers stone, all is emploied and uttered without contradiction. It sufficeth to know that Mars his place lodgeth in the middle of the hands triangle; that of Venus in the thumme; and Mercuries in the little finger: and when the table-line cutteth the fore-finger’s rising, it is a signe of cruelty: when it falleth under the middle finger, and that the natural median-line makes an angle with the vital, under the same side, it is a signe of a miserable death: and when a womans natural line is open, and closes not its angle with the vital, it evidenty denotes that she will not be very chast. I call your self to witness, if with this Science only, a man may not pass with reputation and favor among all companies. Theophrastus was wont to say that mans knowledge, directed by the sense, might judge of the causes of things unto a certain measure, but being come to the extream and first causes, it must necessarily stay, and be blunted or abated, either by reason of its weaknesse or of the things difficulty. It is an indifferent and pleasing kind of opinion to think that our sufficiency may bring us to the knowledge of some things, and has certain measures of power beyond which it’s temerity to employ it. This opinion is plausible and brought in by way of composition: but it is hard to give our spirit any limits, being very curious and greedy, and not tied to stay rather at a thousand then at fifty spaces. Having found by experience that if one had mist to attaine unto some one thing, another has come unto it, and that which one age never knew, the age succeeding has found out: and that Sciences and Arts are not cast in a mold, but rather by little and little formed and shaped by often handling and polishing them over: even as bears fashion their yong whelps by often licking them: what my strength cannot discover, I cease not to sound and try: and in handling and kneading this new matter, and with removing and chasing it, I open some faculty for him that shall follow me, that with more ease he may enjoy the same, and make it more facile, more supple and more pliable: -----vt hymettia sole Cera remollescit, tractataque pollice, multas Vertitur in facies, ipsoque fit vtilis vsu. -- Ovid. Metam. x. 284. As the best Bees wax melteth by the Sun, And handling, into many formes does run, And is made aptly fit For use by using it. As much will the second do for the third, which is a cause that difficulty does not make me despaire, much less my unability: for it is but my own. Man is as well capable of all things as of some. And if (as Theophrastus says) he avow the ignorance of the first causes and beginnings, let him boldly quit all the rest of his knowledge. If his foundation faile him, his discourse is overthrowne. The dispute has no other scope, and to enquire no other end but the principles: If this end stay not his course, he casteth himself into an infinite irresolution. Non potest aliud alio magis minusque comprehendi, quoiam omnium reram vna est definitio comprehendendi: ’One thing can neither more nor less be comprehended than another, since of all things there is one definition of comprehending.’ Now it is likely that if the soul knew any thing, she first know herself: and if she knew any without and besides herself, it must be her veil and body before any thing else. If even at this day the Gods of Physicke are seen to wrangle about our Anatomie, Mulciber in Troiam, pro Troia stabat Apollo, -- Ovid. Trist. El. ii. 5. Apollo stood for Troy, Vulcan Troy to destroy, when shall we expect that they will be agreed? We are nearer unto ourselves, then is whiteness unto snow or weight unto a stone. If man know not himself, how can he know his functions and forces? It is not by fortune that some true notice does not lodge with us but by hazard. And forasmuch as by the same way, fashion and conduct, errours are received into our soul, she has not wherewithall to distinguish them, nor whereby to chose the truth from falshood. The Academikes received some inclination of judgment and found it over raw, to say, it was no more likely snow should be white then blacke, and that we should be no more assured of the moving of a stone, which goeth from our hand, then of that of the eighth Spheare. And to avoid this difficultie and strangenesse, which in truth cannot but hardly lodge in our imagination, howbeit they establish that we were no way capable of knowledge, and that truth is engulfed in the deepest Abysses, where mans sight can no way enter; yet avowed they some things to be more likely and possible then others, and receivd this faculty in their judgement that they might rather incline to one apparence then to another. They allowed her this propension, interdicting her all resolution. The Pyrrhonians advise is more hardy, and therewithall more likely. For this Academicall inclination, and this propension rather to one then another proposition, what else is it then a recognition of some more apparant truth, in this than in that? If our understanding be capable of the form, of the lineaments, of the behaviour and face of truth, it might as well see it all compleat, as but halfe, growing and imperfect. For this apparance of verisimilitude which makes them rather take the left then the right hand, do you augment it; this one ounce of likelihood, which turnes the balance, do you multiply it by a hundred, nay by a thousand ounces; it wil in the end come to pass that the balance will absolutely resolve and conclude one choice and perfect truth. But how do they suffer themselves to be made tractable by likelihood, if they know not truth? How know they the semblance of that whereof they understand not the essence? Either we are able to judge absolutely, or absolutely we cannot. If our intellectuall and sensible faculties are without ground or footing, if they but hull up and down and drive with the wind, for nothing suffer we our judgment to be carried away to any part of their operation, what apparauce soever it seems to present us with. And the surest and most happy situation of our understanding should be that, where without any tottering or agitation it might maintaine itself setled, upright and inflexible. Inter visa, vera, aut falsa, ad animi assensum, nihil interest: (Cic. Acad. Qu. iv.) ’There is no difference betwixt true and false visions concerning the mindes assent.’ That things lodge not in us in their proper form and essence, and make not their entrance into us of their own power and authority, we see it most evidently. For if it were so, we would receive them all likewise: wine should be such in a sicke mans mouth as in a healthy mans. He whose fingers are chopt through cold, and stiffe or benumbed with frost, should find the same ha rdnesse in the wood or iron he might handle, which another does. Then strange subjects yield unto our mercy, and lodge with us according to our pleasure. Now if on our part we receive any thing without alteration, if mans holdfasts were capable and sufficiently powerfull by our proper means to seize on truth, those means being common to all; this truth would successively remove itself from one to another. And of so many things as are in the world, at least one should be found, that by an universall consent should be beleeved of all. But that no proposition is seen, which is not controversied and debated amongst us, or that may not be, declareth plainly that our judgment does not absolutely and clearly seize on that which it seizeth: for my judgment cannot make my fellowes judgment to receive the same: which is a signe that I have seized upon it by some other meane then by a natural power in me or other men. Leave we apart this infinite confusion of opinions, which is seen amonge Philosophers themselves, and this universal and perpetuall disputation, in and concerning the knowledge of things. For it is most truly presupposed that men (I mean the wisest, the best borne, indeed the most sufficient do never agree; no not so much that heaven is over our heads. For they who doubt of all, do also doubt of this: and such as affirme that we cannot conceive any thing, say we have not conceived whether heaven be over our heads; which two opinions are in number (without any comp arison) the most forcible. Besides this diversity and infinite division, by reason of the trouble which our own judgement layeth upon ourselves, and the uncertainty which every man findes in himself, it may manifestly be perceived that this situation is very uncertaine and unstaid. How diversely judge we of things? How often change we our phantasies? What I hold and believe this day I believe and hold with all my beleefe: all my implements, springs and motions, embrace and claspe this opinion , and to the utmost of their power warrant the same: I could not possibly embrace any verity, nor with more assurance keep it, than I do this. I am wholy and absolutely given to it: but has it not been my fortune, not once, but a hundred, nay a thousand times, nay daily, to have embraced some other thing with the very same instruments and condition which upon better advise I have afterward judged false? A man should, at the least become wise at his own cost, and learne by others harmes. If under this colour I have often found my self deceived, if my Touch-stone be commonly found false and my balance un-even and unjust; what assurance may I more take of it at this time than at others? Is it not folly in me to suffer my self so often to be beguiled and couzened by one guide? Nevertheless, let fortune remove us five hundred times from our place, let her do nothing but incessantly empty and fill, as in a vessell, other and other opinions in our mind, the present and last is alwaies supposed certain and infallible. For this must a man have goods, honor, life, state, health and all: -----posterior res illa reperta Perdit; et immutat sensus ad pristina quæque. -- Lucr. v. 1424. The latter thing destroies all found before; And alters sense at all things lik’d of yore. Whatsoever is told us, and what ever we learne, we should ever remember: it is man that delivereth and man that receiveth: it is a mortal hand that presents it, and a mortal hand that receives it. Only things which come to us from heaven have right and authority of persuasion and markes of truth: which we neither see with our eyes nor receive by our means: this sacred and great image would be of no force in so wretched a Mansion except God prepare it to that use and purpose, unless God by his particular grace and supernaturall favor reforme and strengthen the same. Our fraile and defective condition ought at least make us demeane ourselves more moderately and more circumspectly in our changes. We should remember that whatsoever we receive in our understanding we often receive false things, and that it is by the same instruments which many times contradict and deceive themselves. And no marvell if they contradict themselves, being so easy to encline, and upon very slight occasions subject to waver and turn. Certain it is that our apprehension, our judgement, and our soules faculties in general, do suffer according to the bodies motions and alterations, which are continuall. Have we not our spirits more vigilant, our memory more ready, and our discourses more lively in time of health then in sicknesse? Does not joy and blithenesse make us receive the subjects that present themselves unto our soul, with another kind of countenance, then lowring vexation and drooping melancholy does? Doe you imagine that Catullus or Saphoes verses delight and please an old covetous chuff-penny wretch as they do a lusty and vigorous yong man? Cleomenes the son of Anaxandridas being sick, his friends reproved him, saying he had new strange humors and unusuall phantasies: ’It is not unlikely,’ answered he, ’for I am not the man I was wont to be in the time of health; but being other, so are my fantasies and my humors.’ In the rabble case-canvasing of our plea- courts this byword, Gaudeat de bona fortuna: ’Let him joy in his good fortune" is much in use, and is spoken of criminall offenders, who happen to meete with Judges in some mild temper or well-pleased mood. For it is most certain that in times of condemnation the Judges doom or sentence is sometimes perceived to be more sharpen mercilesse and forward, and at other times more tractable, facile, and enclined to shadow or excuse an offence, according as he is well or ill pleased in mind. A man that commeth out of his house troubled with the pain of the goute, vexed with jealousy, or angry that his servant has robbed him, and whose mind is overcome with grief, and plunged with vexation, and distracted with anger, there is not question to be made but his judgement is at that instant distempred, and much transported that way. That venerable senate of the Areopagites was wont to judge and sentence by night, for fear the sight of the suters might corrupt justice. The air itself, and the clearenes of the firmament, does forbode us some change and alteration of weather, as says that Greek verse in Cicero: Tales sunt hominum mentes, quali pater ipse Jupiter auctifera lustravit lampade terras. -- Cic. ex incert. Such are mens mindes, as with increasefull light Our father Jove survaies the world in sight. It is not only fevers, drinkes and great accidents, that over- whelme our judgement: the least things in the world will turn it topsie-turvie. And although we feel it not, it is not to be doubted, if a continuall ague may in the end suppresse our mind, a tertian will also (according to her measure and proportion) breed some alteration in it. If an Apoplexie does altogether stupifie and extinguish the sight of our understanding, it is not to be doubted but a cold and rheum will likewise dazle the same. And by consequence, hardly shall a man in all his life find one hour wherein our judgement may alwaies be found in his right byase, our body being subject to so many continuall alterations, and stuft with so diverse sorts of ginnes and motions, that, giving credit to Physitians, it is very hard to find one in perfect plight, and that does not alwaies mistake his marke and shute wide. As for the rest, this disease is not so easily discovered, except it be altogether extreme and remedilesse; forasmuch as reason marcheth ever crooked, halting and broken-hipt; and with falshood as with truth; and therefore it is very hard to discover her mistaking and disorder. I alwaies call reason that apparance or show of discourses which every man deviseth or forgeth in himself: that reason, of whose condition there may be a hundred, one contrary to another, about one self same subject: it is an instrument of lead and wax, stretching, pliable, and that may be fitted to all byases and squared to all measures: there remaines nothing but the skill and sufficiency to know how to turn and winde the same. How well soever a Judge meaneth, and what good mind so ever he beareth, if diligent care be not given unto him (to which few ammuse themselves) his inclination unto friendship, unto kindred, unto beauty, and unto revenge, and not only matters of so weighty consequence, but this innated and casual instinct which us to favor one thing more than another, and encline to one man more than to another, and which, without any leave or reason, gives us the choice in two like subjects, or some shadow of like vanity, may insensibly insinuate in his judgment the commendation and applause, or disfavour and disallowance of a cause, and give the balance a twitch. I that nearest prie into my self, and who have mine eyes uncessantly fixt upon me as one that has not much else to do else where, -- quis sub Arcto Rex gelidæ metuatur oræ, Quid Tyridatem terreat unice Securus, -- Hor. i. Od. xxvi. 3. Only secure, who in cold coast Under the North-pole rules the rost, And there is fear or what would fright, And Tyridates put to flight, dare very hardly report the vanity and weaknesse I feel in myself. My foot is so staggering and unstable and I find it so ready to trip and so easy to stumble and my sight is so dimme and uncertaine that fasting I find my self other than full fed. If my health applaud me, or but the calmenesse of one fair day smile upon me, then am I a lusty gallant; but if a corne wring my toe, then am I pouting, unpleasant and hard to be pleased. One same pace of a horse is sometimes hard and sometimes easy unto me; and one same way, one time short, another time long and wearisome; and one same form, now more, now less agreeable and pleasing to me: sometimes I am apt to do any thing, and other times fit to do nothing: what now is pleasing to me within a while after will be paineful. There are a thousand indiscreet and casual agitations in me. Either a melancholy humor possesseth me, or a cholericke passion swaieth me, which having shaken off, sometimes frowardilesse and peevishnesse has predominancy, and other times gladnes and blithnesse overrule me. If I chance to take a book in hand I shall in some passages perceive some excellent graces, and which ever wound me to the soul with delight; but let me lay it by and read him another time; let me turn and tosse him as I list, let me apply and manage him as I will, I shall find it an unknown and shapelesse masse. Even in my writings I shall not at all times find the tracke or air of my first imaginations; I wot not my self what I would have said, and shall vexe and fret my self in correcting and giving a new sense to them, because I have perhaps forgotten or lost the former, which happily was better. I do but come and go; my judgement does not alwaies go forward, but is ever floting and wandering. ----- velut minuta magno Deprensa navis in mari, vesaniente vento. -- Catul. Lyr. Epig. xxii.12. Much like a petty skiffe, that’s taken short In a grand Sea, when winds do make mad sport. Many times (as commonly it is my hap to do) having for exercise and sport-sake undertaken to maintaine an opinion contrary to mine, my mind applying and turning it self that way does so tie me unto it, as I find no more the reason of my former conceit, and so I leave it. Where I encline, there I entertaine my self however it be, and am carried away by my own weight. Every man could neer-hand say as much of himself would he but looke into himself as I do. Preachers know that the emotion which surprises them whilst they are in their earnest speech does animate them towards belief, and that being angrie we more violently give ourselves to defend our proposition, emprint it in ourselves, and embrace the same with more vehemence and approbation than we did being in our temperate and reposed sense. You relate simply your case unto a Lawyer; he answers faltring and doubtfully unto it, whereby you perceive it is indifferent unto him to defend either this or that side, all is one to him. Have you paid him well, have you given him a good baite or fee to make him earnestly apprehend it, beginnes he to be enterested in the matter, is his will moved or his mind enflamed? Then will his reason be moved and his knowledge enflamed with all. See then an apparent and undoubted truth presents it self to his understanding, wherein he discovers a new light, and believes it in good sooth, and so perswades himself. Shall I tell you? I wot not whether the heate proceedingk of spight and obstinacy against the impression and violence of a magistrate and of danger: or the interest of reputation have induced some man to maintaine, even in the fiery flames, the opinion for which amongst his friends and at liberty he would never have been moved nor have ventured his fingers end. The motions and fits which our soul receiveth by corporall passions do greatly prevaile in her, but more her own, with which it is so fully possest, as happily it may be maintained she has no other or motion than by the blasts of her winds, and that without their agitation she should remaine without action, as a ship at sea which the winds have utterly forsaken. And he who should maintaine that following the Peripatetike faction should offer us no great wrong, since it is known that the greatest number of the soules actions proceede and have neede of this impulsion of passion; valor (say they) cannot be perfected without the assistance of choler. Semper Aiax fortis, fortissimus tamen in furore. -- CIC. Tusc. Qu. iv. Ajax every valor had, Most then, when he was most mad. Nor does any man run violently enough upon the wicked, or his enemies, except he be throughly angrie; and they are of opinion that an advocate or counsellor at the barre, to have the cause go on his side, and to have justice at the judges hands, does first endevor to provoke him to anger. Longing-desires moved Themistocles and urged Demosthenes, and have provoked Philosophers to long travels, to tedious watchings, and to lingring peregrinations and leads us to honors, to doctrine, and to heal th: all profitable respects. And this demissenes of the soul in suffering molestion and tediousness, serveth to no other purpose, but to breed repentance and cause penitence in our consciences, and for our punishment to feel the scourge of God and the rod of politike correction. Compassion serveth as a sting unto clemencie, and wisdom to preserve and governe ourselves, is by our own fear rouzed up; and how many noble actions by ambition, how many by presumption. To conclude, no eminent or glorious virtue can be without some immoderate and irregular agitation. May not this be one of the reasons which moved the Epicureans to discharge God of all care and thought of our affairs: forasmuch as the very effects of his goodnesse cannot exercise themselves towards us without disturbing his rest by means of the passions which are as motives and solicitations directing the soul to vertuous actions? Or have they thought otherwise, and take them as tempests which shamefully lead astray the soul from her rest and tranquillitie? Vt maris tranquillita intelligitur, nulla, ne minima quidem, aura fluctus, commovente: Sic animi quietus et placatus status cernitur, quam perturbatio nulla est, qua moveri queat: (Cic. ibid. v.) ’As we conceive the seas calmnesse, when not so much as the least pirling wind does stir the waves, so is a peaceable reposed state of the mind then seen when there is no perturbation whereby it may be moved.’ What differences of sense and reason, what contrarietie of imaginations does the diversitie of our passions present unto us? What assurance may we then take of so unconstant and wavering a thing, subject by its own condition to the power of trouble, never marching but a forced and borrowed pace? If our judgement be in the hands of sickenes itself and of perturbation; if by rashnesse and folly it be retained to receive the impression of things, what assurance may we expect at his hands? Dares not Philosophie think that men produce their greatest effects, and neerest approaching to divinity when they are besides themselves, furious, and madde? We amend ourselves by the privation of reason, and by her drooping. The two natural waies to enter the cabinet of the Gods, and there to foresee the course of the destinies, are fury and sleepe. This is very pleasing to be considered. By the dislocation that passions bring into our reason, we become vertuous; by the extirpation which either fury or the image of death bringeth us, we become Prophets and Divines. I never beleeved it more willingly. It is a meere divine inspiration that sacred truth has inspired in a Philosophical spirit which against his proposition exacteth from him; that the quiet state of our soul, the best-settled estate, indeed the healthfullesi that Philosophy can acquire unto it, is not the best estate. Our vigilancie is more drouzie then asleepe itself: our wisdom less wise then folly; our dreames of more worth then our discourses. The worst place we can take is in ourselves. But thinks it not that we have the foresight to marke, that the voice which the spirit uttereth when he is gone from man so clear sighted, so great, and so perfect, and whilst he is in man so earthly, so ignorant, and so overclouded, is a voice proceeding from the spirit which is in earthly, ignorant, and overclouded man; and therefore a trustles and not to be-believed voice? I have no great experience in these violent agitations, being of a soft and dull complexion, the greatest part of which, without giving it leisure to acknowledge herself, do sodainely surprise our soul. But that passion, which in young mens harts is saied to be produced by idleness, although it march but leasurely and with a measured progress, does evidently present to those that have assaid to oppose themselves against her endeavor, the power of the conversion and alteration which our judgement suffereth. I have some times enterprised to arm my self with a resolution to abide, resist, and suppresse the same. For I am so far from being in their rank that call and allure vices, that unless they draw me I scarcely follow them. I felt it mauger my resistance, to breed, to growe, and to augment; and in the end, being in perfect health and clear sighted, to seize upon and pollute me; in such sort that as in drunkennes the image of things began to appeare unto me other wise then it was wont. I saw the advantages of the subject I sought after evidently to swell and grow greater, and much to encrease by the winde of my imagination; and the difficulties of my enterprise to become more easy and plaine, and my discourse and conscience to shrinke and draw backe. But that fire being evaporated all on a sodaine, as by the flashing of a lightning, my soul to reassume an other sight, an other state, and other judgement. The difficultie in my retreate seemed great and invincible, and the very same things of another taste and show than the fervency of desire had presented them unto me. And which more truly, Pyrrho cannot tell. We are never without some infirmitie. Fevers have their heat and their cold: from the effects of a burning passion, we fall into the effects of a chilling passion. So much as I had cast my self forward, so much do I draw my self backe. Qualis ubi alterno procurrens gurgite pontus, Nunc ruit ad terrar, scopilisque superjacit undam, Spumeus, extremamque sinu prefundit arenam, Nunc rapidus retro, atque æstu rvoluta resorbens Saxa, fugit, littusque vado labente relinquit. -- VIRG. Æn. xi. 508 As the Ocean flowing, ebbing in due course, To land now rushes, foming throws his fource On rocks, therewith bedewes the utmost sand, Now swift returns the stones rowld backe from strand By tide resucks, foord failing, leaves the land. Now by the knowledge of my volubilitie, I have by accident engendred some constancy of opinions in my self; indeed have not so much altered my first and natural ones. For, what apparance soever there be in novelty, I do not easily change for fear I should lose by the bargaine: and since I am not capable to chuse, I take the choice from others; and keep my self in the seate that God has placed me in. Else could I hardly keep my self from continuall rowling. Thus have I by the Grace of God preserved my self whole (without agitation or trouble of conscience) in the ancient beliefe of our religion, in the middest of so many sects and divisions which our age has brought forth. The writings of the ancient fathers (I meane the good, the solid, and the serious) do tempt, and in a manner remove me which way they list. Him that I hear seems ever the most forcible. I find them everie one in his turn to have reason, although they contrary one another. That facility which good witts have to prove any thing they please likely; and that there is nopthing so strange but that they will undertake to set so good a gloss on it, as it shall easily deceive a simplicity like unto mine, does manifestly show the weaknesse of their proofe. The heavens and the planets have moved these three thousand years, and all the world beleeved as much, until Cleanthes the Samian, or else (according to Theophrastus) Nicetas the Syracusian took upon him to maintaine, it was the earth that moved, by the oblique circle of the Zodiake, turning about her axell tree. And in our days Copernicus has so well grounded this doctrine, that he does orderly fit it to all astrologicall consequences. What shall we reape by it but only that we neede not care which of the two it be? And who knows whether a thousand years hence a third opinion will rise, which happily shall overthrow these two precedents? Sic volvenda ætas vommutat tempora rerum, Quodque fuit pretio, fit nullo denique honore, Porro aliud succedit, et contemptibus exit, Inque dies magis appetitur, floretque repertum Laudibus, et miro est mortales inter honore. -- Lucr. v. 1286. So age to be past-over alters times of things: What earst was most esteem’d, At last nought-worth is deem’d: Another then succeeds, and from contempt upsprings, Is daily more desir’d, flowreth as found but then With praise and wondrous honor amongst mortal men. So when any new doctrine is represented unto us, we have great cause to suspect it, and to consider how, before it was invented, the contrary unto it was in credit; and as that has been reversed by this latter, a third invention may perhaps succeed in after ages, which in like sort shall front the second. Before the principles which Aristotle found out were in credit, other principles contented mans reason as his do now content us. What learning have these men, what particular priviledge, that the course of our invention should rely only upon them, and that the possession of our beliefe shall for ever hereafter belong to them? They are no more exempted from being rejected than were their fore- fathers. If any man urge me with a new argument, it is in me to imagine that, if I cannot answere it, another can. For, to believe all apparences which we cannot resolve, is meere simplicitie. It would then follow that all the common sort (whereof we are all part) should have his beliefe turning and winding like a weather-cocke: for, his soul being soft and without resistance, should uncessantly be enforced to receive new and admit other impressions: the latter ever defacing the precedents trace. He that perceiveth himself weake, ought to answer, according to law termes, that he will conferre with his learned counsel, or else refer himself to the wisest, f rom whom he has had his prentiseship. How long is it since physicke came first into the world? It is reported that a new start-up fellow, whom they call Paracelsus, changeth and subverteth all the order of ancient and so long received rules, and maintaineth that until this day it has only served to kill people. I think he will easily verify it. But I suppose it were no great wisdom to hazard my life upon the trial of his newfangled experience. ’We must not believe all men,’ says the precept, ’since every man may say all things.’ It is not long since that one of these professours of novelties and physical reformations told me that all our forefathers had notoriously abused themselves in the nature and motion of the winds, which, if I should listen unto him, he would manifestly make me perceive. After I had with some patience given attendance to his arguments, which were indeed full of likelyhood, I demanded of him whether they which had sailed according to Theophrastus his laws, went westward when they bent their course eastward? Or whether they sailed sideling or backward? ’It is fortune,’ answered he, ’but so it is, they took their marke amisse:’ To whom I then replied that I would rather follow the effects than his reason. They are things that often shock together: and it has been told me that in geometry (which supposeth to have gained the high point of certainty amongst all sc iences) there are found unavoidable demonstrations, and which subvert the truth of all experience: as James Peletier told me in my own house, that he had found out two lines bending their course one towards another, as if they would meet and join together; nevertheless he affirmed that, even unto infinity, they could never come to touch one another. And the Pyrrhonians use their arguments, and reason but to destroy the apparance of experience: and it is a wonder to see how far the supplenesse of our reason has in this design followed them to resist the evidence of effects: for they affirme that we move not, that we speak not, that there is no weight, nor heat, with the same force of arguing that we averre the most likeliest things. Ptolomey, who was an excellent man, had established the bounds of the world; all ancient philosophers have thought they had a perfect measure thereof, except it were certain scattered ilands which might escape their knowledge: it had been to Pyrrhonize a thousand years agoe, had any man gone about to make a question of the art of cosmography: and the opinions that have been received thereof, of all men in general: it had been flat heresie to avouch that there were Antipodes. See how in our age an infinite greatness of firme land has been discovered, not an iland only, nor one particular country, but a part in greatness very near equall unto that which we knew. Our modern geographers cease not to affirme that now all is found, and all is discovered: Nam quod adest præsto, placet, et pollere videtur, -- Ibid. 1422. For what is present here, Seemes strong, is held most dear. The question is now, if Ptolomey was heretofore deceived in the grounds of his reason, whether it were not folly in me to trust what these late fellowes say of it, and whether it be not more likely that this huge body which we terme the world is another manner of thing than we judge it. Plato says that it often changeth his countenance, that the heaven, the starres, and the sunne do sometimes re-enverse the motion we perceive in them, changing the east into the west. The Egyptian priests told Herodotus that since their first king, which was eleaven thousand and odde years (when they made him see the pictures of all their former kings, drawne to the life in statues) the sun course had changed his course foure times: that the sea and the earth do enterchangeably change one into an other; that the worlds birth is undetermined: the like said Aristotle and Cicero. And some one amongst us averreth that it is altogether eternall, mortal, and new reviving again, by many vicissitudes, calling Solomon and Esay to witness: to avoid these oppositions, that God has sometimes been a Creator without a creature; that he has been idle; that he has unsaid his idlenesse by setting his hand to this work , and that by consequence he is subject unto change. In the most famous schooles of Greece, the world is reputed a God framed by another greater and mightier God, and is composed of a body and a soul, which abideth in his centre, spreading itself by musicall numbers unto his circumference, divine, thrice happy, very great, most wise and eternall. In it are other Gods, as the sea, the earth, and planets, which with an harmonious celestiall dance; sometime meeting, other times far-sundering themselves; now hiding, them shewing themselves; and changing place, now forward, now backward. Heraclitus firmly mainitained that the world was composed of fire, and by the destinies order it should one day burst forth into flames, and be so consumed into cinders, and another day it should be new borne again. And Apuleius of men says: Sigillatim mortales; cunctim perpetui: (L. APUL. De Deo; SOCRAT.) ’Severally mortal; altogether everlasting.’Alexander wrote unto his mother the narration of an Egyptian priest, drawne from out their monuments, witnessing the antiquitie of that nation, infinite; and comprehending the birth and progresse of their countries to the life. Cicero and Diodorus said in their days that the Chaldeans kept a register of foure hundred thousand and odde years; Aristotle, Plinie, and others, that Zoroaster lived sixe thousand years before Plato. And Plato says that those of the citty of Sais have memories in writing of eight thousand years, and that the town of Athens was built a thousand years before the citty of Sais. Epicurus, that at one same time all things that are looke how we see them, they are all likewise, and in the same fashion, in diverse other Worlds, which he would have spoken more confidently had he seen the similitudes and correspondencies of this new-found world of the West Indiæs with ours, both present and past, by so many strange examples. Truly, when I consider what has followed our learning by the course of this terrestriall policy, I have diverse times wondered at my self, to see in so great a distance of times and places, the simpathy or jumping of so great a number of popular and wild opinions, and of extravagant customs and beliefes, and which by no means seem to hold with our natural discourse. Man’s spirit is a wonderful worker of miracles. But this relation has yet a kind of I wot not what more Heteroclite: which is found both in names and a thousand other things. For there were found Nations which (as far as we know) had never heard of us, where circumcision was held in request; where great states and commonwealths were maintained only by women, and no men: where our fasts and Lent was represented, adding thereunto the abstinence from women; where our crosses were severall waies in great esteeme. In some places they adorned and honored their sepulchres with them, and elsewhere especially that of Saint Andrew, they employed to shield themselves from nightly visions, and to lay them upon childrens couches, as good against enchantments and witchcrafts. In another place they found one made of wood, of an exceeding height, worshipped for the God of raine; which was thrust very deepe into the ground. There was found a very express and lively image of our Penitentiaries: the use of Miters, the Priestes single life; the Art of Divination by the entrailes of sacrificed beasts; the abstinence from all sorts of flesh and fish for their food; the order amongst Priests, in saying of their divine service, to use a not vulgar but a particular tongue; and this erroneous and foolish conceipt, that the first God was expelled his throne by a younger brother of his: that they were at first created with all commodities, which afterward, by reason of their sinnes, were abridged them: that their territory has been changed; that their natural condition has been much impaired: that they have heretofore been drowned by the inundation of Waters come from heaven; that none were saved but a few families, which cast themselves into the cracks or hollows of high Mountaines, which crackes they stoped very close, so that the Waters could not enter in, having before shut therin many kinds of beasts: that when they perceived the Raine to cease and Waters to fall, the first sent out certain doggs, which returned cleane- washt and wet, they judged that the waters were not yet much falne; and that afterward sending out some other, which seeing to return all muddy and foul, they issued forth of the mountaines, to repeople the world again, which they found replenished only with Serpents. There were places found where they used the persuasion of the day of judgement, so that they grew wondrous wroth and offended with the Spaniards, who in digging and searching of riches in their graves, scattered here and there the bones of there deceased friends, saying that those dispersed bones could very hardly be reconjoyned again. They also found where they used traffic by exchange, and no otherwise; and had Faires and Markets for that purpose; they found dwarfes, and such other deformed creatures, used for the ornament of Princes tables: they found the use of hawking and fowling according to the nature of their birdes: tyrannical subsidies, and grievances upon subjects; delicate and pleasant gardens; dancing, tumbling, leaping, and iugling, music of instruments, armories, dicing-houses, tennisse-courts, and casting lottes, or mumme- chaunce, wherein they are often so earnest and moody, that they will play themselves and their liberty: using no other physicke but by charmes: the manner of writing by figures: beleeving in one first man, universall father of all people. The adoration of one God, who heretofore lived man in perfect Virginitie, fasting, and penance, preaching the law of Nature, and the ceremonies of religion; and who vanished out of the world without any natural death: The opinion of Giants; the use of drunkennesse, with their manner of drinkes and drinking and pledging of healths; religious ornaments painted over with bones and dead mens sculs; surplices, holy Water, and holy Water sprinckles, Women and servants which thrivingly present themselves to be burned or enterred with their deceased husbands or masters: a law that the eldest or first borne child shall succeed and inherit all: where nothing at all is reserved for Punies, but obedience: a custom to the promotion of certain officers of great authority, and where he that is promoted takes upon him a new name, and quiteth his own: Where they used to cast lime upon the knees of new borne children, saying unto him: From dust then camest, and to dust then shall return again: the Arts of Augures or prediction. These vain shadowes of our religion, which are seen in some of these examples, witness the dignity and divinity thereof. It has not only in some sort insinuated itself among all infidell Nations on this side by some imitations, but amongst those barbarous Nations beyond, as it were by a common and supernaturall inspiration: For amongst them was also found the beliefe of Purgatory, but after a new form: for, what we ascribe unto fire, they impute unto cold, and imagine that soules are both purged and punished by the vigor of an extreme coldnesse. This example putteth me in mind of another pleasant diversity: For, as there were some people found who took pleasure to unhood the end of their yard, and to cut off the fore-skinne after the manner of the Mahometans and Jewes, some there were found that made so great a conscience to unhood it, that with little strings they caried their fore-skin very carefully out-streched and fastened above, for fear that end should see the aire. And of this other diversity also, that as we honor our Kings and celebrate our Holy-days with decking and trimming our selves with the best habilliments we have; in some regions there, to show all disparity and submission to their King, their subjects present themselves unto him in their basest and meanest apparrell; and entring unto his pallace they take some old torn garment and put it over their other attire, to the end all the glory and ornament may shine in their Soveraigne and Maister. But let us go on: if Nature enclose within the limits of her ordinary progresse, as all other things, so the beliefes, the judgments and the opinions of men; if they have their revolutions, their seasons, their birth, and their death, even as cabbages: if heaven does move, agitate and rowle them at his pleasure, what powerfull and permanent authority do we ascribe unto them? If by uncontroled experience we palpably touch, that the form of our being depends of the aire, of the climate, and of the soile wherein we are borne and not only the hew, the stature, the complexion and the countenance, but also the soules facilities: Et plagæ coeli non serum ad robor corporum, sed etiam animorum facit: ’The climate helpeth not only for strength of body, but of minds,’ says Vegetius: And that the Goddesse, foundresse of the City of Athens, chose a temperature of a country to situate it in, that might make the men wise, as the Egyptian Priests taught Solon: Athenis tenue eoclum: ex quo etiam acutiores putantur Attici: crassum Thebis: itague pingues Thebani, et valentes: (CIC. De Fato.) ’About Athens is a thin aire, whereby those Country-men are esteemed the sharper witted: about Thebes the aire is grosse, and therefore the Thebans were grosse and strong of constitution.’ In such manner that as fruits and beasts do spring up diverse and different; so men are borne either more or less warlike, martiall, just, temperate, and docile: here subject to wine, there to theft and whoredome: here inclined to superstition, addicted to misbehaving; here given to liberty; there to servitude; capable of some one art or science; grosse-witted or ingenious: either obedient or rebellious; good or bad, according as the inclination of the place beareth, where they are seated; and being removed from one soile to another (as plants are) they take a new complexion: which was the cause that Cirus would never permit the Persians to leave their barren, rough, and craggie Country, for to transport themselves into another, more gentle, more fertile, and more plaine: saying, that ’fat and delicious countries make men wanton and effeminate; and fertile soiles yield infertile spirits.’ If sometime we see one art to flourish, or a beliefe, and sometimes another, by some heavenly influence: some ages to produce this or that nature, and so to encline mankind to this or that base: mens spirits one while flourishing, another while barren, even as fields are seen to be; what become of all those goodly prerogatives wherewith we still flatter ourselves. Since a wise man may mistake himself; indeed, many men, and whole nations; and as we say, mans nature either in one thing or other, has for many ages together mistaken herself. What assurance have we that at any time she leaveth her mistaking, and that she continueth not even at this day, in her error? Me thinkes amongst other testimonies of our imbecilities, this one ought not to be forgotten, that by wishing itself, man cannot yet find out what he wanteth; that not by enjoying or possession, but by imagination and full wishing, we cannot all agree in one that we most stand in need of, and would best content us. Let our imagination have free liberty to cut out and sew at her pleasure, she cannot so much as desire what is fittest to please and content her. -----quid enim ratione timemus Aut cupimus? quid tam dextro pede concipis, ut te Conatus non pæniteat, votique peracti? -- Juven. Sat. x. 4. By reason what do we fear, or des ire? With such dexteritie what doest aspire, But you eftsoones repentest it, Though your attempt and vow do hit? That is the reason why Socrates never requested the gods to give him anything but what they knew to be good for him. And the public and private prayer of the Lacedemonians did meerely implie that good and fair things might be granted them, remitting the election and choise of them to the discretion of the highest power. Coniugium petimus partumque uxoris, at illis Notum qui pueri, qualisque futura sit uxor. -- Ibid. 352. We wish a wife, wifes breeding: we would know, What children; shall our wife be sheep or shrow. And the Christian beseecheth God, that his will may be done, least he should fall into that inconvenience which poets faine of King Midas, who requested of the Gods that whatsoever he touched might be converted into gold: his praiers were heard, his wine was gold, his bread gold, the feathers of his bed, his shirt, and his garments were turned into gold, so that he found himself overwhelmed in the injoying of his desire, and being enricht with an intolerable commoditie, he must now unpray his prayers: Attonitus novitate mali, divesque miserque, Effugere optat opes, et quæ modo voverat, odit -- Ovid. Met. xi. 128. Wretched and rich, amaz’d at so strange ill, His riches he would flie, hates his owns will. Let me speak of my self; being very yong I besought fortune above all things that she would make me a knight of the order of Saint Michæl, which in those days was very rare, and the highest tipe of honor the French nobility aymed at; she very kindly granted my request; I had it. In lieu of raising and advancing me from my place for the attaining of it, she has much more graciously entreated me, she has debased and depressed it, even unto my shoulders and under. Cleobis and Biton, Trophonius and Agamedes, the two first having besought the Goddesse, the two latter their God, of some recompence worthy their pietie, received death for a reward. So much are heavenly opinions different from ours, concerning what we have need of. God might grant us riches, honors, long life and health, but many times to our own hurt. For, whatsoever is pleasing to us, is not alwaies healthfull for us. If in lieu of former health he send us death, or some worse sicknesse: Virga tua et baculus tuus ipsa me consolata sunt: (Psal. xxiii. 4.) ’Thy rod and your staffe has comforted me.’ He does it by the reasons of his providence, which more certainly considereth and regardeth what is meet for us then we ourselves can do, and we ought to take it in good part as from a most wise and thrice-friendly hand. ------ si consilium vis, Permittes ipsis expendere numinibus, quid Conveniat nobis, rebusque sit vtile nostris: Charior est illis homo quam sibi. -- Juven. Sat. x. 346. If you will counsell have, give the Gods leave To weigh what is most meet we should receive, And what for our estate most profit were: To them, then to himself man is more dear. For, to crave honors and charges of them, is to request them to cast you in some battle, or play at hazard, or some such thing, whereof the event is unknowen to you, and the fruit uncertaine. There is no combate amongst philosophers so violent and sharpe as that which arises upon the question of mans chief felicitie, from which (according to Varroe’s calculation) arose two hundred and foure score Sects. Qui autem de summo hono dissentit, de tota Philosophiæ ratione disputat: ’But he that disagrees about the chiefest felicitie, cals in question the whole course of Philosophie.’ Tres mihi convivæ prope dissentire videntur, Poscentes vario m ultit diversa palato. Quid dem? quid non dem? renuis tu quod iubet alter: Quod petis, id sane est invisum acidumque duobus. -- Hor. ii. Epist. ii. 61. Three guests of mine do seem allmost at ods to fall, While they with diverse taste for diverse things do call: What should I give? What not? You will not, what he will; What you would, to them twaine is hateful, sowre and ill. Nature should thus answer their contestations and debates. Some say our felicitie consisteth and is in virtue, others in voluptuousness, others in yielding unto Nature, some others in learning, others in feeling no manner of pain or sorrow, others for a man never to suffer himself to be carried away by appearances, and to this opinion seems this other of ancient Pithagoras to incline, Nil admirari, propre res est una, Numici, Solaque, quæ possit facere et servare beatum, -- i. Epist. vi. 1. Sir, nothing to admire, is the only thing, That may keep happy, and to happy bring, which is the end and scope of the Pyrrhonian Sect. Aristotle ascribeth unto magnanimity, to admire and wonder at nothing. And Archesilaus said that sufference and an upright and inflexible state of judgement were true felicities; whereas consents and applications were vices and evils. True it is, that where he establisheth it for a certain Axiome, he started from Pyrrhonisme. When the Pyrrhonians say that ataraxy is the chief felicitie, which is the immobilitie of judgement, their meaning is not to speak it affirmatively, but the very wavering of their mind, which makes them to shun downefalls, and to shrewd themselves under the shelter of calmenesse, presents this phantasie unto them, and makes them refuse another. Oh how much do I desire that while I live, either some other learned men, or Iustus Lipsius, the most sufficient and learned man now living; of a most polished and judicious wit, true Cosingermane to my Turnebus, had both will, health, and leisure enough, sincerely and exactly, according to their divisions and formes, to collect into one volume or register, as much as by us might be seen, the opinions of ancient philosophy, concerning the subject of our being and customs, their controversies the credit, and partaking of factions and sides, the application of the authors and sectators lives, to their precepts in memorable and exemplarie accidents. O what a worthy and profitable labor would it be! Besides, if it be from ourselves that we draw the regiment of our customs, into what a bottomles confusion do we cast ourselves? For what our reason perswades us to be most likely for it, is generally for every man to obey the laws of his country, as is the advise of Socrates, inspired (says he) by a divine persuasion. And what else meaneth she thereby, but only that our devoire or duety has no other rule but casual? Truth ought to have a like and universall visage throughout the world. Law and justice, if man knew any, that had a body and true essence, he would not fasten it to the condition of this or that countries customs. It is not according to the Persians or Indians fantazie that virtue should take her form. Nothing is more subject unto a continuall agitation then the laws. I have, since I was borne, seen those of our neighbors, the English-men, changed and re- changed three or foure times, not only in politike subjects, which is that some will dispense of constancy, but in the most important subject that possibly can be, that is to say, in religion: whereof I am so much the more ashamed, because it is a nation with which my countriemen have heretofore had so inward and familiar acquaintance, that even to this day there remain in my house some ancient monuments of our former alliance. Nay, I have seen amongst ourselves some things become lawfull which erst were deemed capital: and we that hold some others, are likewise in possibilitie, according to the uncertainty of warring fortune, one day or other, to be offenders against the Majestie both of God and man, if our justice chance to fall under the mercy of justice; and in the space of few years possession, taking a contrary essence. How could that ancient God more evidently accuse, in humane knowledge, the ignorance of divine essence, and teach men that their religion was but a peece of their own invention, fit to combine their societies then in declaring, as he did, to those which sought the instruction of it, by his sacred Tripos, that the true worshipping of God was that which he found to be observed by the custom of the place where he lived? Oh God, what bond or dutie is it that we owe not to our Soveragne Creators benignitie, in that he has been pleased to clear and enfranchise our beliefe from those vagabonding and arbitrary devotions, and fixt it upon the eternall base of his holy word? What will Philosophie then say to us in this necessity? that we follow the laws of our country, that is to say, this waveing sea of a peoples or of a Princes opinions, which shall paint me forth justice with as many colours, and reforme the same into as many visages as there are changes and alterations of passions in them. I cannot have my judgement so flexible. What goodnesse is that which but yesterday I saw in credit and esteeme, and to morrow to have lost all reputation, and that the crossing of a river is made a crime? What truth is that which these Mountaines bound, and is a lie in the world beyond them? But they are pleasant, when to allow the laws some certaintie, they say that there be some firme, perpetuall and immoveable; which they call natural, and by the condition of their proper essence, are imprinted in mankind: of which some make three in number, some foure, some more, some less: an evident token that it is a marke as doubtfull as the rest. Now are they so unfortunate (for how can I terme that but misfortune, that of so infinit a number of laws there is not so much as one to be found which the fortune or temeritie of chance has graunted to be universally received, and by the consent of unanimitie of all Nations to be admitted?) they are (I say) so miserable that of these three or four choice-selected laws there is not one alone that is not impugned or disallowed, not by one nation, but by many. Now is the generalitie of approbation the only likely ensigne by which they may argue some laws to be natural; for what nature had indeed ordained us, that should we doubtlesse follow with one common consent; and not one only nation, but every man in particular should have a feeling of the force and violece which he should urge him with, that would incite him to contrary and resist that law. Let them all (for example sake) show me but one of this condition. Protagoras and Ariston gave the justice of the laws no other essence, but the authority and opinion of the law giver, and that excepted, both good and honest lost their qualities, and remained but vain and idle names of indifferent things. Thrasymachus, in Plato, thinkes there is no other right but the commoditie of the superior. There is nothing wherein the world differeth so much as in customs and laws. Some things are here accompted abominable, which in another place are esteemed commendable; as in Lacedemonia, the slight and subtlety in stealing marriages in proximity of blood are amongst us forbidden as capital, elsewhere they are allowed and esteemed; -----gentes esse feruntur, In quibus et nato genitrix, et nata parenti Iungitur, et pietas geminato crescit amore. -- Ovid. Met. x. 331. There are some people where the another weddeth Her son the daughter her own father beddeth, And so by doubling love, their kinduesse spreddeth. The murthering of children and of parents; the communication with women; traffic of jobbing and stealing; free licence to all manner of sensuality; to conclude, there is nothing so extreme and horrible, but is found to be received and allowed by the custom of some nation. It is credible that there be natural laws, as may be seen in other creatures, but in us they are lost: this goodly humane reason engrafting itself among all men, to sway and command, confounding and topsi-turving the visage of all things according to her inconstant vanity and vain inconstancy. Nihil itaque amplius nostrum est, quod nostrum dico, artis est: ’Therefore nothing more is ours: all that I call ours belongs to art.’ Subjects have diverse lustres, and severall considerations, whence the diversity of opinion is chiefly engendred. One nation vieweth a subject with one visage, and thereon it staies; an other with an other. Nothing can be imagined so horrible as for one to eate and devour his own father. Those people which anciently kept this custom hold it nevertheless for a testimony of pietie and good affection: seeking by that meane to give their fathers the worthiest and most honorable sepulchre, harboring their fathers bodies and reliques in themselves, and in their marrow; in some sort reviving and regenerating them by the transmutation made in their quick flesh by digestion and nourishment. It is easy to be considered what abomination and cruelty it had been, in men accustomed and trained in this inhumane superstition, to cast the carcases of their parents into the corruption of the earth, as food for beasts and wormes. Lycurgus wisely considereth in theft, the vivacitie, dilignce, courage, and nimblenesse that is required in surprising or taking any thing from ones neighbour, and the commoditie which thereby redoundeth to the common-wealth, that every man heedeth more curiously the keeping of that which is his own, and judged that by this twofold institution to assaile and to defend, much good was drawne for military discipline (which was the principal Science and chief verue wherein he would enable that nation) of greater respect and more consideration than was the disorder and injustice of prevailing and taking other mens goods. Dionysius, the tyrant offered Plato a robe made after the Persian fashion, long, damask, and perfumed: but he refused the same, saying, ’That being borne a man, he would not willingly put on a womans garment.’ But Aristippus took it, with this answer, ’That no garment could corrupt a chaste mind.’ His friends reproved his demissenesse in being so little offended, that Dionysius had spitten in his face. ’Tut (said he) fishers suffer themselves to be washed over head and ears to get a gudgion.’ Diogenes washing of coleworts for his dinner, seeing him pass by, said unto him, ’If you couldest live with coleworts, you would not court and fawne upon a tyrant;’ to whom Aristippus replied, ’If you couldest live among men, you would not wash coleworts.’ See here how reason yieldeth apparance to diverse effects. It is a pitcher with two ears, which a man may take hold on, either by the right or left hand. ----- bellum o terra hospita portas, Bello arman tur equi, bellum hæc armenta minantur: Sed tamen iidem olim curru succedere sueti Quadrupedes, et froena jugo concordia ferre, Spes est pacis--- -- Virg. Æn. iii. 559. O stranger-harbring land, you bringst us war; Steeds serve for war; These heards do threaten jarre. Yet horses erst were wont to draw our waines, And harnest matches bear agreeing raines, Hope is hereby that we In peace shall well agree. Solon being importuned not to shed vain and bootles tears for the death of his son; ’Thats the reason (answered he) I may more justly shed them, because they are bootlesse and vain.’ Socrates, his wife, exasperated her grief by this circumstance. ’Good Lord (said she) how unjustly do these bad judges put him to death.’ ’ What! would you rather they should execute me justly?’ replied he to her. It is a fashion amongst us to have holes bored in our ears: the Greekes held it for a badge of bondage. We hide ourselves when we will enjoy our wives: the Indians do it in open view of all men. The Scithians were wont to sacrifice strangers in their Temples, whereas in other places Churches are Sanctuaries for them. Inde furor vulgi, quodnumina vicinorum Odit quisque locus, cum solos credat habendos Esse Deos quos ipse colit. -- Juven. Sat. xv. 36. The vulgar hereupon does rage, because Each place does hate their neighbors sovereign laws, And only Gods does deem, Those Gods, themselves esteeme. I have heard it reported of a Judge who, when he met with any sharp conflict betweene Bartolus and Baldus, or with any case admitting contrarieties was wont to write in the margin of his book, ’A question for a friend,’ which is to say, that the truth was so entangled and disputable that in such a case he might favor which party he should think good. There was no want but of spirit and sufficiency, if he set not every where through his books, ’A question for a friend.’ The Advocates and Judges of our time find in all cases byases too-too-many to fit them where they think good. To so infinite a science, depending on the authority of so many opinions, and of so arbitrary a subject, it cannot be but that an exceeding confusion of judgements must arise. There are very few processes so clear but the Lawiers advises upon them will be found to differ: What one company has judged another will adjudge the contrary, and the very same will another time change opinion. Whereof we see ordinary examples by this licence which wonderfully blemisheth the authority and lustre of our law, never to stay upon one sentence, but to run from one to another judge, to decide one same case. Touching the liberty of Philosophicall opinions concerning vice and virtue, it is a thing needing no great extension, and wherein are found many advises which were better unspoken then published to weake capacities. Arcesilaus was wont to say that in pailliardize it was not worthy consideration, where, on what side, and how it was done. Et obcænas voluptates, si natura requirit, non genera, aut loco, aut ordine, sed forma, ætate, figura metiendas Epicurus putat. Ne amores quidem sanctos a sapiente atienos esse arbitrantur. Quæramus ad quam usque, ætatem iuvenes amandi sint: ’Obscene pleasures, if nature require them, the Epicure esteemeth not to be measured by kind, place, or order: but by form, age, and fashion. Nor does he think that holy loves should be strange from a wise man. Let us then question to what years yong folke may be beloved.’ These two last Stoice places, and upon this purpose, the reproch of Diogarchus to Plato himself, show how many excessive licences and out of common use soundest Philosophy does tolerate. Lawes take their authority from possession and custom. It is dangerous to reduce them to their beginning: In rowling on they swell and grow greater and greater, as do our rivers: follow them upward into their source, and you shall find them but a bubble of water, scarce to be discerned, which in gliding on swelleth so proud and gathers so much strength. Behold the ancient considerations which have given the first motion to this famous torrent, so full of dignitie, of honor and reverence, you shall find them so light and weake that these men which will weigh all and complain of reason, and who receive nothing upon trust and authority, it is no wonder if their judgments are often far distant from common judgement. Men that take Natures first image for a patterne it is no marvaile if in most of their opinions they miss the common-beaten path. As for example few amongst them would have approved the false conditions of our marriages, and most of them would have had women in community and without any private respect. They refused our ceremonies: Chrysippus said that some Philosophers would in open view of all men show a dozen of tumbling-tricks, indeed, without any slops or breeches, for a dozen of olives. He would hardly have persuaded Calisthenes to refuse his fair daughter Agarista to Hippoclides, because he had seen him graft the forked tree in her upon a table. Metrocles somewhat indiscreetly, as he was disputing in his Schole, in presence of his auditory, let a fart, for shame whereof he afterwards kept his house and could not be drawen abroad until such time as Crates went to visit him, who to his persuasions and reasons, adding the example of his liberty, began to fart a vie with him and to remove this scruple from off his conscience; and moreover won him to his Stoicall (the more free) Sect, from the Peripateticall (and more civill) one, which the-therunto he had followed. That which we call civilitie not to dare to do that openly, which amongst us is both awful and honest, being done in secret, they termed folly: And to play the wilie Foxe in concealing and disclaiming what nature, custom, and our desire publish and proclaims of our actions, they deemed to be a vice. And thought it a suppressing of Venus her mysteries to remove them from out the private vestry of her temple, and expose them to the open view of the people. And that to draw her sports from out the curtaines was to loose them. Shame is matter of some consequence. Concealing, reservation and circumspection are parts of estimation. That sensuality under the maske of Vertu did very ingeniously procure not to be prostituted in the midst of highwaies, not trodden upon and seen by the common sort, alledging the dignity and commodity of her wonted Cabinets. Whereupon some say that to forbid and remove the common brothel-houses is not only to spread whoredome every where, which only was allotted to those places, but also to incite idle and vagabond men to that vice by reason of the difficultie. Mæchus es Aufidiæ qui vir Corvine fuisti, Rivalis fuerat qui tuus, ille vir est. Cur aliena placet tibi, qua, tua non placet uxor? Nunquid securas non potes arrigere? -- Mart. iii. Epig. lxx. This experience is diversified by a thousand examples. Nullus in vrbe fuit tota, qui tangere vellet Uxorem gratis Cæciliane tuam, Dum licuit: sed nunc positis custodibus, inqens Turba fututorum est, in geniosus homo es. -- i. Epig. lxxiv. A Philosopher being taken with the deed, was demaunded what he did, answered very mildly, ’I plant man,’ blushing no more being found so napping than if he had been taken setting of Garlike. It is (as I suppose) of a tender and respective opinion that a notable and religious Author holds this action so necessarily-bound to secrecy and shame, that in Cynike embracements and dalliances he could not be persuaded that the work should come to her end; but rather that it lingred and stayed only to represent wanton gestures and lascivious motions, to maintaine the impudency of their schooles profession: and that to powre forth what shame had forced and bashfullnesse restrained, they had also afterward need to seek some secret place. He had not seen far enough into their licenciousnesse: for Diogenes in sight of all, exercising his Masturbation, bred a longing desire in the bystanders, that in such sort they might fill their bellies by rubbing or clawing the same. To those that asked him why he sought for no fitter place to feed in than in the open frequented highway he made answer, ’It is because I am hungry in the open frequented high-way.’ The Philosophers Women, which medled with their Sects, did likewise in all places and without any discretion medle with their bodies: And Crates had never received Hipparchia into his fellowship but upon condition to follow all the customs and fashions of his order. These Philosophers set an extreme rate on virtue and rejected al other disciplins except the mortal; hence it is that in all actions they ascribed the Soveraigne authority to the election of their wise, indeed, and above all laws: and appointed no other restraint unto voluptuousness, but the moderation and preservation of others liberty. Heraclitus and Protagoras, forasmuch as wine seems bitter unto the sicke and pleasing to the healthy; and an oar crooked in the water and straight to them that see it above water, and such-like contrary apparances which are found in some subjects; argued that all subjects had the causes of these apparances in them, and that there was some kind of bitternes in the wine which had a reference unto the sick mans taste; in the oar a certain crooked quality, having relation to him that seeth it in the water. And so of all things else. Which implieth, that all is in all things, and by consequence nothing in any : for either nothing is, or all is. This opinion put me in mind of the experience we have, that there is not any one sense or visage, either straight or crooked, bitter or sweet, but mans wit shall find in the writings which he undertaketh to run over. In the purest, most unspotted, and most absolutely perfect word that possibly can be, how many errors, falshoods and lies have been made to proceed from it? What heresie has not found testimon ies and ground sufficient, both to undertake and to maintaine itself? It is, therefore, that the Authors of such errors will never go from this proofe of the testimony of words interpretation. A man of worth going about by authority to approve the search of the Philosophers stone (wherein he was overwhelmed) alleadged at least five or six several passages out of the holy bible unto me, upon which (he said) he had at first grounded himself for the discharge of his conscience (for he is a man of Ecclesiastical profession), and truly the invention of them was not only pleasant, but also very fitly applied to the defense of this goodly and mind-enchanting science. This way is the credit of divining fables attained to. There is no prognosticator if he have but this authority that any one wil but vouchsafe to read him over, and curiously to search all the infoldings and lustres of his words, but a man shall make him say what he pleaseth, as the Sibils. There are so many means of interpretation that it is hard, be it flat-long, side-long, or edge-long, but an ingenious and pregnant wit shal in all subjects meet with some aire that wil fit his turn. Therefore is a clowdy, darke and ambiguous stile found in so frequent and ancient custom, that the Author may gain to draw, allure, and busie posterity to himself, which not only the sufficiency but the casual favor of the matter may gain as much or more. As for other matters let him, be it either through foolishnes or subtilty, show himself somewhat obscure and diverse, it is no matter, care not he for that. A number of spirits sifting and tossing him over will find and express sundry formes, either according, or collaterally, or contrary to his own, all which shall do him credit. He shal see himself enriched by the means of his Disciples, as the Grammer Schools Maisters. It is that which has made many things of nothing, to pass very currant, that has brought diverse books in credit, and charged with all sorts of matter that any has but desired: one selfsame thing admitting a thousand and a thousand, and as many severall images and diverse considerations, as it best pleaseth us. Is it possible that ever Homer meant all that which some make him to have meant? And that he prostrated hiniselfe to so many, and so severall shapes, as, Divines, Lawiers, Captains, Philosophers, and all sort of people else, which, how diversely and contrary soever it be they treat of sciences, do notwithstanding wholy rely, upon him, and refer themselves unto him as a General Maister for all offices, workes, sciences, and tradesmen, and an universall counsellor in all enterprises; whosoever has had need of Oracles or Predictions, and would apply them to himself, has found them in him for his purpose. A notable man, and a good friend of mine, would make one marvel to bear what strange far- fetcht conceits and admirable affinities, in favor of our religion, he maketh to derive from him; and can hardly be drawne from this opinion, but that such was Homers intent and meaning (yet is Homer so familiar unto him, as I think no man of our age is better acquainted with him). And what he finds in favor of our religion, many ancient learned men have found in favor of theirs. See how Plato is tossed and turned over, every man endevoring to apply him to his purpose, gives him what construction he list. He is wrested and inserted to all newfangled opinions that the world receiveth or all oweth of, and according to the different course of subjects is made to be repugnant unto himself. Every one according to his sense makes him to disavow the customs that were lawfull in his days, inasmuch as they are unlawfull in these times. All which is very lively and strongly maintained, according as the wit and learning of the interpreter is strong and quick. Upon the ground which Heraclitus had, and that sentence of his, that all things had those shapes in them which men found in them. And Democritus out of the very same drew a cleane contrary conclusion, id est, that subjects had nothing at all in them of that which we found in them. And forasmuch as honny was sweet to one man and bitter to another, he argued that honny was neither sweet nor bitter. The Pyrrhonians would say they know not whether it be sweet or bitter, or both or neither: for, they ever gain the highest point of doubting. The Cyrenaicks held that nothing was perceptible outwardly, and only that was perceivable which by the inward touch or feeling touched or concerned us, as grief and sensuality, distinguishing neither tune nor collours, but only certain affections that came to us of them; and that man had no other seate of his judgment. Protagoras deemed that to be true to all men, which to all men seems so. The Epicurians place all judgment in the senses, and in the notice of things, and in voluptuousness. Platoes mind was, that the judgmen t of truth, and truth itself drawne from opinions and senses, belonged to the spirit and to cogitation. This discourse has drawne me to the consideration of the senses, wherein consisteth the greatest foundation and trial of our ignorance. Whatsoever is known, is without perhaps known by the faculty of the knower: for, since the judgment commeth from the operation of him that judgeth, reason requireth that he performe and act this operation by his means and will, and not by others compulsion: as it would follow if we knew things by the force, and according to the law of their essence. Now all knowledge is addressed unto us by the senses: they are our maisters: -----via qua munita fidei Proxima fert humanum in pectus, templaque mentis. -- Lucr. v. 102. Whereby a way for credit leads well-linde Into man’s breast and temple of his mind. Science begins by them and in them is resolved. After all, we should know no more then a stone, unless we know that here is sound, smell, light, savor, measure, weight, softnesse, hardnesse, sharpnesse, colour, smoothnesse, breadth and depth. Behold here the platforme of all the frame and principles of the building of all our knowledge. And according to some, science is nothing else but what is known by the senses. Whosoever can force me to contradict my senses, has me fast by the throate, and cannot make me recoyle one foote backward. The senses are the beginning and end of humane knowledge. Invenies primis ab sensibus esse creatam Notitiam veri, neque sensus posse refelli. Quid maiore fide porro, quam sensus, haberi Debet? -- iv. 480,484. You shall find knowledge of the truth at first was bred From our first senses, nor can senses be misseled. What, then our senses, should With us more credit hold? Attribute as little as may be unto them, yet must this ever be graunted them, that all our instruction is addressed by their means and intermission. Cicero says that Chrysippus having assaid to abate the power of his senses, and of their virtue, presented contrary arguments unto himself, and so vehement oppositions, that he could not satisfie himself. Whereupon Carneades (who defended the contrary part boasted that he used the very same weapons and words of Chrysippus to combate against him and therefore cried out upon him, ’Oh miserable man! thine own strength has foiled you.’ There is no greater absurditie in our judgment, then to maintaine that fire heateth not, that light shineth not, that in iron there is neither weight nor firmenesse, which are notices our senses bring unto us: Nor beliefe or science in man, that may be compared unto that, in certaintie. The first consideration I have upon the senses subject is, that I make a question, whether man be provided of all natural senses, or no. I see diverse creatures that live an entire and perfect life, some without sight, and some without hearing; who knows whether we also want either one, two, three, or many senses more: For, if we want any one, our discourse cannot discover the want or defect thereof. It is the senses priviledge to be the extreme bounds of our perceiving. There is nothing beyond them that may stead us to discover them: No one sense can discover another. An poterunt oculos aures reprehendere, an aures Tactus, an hunc porro tactum sapor arguet oris, An confutabunt nares, oculive revincent? -- 488. Can ears the eyes, or can touch reprehend The cares, or shall mouthes taste that touch amend? Shall our nose it confute, Or eyes gainst it dispute? They all make the extreamest line of our facultie. -----seorsum cuique potestas Divisa est, sua vis cuique est. -- 491. To teach distinctly might Is shar’de, each has its right. It is impossible to make a man naturally blind, to conceive that he seeth not; impossible to make him desire to see, and sorrow his defect. Therefore ought we not to take assurance that our mind is contented and satisfied with those we have, seeing it has not wherewith to feel her own malady, and perceive her imperfection, if it be in any It is impossible to tell that blind man any thing, either by discourse, argument, or similitude, that lodgeth any apprehension of light, colour, or sight in his imagination. There is nothing more backward that may push the senses to any evidence. The blind-borne, which we perceive desire to se, it is not to understand what they require; they have learnt of us that something they want, and something they desire, that is in us, with the effects and consequences thereof, which they call good: yet wot not they what it is, nor apprehend they it near or far. I have seen a gentleman of a good house, borne blind, at least blind in such an age that he knowes not what sight is; he understandeth so little what he wanteth, that as we do, he useth words fitting sight, and applieth them after a manner only proper and peculiar to himself. A child being brought before him to whom he was god-father, taking him in his arms, he said, ’Good Lord, what a fine child this is! it is a goodly thing to see him. What a cherefull countenance he has! how prettily he looketh!’ He will say as one of us, ’This hall has a fair prospect. It is very fair weather, The Sunne shines clear.’ Nay, which is more: because hunting, hawking, tennis-play, and shuting at buts are our common sports and exercises (for so he has heard) his mind will be so affected unto them, and he wil so busie himself about them, that he will think to have as great an interest in them as any of us, and show himself as earnestly passionate, both in liking and disliking them, as any else; yet does he conceive and receive them but by hearing. If he be in a fair champion ground, where he may ride, they will tell him, yonder is a Hare started, or the Hare is killed, he is as busily earnest of his game as he heareth others to be that have perfect sight. Give him a ball, he takes it in the left hand, and with the right strikes it away with his racket; in a piece he shutes at randome; and is well pleased with what his men tell him, be it high or wide. Who knowes whether mankind commit as great a folly, for want of some sense, and that by this default the greater part of the visage of things be concealed from us? Who knowes whether the difficulties we find in sundry of Natures workes proceede thence? And whether diverse effects of beasts, which exceed our capacitie, are produced by the facultie of some sense that we want? And whether some of them have by that meane a fuller and more perfect life then ours? We seize on an apple well nigh with all our senses; we find rednesse, smoothnesse, odor and sweetness in it; besides which, it may have other vertues, either drying or binding, to which we have no sense to be referred. The proprieties which in many things we call secret, as in the Adamant to draw iron, is it not likely there should be sensitive faculties in nature able to judge and perceive them, the want whereof breedeth in us the ignorance of the true essence of such things? It is happily some particular sense that unto cockes or chanticleares discovereth the morning and midnight hour, and moveth them to crow: that teacheth a hen, before any use or experience, to fear a hawke and not a goose or a peacocke, far greater birds: that warneth yong chickins of the hostile quality which the cat has against them, and not to distrust a dog; to strut and arm themselves against the mewing of the one (in some sort a flattering and mild voice) and not against the barking of the other (a snarling and quarrelous voice): that instructeth rats, wasps, and emmets, ever to chuse the best cheese and fruit, having never tasted them before: and that addresseth the stag, the elephant, and the serpent, to the knowledge of certain herbs and simples, which, being either wounded or sicke, have the virtue to cure them. There is no sense but has some great domination, and which by his meane affordeth not an infinite number of knowledges. I f we were to report the intelligence of sounds, of harmony and of the voice, it would bring an imaginable confusion to all the rest of our learning and science. For, besides what is tyed to the proper effect of every sense, how many arguments, consequences, and conclusions draw we unto other things, by comparing one sense to another? Let a skilfull, wise man but imagine humane nature to be originally produced without sight and discourse, how much ignorance and trouble such a defect would bring unt o him, and what obscurity and blindnesse in our mind.’ By that shall we perceive how much the privation of one, or two, or three such senses (if there be any in us) does import us about the knowledge of truth. We have by the consultation and concurrence of our five senses formed one Verity, whereas perhaps there was required the accord and consent of eight or ten senses, and their contribution, to attaine a perspicuous insight of her, and see her in her true essence. Those Sects which combate mans science, do principally combate the same by the uncertainty and feeblenesse of our senses. For, since by their meane and intermission all knowledge comes unto us, if they chance to misse in the report they make unto us, if either they corrupt or alter that, which from abroad they bring unto us, if the light which by them is transported into our soul be obscured in the passage, we have nothing else to hold by. From this extreme difficultie are sprung all these phantazies, which everie subject containeth, whatsoever we find in it, that it has not what we suppose to find in it, and that of the Epicurians, which is; that the sunne is no greater than our sight does judge it: Quicquid id est, nihilo fertur maiore figura, Quam nostris oculis quam cernimus esse videtur: -- Lucr. v. 576. Whate’er it be, it in no greater form does pass, Then to our eyes, which it behold, it seeming was: that the apparances, which represent a great body to him that is neare unto it, and a much lesser to him that is further from it, are both true: Nec tamen hic oculis falli concedimzus hilum: Proinde animi vitium hoc oculis adfingere noli: -- iv. 380,387. Yet graunt we not, in this, our eyes deceiv’d or blind, Impute not then to eyes this error of the mind: and resolutely, that there is no deceit in the senses that a man must stand to their mercy, and elsewhere seek reasons to excuse the difference and contradiction we find in them: indeed invent all other untruthes and raving conceits (so far come they) rather than accuse the senses. Timagoras swore, that however he winked or turned his eyes, he could never perceive the light of the candle to double: and that this seeming proceeded from the vice of opinion, and not from the instrument. Of all absurdities the most absurd amongst the Epicurians is to disavow the force and effect of the senses. Proinde quod in quoque est his visum tempore, verum est: Et si non potuit ratio dissolvere causam, Cur ea quæ fuerint iuxtim quadrata, procul sint Visa rotunda: tamen præstat rationis egentem Reddere mendose causas vtriusque figuræ, Quam manibus manifesta suis emittere quoquam, Et violare fidem primam, et convellere tota Fundamenta, quibus nixatur vita salusque. Non modo enim ratio ruat omnis, vita quoque ipsa Concidat extemplo, nisi credere sensibus ausis, Præcipitesque locos vitare, et cætera quæ sint In genere hoc fugienda. -- Lucr. iv. 502. What by the eyes is seen at any time, is true, Though the cause treason could not render of the view, Why, what was square at hand, a far off seemed round, Yet it much better were, that wanting reasons ground The causes of both formes we harp-on, but not hit, Then let slip from our hands things clear, and them omit, And violate our first beliefe, and rashly rend All those ground-workes, whereon both life and health depend, For not alone all reason falls, life likewise must Faile out of hand, unless your senses you dare trust, And breake-neeke places, and all other errours shunne, From which we in this kind most carefully should run. This desperate and so little Philosophicall counsell, represents no other thing but that humane science cannot be maintained but by unreasonable, foolish and mad reason; yet is it better that man use it to prevaile, indeed of all other remedies else how phantasticall soever they be, rather than avow his necessarie foolishnesse: So prejudiciall and disadvantageous a veritie he cannot avoide, but senses must necessarily be the Soveraigne maisters of his knowledge; but they are uncertaine and falsifi able to all circumstances. There must a man strike to the utmost of his power, and if his just forces faile him (as they are wont) to use and employ obstinacy, temeritie and impudencie. If that which the Epicurians affirme, be true, that is to say, we have no science, if the apparances of the senses be false, and that which the Stoics say, if it is also true that the senses apparences are so false as they can produce us no science; we will conclude at the charges of these two great Dogmatist Sects, that there is no science. Touching the error and uncertaintie of the senses operation, a man may store himself with as many examples as he pleaseth, so ordinary are the faults and deceits they use towards us. And the echoing or reporting of a valleys the sound of a trumpet seems to sound before us, which cometh a mile behind us. Exstantesque procul medio de gargite montes Idem apparent longe diverse i licet. -- Lucr. iv. 398. Et fugere ad puppim colles campique videntur Quos agimus prater navim. -- 390. -----ubi in medio nobis equus acer obhæsit Flumine, equi corpus transversum ferre videtur Vis, et in adversum flumen contrudere raptim. -- 423. And hills, which from the main far-off to kenning stand, Appeare all one, though they far distant be, at hand, And hilles and fields do seem unto our boate to flie, Which we drive by our boate as we do pass thereby, When in midst of a streame a stately Horse does stay, The streame’s orethwarting seems his body crosse to sway, And swiftly ’gainst the streame to thrust him the other way. To roule a bullet under the fore finger, the midlemost being put over it, a man must very much enforce himself to affirme there is but one, so assuredly does our sense present us two. That the senses do often maister our discourse, and force it to receive impressions which he knows and judgeth to be false, it is daily seen. I leave the sense of feeling which has his functions nearer more quick and substantiall, and which by the effect of the grief or pain it brings to the body does so often confound and re-enverse all these goodly Stoicall resolutions, and enforceth to cry out of the bellyache him who has with all resolution established in his mind this doctrine, that the cholike, as every other sicknesse or pain, is a thing indifferent, wanting power to abate any thing of sovereign good or chief felicity, wherein the wise man is placed by his own virtue: there is no heart so demiss, but the rattling sound of a drum or the clang of a trumpet will rowse and inflame; nor mind so harsh and stern, but the sweetness and harmony of music will move and tickle; nor any soul so skittish and stubborne, that has not a feeling of some reverence in considering the clowdy vastitie and gloomie canapies of our churches, the eye-pleasing diversitie of ornaments, and orderly order of our ceremonies, and hearing the devout and religious sound of our organs, the moderate, symphonicall, and heavenly harmonie of our voices: even those that enter into them with an obstinate will and contemning mind have in their hearts a feeling of remorse, of chilnesse and horrour, that puts them into a certain diffidence of their former opinions. As for me, I distrust mine own strength to hear with a settled mind some of Horace or Catullus verses sung with a sufficiently well tuned voice, uttered by and proceeding from a fair, yong, and hart- alluring mouth. And Zeno had reason to say that the voice was the flower of beautie. Some have gone about to make me believe that a man, who most of us French men know, in repeating of certain verses he had maide, had imposed upon me that they were not such in writing as in the aire, and that mine eyes would judge of them otherwise than mine ears: so much credit has pronounciation to give price and fashion to those workes that pass at her mercy; whereupon Philoxenus was not to be blamed, when hearing one to give an ill accent to some composition of his, he took in a rage some of his pots or bricks, and breaking them, trode and trampled them under his feet, saying unto him, ’I breake and trample what is thine, even as you manglest and marrest what is mine.’ Wherefore did they (who with an undanted resolve have procured their own death, because they would not see the blow or stroke coming) turn their face away? And those who for their health’s sake cause themselves to be cut and cauterized, why cannot they endure the sight of the preparations, tooles, instruments and workes of the Chirurgion, since the sight can have no part of the pain or smart? Are not these fit examples to verifie the authority which senses have over discourse? We may long enough know that such a ones lockes or flaring tresses are borrowed of a page or taken from some lacky, that this fair ruby-red came from Spain, and this whitenes or smoothnes from the ocean sea: yet must sight force us to find and deem the subject more lovely and more pleasing against all reason. For in that there is nothing of its own. Auferimur cultu: gemnis, auroque teguntur Crimina, pars minima est ipsa puelia sui. Sæpe ubi sit quod ames inter tam multa requiras: Decepit hac oculos Ægide dives amor. -- Ovid. Rem. Am. i. 343. We are misse-led by ornaments: what is amisse Gold and gemmes cover, least part of herself the maiden is, ’ Mongst things so many you may aske, where your love lies, Rich love by this Gorgonian shield deceives thine eye. How much do Poets ascribe unto the virtue of the senses which makes Narcissus to have even fondly lost himself for the love of his shadow ? Cunctaque miratur, quibus est mirabilis ipsa, Se cupit imprudens, et qui probat, ipse probatur, Dumque petit petitur: pariterque accendit et ardit. -- Ovid. metam. iii. 424. He all admires, whereby himself is is admirable, Fond he, fond of himseife, to himself amiable, He that does like, is lik’d, and while he does desire: He is desired, at once he burnes and sets on fire. And Pygmalions wit’s so troubled by the impression of the sight of his ivory statue that he loves and serves it as if it had life: Oscula dat, reddique putat, sequiturque, tenetque Et credit tactis digitos insidere membris, Et metuit pressos veniat ne livor in artus. -- Ovid. Ibid. x. 256. He kisses, and thinks kisses come again, He sues, pursues, and holds, beleeves in vain His fingers sinke where he does touch the place, And feares least black and blew touched-lims deface. Let a Philosopher be put in a cage made of small and thin-set iron wire, and hanged on the top of our Ladies Church steeple in Paris; he shall, by evident reason, perceive that it is impossible he should fall down out of it: yet can he not choose (except he have been brought up to the trade of tilers or thatchers) but the sight of that exceeding height must needs dazle his sight, and amaze or turn his senses. For we have much ado to warrant our selves in the walks or battlements of a high tower or steeple, if they be hattlemented and wrought with pillars, and somewhat wide one from another, although of stone and never so strong. Nay, some there are that call scarcely think or hear of such heights. Let a beame or planke be laid acrosse from one of those two steeples to the other, as big, as thick, as strong, and as broad as would suffice any man to walke safely upon it, there is no philosophicall wisdom of so great resolution and constancy that is able to encourage and persuade us to march upon it, as we would were it below on the ground. I have sometimes made trial of it upon our mountaines on this side of Italie, yet am I one of those that will not easily be affrighted with such things, and I could not without horror to my mind and trembling of legs and thighes endure to looke on those infinite precipices and steepy down-fals, though I were not near the brim, nor any danger within my length and more; and unless I had willingly gone to the perill, I could not possibly have falne. Where I also noted that how deep soever the bottome were, if but a tree, a shrub, or any out-butting crag of a rock presented itself unto our eyes upon those steepe and high Alpes, somewhat to uphold the sight; and divide the same, it does somewhat ease and assure us from fear, as if it were a thing which in our fall might either helpe or upheld us: and that we cannot without some dread and giddinesse in the head so much as abide to looke upon one of those even and down-right precipices: Vt despici sine vertigine simul oculorum animique non possit:’So as they cannot looke down without giddinesse both of eyes and mindes:’ which is an evident deception of the sight. Therefore was it that a worthy Philosopher pulled out his eyes that so he might discharge his soul of the seducing and diverting he received by them, and the better and more freely apply himself unto Philosophy. But by this accompt, he should also have stopped his ears, which (as Theophrastus said) are the most dangerous instruments we have to receive violent and sodaine impressions to trouble and alter us, and should in the end have deprived himself of all his other senses; that is to say, both of his being and life. For they have the power to command our discourses and sway our mind: Fit etiam sæpe specie quadam, sæpe vocum gravitate et cantibus, vt pellantur animi vehementius: sæpe etiam cura et timore: (Cic. Divin. i.) It comes to pass that many times our mindes are much moved with some shadow, many times with deep sounding or singing of voices, many times with care and fear. Physitians hold that there are certain complexions which by some sounds and instruments are agitated even unto fury. I have seen some who, without infringing their patience, could not well hear a bone gnawne under their table: and we see few men but are much troubled at that sharpe, harsh, and teeth-edging noise that smiths make in filing of brasse, or scraping of iron and steele together: others will be offended if they but hear one chew his meat somewhat aloud; nay, some will be angrie with or hate a man that either speaks in the nose or rattles in the throat. That piping prompter of Gracchus, who mollified, raised, and wound his masters voice whilst he was making orations at Rome; what good did he if the motion and quality of the sound had not the force to move and efficacy to alter the auditories judgement: Verily there is great cause to make so much ado, and keep such a coyle about the constancy and firmnesse of this goodly piece, which suffers itself to be handled, changed, and turned by the motion and accident of so light a winde. The very same cheating and cozening that senses bring to our understanding, themselves receive it in their turnes. Our mind does likewise take revenge of it, they lie, they cog, and deceive one another a vie. What we see and hear, being passionately transported by anger, we neither see nor hear it as it is. Et solem geminum, et duplices se ostendere Thebas. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 470. That two Sunnes do appeare, And double Thebes are there. The object which we love seems much more fairer unto us then it is: Multimodis igitur pravos turpesque videmus Esse in delitiis, summoque in honore vigere: --Lucr. iv. 1147. We there fore see that those, who many waies are bad, And fowle, are yet belov’d, and in chief honor had; and that much fowler which we loath. To a pensive and heart-grieved man a clear day seems gloomie and duskie. Our senses are not only altered but many times dulled, by the passions of the mind. How many things see we, which we perceive not, if our mind be either busied or distracted elsewhere? -----in rebus quoque apertis noscere possis, Si non advertas animum, proinde esse, quasi omni Tempore semotæ fuerint, longeque remotæ. -- Ibid. 808. Ev’n in things manifest it may be seen, If you marke not, they are, as they had been At all times sever’d far, remooved cleane. The soul seems to retire herself into the inmost parts, and ammuseth the senses faculties: so that both the inward and outward parts of man are full of weaknes and falshood. Those which have compared our life unto a dreame, have happily had more reason so to do then they were aware. When we dreame, our soul liveth, worketh and exerciseth all her faculties, even and as much as when it waketh; and if more softly and obscurely, yet verily not so, as that it may admit so great a difference as there is betweene a dark night and a clear day: indeed as betweene a night and a shadow: there it sleepeth, here it slumbreth: more or less they are ever darknesses, indeed Cimmerian darknesses. We wake sleeping, and sleep waking. In my sleep I see not so clear; yet can I never find my waking clear enough, or without dimnesse. Sleepe also, in his deepest rest, does sometimes bring dreames asleepe: but our waking is never so vigilant as it may clearely purge and dissipate the ravings or idle phantasies which are the dreames of the waking, and worse then dreames. Our reason and soul, receiving the phantasies and opinions, which sleeping seize on them, and authorising our dreames actions, with like approbation, as it does the days, why make we not a doubt whether our thinking and our working be another dreaming, and our waking some kind of sleeping? If the senses be our first judges, it is not ours that must only be called to counsell: for, in this facultie, beasts have as much (or more) right as we. It is most certain that some have their hearing more sharpe than man; others their sight; others their smelling; others their feeling, or taste. Democritus said that Gods and beasts had the sensitive faculties much more perfect than man. Now, betweene the effects of their senses and ours the difference is extreme. Our spettle cleanseth and drieth our sores, and killeth serpents. Tantaque in his rebus distantia differitasque est, Ut quod alus cibus est, aliis fuat acre venenum. Sæpe etenim serpens, hominis contacta saliva, Disperit, ac sese mandendo conficit ipsa. -- Lucr. iv. 640. There is such distance, and such difference in these things, As what to one is meate, t’another poison brings. For oft a Serpent touched with spettle of a man Does die, and gnaw itself with fretting all he can. What quality shall we give unto spettle, either according to us or according to the serpent? by which two senses shall we verifie its true essence, which we seek for? Pliny says that there are certain Seahares in India that to us are poison, and we bane to them; so that we die if we but touch them; now whether is man or the Sea-hare poison? Whom shall we believe, either the fish of man or the man of fish? Some quality of the air infecteth man which nothing at all hurteth the one: some other the oxe, and not man: which of the two is, either in truth or nature, the pestilent quality? Such as are troubled with the yellow jandise deem all things they looke upon to be yellowish, which seem more pale and wan to them then to us. Lurida præterea fiunt quæcunque tuentur Arquati. -- Ibid. 333. And all that jaundis’d men behold, They yellow straight or palish hold. Those which are sicke of the disease which phisitians call Hyposphagma, which is a suffusion of blood under the skin, imagine that all things they see are bloody and red. Those humors that so change the sights operation, what know we whether they are predominant and ordinary in beasts? For we see some whose eyes are as yellow as theirs that have the jandise, others that have them all blood-shotten with rednesse: it is likely that the objects collour they looke upon seems otherwise to them then to us: which of the two judgements shall be true? For it is not said that the essence of things has reference to man alone. Hardnesse, whiteness, depth, and sharpnesse touch the service and concerne the knowledge of beasts as well as ours: Nature has given the use of them to them as well as to us. When we winke a little with our eye, we perceive the bodies we looke upon to seem longer and outstretched. Many beasts have their eye as winking as we. This length is then happily the true form of that body, and not that which our eyes give it, being in their ordinary seate. If we close our eye above, things seem double unto us. Bina lucernarum flo rentia lumina flammis Et duplices hominum facies, et corpora bina. --Ibid. iii. 728. The lights of candles double flaming then; And faces twaine, and bodies twaine of men If our ears chance to be hindred by any thing, or that the passage of our hearing be stopt, we receive the sound otherwise then we were ordinarily wont. Such beasts as have hairie ears, or that in lieu of an eare have but a little hole, do not by consequence hear that we hear, and receive the sound other then it is. We see at solemn shewes or in theatres that, opposing any collourd glasse betweene our eyes and the torches light, whatsoever is in the roome seems or greene, or yellow, or red unto us, according to the collour of the glasse: Et vulgo faciunt id lutea russaque vela, Et ferruginea, cum magnis intenta theatris Per malos volgata trabesque trementia pendent, Namque ibi consessum caveat subter, et omnem Scenai speciem, patrum matrumque deorumque Inficiunt coguntque suo fluitare colore. -- Ibid. 73. And yellow, russet, rustic curtained work this feate In common sights abroade, where over skaffold great Stretched on masts, spred over beames, they hang still waving. All the seates circuit there, and all the stages braving, Of fathers, mothers, Gods, and all the circle showe They double-dye and in their colours make to flowe. It is likely that those beasts eyes which we see to be of diverse collours, produce the apparances of those bodies they looke upon to be like their eyes. To judge the senses operation, it were then necessary we were first agreed with beasts, and then betweene our selves; which we are not, that ever-and-anon disputing about that one seeth, heareth, or tasteth something to be other then indeed it is; and contend as much as about any thing else, of the diversity of those images our senses report unto us. A yong child heareth, seeth, and tasteth otherwise, by natures ordinary rule, then a man of thirty years; and he otherwise then another of threescore. The senses are to some more obscure and dimme, and to some more open and quick. We receive things differently, according as they are and seem unto us. Things being then so uncertaine and full of controversie, it is no longer a wonder if it be told us that we may avouch snow to seem white unto us; but to affirme that it’s such in essence and in truth, we cannot warrant ourselves: which foundation being so shaken, all the science in the world must necessarily go to wracke. What, do our senses themselves hinder one another? To the sight a picture seems to be raised aloft, and in the handling flat: shall we say that muske is so pleasing or no, which comforteth our smelling and offendeth our taste? There are hearbs and ointments which to some parts of the body are good, and to other some hurtful. Honie is pleasing to the taste, but unpleasing to the sight. Those jewels wrought and fashioned like feathers or sprigs, which in impreses are called feathers without ends, no eye can discerne the bredth of them, and no man warrant himself from this deception, that on the one end or side it groweth not broder and broder, sharper and sharper, and on the other more and more narrow, especially being rouled about ones finger, when notwithstanding in handling it seems equal in bredth, and every where likewise. Those who to encrease and aide their luxury were anciently wont to use perspective or looking glasses, fit to make the object they represented appeare very big and great, that so the members they were to use might, by that ocular increase, please them the more: to whether of the two senses yielded they, either to the sight presenting those members as big and great as they wisht them, or to the feeling that presented them little and to be disdained? Is it our senses that lend these diverse conditions unto subjects, when for all that the subjects have but one? as we see in the Bread we eat: it is but Bread, but one using it, it maketh bones, blood, flesh, hair, and nailes thereof: Ut cibus in membra atque artus cum diditur omnes Disperit, atque aliam naturam sufficit ex se. -- Ibid. iii. 728. As meate distributed into the members, dies, Another nature yet it perishing supplies. The moistnesse which the roote of a tree suckes becomes a trunke, a leafe, and fruite: And the aire being but one, applied unto a trumpet, becommoth diverse in a thousand sorts of sounds. Is it our senses (say I) who likewise fashion of diverse qualities those subjects, or whether they have them so and such? And upon this doubt, what may we conclude of their true essence? Moreover, since the accidents of sicknesse, of madnesse, or of sleepe, make things appeare other unto us then they seem un to the healthy, unto the wise, and to the waking: is it not likely that our right seate and natural humors have also wherewith to give a being unto things, having reference unto their condition, and to appropriate them to itself, as do inordinate humors; and our health as capable to give them his visage as sicknesse? Why has not the temperate man some form of the objects relative unto himself as the intemperate: and shall not he likewise imprint his character in them? The distasted impute wallowishnes unto wine: the healthier good taste; and the thirsty, brisknesse, rellish, and dellicacie. Now our condition appropriating things unto itself, and transforming them to its own humor: we know no more how things are in sooth and truth; for nothing comes unto us but falsified and altered by our senses. Where the compasses, the quadrant, or the ruler are crooked, all proportions drawne by them, and all the buildings erected by their measure, are also necessarily defective and imperf ect. The uncertaintie of our senses yields what ever they produce, also uncertaine. Denique ut in fabrica, si prava est regula prima, Normaque si fallax rectis regionibus exit, Et libella aliqua si ex parte claudicat hilum, Omnia mendose fieri, atque obstipa necessum Prava, cubantia, prona, supina, atque absona tecta, Iam ruere ut quædam videantur velle, ruantque Prodita judiciis fallacibus omnia primis. Hic igitur ratio tibi rerum prava necesse est, Falsaque sit falsis quæcunque a sensibus orta est. -- Ibid. iv. 514. As in building if the first rule be to blame, And the deceitful squire erre from right forms and frame, If any instrument want any jot of weight, All must needs faultie be, and stooping in their height, The building naught, absurd, upward and downeward bended, As if they meant to fall, and fall, as they intended; And all this as betrayde By judgements formost laid. Of things the reason therefore needs must faultie be And false, which from false senses draws its pedigree. As for the rest, who shall be a competent Judge in these differences? As we said in controversies of religion, that we must have a judge inclined to either party, and free from partialitie, or affection, which is hardly to be had among Christians; so happens it in this: For if he be old he cannot judge of ages sense, himself being a party in this controversie: and so if he be yong, healthy, sicke, sleeping, or waking, it is all one: We had need of some body void and exempted from all these qualities, that without any preoccupation of judgement might judge of these propositions as indifferent unto him: by which accompt we should have a judge that were no man. To judge of the apparances that we receive of subjects, we had need have a judicatorie instrument: to verifie this instrument we should have demonstration; and to approve demonstration, an instrument; thus are we ever turning round. Since the senses cannot determine our disputation, themselves being so full of uncertainty, it must then be reason: and no reason can be astiblished without another reason: then are we ever going backe unto infinity. Our phantasie does not apply itself to strange things, but is rather conceived by the interposition of senses; and senses cannot comprehend a strange subject; nay, not so much as their own passions: and so, nor the phantasie, nor the apparence is the subject’s, but rathier the passion’s only, and sufferance of the sense: which passion and subject are diverse things: Therefore, who judgeth by apparences, judgeth by a thing different from the subject. And to say that the senses’ passions refer the quality of strange subjects by resemblance unto the soul: How can the soul and the understanding rest assured of that resemblance, having of itself no commerce with forraigne subjects? Even as he that knowes not Socrates, seeing his picture, cannot say that it resembleth him. And would a man judge by apparences, be it by all it is impossible; for by their contraries and differences they hinder one another, as we see by experience. May it be that some choice apparences rule and direct the others? This choice must be verified by another choice, the second by a third: and so shal we never make an end. In few, there is no constant existence, neither of our being, nor of the objects. And we and our judgement and all mortal things else do uncessantly rowle, turns and pass away. Thus can nothing be certainely established, nor of the one nor of the other; both the judgeing and the judged being in continuall alteration and motion. We have no communication with being; for every humane nature is ever in the middle betwee ne being borne and dying; giving nothing of itself but an obscure apparence and shadow, and an uncertaine and weake opinion. And if perhaps you fix your thought to take its being, it would be even as if one should go about to graspe the water: for, how much the more he shal close and press that which by its own nature is ever gliding, so much the more he shall loose what he would hold and fasten. Thus, seeing all things are subject to pass from one change to another, reason, which therein seeketh a reall subsistence, findes herself deceived as unable to apprehend any thing subsistent and permanent: forasmuch as each thing either commeth to a being, and is not yet altogether: or beginneth to dy before it be borne. Plato said that bodies had never an existence but indeed a birth, supposing that Homer made the Ocean Father, and Thetis Mother of the Gods, thereby to show us that all things are in continuall motion, change and variat ion. As he sayeth, a common opinion amongst all the Philosophers before his time, only Parmenides excepted, who denied any motion to be in things of whose power he maketh no small accompt. Pythagoras that each thing or matter was ever gliding and labile. The Stoics affirme there is no present time, and that which we call present is but conjoyning and assembling of future time and past. Heraclitus avereth that no man ever entered twice one same river; Epicharmus avoucheth that who ere while borrowed any money does not now owe it; and that he who yesternight was bidden to dinner this day, commeth to day unbidden: since they are no more themselves, but are become others; and that one mortal substance could not twise be found in one self estate: for by the sodainesse and lightness of change sometimes it wasteth, and other times it assembleth; now it comes and now it goes; in some sort, that he who beginneth to be borne never comes to the perfection of being. For, this being borne commeth never to an end, nor ever stayeth as being at an end; but after the seed proceedeth continually in change and alteration from one to another. As of mans seed there is first made a shapelesse fruit in the Mothers Wombe, then a shapen Childe, then being out of the Wombe, a sucking babe, afterward he becometh a ladde, then consequently a stripling, then a full grown man, then an old man, and in the end an aged decrepite man. So that age and subsequent generation goeth ever undoing and wasting the precedent. Mutat enim mundi naturam totius ætas, Ex alioque alius status excipere omnia debet, Nec manet vlla sui similis res, omnia migrant, Omnia commutat natura et vertere cogit. -- Ibid. v. 837. Of th’universall world, age does the nature change, And all things from one state must to another range, No one thing like itself remaines, all things do pass, Nature does change, and drive to change, each thing that was. And then we do foolishly fear a kind of death, whenas we have already past and dayly pass to many others; for, not only (as Heraclitus said) the death of fire is a generation of air: and the death of air a generation of water: but also we may most evidently see it in ourselves. The flower of age dieth, fadeth and fleeteth, when age comes upon us, and youth endeth in the flower of a full grown mans age: childhood in youth and the first age dieth in infancie: and yesterday endeth in this day, and to day shall die in to morrow. And nothing remaineth or ever continueth in one state. For to prove it, if we should ever continue one and the same, how is it then that now we rejoice at one thing, and now at another? How comes it to pass we love things contrary, or we bath them, or we love them, or we blame them? How is it that we have different affections holding no more the same sense in the same thought? For it is not likely that without alteration we should take other passions, and what admitteth alterations continueth not the same; and if it be not one self same, then it is not: but rather with being all one, the simple being does also change, ever becoming other from other. And by consequence Natures senses are deceived and lie falsly; taking what appeareth for what is, for want of truly knowing what it is that is. But then what is it that is indeed? That which is eternall, that is to say, that which ne ver had birth, nor ever shall have end; and to which no time can bring change or cause alteration. For time is a fleeting thing, and which appeareth as in a shadow, with the matter ever gliding, alwaies fluent without ever being stable or permanent; to whom rightly belong these termes, Before and After, and it Hath been, or Shall be. Which at first sight does manifestly show that it is not a thing which is: for it were great sottishnesse and apparent falsehood, to say that that is which is not yet in being, or that already has ceased from being. And concerning these words, Present, Instant, Even now, by which it seems that especially we uphold and principally ground the intelligence of time; reason discovering the same does forthwith destroy it: for presently it severeth it asunder and divideth it into future and past times as willing to see it necessarily parted in two. As much happens unto nature which is measured according unto time, which measureth her: for no more is there any thing in her that remaineth or is subsistent; rather all things in her are either borne or ready to be borne or dying. By means whereof it were a sinne to say of God, who is the only that is, that he was or shall be: for these words are declinations, passages, or vicissitudes of that which cannot last nor continue in being. Wherefore we must conclude, that only God is, not according to any measure of time, but according to an immoveable and immutable eternity, not measured by time nor subject to any declination, before whom nothing is, nor nothing shall be after, nor more new nor more recent, but one really being: which by one only Now or Present, filleth the Ever, and there is nothing that truly is but he alone: without saying he has bin or he shall be, without beginning and sans ending. To this so religious conclusion of a heathen man I will only add this word, taken from a testimony of the same condition, for an end of this long and tedious discourse, which might well furnish me with endlesse matter. ’Oh, what a vile and abject thing is man (says he) unless he raise himself above humanity!’ Observe here a notable speech and a profitable desire; but likewise absurd. For to make the handfull greater than the hand, and the embraced greater than the arm, and to hope to straddle more than our legs length, is impossible and monstrous: nor that man should mount over and above himself or humanity; for he cannot see but with his own eyes, nor take hold but with his own arms. He shall raise himself up, if it please God to lend him his helping hand. He may elevate himself by forsaking and renouncing his own means, and suffering himself to be elevated and raised by meere heavenly means. It is for our Christian faith, not for his Stoice virtue, to pretend or aspire to this divine Metamorphosis, or miraculous transmutation. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XIII: OF JUDGING OF OTHERS’ DEATH CHAPTER XIII: OF JUDGING OF OTHERS’ DEATH HEN WE judge of others assurance or boldness in death, which without all perhaps is the most remarkeable action of humane life, great heed is to be taken of one thing, which is, that a man will hardly believe he is come to that point. Few men die with a resolution that it is their last hour: and nowhere does hopes deceit ammuse us more. She never ceaseth to ring in our ears that others have been sicker and yet have not died: the cause is not so desperate as it is taken; and if the worst happen, God has done greater wonders. The reason is, that we make too much account of ourselves, It seems that the generality of things does in some sort suffer for our annullation and takes compassion of our state. Forasmuch as our sight, being altered, represents unto itself things likewise; and we imagine that things faile it as it does to them: As they who travell by sea, to whom mountaines, fields, townes, heaven and earth, seem to go the same motion, and keep the same course they do: Provehimur portu, terræque vrbesque recedunt. -- Virg. Æn. iii. 72. We sayling launch from harbour, and Behinde our backes leave townes, leave land. Who ever saw old age that commended not times past, and blamed not the present, charging the world and mens customs with her misery and lowring discontent? Iamque caput quassans grandis suspirat arator, Et cum tempora temporibus prmsentia confert Præteritis, laudat fortitnas sæpe parentis Et crepat antiquum genus ut pietas repletum. -- Lucr. ii. 113. The gray-beard Plow-man sighes, shaking his hoarie head, Compares times that are now with times past heretofore. Praises the fortunes of his father long since dead, And crackes of ancient men, whose honesty was more. We entertaine and carry all with us: Whence it followeth that we deem our death to be some great ma tter, and which passeth not so easily, nor without a solemn consultation of the Starres; Tot circa unum caput tumultuantes Deos: ’So many Gods keeping a stir about one mans life.’ And so much the more we think it, by how much the more we praise ourselves. What? should so much learning and knowledge be lost with so great dammage, without the Destinies particular care? A soul so rare and exemplar, costs it no more to be killed than a popular and unprofitable soul? This life that covereth so many others, of whom so many other lives depend, that for his use possesseth so great a part of the world and filleth so many places, is it displaced as that which holdeth by its own simple string? No man of us thinkes it sufficient to be but one. Thence came those words of Cæsar to his pilot, more proudly swolne than the sea that threatned him: ------Italiam si, cælo authore, recusas, Me pete: sola tibi causa hæc est iusta timoris, Vectorem non nosse tuum; perrumpe procellas Tutem secure mei. -- Lucan. iii. 579. If Italie you do refuse with heaven your guide, Turn you to me: to you only just cause of fear Is that your passenger you know’st not: stormie tide Breake through, secure by guard of me, whom you do bear. And these: -----credit jam digna pericula Cæsar Fatis esse suis: tantusque evertere (dixi) Me superis labor est, parvi quem puppe sedentem. Tam magno petiere mari. -- Ibid. 653. Cæsar does now believe those dangers worthie are Of his set fate; and saies, do Gods take so much pain Me to undoe, whom they thus to assault prepare Set in so small a skiffe, in such a surging main? And this common foppery that Phoebus for one whole yeare bare mourning weedes on his forehead for the death of him: Ille etiam extincto miseratus Cæsare Romam, Cum caput obscura nitidum ferrugine texit. -- Virg. Geor. i. 466. The Sunne did pity take of Rome when Cæsar dide, When he his radiant head in obscure rust did hide. And a thousand such wherewith the world suffers itself to be so easily conicatcht, deeming that our own interests disturbe heaven, and his infinitie is moved at our least actions. Non tanta cælo societas nobiscum est, ut nostro fato mortalis sit il le quoque siderum fulgar: (Plin. nat. hist. ii. c. 8.) ’There is no such societie betweene heaven and us, that by our destinie the shining of the starres should be mortal as we are.’ And to judge a resolution and constancy in him, who though he be in manifest danger, does not yet believe it, it is no reason; and it sufficeth not that he die in that ward, unless he have directly and for that purpose put himself into it: it happens that most men set a stern countenance on the matter, looke big, and speak stoutly, there by to acquire reputation, which, if they chance to live, they hope to enjoy. Of all I have seen die, fortune has disposed their countenances, but not their desseignes. And of those which in ancient times have put themselves to death, the choice is great, whether it were a sodaine death or a death having time and leisure. That cruel Roman Emperor said of his prisoners that he would make them feel death; and if any fortuned to kill himself in prison, that fellow had escaped me (would he say). He would extend and linger death, and cause it be felt by torments. Vidimus et toto quamvis in corpore cæso, Nil anima, lethale datum, moremque nefanda, Durum sævitiæ, pereuntis parcere morti. -- Lucan. ii. 179. And we have seen, when all the body tortur’d lay, Yet no stroke deadly giv’n, and that in humane way Of tyranny, to spare his death that sought to die. Verily, it is not so great a matter, being in perfect health and well setled in mind, for one to resolve to kill himself: It is an easy thing to show stoutness and play the wag before one come to the pinch. So that Heliogabalus, the most dissolute man of the world, amidst his most riotous sensualities, intended, whensoever occasion should force him to it, to have a daintie death. Which, that it might not degenerate from the rest of his life, he had purposely caused a stately towre to be built, the nether part and forecourt whereof was floored with boards richly set and enchased with gold and precious stones, from off which he might headlong throw himself down: He had also caused cordes to be made of gold and crimson silke, therewith to strangle himself; and a rich golden rapier to thrust himself through, and kept poison in boxes of Emeraldes and Topases, to poison himself with, according to the humor he might have, to chuse which of these deaths should please him. Impiger et fortis virtute coacta. -- iv. 797. Gurio. A ready minded gallant, And in forst vallour valiant. Notwithstanding, touching this man, the wantonnesse of his preparation makes it more likely that he would have fainted had he been put to his trial. But even of those who most undantedly have resolved themselves to the execution, we must consider (I say) whether it were with a life ending stroke, and that took away any leisure to feel the effect thereof. For it is hard to guesse seeing life droope away little by little, the bodies- feeling entermingling itself with the soules, means of repentance being offered, whether in so dangerous an intent, constancy or obstancie were found in him. In Cæsars civill wars, Lucius Dominus taken in Prussia, having empoysoned himself, did afterwards rue and repent his deede. It has hapned in our days that some having resolved to die, and at first not stricken deepe enough, the smarting of his flesh, thrusting his arm backe, twice or thrice more wounded himself, anew, and yet could never stricke sufficiently deepe. Whilst the arraignment of Plantius Silvanus was preparing, Vrgulania, his grandfather, sent him a poignard, wherewith, not able to kill himself thoroughly, he caused his own servants to cut his veines. Albucilla, in Tiberius time, purposing to kill herself, but striking over faintly, gave her enemies leisure to apprehend and imprison her, and appoint her what death they pleased. So did Captain Demosthenes after his discomfiture in Sicilie. And C. Fimbria having over-feeblie wounded himself, became a sutor to his boy to make an end of him. On the other side, Ostorius, who forasmuch as he could not use his own arm, disdained to employ his servants in any other thing but to hold his dagger stiffe and strongly; and taking his running, himself carried his throate to its point, and so was thrust through. To say truth, it is a meate a man must swallow without chewing, unless his throat be frostshod. And therefore Adrianus the emperour made his Physitian to marke and take the just compasse of the mortal place about his pap, that so his aime might not faile him, to whom he had given charge to kill him. See why Cæsar being demanded, which was the death he most allowed, answered, ’The least premeditated, and the shortest.’ If Cæsar said it, it is no faintness in me to believe it. A short death (says Plinie) is the chief happe of humane life. It grieveth them to acknowledge it. No man can be said to be resolved to die that feareth to purchase it, and that cannot abide to looke upon and out-stare it with open eyes. Those which in times of execution are seen to run to their end, and hasten the execution, do it not with resolution, but because they will take away time to consider the same; it grieves them not to be dead, but to die. Emori nolo, sed me esse mortuum, nihil æstimo. -- Cic. Tusc. Qu. i Epicha. I would not die too soone, But care not, when ’tis done. It is a degree of constancy unto which I have experienced to arive, as those that cast themselves into danger, or into the sea, with closed eyes. In mine opinion there is nothing more worthy the noting in Socrates life, then to have had thirty whole days to ruminate his deaths decree, to have digested it all that while, with an assured hope, without dismay or alteration, and with a course of actions and words rather supprest, and loose-hanging, then out-stretched and raised by the weight of such a cogitation. That Pomponius Atticus, to whom Cicero writeth, being sicke, caused Agrippa, his son in lawe, and two or three of his other friends, to be called for, to whom he said, that having assaid how he got nothing in going about to be cured, and what he did to prolong his life did also lengthen and augment his grief, he was now determined to make an end of one and other; intreating them to allow of his determination, and that by no means they would lose their labor to diswade him from it. And having chosen to end his life by abstinence, his sicknesse was cured by accident. The remedy he had employed to make himself away brought him to health again. The Physitians and his friends, glad of so happy a success and rejoycing thereof with him, were in the end greatly deceived; for, with all they could do, they were never able to make him alter his former opinions saying that as he must one day pass that careire, and being now so forward, he would remove the care another time to beginne again. This man having with great leisure apprehended death, is not only no whit discouraged when he comes to front it, but resolutely falls upon it for being satisfied of that for which he was entered the combate, in a braverie he thrust himself into it, to see the end of it. It is far from fearing death to go about to taste and savour the same. The historie of Cleanthes, the Philosopher, is much like to this. His gummes being swolne, his Physitians persuaded him to use great abstinence. Having fasted two days, he was so well amended, as they told him he was well, and might return to his wonted course of life. He contrarily having already tasted some sweetnes in this Painting, resolveth not to drawe back, but to finish what he had so well begunne, and was so far waded into. Tullius Marcellinus, a yong Roman gentleman, willing to prevent the hour of his destiny, to ridde himself of a disease which tormented him more than he would endure, although Physitians promised certainely to cure him, howbeit not sodainely: called his friends unto him to determine about it: some (says Seneca) gave him that counsell, which for weaknesse of heart themselves would have taken; others for flatteries that which they imagined would be most pleasing unto him but a certain Stoike standing by, said thus unto him: ’Toile not your self, Marcellinus, as if you determinedst some weightie matter: to live is no such great thing, your base groomes and bruit beasts live also, but it is a matter of consequence to die honestly, wisely and constantly. Remember how long it is; you doest one same thing, to eate, to drinke, and sleepe; to drinke, to sleepe, to eate. We are ever uncessantly wheeling in this endlesse circle. Not only bad and intolerable accidents, but the very satiety to live, brings a desire of death.’ Marcellinus had no need of a man to counsell, but of one to helpe him: his servants were afraid to meddle with him; but this Philosopher made them to understand that familiars are suspected only when the question is, whether the maisters death has been voluntary: otherwise it would be as bad an example to hinder him as to kill him, forasmuch as, Inuitum qui servat, idemfacit occidenti. -- Hor. Art. Poet. 467. Who saves a man against his will Does ev’n as much as he should kill. Then he advertised Marcellinus, that it would not be unseemely, as fruit or comfets at our tables, when our bellies be full, are given unto bystanders, so, the life ended, to distribute something to such as have been the ministers of it. Marcellinus being of a frank and liberal disposition, caused certain summes of mony to be divided amongst his servants, and comforted them. And for the rest there needed neither yron nor blood; he undertook to departe from this life, not by running from it: not to escape from death, but to taste it. And to have leisure to conditione or bargaine with death having quit all manner of nourishment, the third day ensuing, after he had caused himself to be sprinkled over with luke-warme water, by little and little he consumed away; and (as he said) not without some voluptuousness and pleasure. Verily, such as have had these faintings and swownings of the heart, which proceed from weaknesses say that they feel no pain at all in them, but rather some pleasure, as of a passage to sleepe and rest. These are premeditated and digested deaths. But that Cato alone, may serve to all examples of virtue, it seems his good destiny caused that hand wherewith he gave himself the fatall blow to be sicke and sore: that so be might have leisure to affront death and to embrace it, reenforcing his courage in that danger in lieu of mollifieing the same. And should I have represented him in his proudest state, it should have been all bloody-gored, tearing his entraile, and rending his gutts, rather then with a sword in his hand, as did the statuaries of his time. For this second murther, was much more furious then the first. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XIV: HOW THAT OUR SPIRIT HINDERETH ITSELFE CHAPTER XIV: HOW THAT OUR SPIRIT HINDERETH ITSELFE T IS a pleasant imagination to conceive a spirit iustly ballanced betweene two equall desires. For, it is not to be doubted, that he shall never be reso lved upon any match: forasmuch as the application and choise brings all the inequality of prise: And who should place us betweene a bottle of wine and a gammon of bacon, with an equall appetite to eat and drinke, doubtlesse there were noe remedy, but to die of thirst and of hunger. To provide against this inconvenient, when the Stoics were demanded whence the election of two indifferent things commeth into our soul (and which causeth that from out a great number of Crownes or Angells we rather take one then another, when there is no reason to induce us to prefer any one before others) they answer, that this motion of the soul is extraorainarie and irregular coming into us by a strange, accidentall and casual impulsion. In my opinion, it might rather be said that nothing is presented unto us, wherein there is not some difference, how light so ever it be: And that either to the sight, or to the feeling, there is ever some choice, which tempteth and draws us to it, though imperceptib e and not to be distinguished. In like manner, he that shall presuppose a twine-thrid equally strong all through, it is impossible by all possibility that it should break, for, where would you have the flaw or breaking to beginne? And at once to break in all places together is not in nature. The Geometricall propositions which, by the certainty of their demonstrations, conclude the contained greater then the containing, and the centre as great as his circumference; and that find two lines uncessantly approaching one unto another, which yet can never meete and join together; and the Philosophers stone, and quadrature of the circle, where the reason and the effects are so opposite: might perhaps draw thence some argument to salve and helpe this bold speech of Plinie: Solum certum, nihil esse certi, et homine nihil miserius aut superbius: (1 PLIN. Nat. Hist. 1. ii. 7.) ’This only is sure, that there is nothing sure; and nothing more miserable, and yet more arrogant then man.’ Return to : Book II CHAPTER XV: THAT OUR DESIRES ARE ENCREASED BY DIFFICULTIE CHAPTER XV: THAT OUR DESIRES ARE ENCREASED BY DIFFICULTIE HERE is no reason but has another contrary unto it, says the wisest party of Philosophers. I did erewhile ruminate upon this notable saying, which an ancient writer alleageth for the contempt of life. No good can bring us any pleasure, except that against whole loss we are prepared: In æquo est, dolor amissæ rei, et timor amittendæ:’(Sen. Epist. xcviii.) ’Sorrow for a thing lost, and fear of losing it, are on an even ground.’ Meaning to gain thereby, that the fruition of life cannot perfectly be pleasing unto us, if we stand in any fear to lose it. A man might nevertheless say on the contrary part, that we embrace and claspe this good so much the harder, and with more affection, as we perceive it to be less sure, and fear it should be taken from us. For, it is manifestly found, that as fire is rouzed up by the assistance of cold, even so our will is whetted on by that which does resist it. Si nunquam Danæn habuisset ahenea turis, Non esset Danæ de Iove facta parens --Ovid. Am ii. El. xix. 27. If Danæ had not been clos’d in brazen Tower, Jove had not closed with Danæ in golden shower, And that there is nothing so naturally opposite to our taste as satiety, which comes from ease and facility, nor nothing that so much sharpneth it as rarenesse and difficulty. Omnium rerum voluptas ipso quo debet fugare periculo crescit: ’The delight of all things encreaseth by the danger, whereby it rather should terrify them that affect it.’ Galla nega; satiatur amor, nisi gaudia torquent. -- Mart. iv. Epig. xxxviii. i. Good wench, deny, my love is cloied, Unless joyes grieve, before enjoyed. To keep love in breath and longing, Lycurgus ordained that the maried men of Lacedemonia might never converse with their wives but by stealth, and that it should be as great an imputation and shame to find them laide together, as if they were found living with others. The difficulty of assignations or matches appointed, the danger of being surprised, and the shame of ensuing to-morrow, ------- et languor, et silentium, Et latere petitus imo spiritus. --Hor. Epo. xi. 13. And whispering voice, and languishment, And breath in sighes from deepe sides sent. are the things that give relish and tartnesse to the sawce. How many most lasciviously- pleasant sports proceed from modest and shamefast manner of speech, of the daliances and workes of love? Even voluptuousness seekes to provoke and stir itself up by smarting. It is much sweeter when it itcheth, and endeared when it gauleth. The curtezan Flora was wont to say that she never lay with Pompey but she made him carry away the markes of her teeth. Quod petiere premunt arcte, faciuntque dolorem Corpore, et dentes inlidant sæpe labellis: Et stimuli subsunt, qui instigant lædere id ipsum Quodcumgue est, rabies unde illi germina surgunt, --Lucr. iv. 1070. So goes it every where: rarenesse and difficulty gives esteeme unto things. Those of Marca d’Ancona, in Italy, make their vows, and go on pilgrimage rather unto Iames in Galicia, and those of Galicia rather unto our Lady of Loreto. In the country of Liege they make more account of the Bathes of Luca; and they of Tuscany esteeme the Baths of Spawe more than their own. In Rome the Fence-schooles are ever full of Frenchmen, when few Romans come unto them. Great Cato, as well as any else, was even cloied and distasted with his wife so long as she was his own, but when another mans, then wished he for her, and would faine have lickt his fingers at her. I have heretofore put forth an old stalion to soile, who before did no sooner see or smell a mare but was so lusty that no man could rule him, nor no ground hold him; ease and facilitie to come to his own when he list, has presently quailed his stomacke, and so cloyed him that he is weary of them. But toward strange mares, and the first that passeth by his pasture, there is no hoe with him, but suddenly he returnes to his old wonted neighings and furious heate. Our appetite does contemne and pass over what he has in his free choice and own possession, to run after and pursue what he has not. Transvolat in medio posita, et fugientia captat. -- Hor. Ser. i. Sat. ii. 107 It over flies what open lies, Pursuing only that which flies. To forbid us anything is the ready way to make us long for it. -----nisi tu servare puellam Incipis, incipiet desinere ese mea. -- Ovid. Am. ii. El. xix. 47. If you begin not your wench to enshrine, She will begin to leave off to be mine. And to leave it altogether to our will is but to breede dislike and contempt in us. So that to want and to have store breedeth one self same inconvenience. Tibi quod super est, mihi quod desit, dolet. -- Ter. Phor. act. i.sc. 3. You grieve because you have too much It griev’s me that I have none such. Wishing and enjoying trouble us both likewise. The rigor of a mistris is yrkesome, but ease and facility (to say true) much more; forasmuch as discontent and vexation proceed of the estimation we have of the thing desired, which sharpen love and set it afire. Whereas satiety begets distaste: it is a dull, blunt, weary, and drouzy passion. Si qua volet regnare diu, contemnat amantem. --Ovid. Am. ii. El. xix. 33. If any list long to bear sway, Scorne she her lover, ere she play. -----contemnite amantes, Sic hodie veniet, si qua negavit heri. -- Prop. ii. El. xiv. 19. Lovers your lovers scorne, contemne, delude, deride So will she come to-day, that yesterday denied. Why did Poppea devise to maske the beauties of her face, but to endear them to her lovers? Why are those beauties vailed down to the heels, which all desire to show, which all wish to see? Why do they cover with so many lets, one over another, those parts where chiefly consisteth our pleasure and theirs? And to what purpose serve those baricadoes and verdugalles wherewith our women arm their flankes, but to allure our appetite, and enveagle us to them by putting us off? Et fugit ad salices, et se cupit ante videri. -- Virg. Buco. Ecl. iii. 65. She to the willows runs to hide, Yet gladly would she first be spide, Interdum tunica duxit operta moram. -- Pro. ibid. Eleg. xv. 6. She cover’d with her cote in play, Did sometime make a short delay. Whereto serves this mayden-like bashfulness, this willfull quaintness, this severe countenance, this seeming ignorance of those things which they know better than our selves, that go about to instruct them, but to increase a desire and endeare a longing in us to vanquish, to gourmandize, and at our pleasure to dispose all this squeamish ceremony, and all these peevish obstacles? For, it is not only a delight but a glory to besot and debauch this dainty and nice sweetness, and this infantine bashfullnesse, and to subject a marble and stern gravity to the mercy of our flame. It is a glory (say they) to triumph over modesty, chastity and temperance: and who disswadeth ladies from these parts, betraieth both them and himself. It is to be supposed that their heart yerneth for fear, that the sound of our wordes woundeth the purity of their ears, for which they hate us, and with a forced constraint agree to withstand our importunitie. Beauty with all her might has not wherewith to give a taste of herself without these interpositions. See in Italie, where most, and of the finest beauty is to be sold, how it is forced to seek other strange means, and suttle devices, arts and tricks, to yield herself pleasing and acceptable: and yet in good sooth, do what it can, being venal and common, it remaineth feeble, and even languishing. Even as in virtue of two equall effects, we hold that the fairest and worthiest, wherein are proposed more lets, and which affordeth greater hazards. It is an effect of Gods providence, to suffer his holy Church to be vexed and turmoyled as we see with so many troubles and stormes, to rouze and awaken by this opposition and strife the godly and religious soules, and raise them from out a lethall security and stupified slumber, wherein so long tranquility had plunged them. If we shall counterpoize the loss we have had by the number of those that have strayed out of the right way, and the profit that acrueth unto us, by having taken hart of grace, and by reason of combate raised our zeale and forces; I wot not whether the profit does surmount the loss. We thought to tie the bond of our marriages the faster by removing all means to dissolve them, but by how much faster that of constraint has bin tried, so much more has that of our will and affection bin slacked and loosed: Whereas, on the contrary side, that which so long time held mariages in honor and safety in Rome, was the liberty to break them who list. They kept their wives the better, forasmuch as they might leave them; and when divorces might freely be had, there past five hundred years and more before any would ever make use of them. Quod licet, ingratum est, quod non licet, acrius urit. -- Ovid. Am. ii. El.xix. 3. What we may do, does little please: It woormes us more, that has less ease. To this purpose might the opinion of an ancient writer be adjoined, that torments do rather encourage vices than suppress them; that they beget not a care of well-doing, which is the work of reason and discipline, but only a care not to be surprised in doing evil. Latius excisæ pestis contagia serpunt. Th’ infection of the plague nigh spent And rooted out, yet further went. I wot not whether it be true, but this I know by experience that policy was never found to be reformed that way. The order and regiment of maners dependeth of some ther meane. The Greeke stories make mention of the Agrippians neighbouring upon Scithia, who live without any rod or staffe of offence, where not only no man undertakes to buckle with any other man but whosoever can but save himself, there (by reason of their virtue and sanctity of life) is as it were in a Sanctuary: And no man dares so much as to touch him. Many have recourse to them, to attone and take up quarrels and differences, which arise amongst men else where. There is a nation where the enclosure of gardens and fields they intend keep severall, are made with a seely twine of cotton, which amongst them is found to be more safe and fast than are our ditches and hedges. Furem signata sollicitant, Aperta ffractarius præterit (Sen. Epist. lxix). ’Things sealed up solicite a thief to break them open: Whereas a common burglayer will pass by quietly things that lie open.’ Amongst other means, ease and facility does perhaps cover and fence my house from the violence of civill wares: Inclosure and fencing drawe on the enterprise, and distrust, the offence. I have abated and weakened the soldiers designe by taking hazard and all means of military glory from their exploite, which is wont to serve them, for a title, and stead them for an excuse. What is performed courageously, at what time justice lieth dead, and law has not her due course, is ever done honourably. I yield them the conquest of my house dastardly and treacherous. It is never shut to any that knocketh. It has no other guardian or Provision but a porter, as an ancient custom, and used ceremony, who serveth not so much to defend my gate as to offer it more decently and courteously to all comers. I have nor watch nor sentinell but what the starres keep for me. That gentleman is much to blame who makes a show to stand upon his guards, except he be very strong indeed. Who so is open on one side is so every where. Our fore-fathers never dreamed on building of frontire townes and castles. The means to assaile (I meane without battery and troopes of armed men) and to surprise our houses, encrease daily beyond the means of garding or defending. Mens wits are generally exasperated and whetted on that way. An invasion concerneth all, the defense none but the rich. Mine was sufficiently strong, according to the times when it was made. I have since added nothing unto it that way; and I would fear the strength of it should turn against my self. Seeing a peaceable time will require we shall unfortifie them. It is dangerous not to be able to recover them again, and it is hard for one to be assured of them. For concerning intestine broils, your own servant may be of that faction you stand in fear of. And where religion serveth for a pretence, even alliances and consanguinitie become mistrustful under colour of justice. Common rents cannot entertaine our private garrisons. They should all be consumed. We have not wherewith, nor are we able to do it without our apparent ruine, or more incommodiously and therewithall injuriously without the common peoples destruction. The state of my loss should not be much worse. And if you chance to be a looser, your own friends are readier to accuse your improvidence and unhedinesse than to moan you, and excuse your ignorance and careles enesse concerning the offices belonging to your profession. That so many strongly-garded houses have been lost, whereass mine continueth still, makes me suspect they were overthrowne only because they were so diligently garded. It is that which affoordeth a desire and ministreth a pretence to the assailant. All gards bear a show of war, which if God be so pleased may light upon me. But so it is, I will never call for it. It is my sanctuary or retreate to rest my self from wars. I endeavour to free this corner from the public storme, as I do another corner in my soul. Our war may change form and multiply and diversifie how and as long as it list, but for my self I never stir. Amongst so many barricaded and armed houses, none but my self (as far as I know) of my quality has merely trusted the protection of his unto the heavens: for I never removed neither plate, nor hangings, nor my evidences. I will neither fear nor save my self by halfes. If a full acknowledgement purchaseth the favor of God, it shall last me for ever unto the end: if not, I have continued long enough to make my continuance remarkeable and worthy the registring. What, is not thirty years a goodly time? Return to : Book II CHAPTER XVI: OF GLORY CHAPTER XVI: OF GLORY HERE is both name, and the thing: the name is a voice which noteth and signifieth the thing: the name is neither part of thing nor of substance: it is a stranger-piece joined to the thing and from it. God who in and by himself is all fulnesse, and the type of all perfection, cannot inwardly be augmented or encreased: yet may his name be encreased and augmented by the blessing and praise which we give unto his exteriour workes; which praise and blessing, since we cannot incorporate into him, forasmuch as no accession of good can be had unto him, we ascribe it unto his name, which is a part without him, and the neerest unto him. And that is the reason why glory and honor appertaineth to God only. And there is nothing so repugnant unto reason as for us to go about to purchase any for ourselves: for being inwardly needy and defective, and our essence imperfect and ever wanting amendment, we ought only labor about that. We are all hollow and empty, and it is not with breath and words we should fil ourselves. We have need of a more solid substance to repair ourselves. An hunger starved man might be thought most simple rather to provide himself of a fair garment then of a good meales-meat: we must run to that which most concerneth us. Gloria in excelsis Deo, et in terra pax hominibus. (Luke ii. 14.) ’Glory be to God on high, and peace on earth amongst men,’ as say our ordinary prayers. We are in great want of beautie, health, wisdom, virtue, and such like essentiall parts. Exteriour ornaments may be sought for when we are once provided of necessary things. Divinitie does very amply and pertinently treate of this subject, but I am not very conversant with it. Chrysippus and Diogenes have been the first and most constant authors of the contempt of glory. And amongst all sensualities, they said, there was as none so dangerous nor so much to be avoided as that which commeth unto us by the approbation of others. Verily experience makes us thereby feel and undergoe many damageable treasons. Nothing so much empoisoneth princes as flattery. Nor nothing whereby the wicked minded gain so easy credit about them; nor any enticement so fit, nor pandership so ordinary to corrupt the chastity of women, then to feed and entertaine them with their praises. The first enchantment the Syrens employed to deceive Ulisses is of this nature. Deca vers nous, deca, o treslouable Ulisse, Et le plus grand honneur dont la Grece fleurisse. Turne to us, to us turn, Ulisses thrice-renowned, The principal renown wherewith all Greece is crowned. Philosophers said that all the worlds glory deserved not that a man of wisdom should so much as stretch forth his finger to acquire it. Gloria quantalibet quid erit, si gloria tantum est? -- Juven. Sat. vii. 81. Never so gIorious name, What ist, be it but fame? I say for it alone: for it draws many commodities after it, by which it may yield itself desirable: it purchaseth us good will: it makes us less exposed to others injuries and offences and such like things. It was also one of the principal degrees of Epicurus: for that precept of his sect, H IDE T HY L IFE , which forbideth men to meddle with public charges and negotiations, does also necessarily presuppose that a man should despise despise glory, which is an approbation the world makes of those actions we give evidence of. He that bids usto hide our life and care but for ourselves, and would not have us know of others, would also have us not to be honoured and glorified thereby. So does he counsel Idomeneus by no means to order his actions by the vulgar opinion and public reputation: unless it be to avoide other accidentall in-commodities which the contempt of men might bring unto him. Those discourses (are in mine advise) very true and reasonable: but I wot not how we are double in ourselves, which is the cause that what we believe we believe it not, and cannot rid ourselves of that which we condemne. Let us consider the last words of Epicurus, and which he speaks as he is dying: they are notable and worthy such a Philosopher: but yet they have some badge of his names commendations, and of the humor which by his precepts he had disavowed. Behold here a letter which he edited a little before he yielded up the ghost. ’Epicurus to Hermachus health and greeting. Whilst I pass the happy, and even the last day of my life, I write this, accompanied nevertheless with such pain in my bladder and anguish in my entrails, that nothing can be added unto the greatness of it; yet was it recompensed with the pleasure which the remembrance of my inventions and discourses brought unto my soul. Now as requireth the affection which even from the infancy you hast borne me and Philosophy, embrace the protection of Metrodorus his children.’ See here his letter. And which makes me interpret that the pleasure which in his soul he says to feel of his inventions, does in some sort respect the reputation which after his death he thereby hoped to attaine, is the ordinance of his last will and testament, by which he wills that Aminomachus and Timocrates his heirs should for the celebration of his birth-day every month of January supply all such charges as Hermachus should appoint: and also for the expence he might be at on the twentieth of every moon for the feasting and entertainment of the Philosophers his familiar friends, who in the honor of his memory and of Metrodorus should meete together. Carneades has been chief of the contrary opinion and has maintained that glory was in itself to be desired, even as we embrace our posthumes for themselves, having neither knowledge nor jovissanee of them. This opinion has not missed to be more commonly followed as are ordinarily those that fit most and come nearest our inclinations. Aristotle amongst externall goods yieldeth the first rank unto it: and avoideth as two extreme vices the immoderation either in seeking or avoiding it. I believe that had we the bookes which Cicero wrote upon this subject, we should hear strange matters of him: for he was so foolish in this passion as had he dared he would (as I think) have easily falne into the excess that others fell in; which is that even virtue was not to be desired but for the honor which ever waited on it Paulum sepultæ distat inertiæ Celata virtus. -- Hor. Car. iv. Od. ix. 29. There is but little difference betweene Vertue conceal’d, unskilfulnesse unseen. Which is so false an opinion, as I am vexed it could ever enter a mans understanding that had the honor to bear the name of a philosopher. If that were true a man needed not to be vertuous but in public: and we should never need to keep the soules operations in order and rule, which is the true seate of virtue, but only so much as they might come to the knowledge of others. Does then nothing else belong unto it, but craftily to faile, and subtilly to cozen? If you knowest a serpent to be hidden in any place (says Carneades) to which he by whose death you hopest to reape commodity goeth unawares to sit upon, you committest a wicked act if you warne him not of it: and so much the more because your action should be known but to your self. If we take not the law of weldoing from our selves: if impunity be justice in us: to how many kindes of treacherie are we daily to abandon ourselves? That which Sp. Peduceus did, faithfully to restore the riches which C. Plotius had committed to his only trust and secrecie, and as my self have done often, I think not so commendable, as I would deem it execrable, if we had not done it. And I think it beneficiall we should in our days be mindfull of Publius Sextilius Rufus his example, whom Cicero accuses that he had received a great inheritance against his conscience: not only not repugnant, but agreeing with the laws. And M. Crassus and Q. Hortensius, who by reason of their authority and might, having for certain Quidities been called by a stranger to the succession of a forged will, that so he might make his share good: they were pleased not to be partakers of his forgery, yet refused not to take some profit of it: very closely had they kept themselves under the countenance of the accusations, witnesses, and laws. Meminerint Deum se habere testem, id est (ut ego arbitror) mentem suam: ’Let them remember they have God to witness, that is (as I construe it) their own mind.’ Vertue is a vain and frivolous thing if it draw her commendation from glory. In vain should we attempt to make her keep her rancke apart, and so should we disjoin it from fortune: for what is more casual then reputation? Profecto, fortuna in omni re dominator: Ea res cuizetas ex libidine magis quam ex vero celebrat obscuratque: ’Fortune governeth in all things, and either advaileth or abaseth them rather by froward disposition then upri ght judgement.’ To make actions to be known and seen, is the meere work of fortune. It is chance that applieth glory unto us, according to her temeritie. I have often seen it to go before desert; indeed, and many times to outgoe merit by very much. He that first bethought himself of the resemblance betweene shadow and glory, did better than he thought of. They are exceeding vain things. It also often goeth before her body, and sometimes exceeds by much in length. Those who teach nobility to seek in valor nothing but honor: Quasi non sit honestum quod nobilitatum non sit: ’As though it were not honest except it were ennobled:’ what gain they by it? But to instruct them never to hazard themselves unless they be seen of others; and to be very heedy whether such witnesses are by that may report news of their valor, whereas a thousand occasions to do well are daily offered, and no man by to marke them? How many notable, particular actions are buried in the throng of a battle. Whosoever ammuseth himself to controle others, in so confused a burly-burly, is not greatly busied about it: and produces the testimony which he gives of his fellowes proceedings or exploits against himself. Vera et sapiens animi magnitude, honestum illud quod maxime naturam sequitur, in factis positum, non in gloria indicat: ’A true and wise magnanimity seems that honesty which especially followeth Nature, to consist in good actions and not in glory.’ All the glory I pretend in my life is, that I have lived quietly. Quietly not according to Metrodorus, Arcesilas, or Aristippus, but according to my self. Since philosophy could never find any way for tranquillity that might be generally good, let every man in his particular seek for it. To whom are Cæsar and Alexander beholding for that infinite greatnes of their renown, but to fortune? How many men has she suppressed in the beginning of their progresse, of whom we have no knowledge at all, who bare the same courage that others did, if the ill fortune of their chance had not stayed them even in the building of their enterprises? Amongst so many and so extreme dangers (to my remembrance) I never read that Cæsar received any hurt. A thousand have dyed in less danger than the least of those he escaped. Many worthy exploits and excellent deedes must be lost before one can come to any good. A man is not alwaies upon the top of the breach, nor in the front of an army, in the sight of his general, as upon a stage. A man may be surprised betweene a hedge and a ditch. A man is sometimes put to his sodaine shifts, as to try his fortune against a hens-roost, to ferret out foure seely shotte out of some barne, indeed sometimes straggle alone from his troupes; and enterprise according as necessity and occasion offereth itself. And if it be well noted (in mine advice) it will be found, and experience does teach it, that the least blazoned occasions are the most dangerous, and that in our late home-wars, more good men have perished in slight and little importing occasions, and in contention about a small cottage, than in worthy achievements and honorable places. Whoso thinketh his death ill emploied, except it be in some glorious exploit or famous attempt, in lieu of dignifying his death, he happily obscureth his life: suffring in the meane time many just and honor-affoording opportunities to escape, where in he might and ought adventure himself. And all just occasions are glorious enough; his own conscience publishing them sufficiently to all men. Gloria nostra et testimonium conscientiæ nostra: (2 Cor. i. 12. Aug. Hom. xxxv.) ’Our glory is the testimony of our conscience.’ He that is not an honest man but by that which other men know by him, and because he shall the better be esteemed; being known to be so, that will not do well but upon condition his virtue may come to the knowledge of men; such a one is no man from whom any great service may be drawne, or good expected. Credo ch’il resto di quel verno, cose Facesse degne di tenerne conto, Ma fur fin’ a quel tempo si nascose, Che non e colpa mia s’hor’ non le conto, Per che Orlando a far’ opre virtuose Piu ch’ a narrle poi sempre era pronto Ne mai fu alcun’ de li suoi fatti espresso, Senon quando hebbe testimonii appresso. -- Ariost. Orl. can. xi. stan. 81. I guesse, he of that winter all the rest Atchiev’d exploits, whereof to keep account, But they until that time were so supprest, As now my fault ’tis not, them not to count, Because Orlando ever was more prest To do, than tell deeds that might all surmount. Nor was there any of his deeds related Unless some witness were associated. A man must go to wars for his devoirs sake, and expect this recompence of it, which cannot faile all worthy actions, how secret soever; no not to vertuous thoughts: it is the contentment that a well disposed conscience receiveth in itself by well doing. A man must be valiant for himself and for the advantage he has to have his courage placed in a constant and assured seate, to withstand all assaults of fortune. Virtus repulsæ nescia sordidæ, Intaminatis fulget honoribus: Nec sumit aut ponit secures Arbitrio popularis auræ. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. ii. 17. Vertue unskill’d to take repulse that’s base, In undefiled honors earely shines, At the dispose of peoples airy grace S he signes of honor tak’s not, nor resignes. It is not only for an exterior show or ostentation that our soul must play her part, but inwardly within ourselves, where no eyes shine but ours: there it does shroud us from the fear of death, of sorrowes and of shame: there it assureth us from the loss of our children, friend, and fortunes; and when opportunity is offerd, it also leades us to the dangers of war. Non emoluntento aliquo, sedi psius honestatis decore: (Cic. Fin i.) ’Not for any advantage, but for the gracefulnes of honestie itself.’ Thls benefit is much greater, and more worthie to be wished and hoped than honor and glory, which is nought but a favorable judgment that is made of us. We are often driven to empanell and select a jury of twelve men out of a whole countrie to determine of an acre of land: And the judgement of our inclinations and actions (the weightiest and hardest matter that is) we refer it to the idle breath of the vain voice of the common sort and base raskalitie, which is the mother of ignorance, of injustice and inconstancie. Is it reason to make the life of a wise man depend on the judgement of fooles? An quidquam stultius, quam quos singulos contemnas, eos aliquid putare esse universos? (Ælian. Var. Hist. ii. c. 1.) ’Is there anything more foolish then to think that al together they are oughts, whom every one single you would set at noughts? Whosoever aimeth to please them has never done. It is a Butt, that has neither form nor holdfast. Nil tam inæstimabile est, quam aninti multitudinis: ’Nothing is so incomprehensible to be just waied, as the minds of the multitude.’ Demetrius said merrily of the common peoples voice, that he made no more reckoning of that which issued from out his mouth above, then of that which came from a homely place below; and says moreover: Ego hoc judico, si quando turpe non sit, tamen non esse non turpe, quum id a multitudine laudetur: (Cic. Fin. Bon. ii.) ’Thus I esteem of it, if of itself it be not dishonest, yet can it not but be dishonest, when it is applauded [by] the many.’ No art, no mildness of spirit might direct our steps to follow so stragling and disordered a guide. In this breathie confusion of bruites and frothy Chaos of reports and of vulgar opinions, which still push us on, no good course can be established. Let us not propose so fleeing and so wavering an end unto ourselves. Let us constantly follow reason: And let the vulgar approbation follow us that way. If it please: And as it depends all on fortune, we have no law to hope for it, rather by any other way then by that. Should I not follow a strait path for its straightnesse, yet would I do it because experience has taught me that in the end it is the happiest and most profitable. Dedit hoc providentia hominibus munus at honesta magis juvarent: ’ Mans providence has given him this gift, that honest things should more delight and avail him.’ The ancient Sailer said thus to Neptune in a great storme, ’Oh God, you shall save me if you please, if not, you shall lose me; yet will I keep my helme still fast,’ I have in my days seen a thousand middle, mungrell and ambiguous men, and whom no man doubted to be more worldly-wise than my self, lose themselves, where I have saved my self. Risi successu posse carere dolos -- Ovid. Epist. Penel. v. 18. I smild to see that wily plots Might want success (and leave men sots). Paulus Emilius going to the glorious expedition of Macedon, advertised the people of Rome during his absence not to speak of his actions: For the licence of judgements is an especiall let in great affairs. Forasmuch as all men have not the constancy of Fabius against common, contrary and detracting voices: who loved better to have his authority dismembred by mens vain fantasies, then not to performe his charge so well, with favourable and popular applause. There is a kind of I know not what natural delight that man has to hear himself commended, but we yield too-too much unto it. Laudari haud metuam, neque enim mihi cornea fibra est, Sed recti finemque extremumque esse recuso Euge tuum et belle. -- Pers. Sat. i. 47. Nor fear I to be prais’d, for my guttes are not horne, But that the utmost end of good should be, I scorne, Thy O well said, well done, well plaid.’ I care not so much what I am with others, as I respect what I am in my self. I will be rich by my self and not by borrowing. Strangers see but external apparances and events: every man can set a good face upon the matter, when within he is full of care, grief and infirmities. They see not my heart when they looke upon my outward countenance. There is great reason the hypocrisie that is found in war should be discovered: for, what is more easy in a man of practise then to flinch in dangers and to counterfeit a gallant and a boaster when his heart is full of faintnesse and ready to droope for fear? There are so many waies to shunne occasions for a man to hazard himself in particular, that we shall have deceived the world a thousand times before we need engage ourselves into any perillous attempt; and even when we find ourselves entangled in it, we shall not want skill how to cloake our sport with a good face, searne countenance, and bold speeches; although our heart do quake within us. And he that had the use of the Platonicall Ring, whose virtue was to make him invisible that wore it upon his finger, if it were turned toward the flat of the hand; many would hide themselves when they should most make shewe of their worth, and would be sorie to be placed in so honorable a place where necessity may be their warrant of safetie. Falsus honor iuvat, et mendax infamia terra Quem nisi mendosum et mendacem -- Hor. i. Ep. xvi. 39. False honor tickles; false defame affrights, Whom, but the faulty, and false-fierd sprights? See how all those judgements that men make of outward apparences are wonderfully uncertaine and doubtfull, and there is no man so sure a testimony, as every man is to himself: How many horse-boye’s have we in them as parteners and companions of our glory? He that keepes his stand in an open trench, what does he more, but diverse poore pioners do as much before him, who open the way for him, and with their bodies shelter him for poore sixpence a day, and happily for less? ----- non quicguid turbida Roma Elevet, acced as, examenque improbum in illa Castiges trutina, nec te quæsiveris extra. -- Pers. Sat. i. 5. If troublous Rome set ought at nought, make you not one, Nor chastise you unjust examination In balance of their lode: Nor seek your self abrode. We call that a magnifying of our name, to extend and diperse the same in many mouthes; we will have it to be received in good part, and that its increase redound to his benefit: this is al that is most excusable in its design. But the infirmity of its excess proceeds so far that many labor to have the world speak of them, however it be. Trogus Pompeius says of Herostratus, and Titus Livius of Manlius Capitolinus, that they were more desirous of great then good reputation. It is an ordinary fault; we endeavor more that men should speak of us, then how and what they speak, and it sufficeth us that our name run in mens mouthes, in what manner soever. It seems that to be knowen is in some sort to have life and continuance in other mens keeping. As for me I hold that I am but in my self; and of this other life of mine which consisteth in the knowledge of my friends, being simply and barely considered in my self well I wot, I neither feel fruite or jovissance of it, but by the vanity of fantastic opinion. And when I shall be dead, I shall much less have a feeling of it: And shall absolutely lose the use of true utilities which sometimes accidentally follow it: I shall have no more fastnesse to take hold on reputation, nor whereby it may either concerne or come unto me. For, to expect my name should receive it, First, I have no name that is sufficiently mine: of two I have, the one is common to all my race, indeed also to others. There is a family at Paris and another at Montpellier called Montaigne, another in Britany, and one in Xaintonge, surnamed de la Montaigne. The removing of one only syllable may so confound our webbe, as I shall have a share in their glory, and they perhaps a part of my shame. And my Ancestors have heretofore been surnamed Higham or Eyquem, a surname which also belongs to a house well knowen in England. As for my other name, it is any bodies that shall have a mind to it. So shall I happily honor a Porter in my stead. And suppose I had a particular marke or badge for my self, what can it marke when I am no more extant? May it design or favor inanity? -----nunc levior cippus non imprimit ossa? Laudat posteritas; nunc non e manibus illis, Nunc non e tumulo fortunataque favilla Nascuntur violæ? -- Ibid. 37. Does not the grave-stone on such bones sit light? Posterity applaudes: from such a spright, From such a tombe, from ashes blessed so, Shall there not Violets (in cart-lodes) grow? But of this I have spoken elsewhere. As for the rest, in a whole battle, where ten thousand are either maymed or slain, there are not perhaps fifteene that shall be much spoken off. It must be some eminent greatness or important consequence that fortune has joined unto it to make a private action prevaile, not of a meane shot alone, but of a chieftaine: for to kill a man or two or tenne; for one to present himself undantedly to death, is indeed something to every one of us in particular: for a mans free- hold goes on it: But in regarde of the world they are such ordinary things, so many are daily seen, and so sundry likewise must concurre together to produce a notable effect, that we can looke for no particular commendation by them. ---- casus multis hic cognitus, ac iam Tritus, et e medio fortuno ductus acervo. -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 9. This case is known of many, worne with nothing, Drawne from the midle heape of fortunes doting. Of so many thousands of worthie-valiant men, which fifteene hundred years since have died in France with their weapons in hand, not one hundred have come to our knowledge: The memory not only of the Generals and Leaders, but also of the battles and victories lieth now low-buried in oblivion. The fortunes of more than halfe the world, for want of a register, stir not from their place, and vanish away without continuance. Had I all the unknown events in my possession, I am persuaded I might easily supplant those that are known in all kindes of examples. What, of the Romanes themselves and of the Græcians, amongst so many writers and testimonies, and so infinit rare exploites and matchles examples, how are so few of them come to our notice? Ad nos vix tenuis famæ perlabitur aura. -- Virg. Æn. vii.646. Scarcely to us does pass Fames thin breath, how it was. It shall be much, if a hundred years hence the civill wars which lately we have had in France, be but remembred in grosse. The Lacedemonians, as they were going to their battles, were wont to sacrifice unto the Muses to the end their deedes might be well written and worthily registred; deeming it a divine favor and unusuall grace, that noble actions might find testimonies able to give them life and memory. Thinke we that at every shot that hits us or at every dangerous attempt we run into to have a clarke present to enrole it : and besides, it may be that an hundred clarkes shall write them, whose commentaries shall not continue three days and shall never come to anybodys sight. We have but a thousandth part of ancient writings: It is Fortune, which according to her favor gives them either shorter or longer life; and what we have, we may lawfully doubt of, whether it be the worse, since we never saw the rest. Histories are not written upon every small trifle: It is requisite that a man have been conqueror of an Empire or of a Kingdome; a man must have obtained two and fiftie set battles, and ever with a lesser number of men, as Cæsar did. Tenne thousand good-fellowes, and many great captaines have died most valiantly and coragiously in pursuite of her, whose names have continued no longer then their wives and children lived: ------- quos fama obscura recondit. -- Virg. Æn. v. 292. Whom fame obscure before Layes up in unknown store. Even of those whom we see to do excellently well, if they have but once continued so three months, or so many years, there is no more speech of them then if they had never bin. Whosoever shall in due measure proportion and impartially consider, of what kind of people, and of what deedes the glory is kept in the memory of bookes, he shall find there are few actions and very few persons that may justly pretend any right in them. How many vertuous men have we seen to survive their own reputation, who even in their presence have seen the honor and glory which in their young days they had right-justly purchased, to be cleane extinguished? And do we for three years of this fantastic and imaginarie life lose and foregoe our right and essentiall life, and engage ourselves in a perpetuall death? The wiser sort propose a right-fairer and much more just end unto themselves, to so urgent and weighty an enterprise. Recte facti, f ecisse merces est: Officii fructi, ipsum officium est: (Senec. Epist. lxxxi.) ’The reward of well-doing is the doing, and the fruit of our duty is our duty.’ It might perhaps be excusable in a Painter or other artificer, or also in a Rhetorician or Gramarian, by his labours to endevor to purchase a name: But the actions of virtue are themselves too-too noble to seek any other reward then by their own worth and merit, and especially to seek it in the vanity of mans judgement. If this false- foolish opinion do notwithstanding serve and stead a common wealth to hold men to their dutie: if the people be thereby stirred up to virtue: if Princes be any way touched to see the world blesse and commend the memory of Trajan, and detest the remembrance of Nero: if that does moove them to see the name of that arch-villanie, heretofore so dreadfull and so much redoubted of all, so boldly cursed and so freely outraged by the first scholer that undertakes him: Let it hardly be increased, and let us (as much as in us l ieth) still foster the same amongst ourselves. And Platoe employing all means to make his Citizens vertuous, does also persuade them not to contemne the peoples good estimation. And says that through some divine inspiration it commeth to pass that even the wicked know often, as well by word as by opinion, how to distinguish justly the good from the bad. This man, together with his master, are wonderful and bold workmen to join divine operations and revelations wherever humane force faileth. And therefore did perventure Timon (deeming thereby to wrong him) surname him the great forger of miracles. Vt tragici poetæ confugiunt ad Deum, cum explicare argumenti exitum non possunt. (Cic. Nat. Deor. i.) ’As Poets that write Tragedies have recourse to some God when they cannot unfold the end of their argument.’ Since men by reason of their insufliciencie cannot well pay themselves with good lawfull coine, let them also employ false money. This meane has been practised by all the law-givers: And there is no common wealth where there is not some mixture either of ceremonious vanity or of false opinion, which as a restraint serveth to keep the people in awe and dutie. It is therefore that most of them have such fabulous grounds and trifling beginnings, and enriched with supernaturall mysteries. It is that which has given credit unto adulterate and unlawfull religions, and has induced men of understanding to favor and countenance them. And therefore did Noma and Sertorius, to make their men have a better beliefe, feed them with this foppery: the one, that the Nimph Egeria, the other that his white Hinde, brought him all the councels he took from the Gods. And the same authority which Numa gave his laws under the title of this Goddesses patronage, Zoroaster, Law-giver to the Bactrians and Persians, gave it to his, under the name of the God Oromazis. Trismegistus, of the Egyptians, of Mercury: Zamolzis, of the Scithians, of Vesta: Charondas, of the Chalcedonians, of Saturne: Minos, of the Candiots, of Jupiter: Lycurgus, of the Lacedemonians, of Apollo: Dracon and Solon, of the Athenians, of Minerva. And every common wealth has a God to her chief: al others falsly, but that truly which Moses instituted for the people of Jewry descended from Egypt. The Bedoins religion (as says the Lord of Jouinvile) held among other things that his soul which among them all died for his Prince went directly into another more happy body much fairer and stronger than the first: by means whereof they much more willingly hazarded their lives for his sake. In ferrum mens prona viris animæque capaces Mortis: et ignavum est redituræ parcere vitæ. -- Lucan. i. 461. Those men sword minded, can death entertaine, Thinke base to spare the life that turnes again. See here, although very vain , a most needfull doctrine and profitable beliefe. Everie Nation has store of such examples in itself. But this subject would require a severall discourse. Yet to say a word more concerning my former purpose: I do not counsell Ladies any longer to call their duty honor: vt enim consuetudo loquitur, id solum dicitur honestum, quod est populari fama gloriosum: (Cic. Fin. ii.) ’For as custom speaks, that only is called honest which is glorious by popular report.’ Their duty is the marke; their honor but the barke of it. Nor do I persuade them to give us this excuse of their refusall in payment; for I suppose their intentions, their desire, and their will, which are parts wherein honor can see nothing, forasmuch as nothing appeareth outwardly, there are yet more ordered then the effects. Quæ, quia non liceat, non facit, illa facit. -- Ovid. Am. iii. El. iv. 4. She does it, though she do it not Because she may not do’t (Got wot). The offence both toward God and in conscience would be as great to desire it as to effect the same. Besides, they are in themselves actions secret and hid; it might easily be, they would steale some one from others knowledge, whence honor dependeth, had they no other respect to their duty and affection which they bear unto chastity, in regard of it self. Each honorable person chuseth rather to lose his honor than to forgoe his conscience. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XVII: OF PRESUMPTION CHAPTER XVII: OF PRESUMPTION HERE IS another kind of glory, which is an over-good opinion we conceive of our worth. It is an inconsiderate affection, wherewith we cherish ourselves, which presents us unto ourselves other then we are. As an amorous passion addeth beauties and lendeth graces to the subject it embraceth, and maketh such as are therewith possessed, with a troubled conceit and distracted judgmement, to deem what they love, and find what they affect, to be other, and seem more perfect, then in trueth it is. Yet would I not have a man, for fear of offending in that point, to misacknowledge himself, nor think to be less then he is: A true judgement should wholly and in every respect mainetaine his right. It is reason, that as in other things, so in this subject he see what truth presenteth unto him. If he be Cæsar, let him boldly deem himself the greatest Captain of the world. We are nought but ceremony: ceremony does transport us, and we leave the substance of things; we hold-fast by the boughs, and leave the trunke or body. We have taught ladies to blush, only by hearing that named which they nothing fear to do. We dare not call our members by their proper names, and fear not to employ them in all kind of dissolutenese. Ceremonie forbids us by words to express lawfull and natural things; and we believe it. Reason wills us to do no bad or unlawfull things, and no man gives credit unto it. Here I find my self entangled in the laws of Ceremonie, for it neither allowes a man to speak ill or good of himself. Therefore will we leave her at this time. Those whom fortune (whether we shall name her good or bad) has made to pass their life in some eminent or conspicuous degree, may by their public actions witness what they are; but those whom she never emploied but in base things, and of whom no man shall ever speak, except themselves do it, they are excusable if they dare speak of themselves to such as have interest in their acquaintance, after the example of Lucillus: Ille velut fidis arcana sodalibus olim Credebat libris: neque si male cesserat, usquam Decurrens alio, neque si bene: quo fit, ut omnis Votiva pateat veluti descripta tabella Vita senis. -- Hor. Ser. ii. Sat. i. 30. He trusted to his book, as to his trusty friend His secrets, nor did he to other refuge bend, How ever well, or ill, with him his fortune went. Hence is it, all the life is seen the old man spent, As it were in a Table noted, Which were unto some God devoted. This man committed his actions and imaginations to his paper, and as he felt, so he pourtraied himself. Nec id Rutilio et Scauro citra fidem, aut obtrectationi fuit: (Corn. Tacit. Vit. Jul. Agric.) ’Nor was that without credit, or any imputation to Rutilius or Scaurus.’ I remember then, that even from my tenderest infancy, some noted in me a kind of I know not what fashion in carrying of my body and gestures, witnessing a certain vain and foolish fiercenesse. This I will first say of it, that it is not inconvenient to have conditions so peculiar, and propensions so incorporated in us, that we have no meane to feel, or way to know them. And of such natural inclinations, unknown to us, and without our consent, the body does easily retaine some signe or impression. It was an affectation witting of his beauty, which made Alexander to bend his head a little on one side, and Alcibiades, his speech somewhat effeminate and lisping: Julius Cæsar was wont to scratch his head with one finger, which is the countenance of a man surcharged with painefull imaginations: and Cicero (as I remember) had gotten a custom to wryth his nose, which signifieth a natural scoffer. Such motions may unawares and imperceptibly possesse us. Others there be which are artificiall, whereof I will not speak. As salutations, reverences, or conges, by which some do often purchase the honor (but wrongfully) to be humble, lowly, and courteous: a man may be humble through glory. I am very prodigall of cappings, namely in Summer, and I never receive any from what quality of men soever, but I give them as good and as many as they bring, except he be some servant of mine. I wish that some Princes whom I know would be more sparing and impartiall dispencers of them, for, being so indiscreetly employed, they have no force at all: If they be without regard, then are they without effect. Amongst disordered countenances, let us not forget the stern looke of Constantius the Emperor, who in public held ever his head bolt-upright, without turning or bending the same on any side, no not so much as to looke on them that saluted him sideling, holding his body so fixt and unmoveable, that let his coche shake never so much, he kept still up-right: he durst never spit nor wipe his nose nor drie his face before the people. I wot not whether those gestures which were noted in me were of this first condition, and whether in truth I had any secret propension to this fault, as it may well be: and I cannot answer for the motions of my body. But concerning those of the soul, I will here ingenuously confesse what I think of them. There are two parts in this glory: which is to say, for a man to esteeme himself overmuch, the other, not sufficiently to esteeme of others. For the one, first me thinks these considerations ought somewhat to be accompted of. I feel my self surcharged with one error of the mind, which both as bad, and much more as importunate, I utterly dislike. I endeavor to correct it; but I cannot displace it. It is, because I abate the just value of those things which I possesse; and enhance the worth of things by how much they are more strange, absent and not my own. This humor extends itself very far, as does the prerogative of the authority, wherewith husbands looke upon their own wives with a vicious disdaine, and many fathers upon their children: so do I, and betweene two like workes would I ever weigh against mine. Not so much that the jealousie of my preferment, and amendment troubleth my judgement, and hindereth me from pleasing my self, as that mastery herself begets a contempt of that which a man possesseth and oweth. Policies, far customs and tongues flatter me; and I perceive the Latine tongue by the favor of her dignity to deceive me, beyond what belongs unto her, as children and the vulgar sort. My neighbors economie; his house, and his horse, though but of equall value, is more worth then mine by how much more it is not my own. Besides, because I am most ignorant in my own matters, I admire the assurance, and wonder at the promise that every man has of himself: whereas there is almost nothing that I wot I know, nor that I dare warrant my self to be able to do. I have not my faculties in proposition or by estate, and am not instructed in them but after the effect; as doubtfull of my own strength, as uncertaine of anothers force. Whence it followeth, if commendably I chance upon any one piece of work, I rather impute it to my fortune, then ascribe it to mine industry; forasmuch as I designe them all to hazard and in fear. Likewise I have this in general, that of all the opinions which Antiquity has had of men in gross, those which I most willingly embrace, and whereon I take most hold, are such as most vilifie, condemne, and annihilate us. Me thinks Philosophy has never better cards to show then when she checketh our presumption, and crosseth our vanity; when in good sooth she acknowledgeth her irresolution, her weaknesse and her ignorance. Me seems the over good conceit and self-weening opinion man has of himself, is the nurse- mother of the falsest opinions, both public and particular. Those which a cocke-horse will pearch themselves upon the Epicicle of Mercury and see so far into heaven, they even pull out my teeth. For in the study which I professe, the subject whereof is Man, finding so extreme a inextricable a labyrinth of difficulties, one upon the necke of another, so great diversitie, and so much uncertaintie, indeed even in the school of wisdom itself: you may imagine since those men could never be resolved of the knowledge of themselves and of their own condition, which is continually before their eyes, which is ever within them; since they know not how that moveth which themselves cause to move, nor how to set forth the springs, and decipher the wards, which themselves hold and handle, how should I think of the true cause of the flux and reflux of the river Nilus? The curiosity to know things has been given to men (as says the holy Scripture for a scourge. But to come to my particular, it is very hard (me seems) that some other regardeth him self less, indeed some other esteemeth me less than I esteeme my self. I accompt my self of the common sort, except in that I deem myself guiltie of the basest, and culpable most popular defects: but not disavowed nor excused. And I only prise my self wherein I know my worth. If any glory be in me, it is but superficially infused into me; by the treason of my complexion: and has no solid body appearing to the sight of my judgement. I am but sprinckled over, but not throughly dyed. For in truth, touching the effects of the spirit in what manner soever, there never came any thing from me that contented me. And others approbation is no currant payment for me. My judgement is tender and hard, especially in my own behalf. I feel my self to waver and bend through weaknesse: I have nothing of my own to satisfie my judgement. My sight is indifferently clear and regular; but if I take any serious work in hand, it is troubled and dimmed: as I perceive most evidently in poesie: I love it exceedingly: I have some insight or knowledge in other mens labours, but in truth I play the novice when I set my hand unto it: then can I not abide my self. A man may play the foole every where else, but not in poesie: -----mediocribus esse poetis Non dii, non homines, non concessere, columnæ. -- Hor. Art. Poet. 372. Nor Gods, nor men, nor pillers gave the graunt, That Poets in a meane, should meanely chaunt. I would to God this sentence were found in the front of our printers or stationers shops, to hinder the entrance of so many bald-rimers. -----verum Nil securius est malo Poeta. -- Mart. xii. Epig. lxiv. Nothing securer may be had, Then is a Poet bold and bad. Why have we no such people? Dionysius the father esteemed nothing in himself so much as his poesie. In the times of the Olimpike games, with chariots exceeding all other in magnificence, he also sent poets and musitians to present his verses, with tents and pavillions gilt and most suinptuously tapistried. When they first beganne to rehearse them, the favor and excellencie of the pronunciation did greatly allure the peoples attention: but when they beganne to consider the fondnesse of the composition, they fell as soone to contemne them: and being more and more exasperated, fell furiously into an uproare; and headlong ranne in most spitefull manner to teare and cast down all his pavillions. And forasmuch as his rich chariots did no good at all in their course, and the ship which carried his men, returning homeward, missed the shore of Sicilie, and was by violent stormes driven and spilt upon the coast of Tarentum, they certainely beleeved the wrath of the Gods to have been the cause of it, as being greatly offended both against him and his vile and wicked poeme: indeed the mariners themselves that escaped the shipwracke did much second the peoples opinion: to which the oracle that foretold his death seemed in some sort to subscribe: which implied that Dionysius should be neare his end, at what time he had vanquished those that should be of more worth than himself; which he interpreted to be the Carthaginians, who exceeded him in might. And having at any time an occasion to fight with them, that that he might not incur the meaning of his prediction, he would often temper and avoide the victory. But he mis-understood the matter, for God observed the time of advantage, when as through partiall favor and injustice he obtained the victory over the tragical poets of Athens, who were much better than he was, where he caused, in contention of them, his tragedie, entitled the Leneiens, to be publikely acted. After which usurped victory, he presently deceased: and partly through the excessive joy he thereby conceived. What I find excusable in mine is not of itself and according to truth: but in comparison of other compositions, worse then mine, to which I see some credit given. I envie the good the happe of those which can applaude and gratifie themselves by their own labours; for it is an easy matter for one to please himself, since he draws his pleasure from himself: especially if one be somewhat constant in his own wilfulnesse. I know a poetaster, gainst whom both weake and strong, in company and at home, both heaven and earth, affirme and say he has no skill or judgement in poesie, who for all that is nothing dismaied, nor will not abate one jote of that measure whereunto he has fitted himself; but is ever beginning again, ever consulting anew, and alwaies persisting; by so much the more fixed in his opinion by how much the more it concerneth him alone, and he only is to maintaine it. My compositions are so far from applauding me, that as many times as I looke them over, so often am I vexed at them. Cum relego, scripsisse pudet, quia plurima cerno, Me quoque qui feci judice, digna lini. --- Ovid. Pont. 1.i. c.vi. 15. When I re-read, I shame I write; for much I see, My self, who made them, being judge, blotted to be. I have ever an Idea in my mind which presents me with a better form then that I have alreadie framed; but I can neither lay hold on it nor effect it. Yet is that Idea but of the meaner stamp. I thereby conclude that the productions of those rich and great mindes of former ages are far beyond the extreme extention of my wish and imagination. Their compositions do not only satisfie and fill me, but they astonish and wrap me into admiration. I judge of their beauty, I see it, if not to the end, at least so far as it is impossible for me to aspire unto it. Whatsoever I undertake (as Plutarke says of one) I owe a sacrifice to the Graces, hoping thereby to gain their favor. ------ si quid enim placet, Si quid dulce hominum, sensibus influit. Debentur lepidis omnia gratiis. If ought do please, if any sweet The sense of men with pleasures greet, To thank the Graces it is meet. They altogether forsake me: what I do, it is but bunglingly, and wants both polishing and beauty. I can rate them at no higher value then they are worth. My workmanship addeth no grace unto the matter. And that’s the reason I must have it strong, with good holdfast, and shining of itself. If I chance to seize on any popular or more gay, it is to follow me, who love not a ceremonious prudence and gloomy wisdom, as does the world; and to glad my self, not my stile, who would rather have it grave and severe; if at least I may call that a stile which is formelesse and abrupt speech; a popular gibrish, and a proceeding without definition, without partition, and sans conclusion, troubled as that of Amasanius and Rabirius. I am neither pleased, nor glad, nor tickled. The best tale in the world coming into my hands becomes withered and tarnished. I cannot speak but in good earnest, and am altogether barren of that facility which I see in many of my companions, to entertaine [first] commers, to keep a whole troupe in talk, to ammuse a princes ears with all manner of discourses and never to be weary, and never to want matter, by reason of the graces they have in applying their first approches, and fitting them to the humor and capacity of those they have to do withall. Princes love not greatly serious and long discourses, nor I to tell tales. The first and easiest reasons (which are commonly the best taken) I can neither employ nor make use of them. I am an ill orator to the common sort. I speak the utmost I know of all matters. Cicero thinks, in discourses of philosophy, the exordium to be the hardest part: if it be so, I wisely lay hold on the conclusion. Yet should a man know how to turn his strings to all aires: and the sharpest comes ever last in play. There is at last as much perfection in raising up an empty as to uphold a weighty thing: a man must sometimes handle matters but superficially, and at other times dive into them. I wot well that most men keep themselves on this low stage because they conceive not of things but by the outward show. I also know that the greatest clarkes, indeed Xenophon and Plato, are often seen to yield to this low and popular fashion, in speaking of matters, upholding it with those graces which they never want. As for the rest, my language has neither facility nor fluency in it, but is harsh and sharpe, having free and unsinnowy dispositions. And so it liketh me, if not by my judgement, yet by my inclination. But yet I perceive that sometimes I wade too far into it, and that forcing my self to avoide art and affectation, I fall into it another way. ------ brevis esse labore: Obscurus fio. -- Hor. Art. Poet. 25. To be short labor I? I darker grow thereby. Plato says, that either long or short are not properties that either diminish or give price unto speech. If I should undertake to follow this other smoothe, even and regular stile, I should never attaine unto it. And although the cadences and breakings of Salust do best agree with my humor, yet do I find Cæsar both greater and less easy to be represented. And if my inclination does rather carrie me to the imitation of Senecæs stile, I omit not to esteeme Plutarke much more. As well in silence as in speech, I am simply my natural form, whence happily ensueth that I am more in speaking than in writing. The motions and actions of the body give life unto words, namely, in them that move roundly and without affectation, as I do, a nd that will be earnest. Behaviour, the face, the voice, the gowne, and the place, may somewhat endeare those things which in themselves are but meane, as pratling. Messala complaineth in Tacitus of certain strait garments used in his time, and discommendeth the fashion of the benches whereon the Orators were to speak, saying they weakened their eloquence. My French tongue is corrupted both in the pronunciation and elsewhere by the barbarisme of my country. I never saw men of these hither-countries that did not evidently taste of his home-speech, and who often did not wound those ears that are purely French. Yet it is not because I am so cunning in my Perigordin: for I have no more use of it than of the Dutch, nor do I greatly care. It is a language (as are many others round about me) like to that of Poitou, Xaintonge, Angoulesme, Limosin, and Auvergne, squattering, dragling, and filthie. There is about us, towards the mountaines, a Gascoine tongue, which I much commend and like, sinnowie, pithie, short, significant, and in truth man-like and military; more than any other I understand. As compendious, powerfull, and pertinent as the French is gracious, delicate, and copious. As for the Latine, which was given me for my mother-tongue, by reason of discontinuance, I have so lost the promptitude, of it, as I cannot well make use of it in speech, and scarcely in writing, in which I have heretofore been so ready, that I was called a master in it. See here my little sufficiencie in that behalfe. Beauty is a part of great commendation in the commerce and societie of men. It is the chief meane of reconciliation betweene one and other. Nor is there any man so barbarous and so hard- hearted, that in some sort feeleth not himself strucken with her sweetnes. The body has a great part in our being, and therein keepes a speciall rancke. For his structure and composition are worthy due consideration. Such as go about to sunder our two principal parts, are much to blame; they ought rather to be coupled and joined fast together. The soul must be enjoyned not to retire to herself her quarter, nor to entertaine herself apart, nor to despise and leave the body (which she cannot well do, except it be by some counterfeited, apish tricke) but ought so combine and cling fast unto him, to embrace, to cherish, assist, correct, persuade, and advise him, and if he chance to sway or stray, then to leade and direct him: In fine, she should wed and serve him instead of a husband, that so their effects may not seem contrary and diverse, but agreeing and uniform. Christians have a particular instruction concerning this bond, for they know that Gods justice alloweth this society, and embraceth this conjunction of the body and soul, indeed so far as to make the body capable of everlasting rewards. And that God beholds the whole man to work, and will have him entirely to receive either the punishment or the recompence, ac cording to his demerits. The Peripatetike Sect (of all Sects the most sociable) attributeth this only care unto wisdom, in common to procure and provide the good of these two associated parts: and declareth other sects to have partialized overmuch, because they had given themselves to the full consideration of this commixture; this one for the body, this other for the soul, with one like error and oversight, and had mistaken their subject, which is man; and their guide, which in general they avouched to be Nature. The first distinction that has been amongst men, and the first consideration that gave preheminences to some over others, it is very likely it was the advantage of beauty. ------ agros divisere atque dedere Pro facie cuiusque et viribus ingenioque: Nam facies multum valuit virisque vigebant. -- Lucr. v. 1120. They lands divided, and to each man shared As was his face, his strength, his wit compared, For face and strength were then Much priz’d amongst men. I am of a stature somewhat under the meane. This default has not only uncomlinesse in it, but also incommoditie: Yea even in those which have charge and commandement over others; for the authority which a fair presence and corporall majestic endoweth a man withal is wanting. Caius Marius did not willingly admit any Soldiers in his bands that were not six foot high. The Courtier has reason to require all ordinary stature in the gentleman he frameth, rather than any other: and to avoid all strangenesse that may make him to be pointed at. But if he misse of this mediocritie, to chuse that he rather offend in lownes than in tallnes. I would not do it in a militarie man. Little men, says Aristotle, are indeed pretty, but not beauteous, nor goodly; and in greatnes is a great soul known as is beauty in a great and high body. The Ethiopians and Indians, says he, in chusing of their Kings and Magistrates, had an especiall regard to the beautie and tallnes of the persons. They had reason, for it breedeth an awful respect in those that follow him, and a kind of fear in his enemies, to see a goodly, tall, and handsome man march as chief and general in the head of any army, or front of a troupe: Ipse inter primos præstanti corporeTurnus Vertitur, arma tenens, et toto vertice suprit est. -- Virg. Æn. vii. 725. Turnus, a goodly man, mongst them that led, Stood arm’d, then all they higher by the head. Our great, divine, and heavenly King, all whose circumstances ought with much care, religion, and reverence, to be noted and observed, has not refused the bodies commendation. Speciosus forma præ filiis hominum. (Psal. xlv. 3) ’In favor beautiful above the sons of men.’ And Plato wisheth beautie to be joined unto temperance and fortitude in the preservers of his Commonwealth. Is it not a great spite, if being amongst your own servants, a stranger commeth to yourselfe to ask you where your Lord or Master is? And that you have nothing but the remainder of a capping, which is as well put off to your Barber, or to your Secretarie? As it happened to poore Philopoemen, who having left his company behind, and coming alone into a house where he was expresly looked for, his hostess, who knew him not, and saw him to be so il-favored a fellow, employed him to help her maides draw water, and to mend the fire for the service of Philopoemen. The gentlemen of his traine being come and finding him so busily at work (for he failed not to fulfil his hostesses commandement, enquired of him what he did, who answered,’ I pay the penaltie of my unhandsomnesse.’ Other beauties are for women. The beautie of a handsome comely tallnesse is the only beautie of men. Where lownesse and littlenesse is, neither the largenesse nor roundnesse of a forehead, nor the whiteness nor lovelinesse of the eyes, nor the pretty fashion of a nose, nor the slendernes of the eare, littlenesse of the mouth, order and whiteness of teeth, smooth thicknesse of a beard, browne like a chesse-nut, well-curled and upstanding hair, just proportion of the head, freshnes of colour, the cheereful aspect of a pleasing face, the sweet-smelling of a body, nor the well decorated composition of all limbs, can make a handsome beauteous man. As for me, I am of a strong and well compacted stature, my face is not fat but full, my complexion betweene joviall and melancholy, indifferently sanguine and hot. Vnde rigent setis mihi crura, et pectora villis: -- Mart. vi. Epig. lvi. 1. Whereby my legs and brest, With rough hair are opprest. My health is blith and lustie, though well-stroken in age, seldom troubled with diseases: Such I was, for I am now engaged in the approaches of age, having long since past over forty years. -----minutatim vires et robur adultum Frangit, et in partem pejorem liquitur ætas. -- Lucr. ii. 1140. By little and a little age breakes strength, To worse and worse declining melts at length. What hereafter I shall be will be but half a being. I shall be no more my self. I daily escape, and still steale my self from my self: Singula de nobis anni prædantur euntes. -- Hor. ii. Epist. ii. 55. Yeares as they pass away, Of all our things make prey. Of addressing, dexteritie, and disposition, I never had any, yet am I the son of a well disposed father, and of so blithe and merry a disposition, that it continued with him even to his extreamest age. He seldom found any man of his condition, and that could match him in all exercises of the body; as I have found few that have not out-gone me, except it were in running, wherein I was of the middle sort. As for music, were it either in voice, which I have most harsh, and very unapt, or in instruments, I could never be taught any part of it. As for dancing, playing at tennis, or wrestling, I could never attaine to any indifferent sufficiencie, but none at all in swimming, in fencing, in vaulting, or in leaping. My hands are so stiffe and nummie, that I can hardly write for my self, so that what I have once scribled, I had rather frame it anew than take the paines to correct it; and I read but little better. I perceive how the auditorie censureth me; otherwise I am no bad clarke. I cannot very well close up a letter, nor could I ever make a pen. I was never good carver at the table. I could never make readie nor arm a horse; nor handsomely array a hawke on my fist, nor cast her off, or let her flie, nor could never speak to dogges, to birds, or to horses. The conditions of my body are, in fine, very well agreeing with those of my mind, wherein is nothing lively, but only a compleate and constant vigor. I endure labor and pain, yet not very well, unless I carry myself unto it, and no longer than my desire leadeth and directeth me. Molliter austerum studio fallente laborem. -- Ser. ii. Sa. ii. 12. While earnestnesse for sport or gain, Sweetly deceives the sowrest pain. Otherwise, if by any pleasure I be not allured, and if I have other direction than my genuine and free will, I am nothing worth, and I can never fadge well: for I am at such a stay, that except for health and life, there is nothing I will take the paines to fret my self about, or will purchase at so high a rate as to trouble my wits for it, or be constrained thereunto. ------ Tanti mihi non sit opaci Omnis arena Tagi, quodgue in mare volvitur aurum. -- Juven. Sat. iii. 54. So much I weigh not shadow Tagus sande, Nor gold that roules into the Sea from land. I am extreamelie lazie and idle, and exceedingly free, both by nature and art. I would as willingly lend my blood as my care. I have a mind free and altogether her own; accustomed to follow her own humor. And to this day never had, nor commanding, nor forced master. I have gon as far, and kept what pace pleased me best: which has enfeebled and made me unprofitable to serve others, and made me fit and apt, but only for my self. And as for me, no man ever needed to force this heavy, lither, and idle nature of mine; for, having even from my birth found my self in such a degree of fortune, have found occasion to stay there (an occasion notwitlistanding, that a thousand others of mine acquaintance would have taken as a plancke to pass over to search, to agitation, and to unquietness.) And as I have sought for nothing, so I have taken nothing. Non agimur tumidis venus Aquilone secundo, Non tamen adversis ætatem ducimus austris: Viribus, ingenio, specte, virtute, loco, re, Extremi primorum, extremis usque priores. -- Hor. ii. Epist. ii. 201. With full sailes prosp’rous winde, we do not drive, Nor yet with winde full in our teeth do live. In strength, in wit, in virtue, shape, goods, place, Last of the first, before the last we pace. I have had no need but of sufficiencie to content my self, which being well taken is ever a regiment for the mind, equally difficult in all sorts of conditions; and which by use we see more easily found in want than in plenty; perhaps, because that according to the course of our other passions, the greedinesse of riches is more sharpened by their uses than by their need: and the virtue of moderation more rare than that of patience. And I have had no need but to enjoy those goods quietly, which God of his bounty had bestowed upon me. I have tasted no kind of tedious trouble. I have seldom mannaged other than my own business: or if I have, it has been on condition I might do it at my leisure, and according to my will, committed unto me, by such as trusted me and knew me well, and would not importune me. For the skilfull rider will reape some service of a restie and wind-broken jade. My very child-hood. has been directed by a soft, mild, gentle and free fashion, and ever exempted from rigorous subjection. Al which has endowed me with a delicate kind of complexion, and made me incapable of any care: So that I love men should conceal my losses from me and the disorders which concerne me. In the chapter of my charges and expences, I have set down, what my negligence or carelessnesse costs me, both to feed and entertaine my self. ------ hæc nempe super sunt, Quæ dominum fallant, quæ prosint furibus. -- Hor. i. Epist. vi. 45. This remnant of accompts I have, Which may deceive Lords, help a Knave. I love not to know an accompt of what I have, that I may less exactly feel my losses: I desire those that live with me, where they want affection or good effects, to cozen and pay me with good apparances. For want of sufficient constancy to endure the importunity of contrary or crosse accidents, whereunto we are subject; and because I cannot alwaies keep my self prepared to governe and order my affairs as much as I am able, I foster this opinion in me, relying wholly upon fortune, and ready to take everything at the worst, and resolve to bear that worst mildly and patiently. About that only do I busie my self, and to that end do I direct all my discourses. In any dangerous matter I care not so much how I may avoide it, and how little it importeth whether I avoid it or no; and what were it if would continue in it? Being unable to direct events I governe my self; and if they apply not themselves to me, I apply my self to them: I have no great art to shunne fortune, and how to scape or force it, and with wisdom to addresse matters to my liking: I have also less sufferance to endure the sharpe and painefull care which belongeth to that. And the most toilsome state for me is to be doubtful in matters of weight, and agitated between fear and hope. To deliberate, be it but in slight matters, does importune me. And I feel my spirit more perplexed to suffer the motions of doubt and shakings of consultation, than to be settled and resolved about any accident whatsoever after the chance is once cast. Fewe passions have troubled my sleepe but of deliberations the least does trouble it. Even as of high-waies, I willingly seek to avoid the down-hanging and slippery, and take the beaten-path, though myrie and deepe, so I may go no lower, and there seek I safetie. So love I pure mishapes, and which exercise and turmoile me no more, after the uncertaintie of their mending: and which even at the first cast, drive me directly into sufferance. ------ dubiæ plus torquent mala. -- Sen. Agam. act. iii. sc. i. 29. Evils yet in suspence, Doe give us more offence. In events, I carry my self man-like; in the conduct childishly. The horror of a fall does more hurt me than the blow. The play is not worth the candle. The covetous man has a worse reckoning of his passion than the poore; and the jealous man than the cuckold. And it is often less harme for one to loose his farme, than pleade and wrangle for it: the slowest march is the safest. It is the seate of constancy. Therein you have no need but of yourselfe. There she takes her footing and wholly resteth upon herself. This example of a gentleman, whom many have known, has it not some Philosophicall show? This man having passed all his youth like a good fellow, a jollie companion, a great talker, and a merry ladd, being now well in years, would needs be married. Remembring himself how much the subject of cuckoldry had given him cause to speak and scoff at others; to put himself under covert-baron, he took him a wife from out that place where all men may have them for money, and with her made his alliance: good morrow whoore, good morrow cuckold. And there is nothing wherewith he oftener and more openly entertained such as came unto him, than with this tale: whereby he bridled the secret pratlings of mockers, and blunted the point of their reproch. Concerning ambitious which is next neighbor, or rather daughter, to presumption, it had been needfull (to advance me) that fortune had come to take me by the hand: for to put in my self into any care for an uncertaine hope, and to submit my self to all difficulties, waiting on such as seek to thrust themselfe into credite and reputation, in the beginning of their progresse I could never have done it. ------ Spem pretio non emo, -- Ter. Adel. act. ii. sc. 2. Expence of present pay For hope, I do not lay. I fasten myself on that which I see and hold, and go not far from the shore: Alter remus aquas, alter tibi radat arenas. -- Prop. iii. El. 23. Keeps water with one oar, With the other grate the shore. Beside,s a man seldom comes to these preferments but in hazarding first his own: and I am of opinion if that which a man has sufficeth to maintaine the condition wherein he was borne and brought up, it is folly to let it go upon the uncertainety of encreasing the same. He to whom fortune refuseth means to settle his estate and establish a quiet and reposed being is excusable if he cast what he has at hazards since thus as well as thus necessitie sends him to shift and search out. [R]apienda rebus in malis preceps via est. -- Sen. Agam. act. ii. sc. i. 47. A headlong course is best, When mischiefes are addrest. And I rather excuse a younger brother to make sale of his inheritance than him who has the honor of his house in charge, who cannot fall into wants but through his default. I have by the counsell of my good friends of former times found the way shorter and easier to rid my self of this desire and keep my self husht: Cui sit conditio dulcis, sine pulvere palmæ. -- Hor. i. Epist. i. 51. Who like it well to bear the prise, But take no toile in any wise. Judging also rightly of my forces that they were not capable of great matters: and remembering the saying of Lord Oliver, whilome Chancellor of France, who said that Frenchmen might be compared to apes, who, climbing up a tree, never cease skipping from bough to bough, till they come to the highest, where they show their bare tailes. Turpe est quod nequeat capiti committere pondus, Et pressum inflexo mox dare terga genu. -- Prop. iii. Ele. viii. 5. ’Tis shame, more than it can well bear, on head to packe, And thereby soone oppress’t with bended knee flie backe. Such qualities as are now in me void of reproach, in that age I deemed unprofitable. The facilitie of my maners had been named faintnesse and weakness, faith and conscience would have been thought scrupulous and so superstitious: liberty and freedome, importunate, inconsiderate, and rash. Misfortune serveth to some purpose. It is not amiss to be born in a much depraved age for in comparison of others, you are judged vertuous, very cheape. In our dayes he that is but a parricide, or a sacrilegious person, is a man of honesty and honor. Nunc si depositum non inficiatur amicus, Si reddat veterem cum tota æruigine follem, Prodigiosa fides, et Thuscis digna libellis, Quæque coronata lustrari debeat agna. -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 60. If now a friend deny not what was laid in trust, If wholly he restore th’old bellowes with their rust: A wondrous trust, to be in chronicles related, And should with sacrifice, as strange, be expiated. And never was there time or place wherein more assured and great reward was proposed unto Princes for goodnesse and justice. The first that shall be advised by these means to thrust himself into favor and credit, I am much deceived if in part of paiment he get not the start of his fellowes. Force and violence can do very much, but, never all. We see merchants, country justices, and artificers to march cheeke by jowl with our nobility in valor and militarie discipline. They performe honorable combates, both public and private. They batter and defend townes and cities in our present wars. A Prince smothereth his commendation amid this throng. Let him shine over others with humanities, with truth, loyalties temperance, and above all with justice, markes now adaies rare, unknown, and exiled. It is only the peoples will wherewith he may effect what he pleaseth: and no other qualities can allure their will so much as they as being the profitablest for them: Nihil est tam populare quam bonitas. ’Nothing is so popular as goodnesse is.’ By this proposition I had been a rare great man as by that of certain ages past I am now a pigmey and popular man; in which it was common. If stronger qualities did not concurre with all, to see a man temperate in his revenges, mild in revenging of offences, religious in keeping of his word, neither double nor over tractable, nor applying his faith to others will, or to every occasion. I would rather let all affairs go to wracke than breake my word for their avail. For touching this new-found virtue of faining and dissimulation, which now is so much in credit, I hate it to the death: and of all vices I find none that so much witnesseth demissenesse and basenesse of heart. It is a coward and servile humor for a man to disguise and bide himself under a maske, and not dare to show himself as he is. Thereby our men address themselves to trecherie: being trained to utter false words, they make no conscience to breake them. A generous mind ought not to belie his thoughts, but, make show of his inmost parts: there all is good, or at least all is humane. Aristotle thinkes it an office of magnanimity to hate and love openly, to judge and speak with all liberty, and never (though prise of truth go on it) to make esteeme either of the approbation or reprobation of others. Appolonius said it was for servants to lie, and for free-men to speak truth. It is the chief and fundamentall part of virtue. Shee must be loved for her own sake. He that speaks truth because he is bound to do so, and for that he serveth, and that feares not to tell a lie when it little importeth another man, is not sufficiently true. My mind of her own complexion detesteth falsehood and hateth to think on it. I feel an inward bashfulnes and a stinging remorse if at any time it scape me, as sometimes it does if unpremeditated occasions surprise me. A man must not alwaies say all he knowes, for that were folly: but what a man speaks ought to be agreeing to his thoughts, otherwise it is impiety. I know not what benefit they expect that ever faine, and so uncessantly dissemble: except it be not to be beleeved, even when they speak truly. That may deceive men once or twice, but to make a profession to cary it away smoothly, and as some of our Princes have done, to boast that if their shirt were privie to their secret and true cogitations, they would burne it: which was the saying of ancient Metellus Macedonicus and that he who cannot dissemble cannot reign, serves but only to warne those who have to deale with them, that what they say is but untruth and dissimulation: Quo quis versutior et callidior est hoe invisior et suspectior, detracta opinione probitatis: (Cic. Off. i.) ’The finer-headed and more subtle-brained a man is, the more is he hated and suspected if once the opinion of honesty be taken from him.’ It were great simplicity for a man to suffer himself to be mis-led either by the looks or wordes of him that outwardly professeth what he is not inwardly, as did Tiberius. And I know not what share such people may challenge in the commerce of men, never producing any thing that may be taken for good paiment. He who is disloyall to truth is likewise false against lying. Such as in our days; in the establishing of a Princes dutie, have only considered the good and felicitie of his affairs, and preferred the same before the respect of his faith and conscience, would say something to a Prince whose affairs fortune has so disposed that with once breaking and falsifying of his word he might for ever confirme and establish them. But it goeth otherwise. A man may more than once come to such a bargaine. A man during his life concludeth more than one peace or treatie. The commodity or profit that inviteth them to the first disloyalty (and daily some offer themselves, as to all other trecheries), sacrileges, murders, rebellions, treasons, are undertaken for some kind of profit. But this first gain brings ever infinite losses and dangers with it: casting this Prince from-out all commerce and means of negotiation by the example of this infidelitie. Soliman of the Ottomans race (a race little regarding the keeping of promises or performance of covenants), at what time he caused his army to land at Otranto (I being then but a child), having known that Mercurin of Gratinara, and the inhabitants of Castro, were detained prisoners after the town was yielded, contrary to that which by his captaines had been capitulated with them, he sent word they should be released, and that having otherweighty enterprises in hand in that country, such disloyalty, although it had apparance of great and present benefit, yet in time to come it would bring a distrust and reproch of infinite prejudice. As for me, I had rather be importunate and indiscreet than a flatterer and a dissembler. I allow a man may entermingle some point of fiercenesse and wilfulnesse to keep himself so entire and open as I am, without consideration of others. And me seems I become a little more free where I should be less, and that by the opposition of respect I grow earnest. It may also be that for want of art I follow my own nature. Presenting to the greater sort the very same licence of speech and boldnes of countenance that I bring from my house: I perceive how much it inclineth towards indiscretion and incivilitie. But although I be so fashioned, my spirit is not sufficiently yielding to avoid a sudden question, or to scape it by some winding, nor to dissemble a truth, nor have I memory able to continue it so feigned, nor assurance sufficient to maintaine it; and I play the braggard through feeblenesse. And therefore I apply my self to ingenuitie, and ever to speak truth and what I think; both by complexion and by intention; leaving the success thereof unto fortune. Aristippus said that the chiefest commoditie he reaped by philosophy was, that he spake freely and sincerely to all men. Memory is an instrument of great service, and without which, judgement wil hardly discharge his duty, wherof I have great want. What a man will propose unto me, he must do it by peecemeales: for, to answer to a discourse that has many heads, lieth not in my power. I cannot receive a charge, except I have my writing tables about me: and if I must remember a discourse of any consequence, be it of any length, I am driven to this vile and miserable necessitie, to learne every word I must speak by rote; otherwise I should never do it well or assuredly, for fear my memory should in my greatest need faile me; which is very hard unto me, for I must have three hours to learne three verses. Moreover, in any long discourse, the liberty or authority to remoove the order, to change a word, uncessantly altering the matter, makes it more difficult to be confirmed in the authors memory. And the more I distrust it, the more it troubleth me. It serveth me better by chance, and I must carelesly sollicite her, for if I urge her, she is astonished; and if it once beginne to waver, the more I sound her, the more entangled and intricate she proveth. She wil wait upon me when she list, not when I please. And what I feel in my memories I feel in many other parts of mine. I eschew cornmandement, duty, and compulsion. What I do easily and naturally, if I resolve to do it by express and prescribed appointment, I can then do it no more. Even in my body, those parts that have some liberty, and more particular jurisdiction, do sometimes refuse to obey me if at any time I appoint and enjoine them to do me some necessarie services. This forced and tyrannical preordinance does reject them, and they either for spight or fear shrinke and are quailed. Being once in a place where it is reputed a barbarous discourtesy not to pledge those that drinke to you, where although I were used with al liberty, in favor of certain ladies that were in company, according to the fashion of the country, I would needs play the good fellow. But it made us all mery; for the threats and preparation, that I should force my self beyond my natural custom, did in such sort stop and stuffe my throat, that I was not able to swallow one drop, and was barr’d of drinking all the repast. I found my self glutted and ful of drink by the overmuch swilling that my imagination had fore-conceived. This effect is more apparant in those whose imagination is more vehement and strong: yet it is natural: and there is no man but shall sometimes have a feeling of it. An excellent archer being condemned to death, was offered to have his life saved if he would but show any notable trial of his profession, refused to make proofe of it; fearing lest the contention of his will should make him to misse-direct his hand, and that in lieu of saving his life, he might also lose the reputation he had gotte in shooting in a bow. A man whose thoughts are busie about other matters, shall very near within an inch keep and alwaies hit one self same number and measure of paces, in a place where he walketh; but if heedily he endeavor to measure and count them, he shall find that what he did by nature and chance, he cannot do it so exactly by desseign. My library (which, for a countrey library, may pass for a very fair one) is seated in a corner of my house: if any thing come into my mind, that either I must go seek or write in it, for fear I should forget it in crossing of my court, I must desire some other body to remember the same for me. If speaking, I embolden my self never so little to digresse from my discourse, I do ever lose it; which makes me to keep my self in my speech, forced, near and close. Those that serve me, I must ever call them either by their office or countrey: for I find it very hard to remember names. Well may I say it has three syllables, that its sound is harsh, or that it beginneth or endeth with such a letter. And should I live long, I doubt not but I might forget my own name, as some others have done heretofore. Messala Corvinus lived two yeeres without any memory at all, which is also reported of George Trapezoncius. And for my own interest, I do often ruminate what manner of life theirs was, and whether wanting that part, I shall have sufficient to maintaine my self in any good sort: which looking near unto I fear that this defect, if it be perfe ct, shall lose all the functions of my soul. Plenus rimarum sum, hac atque illac perfluo. -- Ter. Eun. act. i. sc. 2. I am so full of holes, I cannot hold, I run out ev’ry way, when tales are told. It has often befallen me to forget the word which but three hours before I had either given or received of another, and to forget where I had laid my purse; let Cicero say what he list. I helpe my self to loose what I particularly locke up. Memoria certe non modo philosophiam, sed omnis vitæ usum, omnesque artes una maxime continet: ’Assuredly memory alone, of all other things, compriseth not only philosophy, but the use of our whole life, and all the sciences.’ Memorie is the receptacle and the case of knowledge. Mine being so weake, I have no great cause to complain if I know but little. I know the names of Arts in general, and what they treate of, but nothing further, I turn and tosse over bookes, but do not studie them; what of them remaines in me is a thing which I no longer acknowledge to be any bodies else. Only by that has my judgement profited: and the discourses and imaginations wherewith it is instructed and trained up. The authours, the place, the words; and other circumstances, I sodainly forget: and am so excellent in forgetting, that as much as any thing else I forget my own writings and compositions. Yea, my own sayings are every hand-while alleadged against my self, when God wot I perceive it not. He that would know of me, whence or from whom the verses or examples which here I have hudled up are taken, should greatly put me to my shifts, and I could hardly tell it him. Yet have I not begged them, but at famous and very well knowen gates, which though they were rich in themselves, did never please me, unless they also came from rich and honorable hands, and that authority concurre with reason. It is no great marvell if my book follow the fortune of other bookes, and my memory forgo or forget as well what I write as what I read: and what I give as well as what I receive. Besides the defect of memory, I have others, which much further my ignorance. My wit is dull and slow, the least cloud dimmeth it, so that (for example sake) I never proposed riddle unto it (were it never so easy) that it was able to expound. There is no subtilitie so vain but confounds me. In games wherein wit may bear a part, as of chesse, of card, of tables, and others, I could never conceive but the common and plainest draughts. My apprehension is very sluggish and gloomy; but what it once holdeth the same it keepeth fast: and for the time it keepes it, the same it embraceth generally, strictly, and deepely. My sight is quick, sound, perfect, and far-seeing, but easily wearied if much charged or emploied. By which occasion I can have no great commerce with books but by others service which read unto me. Plinie the younger can instruct those tha thave tried it, how much this fore- slowing importeth those that give themselves to this occupation. There is no spirit so wretched or so brutish wherein some particular facultie is not seen to shine; and none so low buried, but at one hole or other it will sally out sometimes. And how it commeth to pass that a mind blinde and slumbering in all other things, is in some particular effects, lively, clear, and excellent, a man must inquire of cunning masters. But those are the fair spirits which are universall, open and readie to all, if not instructed, at least to be instructed. Which I alleage to accuse mine: for, be it either through weakenesse, or retchlessenesse (and to be carelesse of that which lieth at our feet, which we have in our hands, which neerest concerneth the use of life, is a thing far from my dogma or doctrine) there is none so simple or so ignorant as mine, in diverse such common matters, and of which, without imputation or shame, a man should never be ignorant; whereof I must needs tell some examples. I was borne and brought up in the countrie, and amidst husbandry: I have since my predecessours quit me the place and possession of the goods I enjoy, both business and husbandry in hand, I cannot yet cast account either with penne or counters. There are diverse of our French coines I know not: nor can I distinguish of one graine from another, be it in the field or in the barne, unless it be very apparant: nor do I scarcely know the difference betweene the cabige or letuce in my garden. I understand not the names of the most usual tooles about husbandrie, nor of the meanest principles of tillage, which most children know. I was never skilfull in mechanicall arts, nor in traffike or knowledge of merchandise, nor in the diversitie and nature of fruits, wines, or cates, nor can I make a hawke, physike a horse, or teach a dogge. And since I must make ful show of my shame or ignorance, it is not yet a moneth since that I was found to be ignorant wherto leven served to make bread withal; or what it was to cunne wine. The Athenians were anciently wont to think him very apt for the mathematikes, that could cunningly order or take up a faggot of brushe wood. Verily a man might drawe a much contrary conclusion from me: for let me have all that may belong to a kitchin, yet shall I be ready to starve for hunger. By these parts of my confession one may imagine diverse others to my cost and detriment. But however I make myself known, alwaies provided it be as I am, indeed I have my purpose. And I excuse not my self that I dare set down in writing so base and frivolous matters as these. The basenesse of the subject forceth me thereunto. Let who so list accuse my project, but not my progresse. So it is that without being warned of others I see very well how little this weigheth or is worth, and I perceive the fondnesse of my purpose. It is sufficient that my judgement is not dismayed or distracted, whereof these be the Essaies. Nasutus sis usque licet, sis denique nasus Quantum noluerit ferre rogatus Atlas: Et possis ipsum tu deridere Latinum, Non potes, in nugas dicere plura meas, Ipse ego quam dixi; quid dentem dente juvabit Rodere? carne opus est, si satur esse velis Ne perdas operam, qui se mirantur, in illos Virus habe, nos hæc novimus es se nihil. Mart. xiii. Epig. ii. 1. Suppose you were long-nos’d, suppose such nose you weare As Atlas, if you should intreat him, would not bear, That you in flouting old Latinus can be fine. Yet can you say no more about these toyes of mine, Then I have said; what boote, tooth with a tooth to whet? You must have fleshe, if you to glut your self be set. Loose not your paines; ’gainst them who on themselves are doting Keepe you your sting: we know these things of ours are nothing. I am not bound to utter no follies so I be not deceived to know them: and wittingly to erre is so ordinary in me that I erre not much otherwise; and seldom erre casually. It is a small matter to yield the foolish actions unto the rashnesse of my humors since I cannot warrant my self ordinarily to yield them the vicious. Being at Barleduc I saw for the commendation of Renate the King of Sicilies memory a picture which with his own hands he ha d made of himself, presented unto our King Francis the second: why is it not as lawfull for every man else to portray himself with his pen, as it was for him to do it with a pensell? I wil not then forget this blemish, unfit to be seen of all. That is irresolution, a most incommodious defect in the negotiation of worldly affairs: I cannot resolve in matters admitting doubtfulnesse: Ne si, ne no, nel cuor mi suona intiero. -- Petr. pa. i. son. cxxxviii. 8. Nor indeed, nor nay, sounds clearely in my heart. I can maintaine an opinion, but not make choice of it: for in Humane things what side soever a man leaneth on, many apparences prevent themselves unto us, which confirm us in them: and Chrysippus the Philosopher was wont to say that he would learne nothing else of his maisters, Zeno and Cleanthes, but their doctrines simply: for proofes and reasons he would find enough of himself. Let me turn to what side I will, I ever find sufficient matter and liklyhood to keep my self unto it. Thus keep I doubt and liberty to my self, to chuse, until occasion urge me, and then (to confesse the truth), as the common saying is, I cast my feather to the wind, and yield to fortunes mercy. A very light inclination and a slender circumstance carries me away. Dum in dubio est animus paulo momento huc atque illuc impellitur. -- Ter. And. act. i. sc. 3. While mind is in suspence, with small ado, ’Tis hither, thither, driven fro and to. The uncertainty of my judgement is in many occurrences so equally balanced as I would willingly compromise it to the deciding of chance and of the dice. And I note with great consideration of our humane imbecilities the examples which the history of God it self has left us of this use, to remit the determination of elections in doubtfull matters unto fortune and hazard. Sors cecidit super Matthiam: (Act. i. 26) ’The lot fell upon Matthias.’Humane reason is a two-edged dangerous sword; even in Socrates his hand, her most inward and familiar friend, marke what a many-ended staffe it is. So am I only fit to follow, and am easily carried away by the throng. I do not greatly trust my own strength, to undertake to command or to lead. I rejoice to see my steps traced by others. If I must run the hazard of an uncertaine choice, I would rather have it be under such a one who is more assured of his opinions, and more wedded to them, then I am of mine; the foundation and platforme of which I find to be very slippery; yet am I not very easy to change, forasmuch as I perceive a like weaknesse in contrary opinions. Ipsa consuetudo assentiendi periculosa esse videtur, et lubrica: (Cic. Acad. Qu. iv.) ’The very custom of assenting seems hazardous and slippery:’ Namely in politick affairs, wherein is a large field open to all motions, and to contestation: Iusta pari premitur veluti cum pondere libra, Prona nec hac plus parte sedet, nec surgit ab illa. -- Tibulla iv. hero. v. 41. As when an even skale with equall weight is peized, Nor falles it down this way, or is it that way raised. As for example, Machiavels discourses were very solid for the subject: yet has it been very easy to impugne them, and those that have done have left no less facilitie to impugne theirs. A man might ever find answeres enough to such an argument, both rejoynders, double, treble, quadruple, with this infinite contexture of debates, that our petty-foggers have wrye-drawne and wrested as much as ever they could in favor of their pleas and processes: Cædimur, et totidem plagis consumimus hostem. -- Hor. ii. Epist. ii. 97. We by our foes are beaten, if not slain, We with as many strokes waste them again; Reasons having no other good ground than experience, and the diversity of humane events presenting us with infinite examples of all manner of formes. A wise man of our times says that where our Almanakes say warme should a man say cold, and in lieu of drie, moyst; and ever set down the contrary of what they foretell; were he to lay a wager of one or others successes he would not care what side he took, except in such things as admit no uncertaintie; as to promise extreme heat at Christmas, and exceeding cold at Midsomer. The like I think of these politike discourses. What part soever you are put unto, you have as good a game as your fellow: provided you affront not the apparant and plain principles. And therefore (according to my humor) in public affairs there is no course so bad (so age and constancy be joined unto it) that is not better then change and alteration. Our manners are exceedingly corrupted, and with a marvellous inclination bend towards worse and worse. Of our laws and customs many are barbarous, and diverse monstrous; notwithstanding, by reason of the difficultie to reduce us to better estate, and of the danger of this subversion, if I could fix a pegge into our wheel and stay it where it now is, I would willingly do it. -----nunquam adeo foedis adeoque pudendis Ultimur exemplis, ut non peiora suiper sint. -- Juven. Sat. viii. 183. Examples of so filthy shamefull kind We never use, but worse remaines behind. Instabilitie is the worst I find in our state, and that our laws, no more than our garments, can take no setled form. It is an easy matter to accuse a state of imperfection, since all mortal things are full of it. As easy is it to beget in a people a contempt of his ancient observances: No man ever undertook it, but came to an end: But to establish a better state in place of that which is condemned and raced out, diverse who have attempted it have shro nk under the burden. Touching my conduct, my wisdom has small share therein. I am very easily to be directed by the worlds public order. Oh happy people that does what is commanded, better then they which command, without vexing themselves about causes; which suffer themselves gently to be rowled on, according to the heavens rowling. Obedience is never pure and quiet in him who talketh, pIeadeth, and contendeth. In some (to return to my self) the only matter for which I make some accompt of my self is that wherein never man did think himself defective. My commendation is vulgar, common, and popular; for who ever thought he wanted wit? It were a proposition which in itself would imply contradiction. It is an infirmity that is never where it is seen, it is very strong and fast-holding, but yet pierced and dissipated by the first beame of the patients sight, as does the sunnes raies scatter and disperse a gloomie mist. For a man to accuse himself were to excuse himself of that subject; and to condemne himself, an absolving of himself. There was never so base a porter, nor so silly a woman, but thought he had sufficient wit for his provision. We easily know in others the advantage of courage, of bodily strength, of experience of disposition, and of beauties but we never yield the advantage of judgement to any body: and the reasons which part from the simple’natural discourse in others, we th inke that had we but looked that way, we had surely found them. The skill, the knowledge, the stile, and such like parts which we see in strange workes, we easily perceive whether they exceed ours; but the meere productions of wit and understanding every man deemeth it lyeth in him to meete with the very like, and does hardly perceive the weight and difficultie of it, except (and that very scarcelv) in an extreme and incomparable distance. And he that should clearely see the height of a strangers judgement, would come and bring his unto it. Thus is it a kind of exercising whereof a man may hope but for meane commendation and small praise, and a manner of composition of little or no harme at all. And then for whom do you write? The wiser sort, unto whom belongeth bookish jurisdiction, know no other price but of doctrine, and avow no other proceeding in our wits but that of erudition and art. If you have mistaken one Scipio for an other, what of any worth have you left to speak of? He that is ignorant of Aristotle (according to them) he is therewithall ignorant of himself. Popular and shallow- beaded mindes cannot perceive the grace or comelinesse, nor judge of a smooth and quaint discourse. Now these two kindes possess the world. The third, unto whose share you fall, of regular wits, and that are strong of themselves, is so rare that justly it has neither name or rank amongst us; he loses halfe his time that does aspire or endeavour to please it. It is commonly said that the justest portion nature has given us of the graces is that of sense and understanding: for there is no man but is contented with the share she has allotted him. Is it not reason? He who should see beyond that, should see further then his sight. I persuade my self to have good and sound opinions: but who is not so persuaded of his own: One of the best trials I have of it is the small esteeme I make of myself: for had they not been well assured they would easily have suffered themselves to be deceived by the affection I bear unto my self, singular, as he who bring it almost all unto my self, and that spill but a little besides. All that which others distribute thereof unto an infinite number of acquaintances, to their glory and greatness, I refer to the repose of my spirit and to myself. What else where escapes of it is not properly by the appointment of my discourse: ----- mihi nempe valere et vivere doctus. Well learn’d in what concerneth me, To live, and how in health to be. As for my opinions, I find them infinitely bold and constant to condemne mine insufficiencies. And to say truth, it is a subject whereabout I exercise my judgement as much as about any other. The world looks ever for right, I turn my sight inward, there I fix it, there I ammuse it. Every man looks before himself, I looke within my self: I have no busines but with my self. I uncessantly consider, controle and taste my self: other men go ever else where if they think well on it: they go ever foreward. ------ nemo in sese tentat descendere. -- Pers. Sat. iv. 32. No man attempteth this Essay, Into himself to find the way. As for me, I roule me unto my self. This capacitie of sifting out the truth, what and however it be in me, and this free humor I have, not very easily to subject my beliefe, I owe especially unto my self, for the most constant and general imaginations I have are those which (as one would say) were borne with me: they are natural unto me, and wholy mine. I produced them raw and simple, of a hardy and strong production, but somewhat troubled and imperfect: which I have since established and fortified by the authority of others, and by the sound examples of ancients, with whom I have found my self conformable in judgement: those have assured me of my hold-fast of them, and have given me both the enjoying and possession thereof more absolute and more clear. The commendation which every man seekes after for a vivacitie and promptitude of wit, I chalenge the same by the order of a notable and far-sounding action, or of some particular sufficiencie; I pretend it by the order, correspondencie, and tranquillitie of opinions and customs. Omnino si quidquam est decorum, nihil est profecto magis quam æquabilitas universæ vitæ, tum singularum actionum: quam conservare non possis, sit aliorum nat uram imitans, omittas tuam: (Cic. Off. i.) ’Clearely if any thing be decent for a man, nothing is more than an even carriage and equability of his whole life, and every action therein: which you cannot uphold if following the nature of others you let pass your own.’ Behold here then how far forth I find my self guilty of that first part I said to be in the vice of presumption. Concerning the second, which consisteth in not esteeming sufficiently of others, I wot not whether I can so well excuse my self; for whatsoever it cost me, I intend to speak what is of it. It may be the continuall commerce I have with ancient humors, and the idea of those rich mindes of former ages does bring me out of liking and distaste both of others and of my self, or that in truth we live in an age which produces things but meane and indifferent. So it is that I know nothing worthy any great admiration. Also I know not many men so familiarly as I should to be able to judge of them: and those with whom the quality of my condition does ordinarily make me conversant are for the most part such as have little care for the manuring of the soul, and to whom nothing is proposed for chief felicitie but honor, and for absolute perfection but valor. Whatsoever I see or beauteous or worthy in any other man, I willingly commend and regard; indeed, and I often endeare my self with what I think of it, and allow my self to lie so far forth: for I cannot invent a false subject. I willingly witness with my friends what I find praise-worthy in them. And of an inch of valor, I willingly make an inch and a halfe; but to lend them qualities they have not, I cannot; and openly to defend their imperfections, I may not: indeed, be they mine enemies, I shall sincerely give them their due in witnessing their worth or honor. My affection may change; my judgement never. And I confound not my quarrell with other circumstances that are impertinent and belong not unto it. And I am so jealous of the liberty of my judgement, that for what passion soever I can hardly quit it. I wrong my self more in lying than him of whom I lie. This commendable and generous custom of the Persian nation is much noted; they speak very honourably and justly of their mortal enemies, and with those with whom they were at deadly fude and war, so far forth as the, merit of their virtue deserved. I know diverse men who have sundry noble and worthy parts; some wit, some courage, some dexteritie, some conscience, some a readinesse in speech, some one science, and some another: but of a great man in general, and that has so many excellent parts together, or but one in such a degree of excellencie as he may thereby be admired, or but compared to those of former ages whom we honor, my fortune has not permitted me to see one. And the greatest I ever knew living (I meane of natural parts of the mind, and the best borne) was Stephanusde la Boetie. Verily it was a compleat mind, and who set a good face and showed a fair countenance upon all matters; a mind after the old stampe, and which had fortune therewith been pleased, would no doubt have brought forth wondrous effects, having by skill and study added very much to his rich natural gifts. But I know not how it comes to pass, and surely it does so, there is, as much vanity and weakenesse of understanding found in those that professe to have most sufficiencie, that will entermeddle with learned vocations, and with the charges that depend of books, as in any sort of people; whether it be because there is more required and expected at their hands, and common faults cannot be excused in them, or that the self-opinion of knowledge emboldeneth them the more to produce and discover themselves over-forward, whereby they lose and betray themselves. As an artificer doeth more manifest his sottishnesse in a rich piece of work which he has in hand, if foolishly and against the rules of his trade he seek to apply it and entermeddle, than in a vile and base one; and men are more offended at a fault or oversight in a statue of gold than in one of clay. These do as much when they set foorth things which in themselves and in their place would be good; for they employ them without discretion, honouring their memory at the cost and charge of their understanding: and doing honor to Cicero, to Galen, to Ulpian, and to Saint Jerome to make themselves ridiculous. I willingly return to this discourse of the fondnesse of our institution: whose aime has been to make us not good and wittie, but wise and learned. She has attained her purpose. It has not taught us to follow virtue and embrace wisdom: but made an impression in us of its Etymologie and derivation. We can decline virtue, yet can we not love it. If we know not what wisdom is by effect and experience, we know it by prattling and by rote. We are not satisfied to know the race, the alliances, and the pedigrees of our neighbors, but we wil have them to be our friends and contract both conversation and intelligence with them: It has taught us the definitions, the divisions and distinctions of virtue, as of the surnames and branches of a genealogie, without having other care to contract practise of familiaritie or private acquaintance betweene us and it. She has appointed us for our learning, not bookes that have sounder and truer opinions, but volumes that speak the best Greeke or Latine; and amongst her choice words has made the vainest humors of antiquitie to glide into our conceits. A good institution changeth judgement and manners, as it hapned to Polemon. This dissolute young Græcian going one day by chance to hear a lecture of Xenocrates, where he not only marked the eloquence and sufficiencie of the reader, and brought not home the knowledge of some notable thing, but a more apparant and solid fruit, which was the sodaine change and amendment of his former life. Who ever heard such an effect of our discipline? ------ faciasne quod olim Nutatus Polemon, ponas insignia morbi Fasciolas, cubital, focalia? Potus ut ille Dicitur ex collo furtim carpsisse coronas, Postquam est impransi correptus voce magistri? -- Hor. Ser. ii. Sat. iii. 253. Can you do as did Polemon reformed, Cast-off your sicknes signes, which you deformed, Your bolsters, mufflers, swathes? As he drink-linde, His drunken garland covertly declinde, By speech of fasting reader disciplinde? The least disdainful condition of men, me thinkes, is that which through simplicitie holds the last rank, and offereth us more regular commerce. The customs and discourses of countrie-clownish-men, I find them commonly to be more conformable and better disposed, according to the true prescription of Philosophie, then are those of our Philosophers. Plus sapit vulqus, quia tantum, quantum opus cut, sapit: ’The vulgar is the wiser, because it is but as wise as it must needs.’ The worthiest men I have judged by eternall apparances (for, to judge them after my fashion, they should be sifted nearer) concerning war and military sufficiencie have been, the Duke of Guise, that died before Orleans, and the whilom Marshal Strozzi: For men extraordinarily sufficient and endowed with no vulgar virtue, Oliver and L’Hospitall, both great Chancelors of France. Poesie has likewise in mine opinion had her vogue and credit in our age. We have store of cunning and able men in that profession: Aurate, Beza, Buchanan, L’Hospital, Mont-dore, and Turnebus. As for French-men, I think they have attained the highest degree of perfection that can or ever shall be, and in those parts wherein Ronsart and excellent Bellay have written, I think they are not far short of the ancient perfection. Adrianus Turnebus knew more, and better what he knew, than any man in his age or of many ages past. The lives of the late Duke of Alva and our Constable Mommorencie have been very noble, and have had sundrie rare resemblancies of fortune. But the worthily-fair and glorious death of the last in the full sight of Paris and of his King, for their service against his nearest friends and alliance in the front of an army, victorious through his conduct of it, and with an handstroke in that old age of his, deserveth in mine opinion to be placed and registred amongst the most renouned and famous accidents of my times. As also the constant goodness, the mildnes in behaviour, and conscionable fecility of Monsieur de la Noue in such an injustice of armed factions (a very schoole of treason, of inhumanitie and brigandage) wherein he was ever brought up, a worthie and famous man of war and most experienced in his profession . I have greatly pleased my self in publishing in sundrie places the good hope I have of Marie de Gournay le Jars, my daughter in alliance, and truely of me beloved with more then a fatherly love, and as one of the best parts of my being enfeofed in my home and solitariness. There is nothing in the world I esteem more then her. If child-hoode may presage any future successes her mind shal one day be capable of many notable things, and amongst others, of the perfection of this thrice-sacred amitie whereunto we read not, her sex could yet attaine; the sinceritie and soliditie of her demeanors are therein already sufficient; her kind affection towards me is more than superabounding and such indeede as nothing more can be wished unto it, so that the apprehension which she has of my aproching end, by reason of the fiftie five years wherein her hap has been to know me, would somewhat less cruelly trouble her. The judgement she made of my first Essayes, being a woman of this age so yong, alone where she dwelleth, and the exceeding vehemence wherewith she loved me and long time by the only esteem which before ever she saw me, she had by them conceived of me she desired me, is an accident most worthy consideration. Other vertues have had little or no currantnesse at all in this age: but valor is become popular by reason of our civill wars, and in this part there are minds found amongst us very constant, even to perfection and in great number, so that the choice is impossible to be made. See here what hitherto I have knowen of any extraordinary and not common greatness. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XVIII: OF GIVING THE LIE CHAPTER XVIII: OF GIVING THE LIE EA but, will some tell me, this design in a man to make himself a subject to write of might be excused in rare and famous men, and who by their reputation had bred some desire in others of their acquaintance. It is true, I confesse it, and I know that a handicraftsman will scarcely looke off his work to gaze upon an ordinary man: whereas to see a notable great person come into a town, he will leave both work and shop. It ill-beseemeth any man to make himself knowen, only he excepted that has somewhat in him worthy imitation, and whose life and opinions may stand as a pattern to all. Cæsar and Xenophon have had wherewithall to ground and establish their narration in the greatness of their deedes as on a just and solid groundwork. So are the jornall bookes of Alexander the great, the Commentaries which Augustus, Cato, Brutus, Sylla, and diverse others had left of their gests, greatly to be desired. Such mens images are both beloved and studied, be they either in brasse or stone. This admonition is most true, but it concerneth me very little. Non recito cuiquam: nisi amicis, idque rogatus, Non ubivis, coramve quibuslibet. In medio qui Scripta foro recitant sunt multi, quique lavantes. -- Hor. Ser. i. Sat. iv. 73. My writings I read not, but to my friends, to any, Nor each-where, nor to all, nor but desir’d, yet many In market-place read theirs, In bathes, in barbers-chaires. I erect not here a statue to be set up in the marketplace of a town, or in a church, or in any other public place: Non equidem hoc studeo bullatis ut mihi nugis Pagina turgescat: ---- Pers. Sat. v. 19. I studie not, my written leaves should grow Big-swolne with bubled toyes, which vain breathes blow. Secreti loquimur. --- 21. We speak alone, Or one to one. It is for the corner of a Library, or to ammuse a neighbour, a kinsman, or a friend of mine withall, who by this image may happily take pleasure to renew acquaintance and to reconverse with me. Others have been emboldned to speak of themselves because they have found worthy add rich subject in themselves. 1, contrariwise, because I have found mine so barren and so shallow, that it cannot admit suspition of ostentation. I willingly judge other mens actions; of mine by reason of their nullity, I give small cause to judge. I find not so much good in my self, but I may speak of it without blushing. Oh what contentment were it unto me to hear somebody that would relate the custom, the visage, the countenance, the most usual words, and the fortunes of my ancestors. Oh, how attentively would I listen unto it. Verily it were an argument of a bad nature, to seem to despise the very pictures of our friends and predecessors, the fashion of their garments and arms. I keep the writing, the manuall seale, and a peculiar sword: and I reserve still in my cabinet certain long switches or wands which my father was wont to carry in his hand. Paterna vestis et annulus, tanto charior est posteris, quanto erga parentes maior affectus: ’The fathers garment and his ring is so much more esteemed of his successors, as their affection is greater towards their progenitors.’ Notwithstanding if my posterity be of another mind, I shall have wherewith to be avenged, for they cannot make so little accompt of me, as then I shal do of them. All the commerce I have in this with the world is that I borrow the instruments of their writing, as more speedy and more easy; in requitall whereof I may perhaps hinder the melting of some piece of butter in the market or a grocer from selling an ounce of pepper. Ne toga cordyllis, ne penula desit olivis. -- Mart. xiii. Epig. i. I. Lest fish-fry should a fit gowne want, Lest cloakes should be for olives scant. Et laxas scombris sæpe dabo tunicas. -- Catul. Epig. Eleg. xxvii.8. To long-tail’d mackrels often I, Will side-wide (paper) cotes apply. And if it happen no man read me, have I lost my time to have entertained my self so many idle hours about so pleasing and profitable thoughts? In framing this pourtraite by my self, I have so often been faine to frizle and trimme me, that so I might the better extract my self that the patterne is thereby confirmed, and in some sort formed. Drawing my self for others, I have drawne my self with purer and better colours than were my first. I have no more made my book then my book has made me. A book consubstantiall to his author: a peculiar and fit occupation. A member of my life. Not of an occupation and end strange and forraine, as all other bookes. Have I mis-spent my time to have taken an account of my self so continually and so curiously? For those who only run themselves over by fantasie, and by speech for some hours, examine not themselves so primely and exactly, nor enter they into themselves, as he does who makes his studie his work, and occupation of it; who with all his might, and with all his credit, engageth himself to a register of continuance. The most delicious pleasures, though inwardly digested, shun to leave any trace of themselves, and avoide the sight not only of the people, but of any other. How often has this busines diverted me from tedious and yrksome cogitations? (and all frivolous ones must be deemed tedious and yrksome). Nature has endowed us with a large faculty to entertaine ourselves apart, and often calleth us unto it: to teach us that partly we owe ourselves unto society, but in the better part unto ourselves. To the end I may in some order and project marshall my fantasie even to dote and keep it from loosing and straggling in the aire, there is nothing so good as to give it a body and register so many idle imaginations as present themselves unto it. I listen to my humors and hearken to my conceits, because I must enroule them. How often, being grieved at some action, which civility and reason forbad me to with stand openly, have I disgorged my self upon them here, not-without an intent of public instruction? And yet these poeticall rods, Zon dessus l’oeil, zon sur le groin, Zon sur le dos du Sagoin, are also better imprinted upon paper than upon the quick flesh; what if I lend mine ears somewhat more attentively unto bookes, sith I but watch if I can filch something from them wherewith to enammell and uphold mine? I never studie to make a book, yet have I somewhat studied, because I had already made it (if to nibble or pinch, by the head or feet, now one Authour, and then another be in any sort to study), but nothing at all to form my opinions. Yea, being long since formed to assist, to second, and to serve them. But whom shall we believe, speaking of himself in this corrupted age? since there are few or none who may believe speaking of others, where there is less interest to lie. The first part of customs corruption is the banishment of truth: for, as Pindarus said, to be sincerely true is the beginning of a great virtue; and the first article Plato requireth in the Governor of his Commonwealth. Now adaies, that is not the truth which is true, but that which is persuaded to others. As we call money not only that which is true and good, but also the false; so it be currant. Our nation is long since taxed with this vice. For Salvianus Massiliensis, who lived in the time of Valentinian the Emperor, says that amongst French-men to lie and forsweare is no vice, but a manner of speach. He that would endeare this testimony might say, it is now rather deemed a virtue among them. Men frame and fashion themselves unto it as to an exercise of honor; for, dissimulation is one of the notablest qualities of this age. Thus have I often considered whence this custom might arise, which we observe so religiously, that we are more sharpely offended with the reproach of this vice, so ordinary in us, than with any other; and that it is the extremest injury may be done us in words, to upbraid and repoach us with a lie. Therein I find that it is natural for a man to defend himself most from such defects as we are most tainted with. It seems that if we but show a motion of revenge, or are but moved at the accusation, we in some sort discharge ourselves of the blame of imputation; if we have it in effect, at least we condemne it in apparance. May it not also be that this reproch seems to enfold cowardice and faintnesse of hart? Is there any more manifest than for a man to eate and deny his own word? What, to deny his word wittingly. To lie is a horrible filthy vice; and which an ancient writer setteth forth very shamefully, when he says that whosoever lieth witnesseth that he contemneth God and therewithall feareth men. It is impossible more richly to represent the horrour, the vilenesse and the disorder of it: for, what can be imagined so vile and base as to be a coward towards men and a boaster towards God? Our intelligence being only conducted by the way of the word: whoso falsifieth the same betraieth public society. It is the only instrument by means whereof our wils and thoughts are communicated: it is the interpretour of our soules: If that faile us, we hold ourselves no more, we enter-know one another no longer. If it deceive us, it breaketh al our commerce, and dissolveth al bonds of our policies. Certain Nations of the new Indiæs (whose names we need not declare, because they are no more, for the desolation of this conquest has extended itself to the absolute abolishing of names and ancient knowledge of places, with a marvellous and never the like heard example) offered humane blood unto their Gods, but no other than that which was drawne from their tongues and ears for an expiation of the sinne of lying as well heard as pronounced. That good fellow Græcian said children were dandled with toies, but men with words. Concerning the sundry fashions of our giving the lie, and the laws of our honor in that and the changes they have received, I wil refer to another time to speak what I think and know of it, and if I can I will in the meane time learne at what time this custom took his beginning, so exactly to weigh and precisely to measure words, and tie our honor to them: for it is easy to judge that it was not anciently amongst the Romans and Græcians. And I have often thought it strange to see them wrong and give one another the lie, and yet never enter into quarrell. The laws of their duty took some other course than ours. Cæsar is often called a thiefe, and sometimes a drunkard to his face. We see the liberty of their invectives, which they write one against another: I meane the greatest Chieftaines and Generals in war, of one and other nation, where words are only retorted and revenged with words, and never wrested to further consequence. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XIX: OF THE LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE CHAPTER XIX: OF THE LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE T IS ordinarily seen how good intentions, being managed without moderation, thrust men into most vicious effects. In this controversie, by which France is at this instant molested with eivill wars, the best and safest side is no doubt that which maintained both the ancient religion and policy of the country. Nevertheless amongst the honest men that follow it (for my meaning is not to speak of those who use them as a colour, either to exercise their particular revenges, or to supply their greedy avarice, or to follow the favor of Princes: but of such as do it with a true zeale towards their religion, and an unfained holy affection, to maintaine the peace and uphold the state of their country), of those I say diverse are seen, whome passion thrusts out of the bounds of reason, and often forceth them to take and follow unjust, violent and rash counsels. Certain it is, that when first our religion began to gain authority with the laws, its zeale armed many against all sorts of Pagane bookes, whereof the learned sort have a great loss. My opinion is that this disorder has done more hurt to learning than all the Barbarian flames. Cornelius Tacitus is a sufficient testimony of it, for, howbeit the Emperor Tacitus his kinsman had by express appointment stored all the libraries in the world with it, notwithstanding one only entire copy could not escape the curious search of those who sought to abolish it, by reason of five or sixe vain clauses contrary to our beleefe. They have also had this easily to affoord false commendations to all the Emperours, that made for us, and universally to condemne al the actions of those which were our adversaries, as may plainly be seen in Julian the Emperor, surnamed the Apostate; who in truth was a notable-rare-man, as he whose mind was lively endowed with the discourses of Philosophy, unto which he professed to conforme all his actions; and truely there is no kind of virtue whereof he has not left most notable examples. In chastity (whereof the whole course of his life gives aparant testimony) a like example unto that of Alexander and Scipio is read of him, which is, that of many wonderful fair captive ladies brought before him, being even in the very prime of his age (for he was slain by the Parthians about the age of one and thirty years) he would not see one of them. Touching justice, himself would take the paines to hear all parties: and although for curiosity sake, he would enquire of such as came before him what religion they were of, nevertheles the enmitie he bare to ours did no whit weigh down the balance. Himselfe made sundrie good laws, and revoked diverse subsidies and impositions, his predecessours before him had receaved. We have two good historians as eye witnesses of his actions. One of which (who is Marcellinus) in sundry places of his historie bitterly reprooveth this ordinance of his, by which he forbade schooles and interdicted all Christian rhetoricians and grammarians to teach, saying he wished this his action might be buried under silence. It is very likely, if he had done anything else more sharpe or severe against us, he would not have forgot it, as he that was well affected to our side. He was indeede very severe against us, yet not a cruel enemy. For, our people themselves report this historie of him that walking one day about the city of Calcedon, Maris, Bishop thereof, durst call him wicked and traitor to Christ, to whom be did no other thing but answered thus: ’Goe, wretched man, weepe and deplore the loss of thine eyes;’ to whom the Bishop replied: ’I thank Jesus Christ that he has deprived me of my sight, that so I might not view your impudent face;’ affecting therby (as they say) a kind of Philosophicall patience. So it is this part cannot be referred to the cruelties which he is said to have exercised against us. He was (says Eutropius, my other testimony) an enemy unto Christianity, but without shedding of blood. But to return to his justice, he can be accused of nothing but of the rigors he used in the beginning of his Empire, against such as had followed the faction of Constantius, his predecessour. Concerning sobriety, he never lived a soldiers kind of life, and in time of peace would feed no otherwise than the one who prepared and enured himself to the austeritie of war. Such was his vigilancie that he divided the night into three or foure parts, the least of which he allotted unto sleepe; the rest he employed in visiting the state of his army and his guards, or in study, for, amongst other his rare qualities, he was most excellent in al sorts of learning. It is reported of Alexander the Great, that being laid down to rest, fearing lest sleep should divert him from his thoughts and studies, he caused a bason to be set near his bed side, and holding one of his hands out, with a brazen ball in it, that, if sleep should surprise him, loosing his fingers ends, the ball falling into the bason, might with the noyse rouse him from out his sleep. This man had a mind so bent to what he undertook, and by reason of his singular abstinence so little troubled with vapours, that he might well have past this devise. Touching military sufficiencie he was admirable in all parts belonging to a great Captain. So was he almost al his life time in continual exercise of war, and the greater part with us in France against the Almains and Franconians. We have no great memory of any man that either has seen more dangers, nor that more often has made trial of his person. His death has some affinitie with that of Epaminondas, for being strucken with an arrow, and attempting to pull it out, he had surely done it, but that being sharpe-cutting, it hurt and weakened his hand. In that plight he earnestly requested to be carryed forth in the middest of his army, that so he might encourage his soldiers, who without him courageously maintained the battle, until such time as darke night severed the armies he was beholding to philosophie for a singular contempt, both of himself and of all humane things. He assuredly believed the eternitie of soules. In matters of religion, he was vicious everywhere. He was surnamed Apostata, because he had forsaken ours; notwithstanding, this opinion seems to me more likely, that he never took it to heart, but that for t he obedience which he bare to the law he dissembled til he had gotten the empire into his hands. He was so superstitious in his, that even such as lived in his time, and were of his own religion, mocked him for it; and it was said that if he had gained the victory of the Parthians, he would have consumed the race or breede of oxen to satisfie his sacrifices. He was also besotted with the art of soothsaying, and gave authority to all manner of prognostikes. Amongst other things he spake at his death, he said he was much beholding to the Gods, and greatly thanked them that they had not suffered him to be slain sodainly or by surprise as having long before warned him both of the place and hour of his end; nor to die of a base and easy death, more beseeming idle and effeminate persons, nor of a lingering, languishing, and dolorous death; and that they had deemed him worthy to end his life so nobly in the course of his victories and in the flower of his glory. There had before appeared a vision unto him, like unto that of Marcus Brutus, which first threatened him in Gaule, and afterward even at the point of his death presented itself to him in Persia. The speach he is made to speak when he felt himself hurt, ’Thou hast vanquished, O Nazarean,’ or; as some will have it, ’Content your self, O Nazarean,’ would scarce have been forgotten, had it been believed of my testimonies, who being present in the army, have noted even the least motions and words at his death, no more than certain other wonders which they annex unto it. But to return to my theame, he had long before (as says Marcellinus) hatched Paganisme in his hart, but forasmuch as he saw al those of his army to be Christians, he durst not discover himself. In the end, when he found himself to be sufficiently strong, and durst publish his mind, he caused the Temples of his Gods to be opened, and by all means endeavoured to advance idolatrie. And to attaine his purpose, having found in Constantinople the people very loose, and at ods with the Prelates of the Christian Church, and caused them to appeare before him in his pallace, he instantly admonished them to appease all their civill dissentions, and every one without hindrance or fear apply themselves to follow and serve religion. Which he very carefully solicited, hoping this licence might encrease the factions and controversies of the division, and hinder the people from growing to any unity, and by consequence from fortifying themselves against him by reason of their concord and in one mind-agreeing intelligence: having by the cruelty of some Christians found that ’there is no beast in the world so much of man to be feared as man,’ lo, here his very words, or very neare: wherewith this is worthy consideration, that the Emperor Julian useth the same receipt of liberty of conscience, to enkindle the trouble of civill dissention, which our Kings employ to extinguish. It may be said on one side that, to give faction the bridle to entertaine their opinion is to scatter contention and sow division, and as it were to lend it a hand to augment and encrease the same: there being no barre or obstacle of laws to bridle or hinder his course. But on the other side it might also be urged that to give factions the bridle to uphold their opinion, is by that facilitie and ease the readie way to mollifie and release them, and to blunt the edge which is sharpned by rareness, novelties and difficultie. And if for the honor of our Kings devotion, I believe better it is that since they could not do as they would, they have feigned to will what they could not. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XX: WE TASTE NOTHING PURELY Note on th e-text: this text was provided by Ben R. Schneider, Lawrence CHAPTER XX: WE TASTE NOTHING PURELY HE weaknes of our condition causeth that things in their natural simplicitie and puritie cannot fall into our use. The elements we enjoy are altered: metals likewise, indeed gold, must be empaired with some other stuffe to make it fit for our service. Nor virtue so simple which Ariston, Pyrrho, and Stoics made the end of their life, has been able to do no good without composition: nor the Cirenaike sensualitie or Aristipian voluptuousness. ’Of the pleasures and goods we have, there is none exempted from some mixture of evil and incommoditie.’ ----- medio de fonte leporum Surgit amari aliquid, quod in ipsis floribus angat. Lucr. iv. 1224. From middle spring of sweetes some bitter springs, Which in the very flower smartly stings. Our exceeding voluptuousness has some aire of groning and wailing. Would you not say it dieth of anguish? Yea, when we forge its image in her excellencie, we deck it with epithets of sickish and dolorous qualities: languor, effeminacy, weaknesse, fainting and Morbidezza, a great testimony of their consanguinity and consubtantiality. Excessive joy has more severity then jolity: extreme and full content more settlednes then cheerfulnesse. Ipsa fælicitas, so nisi temperat, premit (Sest. quare, etc.) Felicitie itself, unless it temper itself, distempers us.’ Ease consumeth us. It is that which an old Greek verse says of such a sense: ’The Gods sell us all the goods they give us:’ that is to say they give us not one pure and perfect, and which we buy not with the price of some evil. Travail and pleasure, most unlike in nature, are notwithstanding followed together by a kind of I wot not what natural conjunction. Socrates says that some God attempted to huddle together and confound sorrow and voluptuousness: but being unable to effect it, he bethought himself to couple them together, at least by the tail. Metrodorus said that in sadnesse there is some aloy of pleasure. I knowe not whether he meant any thing else, but I imagine that for one to enure himself to melancholy, there is some kind of purpose of consent and mutual delight: I meane besides ambition, which may also be joined unto it. There is some shadow of delicacy and quaintness which smileth and fawneth upon us even in the lap of melancholy. Are there not some complexions that of it make their nourishment? ------ est quædam flere voluptas.-- Ovid. Trist. iv. El. iii. 37. It is some pleasure yet With tears our cheekes to wet. And one Attalus in Seneca says the remembrance of our last friends is as pleasing to us as bitternesse in wine that is over old. Minister veteris puer falerni Ingere mi calices amariores: -- Cat. Lyr. Epi. xxiv. I. Sir boy, my servitor of good old wine, Bring me my cup thereof, bitter, but fine. and as of sweetly-sower apples, nature discovereth this confusion unto us: painters are of opinion that the motions and wrinkles in the face which serve to weepe serve also to laugh. Verily before one or other be determined to express which, behold the pictures success, you are in doubt toward which one enclineth. And the extreamity of laughing entermingles itself with tears. Nullum sine auctoramento malum est (Sen. Epig. lxix.). ’There is no evil without some obligation.’ When I imagine man fraught with all the commodities may be wished, let us suppose all his severall members were for ever possessed with a pleasure like unto that of generation, even in the highest point that may be: I find him to sinke under the burden of his ease, and perceive him altogether unable to bear so pure, so constant, and so universall a sensuality. Truely he flies when he is even upon the nicke, and naturally hasteneth to escape it, as from a step whereon he cannot stay or containe himself, and feareth to sinke into it. When I religiously confesse my self unto my self, I find the best good I have has some vicious taint. And I fear that Plato in his purest virtue (I that am as sincere and loyall an esteemer thereof, and of the vertues of such a stampe, as any other can possibly be) if he had neerely listened unto it (and sure he listened very near) he would therein have heard some harsh tune of humane mixture, but an obscure tune, and only sensible unto himself. Man all in all is but a botching and party coloured work. The very laws of Justice can not subsist without some commixture of injustice. And Plato says they undertake to cut off Hidræs heads that pretend to remove all incommodities and inconveniences from the laws. Omne magnum exemplum habet aliquid ex iniquo, quod contra singulos utilitate publica rependitur: (Tacitus, Ann. xiv. Cassi.) ’Every great example has some touch of injustice which is requited by the common good against particulars,’ says Tacitus. It is likewise true that for the use of life and service of public society there may be excess in the purity and perspicuity of our spirits. This piercing brightnes has overmuch subtility and curiosity. They should be made heavy and dull io make them the more obedi ent to example and practice, and they must be thickned and obscured to proportion them to this shady and terrestriall life. Therefore are vulgar and less wire drawne wits found to be more fit and happy in the conduct of affairs. And the exquisite and high- raised opinions of Philosophy unapt and unfit to exercise. This sharpe vivacity of the spirit, and this supple and restlesse volubility troubleth our negotiations. Humane enterprises should be managed more grosely and superficially, and have a good and great part of them left for the rights of fortune. Affaires need not be sifted so nicely and so profoundly. A man looseth himself about the considerations of so many contrary lustres and diverse formes. Volutantibus res inter se pugnantes, obtorpuerant animi: (Liv. dec. iv. lib. 2). ’Their mindes were astonished while they revolved things so different.’ It is that which our elders report of Simonides; because his imagination concerning the question Hieron the King had made unto him (which the better to answer he had diverse dayes allowed him to think of it) presented sundry subtil and sharpe considerations unto him; doubting which might be the likeliest; he altogether dispaireth of the truth. Whosoever searcheth all the circumstances and embraceth all the consequences thereof hindereth his election. A meane engine does equally conduct and sufficeth for the executions of great and little weights. It is commonly seen that the best husbands and the thriftiest are those who cannot tell how they are so: and that these cunning arithmeticians do seldom thrive by it. I know a notable pratler and an excellent blasoner of all sorts of husbandry and thrift who has most pitteously let ten thousand pound sterling a yeare pass from him. I know another who says he consulteth better than any man of his counsell, and there cannot be a properer man to see unto or of more sufficiencie; notwithstanding, when he commeth to any execution, his own servants find he is far otherwise: this I say without mentioning or accounting his ill lucke. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XXI: AGAINST IDLENESSE, OR DOING NOTHING CHAPTER XXI: AGAINST IDLENESSE, OR DOING NOTHING HE Emperor Vespasian, lying sicke of the disease whereof he died, omitted not to endeavour to understand the state of the empire; and lying in his bed, uncessantly dispatched many affairs of great consequence; and his physicians chiding him, as of a thing hurtful of his health, he answered that an Emperor should die standing upright. See here a notable saying, fitting my humor, and worthy a great prince. Adrian the Emperor used the same afterward to like purpose. And Kings ought often to be put in mind of it, to make them feel that this great charge which is given them of the commandement over so many men is no idle charge: and that there is nothing may so justly distaste a subject from putting himself in pain and danger for the service of his Prince then therewhilst to see him given to lazinesse, to base and vain occupations, and to have care of his conservation, seeing him so carelesse of ours. If any shall go about to maintaine that it is better for a Prince to manage his wars by others then by himself. Fortune will store him with sufficient examples of those whose lieutenants have achieved great enterprises, and also of some whose presence would have been more hurtful then profitable. But no vertuous and coragious Prince will endure to be entertained with so shame-full instructions. Under colour of preserving his head (as the statue of a Saint) for the good fortune of his estate, they degrade him of his office, which is altogether in military actions, and declare him uncapable of it. I know one would rather choose to be beaten then sleepe whilst others fight for him; and who without jealousie never saw his men performe any notable act in his absence. And Selim the first had reason to say that he thought victories gotten in the masters absence not to be complete. So much more willingly would he have said that such a master ought to blush for shame, who only by his name should pretend any share in it, having thereunto employed nothing but his thought and verbal direction. Nor that since in such a busines the advices and commandements which bring honor are only those given in the field and even in the action. No Pilot exerciseth his office standing still. The Princes of Otomans race (the chiefest race in the world in warlike fortune) have earnestly embraced this opinion. And Baiazeth the second, with his son, who, ammusing themselves about sciences and other private home matters, neglected the same, gave diverse prejudiciall blowes unto their Empire. And Amurath the third of that name, who now raigneth, following their example, beginneth very well to feel their fortunes. Was it not the King of England, Edward the third, who spake these words of our King Charles the fifth: ’There was never King that less armed himself; and yet Was never King that gave me so much so do, and put me to so many plunges.’ He had reason to think it strange, as an effect of fortune, rather than of reason. And let such as will number the Kings of Castile and Portugall amongst the warlike and magnanimous conquerors, seek for some other adherent then my self, forasmuch as twelve hundred leagues from their idle residence they have made themselves masters of both Indias, only by the conduct and direction of their factors, of whom it would be known whether they durst but go and enjoy them il person. The Emperor Julian said moreover that a Philosopher and gallant minded man ought not so much as breathe; that is to say, not to give corporall necessities, but what may not be refused them; ever holding both mind and body busied about notable, great and vertuous matters. He was ashamed any man should see him spitte or sweate before peo ple (which is also said of the Lacedemonian youths, and Xenophon reporteth it of the Persian) forasmuch as he thought that continuall travell, exercise, and sobriety should have concocted and dried up all such superfluities. What Seneca says shall not impertinently be alleadged here; that the ancient Romans kept their youth upright, and taught their children nothing that was to be learned sitting. It is a generous desire to endevor to die both profitable and manlike: but the effect consisteth no t so much in our good resolution, as in our good fortune. A thousand have resolved to vanquish or to die fighting, which have missed both the one and other: Hurts or imprisonment crossing their design and yielding them a forced kind of life. There are diseases which vanquish our desires and knowledge. Fortune should not have seconded the vanity of the Roman Legions, who by oath bound themselves either to die or conquer. Victor, Marce Fabi, revertur ex acie: Si fallo, Iovem patrem Gradinum que Martem aliosque iratos invoco Deos: (dec. i. lib. 2). ’I will, O Marcus Fabius, return conqueror from the army. If in this I deceive you, I wish both great Jupiter and Mars, and t he other Gods offended with me.’ The Portugalles report that in certain places of their Indian conquests they found some soldiers who with horrible execrations had damned themselves never to enter into any composition, but either they would be killed or remaine victorious; and in signe of their vowe wore their heads and beards shaven. We may hazard and obstinate ourselves long enough. It seems that blowes shunne them who over-joyfully present themselves unto them; and unwillingly reach those that overwillingly go to meet them and corrupt their end. Some unable to lose his life by his adversaries force, having assaid all possible means, has been enforced to accomplish his resolution, either to bear away the honor, or not to carry away his life, and even in the fury of the fight to put himself to death. There are sundrie examples of it, but note this one. Philistus, chief General of yong Dionysius his navie against the Siracusans, presented them the battle, which was very sharply withstood, their forces being likewise; wherein by reason of his prowess he had the better in the beginning. But the Siracusans flocking thicke and threefold about his gally to grapple and board him, having performed many worthy exployts with his own person to ridde himself from them, dispairing of all escape, with his own hand deprived himself of that life which so lavishly and in vain he had abandoned to his enemies hands. Moly Moluch, King of Fez, who not long since obtained that famous victory against Sebastian, King of Portugall, a notable victory by reason of the death of three Kings, and transmission of so great a Kingdome to the crowne of Castile, chanced to be grievously sicke at what time the Portugales with armed hand entered his dominions, and afterwards, though he foresaw it approaching nearer unto death, empaired worse and worse. Never did man more stoutly or more vigorously make use of an undanted courage than he. He found himself very weake to endure the ceremonious pompe which the Kings of that country, at their entrance into the camp are presented withall, which according to their fashion is full of all magnificence and state, and charged with all manner of action; and therefore he resigned that honor to his brother, yet resigned he nothing but the office of the chief Captain. Himselfe most gloriously executed and most exactly perfourmed all other necessary duties and profitable offices: holding his body laid along his cowch, but his mind upright and courage constant, even to his last gasp and in some sort after. He might have undermined his enemies, who were foolhardily advanced in his dominions, and was exceedingly grieved that for want of a little longer life and a substitute to manage the war and affairs of so troubled a State, he was enforced to seek a bloody and hazardous battle, having another pure and undoubted victory in hand. He notwithstanding managed the continuance of his sicknesse so miraculously that he consumed his enemy, diverted him from his sea-fleete and maritime places he held along the coast of Affricke, even until the last day of his life, which by designe he reserved and employed for so great and renowned a fight. He ranged his battle in a round, on every side besieging the Portugals army, which bending round and coming close, did not only hinder them in the conflict of (which through the valor of that yong assailant King was very furious), since they were were to turn their faces on all sides, but also hindred them from running away after the rowte. And finding all issues seized, and all passages closed, they were constrained to turn upon themselves: Coacervantur que non solum cede, sed etiam fuga: ’They fall on heapes not only by slaughter but by flight:’ And so pel mell to heape on one anothers necke, preparing a most murtherous and compleate victory for the conquerors. When he was even dying he caused himself to be carryed and hauled where-ever neede called for him; and passing along the files he exhorted the captaines and animated the soldiers one after another. And seeing one wing of the light to have the worst, and in some danger, no man could hold him, but he would needs, with his naked sword in hand, get on hors-backe striving by all possible means to enter the throng, his men holding him some by the bridle, some by the gowne, and some by the stirrops. This toyle and straining of himself made an end of that Iittle remainder of his life; then was he laid on his bed: but coming to himself again, starting up as out of a swown, each other faculty failing him, he gave them warning to conceal his death (which was the necessariest commandement he could give his servants, lest the soldiers, hearing of his death, might fall into despaire) and so yielded the Ghost, holding his fore-fingers upon his mouth, an ordinary signall to impose silence. What man ever lived so long and so near death? Who ever died so upright and undaunted? The extreamest degree, and most natural, courageously to manage death, is to see or front the same, not only without amazement, but without care; the course of life continuing free even in death. As Cato, who amused himself to studie and sleepe, having a violent and bloudy death present in his heart, and as it were holding it in his hand. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XXII: OF RUNNING POSTS, OR COURIERS. CHAPTER XXII: OF RUNNING POSTS, OR COURIERS. HAVE been none of the weakest in this exercise, which is proper unto men of my stature, well-trussed, short and tough, but now I have given it over: it toyles us over-much to hold out long. I was even now reading how King Cyrus, that he might more speedily receave news from al parts of his Empire (which was of exceeding great length), would needs have it tried how far a horse could in a day go outright without baiting, at which distance he caused stations to be set up, and men to have fresh horses ready for al such as came to him. And some report this swift kind of running answereth the flight of cranes. Cæsar says that Lucius Vibullis Rufus, making hast to bring Pompey an advertisement, rode day and night, and to make more speed shifted many horses. And himself (as Suetonius writeth) would up on an hyred coache run a hundred miles a day. And sure he was a rancke-runner: for where any river hindred his way he swam it over, and never went out of his way to seek for a bridge or foard. Tiberius Nero going to visite his brother Drusus who lay sick in Germany, having three coaches in his company, ranne two hundred miles in foure and twenty hours. In the Roman wars against King Antiochus, Titus Sempronius Gracchus (says Titus Livius) per dispositos equos prope incredibili celeritate ab Anmphisa tertio die Pellam pervenit: ’By horse laid poste, with incredible speede within three dayes he past from Amphisa to Pella.’ And viewing the place, it seems they were set stations for postes, and not newly appointed for that race. The invention of Cecina in sending news to those of his house had much more speede; he carried certain swallowes with him, and having occasion to send news home, he let them flie toward their nests, first marking them with some colour proper to signifie what he meant, as before he had agreed upon with his friends. In the theaters of Rome the household masters carried pigeons in their bosomes, under whose wings they fastened letters, when they would send any word home, which were also taught to bring back an answer. D. Brutus used some, being besieged in Mutina, and others elsewhere. In Peru they went poste upon mens backes, who took theire masters upon their shoulders, sitting upon certain bears or chaires with such agilitie that, in full running speede, the first porters, without any stay, cast their load upon other who upon the way waited for them, and so they to others. I understand that the Valachians, which are messengers unto the great Turk, use extreme diligence in their businesses forasmuch as they have authority to dismount the first passengers they meet upon the high-way, and give him their tyred horse. And because they shal not be weary, they are won t to swaithe themselves hard about the body with a broad swathe or seare-cloth, as diverse others do with us: I cold never find ease or good by it. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XXIII: OF BAD MEANES EMPLOIED TO A GOOD END CHAPTER XXIII: OF BAD MEANES EMPLOIED TO A GOOD END HERE is a wonderful relation and correspondencie found in this universall policy of Natures workes, which manifestly sheweth it is neither casual nor directed by diverse masters. The infirmities and conditions of our bodies are likewise seen in states and governments: Kingdomes and Commonwealths as well as we, are borne, florish, and fade through age. We are subject unto a repleatnesse of humors, hurtful and unprofitable, indeed be it of good humors (for even physicians fear that, and because there is nothing constant in us; they say, that perfection of health, over joyful and strong, must by art be abated and diminished, lest our nature, unable to settle itself in any certain place, and for her amendment to ascend higher, should over-violently recoile backe into disorder; and therefore they prescribe unto wrestlers purging and phlebotomies to subtract that superabundance of health from them or of bad, [sic] which is the ordinary cause of sicknesse. Of such like repletion are states often seen to be sicke, and diverse purgations are wont to be used to purge them. As we have seen some to dismisse a great number of families (chiefly to disburthen the country) which elsewhere go to seek where they may at others charge seat themselves. In this sorte our ancient French, leaving the high countries of Germany, came to possesse Gaule, whence they displaced the first inhabitants. Thence grew that infinite confluence of people which afterward, under Brenus and others, overranne Italie. Thus the Gothes and Vandalls, as also the nations which possesse Greece, left their natural countries to go where they might have more elbow-roome: and hardly shall we see two or three corners in the world that have not felt the effect of such a remooving alteration. The Romanes, by such means, erected their Colonies; for, perceiving their citie to growe over-populous, they were wont to discharge it of unnecessary people, which they sent to inbabite and manure the countries they had subdued. They have also sometimes maintained war with some of their enemies, not only thereby to keep their men in breath, lest idleness, the mother of corruption, should cause them some inconvenience. Et patimur longæ pacis mala, sævior armis Luxuria incumbit. --Juven, Sat. vi. 292. We suffer of long peace the soking harmes, On us lies luxury more fierce then arms. But also to let the Common-wealth blood and somewhat to allay the over vehement heat of their youth, to lop the sprigs and thin the branches of this over-spreading tree, too much abounding in ranknesse and gaillardise. To this purpose they maintained a good while war with the Carthaginians. In the treaty of Bretigny, Edward the 3. King of England, would by no means comprehend in that general peace the controversie of the Dutchie of Britany, to the end he might have some way to disburthen himself of his men of war, and that the multitude of English-men, which he had emploied about the wars of France should not return into England. It was one of the reasons induced Philip our king to consent that his son John should be sent to war beyond the seas, that so he might carry with him a great number of yong hot-blouds which were amongst his trained military men. There are diverse now adaies, which will speak thus, wishing this violent and burning emotion we see and feel amongst us might be derived to some neighbor war, fearing lest those offending humors, which at this instant are predominant in our body, if they be not diverted elsewhere, will still maintaine our fever in force, and in the end cause our utter destruction: And in truth a forraine war is nothing so dangerous a disease as a civill: But I will not believe that God would favor so unjust an enterprise, to offend and quarrell with others for our commodity. Nil mihi tam valde placeat Rhamnusia virgo, Quod temere invitis suscipiatur heris. -- Cat. Epig. Eleg. iv. 77. That fortune likes me not which is constrained By Lords unwilling rashly entertained. Notwithstanding the weaknesse of our condition, does often urge us to this necessity, to use bad means to a good end. Lycurgus the most vertuous and perfect law-giver that ever was, devised this most unjust fashion, to instruct his people unto temperance, by force to make the helots, which were their servants, to be drunken that seeing them so lost and buried in wine, the Spartanes might abhor the excess of that vice. Those were also more to be blamed, who anciently allowed that criminall offenders what death soever they were condemned unto, should by physicians all alive be torn in pieces, that so they might naturally see our inward parts, and thereby establish a more assured certainty in their art: for if a man must needs erre or debauch himself, it is more excusable if he do it for his soules health then for his bodies good. As the Romans trained up and instructed their people to valor, and contempt of dangers and death, by the outragious spectacles of gladiators and deadly fighting fencers, who in presence of them all combated, mangled, sliced, and killed one another. Quid vesani aliud sibi vult a rs impia ludi, Quid mortes iuvenum, quid sanguine pasta voluptas? What else means that mad art of impious sense, Those yong-mens deaths, that blood-fed pleasing sense? which custom continued even until the time of Theodosius the Emperor. Arripe delatam tua dux in tempora famam, Quodque patris superest successor laudis habeto: Nullus in vrbe cadat, cujus sit poena voluptas, Jam solis contenta feris infamis arena, Nulla cruentatis homicidia ludat in armis. Prud. cont. Sym. ii. f. The fame defer’d to your times entertaine, Enherite praise which does from Sire remaine Let none die to give pleasure by his pain: Be shamefull Theaters with beasts content Not in goar’d arms manslaughter represent. Surely it was a wonderful example, and of exceeding benefit for the peoples institution, to see dayly one or two hundred, indeed sometimes a thousand brace of men, armed one against another, in their presence to cut and hacke one another in pieces with so great constancy of courage, that they were never seen to utter one word of faintness or commiseration, never to turn their backe, nor so much as to show a motion of demissenesse, to avoide their adversaries blowes: but rather to extend their necks to their swords, and present themselves unto their strokes. It has hapned to diverse of them, who through many hurts being wounded to death, have sent to ask the people whether they were satisfied with their duty, before they would lie down in the place. They must not only fight and die constantly, but jocondly: in such sort as they were cursed and bitterly scolded at, if in receiving their death they were any way seen to strive, indeed madnesse encited them to it. -----consurgit ad ictus, Et quoties victor ferrum iugulo inserit, illa Delicias ait esse suas, pectusque jacentis Virgo modesta ubet converso pollice rumpi. -- Prud. cont Sym. ii. The modest maide, when wounds are given, upriseth; When victors sword the vanquisht throate surprises, She says, it is her sport, and does command T’embrue the conquer’d breast, by signs of hand. The first Romans disposed thus of their criminals: but afterward they did so with their innocent servants; indeed, of their free men, which were sold to that purpose: indeed of Senators, and Roman Knights and women also. Nunc caput in mortem vendant, et funus arenæ, Atque hostem sibi quisqe parat cum bella quiescunt. They sell mens lives to death and stages sight, When wars do cease, they find with whom to fight. Hos inter fremitus novosque lusus, Stat sexus rudis insciusque ferri. Et pugnas capit improbus viriles: Amidst these tumults, these strange sporting sights, That sex does sit which knowes not how sword bites, And entertaines unmov’d those manly fights. Which I should deem very strange and incredible; if we were not dayly accustomed to see in our wars many thousands of foreigne nations, for a very small sum of mony, to engage both their blood and life in quarrels wherein they are nothing interessed. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXIV: OF THE ROMAN GREATNESS. CHAPTER XXIV: OF THE ROMAN GREATNESS. WILL but speak a word of this infinite argument, and slightly glance at it, to show the simplicitie of those who compare the seely greatness of these times unto that. In the seaventh book of Ciceroes familiar Epistles (and let Gramarians remove this title of familiar if they please, for, to say truth, it makes but little to the purpose: and they who in lieu of familiar have placed ad familiares, may wrest some argument for themselves, from that which Suetonius says in Cæsars Life, that there was a volume of his Epistles ad familares) there is one directed unto Cæsar then being in Gaule, in which Cæsar repeats these very words which were in the end a former letter that Cæsar had written to him: ’Touching Marcus Furius, whom you bast commended unto me, I will make him King of Gaule, and if you wilt have me prefer any other of your friends, send them to me.’ It was not new in a simple Roman Citizen (as Cæsar then was) to dispose of kingdomes, for as well deprived he King Deiotarus of his, to give it to a gentleman of the city of Pergamo, called Mithridates. And those who wrote his Life mention many kingdomes sold by him. And Suetonius reporteth that he at one time wrested three millions and five hundred thousand crownes of gold from King Ptolomæus, which amounted very near unto the price of his kingdome. Tot Galatæ, tot Pontus est, tot Lydia numnis -- CLAUD. in Eutrop. 1. i. 20, 3 Forasmuch let Galatia go, Forasmuch Lidia, Pontus so. Marcus Antonius said, ’The greatness of the Roman people was not so much discerned by what it took as by what it gave.’ Yet some ages before Antonius was there one amongst others of so wonderful authority, as through all his history I know no marke carrieth the name of his credit higher. Antiochus possessed all Egypt, and was very near to conquer Cyprus and others depending of that Empire. Vpon the progresse of his victories, C. Popilius came unto him in the behalfe of the Senate, and at first arrivall refused to take him by the hand before he had read the letters he brought him. The King having read them, said he would deliberate of them. Popilius with a wand encireled the place about where he stood, and thus bespake him: ’Give me an answer to carry back to the Senate before you goest out of this circle.’ Antiochus, amazed at the rudenesse of so urging a commandement, after he had paused a while, replyed thus: ’I will do what the Senat commandeth me.’ Then Popilius saluted him as a friend unto the Roman people. ’To have renounced so great a Monarchy and forgon the course of so successfull prosperity by the only impression of three written lines! He had good reason, as afterward he did, by his Ambassadors to send the Senate word that he had received their ordinances with the same respect as if they had come from the immortall Gods. All the kingdomes Augustus subdued by right of war, he restored to those who had lost them, or presented strangers with them. And concerning this purpose, Tacitus, speaking of Cogidunus, King of England, by a wonderful trait makes us perceive this infinit greatnes and might. The Romans (says he) were from all antiquity accustomed to leave those kings whom they had vanquished in the possession of their kingdomes under their authority: Vt haberent instrumenta servitutis et reges: (CORN. TACIT. Vit. Jul. Agric.) ’That they might have even Kings also f or instruments of their bondage.’ It is very likely that Soliman, the great Turke, whom we have seen to use such a liberality and give away the Kingdome of Hungary and other dominions, did more respect this consideration then that he was wont to alleage; which is, that he was over wearied with the many monarchies and surcharged with the severall dominions, which either his own or his ancestors virtue had gotten him. Previous Essay. Next Essay. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXV: HOW A MAN SHOULD NOT COUNTERFEIT TO BE SICKE. CHAPTER XXV: HOW A MAN SHOULD NOT COUNTERFEIT TO BE SICKE. HERE is an epigram in Martiall that may pass for a good one (for there are of all sorts in him), wherein he pleasantly relateth the story of Cælius, who to avoide the courting of certain great men in Rome, to give attendance at their rising, and to waite, assist and follow them, feigned to be troubled with the goute; and to make his excuse more likely, he caused his legs to be ointed and swathed and lively counterfeted the behaviour and countenance of a goutie man. In the end fortune did him the favor to make him goutie indeede. Tantum cura potest et ars doloris, Desiit fingere Cælius podagram. -- MART. 1. vii. Epig. xxxviii. 8. So much the care and cunning can of pain: Cælius (grown gowty) leaves the gowt to faine. As far as I remember I have read a like history in some place of Appian, of one who, purposing to escape the proscriptions of the Triumvirat of Rome, and to conceal himself from the knowledge of those who pursued him, kept himself close and disguised, adding this other invention to it, which was to counterfeit blindnes in one eye, who when he came somewhat to recover his liberty, and would have left off the plaster he had long time worne over his eyes, he found that under that mask he had altogether lost the sight of it. It may be the action of his sight was weakned, having so long continued without exercise and the usual virtue was wholly converted into the other eye. For we may plainly perceive that holding one eye shut, it convaieth some part of its effect into his fellow; in such sort as it will swell and grow bigger. As also the idlenes, together with the warmth of the medicaments and swathing, might very well draw some goutie humor into the legge of Martials goutie fellow. Reading in Froisart the vow which a gallant troupe of younge English-men had made to weare their eyes hudwinkt until such time as they should pass into France, and there performe some notable exploite of arms upon us: I have often laughed with my self to think what they would have imagined if as to the fore aleaged it had hapned to them, and had all been blind of the left eye at what time they turned to look upon their mistresses, for whose sake they had made their vowe and undertaken such an enterprise. Mothers have great reason to chide their children when they counterfeit to be blind with one eye, crompt backe, squint-eyed, or lame, and such other deformities of the body; for besides that the body thus tender may easily receive some ill custom, I know not how, it seems that fortune is glad to take us at our word: and I have heard diverse examples of some who have fallen sicke in very deede because they had purposed to faine sick. I have at all times enured my self, whether I be on horsebacke or afoote, to carry a good heavy wand or cudgell in my hand; Yea, I have endeavoured to do it handsomely, and with an effected kind of countenance to continue so. Many have threatned me that fortune will one time or other turn this my wantonnes into necessitie. I presume upon this that I should be the first of my race that ever was troubled with the gowt. But lett us somewhat amplifie this chapter, and patch it up with another piece concerning blindnes. Plinie reports of one who, dreaming in his sleepe that he was blind, awaking the next morning, was found to be stark blinde, having never had any precedent sickenes. The power of imagination may very well further such things as elsewhere I have showed; and Plinie seems to be of this opinion; but it is more likely that the motions which the body felt inwardly (whereof Physitians may, if they please, find out the cause), and which took away his sight, were the occasion of his dreame. Let us also add another story concerning this purpose, which Seneca reporteth in his Epistles. Thou knowest (says he, writing unto Lucilius) that Harpaste, my wifes foole, is left upon me as an hereditarie charge; for by my own nature I am an enemy unto such monsters, and if I have a desire to laugh at a foole, I neede not seek one far; I laugh at my self. This foolish woman has sodainly lost her sight. I report a strange thing, but yet very true. She will not believe she is blind, and urgeth her keeper uncessantly to lead her, saying still, my house is very darke. What we laugh at in her, I entreat you to believe that the same happens to each of us. No man knows himself to be covetous or niggardly. Even the blinde require a guide, but we stray from ourselves. I am not ambitious, say we, but no man can live otherwise at Rome: I am not sumptuous, but the citie requireth great charges. It is not my fault if I be collerike; if I have not yet set down a sure course of my life, the fault is in youth. Let us not seek our evil out of us; it is within us, it is rooted in our entrailes. And only because we perceive not that we are sicke, makes our recoverie to prove more difficult. If we beginne not betimes to cure ourselves, when shall we provide for so many sores, for so many evils? Yet have we a most sweet and gentle medicine of Philosophy; for of others no man feeles the leisure of them but after his recoveries whereas she pleaseth, easeth, and cureth all at once. See here what Seneca says, who has some what diverted me from my purpose: but there is profit in the exchange. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXVI: OF THUMBS. CHAPTER XXVI: OF THUMBS. ACITUS reporteth that amongst certain barbarous kings, for the confirmation of an inviolable bonde or covenant, their manner was to join their right hands close and hard together with enterlacing their thumbs: and when by hard wringing them the blood appeared at their ends, they pricked them with some sharp point, and then mutually entersuckt each one the others. Phisicians say thumbes are the master fingers of the hand, and that their Latine etymologie is derived of Pollere. The Græcians call it αντιχειρ, as a man would say, another hand. And it seems the Latines likewise, take them sometimes in this sense, id est, for the whole hand: Sed nec vocibus excitata blandis, Molli pollice nec rogata surgit.-- MART. 1. xii. Epig. xcix. 8. It wil not rise, though with sweet words excited, Nor with the touch of softest thumb invited. In Rome it was heretofore a signe of favor to wring and kisse the thumbs: Fautor utroque tuum laudabit pollice ludum -- HOR. 1. i. Epist. xviii. 66. He that applaudes will praise, With both his thumbs, your plaies: and of disfavor or disgrace to lift them up and turn them outward. converso pollice vulgi Quemlibet occidunt populariter. -- JUVEN. Sat. iii. 36 When people turn their thumbs away, They popularly any slay. Such as were hurt or maymed in their thumbs were by the Romanes dispensed from going to war, as they who had lost their weapons hold-fast. Augustus did confiscate all the goods of a Roman knight, who through malice had cut off the thumbes of two young children of his, thereby to excuse them from going to war and before him the Senate in the time of the Italian wars had condemned Caius Vatienus to perpetuall prison, and confiscated all his goods, forasmuch as he had willingly cut off the thumb of his left hand, so to exempt himself from the voyage. Some one, whose name I remember not, having gained a great victory by sea, caused all the enemies whom he had vanquished and taken prisoners to have their thumbs cut off, thinking thereby to deprive them of all means of fighting, or rowing, or handling their oares. The Athenians likewise caused them to be cut off from them of Ægina, to take from them the preeminence in the art of navigation. In Lacedæmon masters punished their schollers by byting their thumbs. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXVII: COWARDIZE, THE MOTHER OF CRUELTY CHAPTER XXVII: COWARDIZE, THE MOTHER OF CRUELTY HAVE often heard it reported that Cowardize is the mother of Cruelty: And have perceived by experience that this malicious sharpnes and inhumane severitie of corage is commonly accompanied with feminine remissenesse. I have seen some of the cruelest subject to weepe easily, and for frivolous causes. Alexander the tyrant of Pheres could not endure to see tragedies acted in the theatres for fear his subjects should see him sob and weepe at the misfortunes of Hecuba and Andromache; he who without remorse or pity caused daily so many poore people to be most cruelly massacred and barbarously murthered. May it be weaknesse of spirit makes them so pliable to all extremities? valor (whose effect is only to exercise itself against resistance, Nec nisi bellantis gaudet cervice iuvenci. -- Claud. Epist. ad Hadr. v. 30. Nor takes he joy to domineere But on the necke of sturdie steere) refraines itself in seeing her enemy prostrate to her mercy: but pusillanimitie, to say that she also is of the feaste, since it cannot be joined to the first part takes for her share the second, which is massacre and blood. Murthers after victories are commonly effected by the baser kind of people and officers that waite upon the baggage and cariage. And the reason we see so many unheard-of cruelies in popular wars is that this vulgar rascalitie does martially flesh and enure itself to dive in blood up to the elbowes, and mangle a body, or hacke a carcase lying and groveling at their feete, having no manner of feeling of other valor. Et Lupus et turpes instant morientibus Ursi. Et quæcumque minor nobilitate fera est. -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. v. 35. A Wolfe or filthie Beare the dying man oppresse. Or some such beast as in nobilitle is less. As the Craven Curres, which at home or in their Kennels will tugge and bite the skins of those wild beastes which in the fields they durst not so much as bark at. What is it that now adaies makes all our quarrels mortal? And whereas our forefathers had some degree of revenge, we now beginne by the last; and at first brunt nothing is spoken of but killing? What is it, if it be not cowardice? Every man seeth it is more bravery and disdaine for one to beat his enemy than make an end of him, and to keep him at a bay, then make him die. Moreover, that the desire of revenge is thereby allayed and better contented; for it aymeth at nothing so much as to give or show a motion or feeling of revenge only of herself. And thats the reason we do not challenge a beast, or fall upon a stone when it hurts us, because they are incapable to feel our revenge. And to kill a man is to shelter him from our offence. And even as Bias exclaimed upon a wicked man: ’I know that soone or late you shall be punished for your lewdness but I fear me I shall not see it;’ and moaned the Orchomenians, because the penance which Liciscus had for his treason committed against them, came at such a time as none of them were living whom it had concerned, and whom the pleasure of that punishment might most delight so ought revenge to be moaned when he on whom it is inflicted looseth the means to endure or feel it; For, even as the revenger will see the action of the revenge, that so he may feel the pleasure of it, so must he on whom he is revenged, both see and feel that he may hereby receive both repentance and grief. He shall rew it, say we. And though he receive a stab, or a blow with a pistol on his head, shal we think he wil repent? Contrariwise, if we marke him well, we shal perceive that in falling, he makes a moe or bob at us. He is far from repenting when he rather seems to be beholding us: inasmuch as we affoord him the favourablest office of life, which is to make him dye speedily and as it were insensibly. We are left to shift up and down, run and trot, and squat here and there, and al to avoyd the officers or escape the magistrates that pursue us; and he is at rest. ’To kill a man is good to escape a future offence, and not revenge the wrongs past.’ It is rather an action of fear than of bravery; of precaution than of an enterprise. It is apparent that by it we quit both the true end of revenge and the respect of our reputation: if he live we fear he will or may charge us with the like. It is not against him, it is for you, you riddest your self of him. In the kingdome of Narsinga this expedient would be bootlesse. There not only soldiers, and such as professe arms, but every meane artificer, decide their quarels with the swords point. The King never refuseth any man the combate that is disposed to fight, and if they be men of quality he wil be by in person, and reward the victor with a chaine of gold: which, whosoever has a mind unto, and wil obtaine it, may freely challenge him that weareth the same, and enter combate with him. And having overcome one combate, has many following the same. If we thought by virtue to be ever superiors unto our enemy, and at our pleasure gourmandize him, it would much grieve us he should escape us, as he does in dying. We rather endeavour to vanquish surely then honourably. And in our quarrels we rather seek for the end then for the glory. Asinius Pollio for an honest man less excusable, committed a like fault; who, having written many invectives against Plancus, stayed until he were dead to publish them. It was rather to flurt at a blind man, and rail in a dead mans eare, and to offend a senselesse man, than incur the danger of his revenge. And men answered in this behalfe, that it only belonged to Hobgoblins to wrestle with the dead. He who stayeth till the author be dead whose writings he will combate, what says he but that he is weake and quarrellous? It was told Aristotle, that somebody had spoken ill of him, to whom he answered, ’Let him also whippe me, so my self be not by.’ Our forefathers were content to revenge an insult with the lie, a lie with a blowe, a blowe with blood, and so in order. They were sufficiently valiant not to fear their adversary, though he lived and were wronged: whereas we quake for fear so long as we see him afoot. And that it is so, does not our modern practise pursue to death as well him who has wronged us as him whom we have offended? It is also a kind of dastardlinesse which has brought this fashion into our single combates, to accompany us in the fields with seconds, thirdes, and fourths. They were anciently single combates, but now they are skirmishes and battles. To be alone, feared the first that invented it. Quum in se cuique minimum fiducite esset: ’When every man had least confidence in himself.’ For, what company soever it be, it does naturally bring some comfort and ease in danger. In ancient time they were wont to employ third persons as sticklers, to see no treachery or disorder were used, and to bear witnes of the combates success. But now this fashion is come up, let any man be engaged, whosoever is envited cannot well containe himself to be a spectator, lest it be imputed unto him it is either for want of affection or lack of courage. Besides the injustice of such an action and villany, for your honors protection, to engage other valor and force than your own, I find it a disadvantage in an honest and worthy man, and who wholly trusts unto himself, to entermingle his fortune with a second man: every one runneth sufficient hazard for himself, and need not also run it for another: and has enough to do to assure himself of his own virtue for the defense of his life, without committing so precious a thing into third mens hands. For, if the contrary has not expresly been covenanted of all foure, it is a combined party. If your fellow chance to faile, you have two upon you, and not without reason: and to say it is a Superchiery, as it is indeed: as being well armed, to charge a man who has but a piece of a sword, or being sound and strong, to set upon a man sore hurt. But if they be advantages you have gotten fighting, you may use them without imputation. Disparitie is not considered, and inequality is not balanced, but by the state wherein the fight is begun. As of the rest you must rely on fortune, and if alone or single you chance to have three upon you, your other two companions being slain, you have no more wrong done you than I should offer in wars in striking an enemy whom at such an advantage I should find grappled with one of my fellow-soldiers. The nature of societie beareth where troupe is against troupe (as where our Duke of Orleans chalenged Henry King of England, one hundred against another hundred; three hundred against as many, as did the Argians against the Lacedemonians; three to three, as were the Horatij against the Curatij), the pluralitie of either side is never respected for more than a single man. Wheresoever there is company, the hazard is confused and disordered. I have a private interest in this discourse. For my brother, the Lord of Matecoulom, being desired in Rome to second and accompany a gentleman with whom he had no great acquaintance, who was defendant and challenged by another; the fight begunne, my brother by chance found himself confronted with one nearer and better known to him (I would faine be resolved of these laws of honor, which so often shock and trouble those of reason), whom after he had vanquished and dispatched, seeing the two principals of the quarrell yet standing and unhurt, he went to reskew his fellow. What could he do less? should he have stood still, and (if chance would so have had it) see him defeated for whose defense he was entered the quarrell? What until then he had done was nothing to the purpose, and the quarrel was still undecided. Al the courtesy you can, you ought surely use to your enemy, especially when you have brought him under, and to some great advantage; I know not how a man may use it, when anothers interest depends on it, where you are but accessory and where the quarrel is not yours. He could never be just nor curteous in hazard of him unto whom he had lent himself. So was he presently delivered out of the Italian prisons by a speedy and solemn letter of commendations from our King. Oh, indiscreet nation! We are not contented to manifest our follies and bewray our vices to the world by reputation; but we go into forraigne nations, and there in person show them. Place three Frenchmen in the deserts of Libya, and they will never live one moneth together without brawling, falling out, and scratching one another; you would say this peregrination is a party erected to please strangers with our tragedies; and those most commonly who rejoice and scoffe at our evils. We travel into Italie to learne the art of fencing, and practise it at the cost of our lives, before we know it; it were requisite, according to the order of true discipline, we should prefer the theorike before the practike. We betray our apprentisage. Primitiæ iuvenum miseræ, bellique futuri Dura rudimenta. -- Stat. Sylv. v. The miserable first essayes of youth And hard beginnings of war that ensu’th. I know it is an art profitable to her end (in the single combate betweene the two Princes, cosin-Germans, in Spain, the eldest of which (says T. Livius) by the skil of his weapons, and by craft, overcame easily the dismayed forces of the younger) and as by experience I have knowen the knowledge and skil whereof has puffed the heart of some beyond their natural proportion. But it is not properly a virtue, since she draweth her stay from dexteritie and takes her foundation from other than from herself. The honor of combates consisteth in the jealousie of the heart, not of the science. And therefore have I seen some of my friends, renowned for great Masters in this exercise, in their quarrels to make choice of weapons that might well take the meane of this advantage or oddes from them; and which wholly depend on fortune and assurance that their victory might not rather be imputed to their fencing then ascribed to their valor. And in my infancy our nobility scorned the reputation of a fencer, though never so cunning, as injurious; and if any learnt it they would sequester themselves from company, deeming the same as a mystery of craft and subtility, derogating from true and perfect virtue. Non scntivar, non parar, non ritirarsi Voglion costor, ne qui destrezza ha parte; Non danno i colpi finti hor pie ni, hor scarsi; Togli l’ira e’l furor l’uso dell’arte, Odi le spade horribilmente urtarsi A mezzo il ferro, il pie d’orma non parte, Sempre e il pie fermo, e la man sempre in moto, Ne scende taglio in van, ne punta a voto. -- Tasso, Gier. can. xii. stan. 55. T’ avoyde, toward retiring to give ground They reke not, nor has nimblenes here part, Nor give false blowes, nor full, nor scarce, nor sound, Rage and revenge bereave all use of arte . T heir Swordes at halfe Sword horribly resound You might hear mette: No foote from steppe does parte: Their foote still fast, their hand still faster mooveth: No stroke in vain, no thrust in vain, but prooveth. Shooting at Buts, Tilting, Torneyes, Barriers, the true images of martiall combats, were the exercises of our forefathers. This other exercise is so much the less noble, by how much it respecteth but a private end: which against the laws of justice teacheth us to destroy one another, and every way produces ever mischievous effects. It is much more worthy and better beseeming for a man to exercise himself in things that assure and offend not our Commonwealth and which respect public securitie and general glory. Publius Rutilius was the first that ever instituted the Souldier to manage his arms by dexteritie and skil, and joined art onto virtue, not for the use of private contentions, but for the wars and Roman peoples quarrels; a popular and civill manner of fencing; and besides the example of Cæsar, who appointed his Souldier, above all things, to aime and strike at the face of Pompeyes men in the battle of Pharsalia: a thousand other Chieftaines and Generals have devised new fashions of weapons and new kindes of striking, and covering of themselves, according as the present affairs require. But even as Philopoemen condemned wrestling, wherein he excelled others, forasmuch as the preparations appertaining to this exercise differed from those that belong to military discipline, to which he supposed men of honor should amuse and addict themselves, me thinkes also that this nimblenesse or agilitie to which men fashion and enure themselves, their Iimbes, their turnings, windings, and nimble-quick motions wherein youth is instructed and trained in this new schoole, are not only unprofitable but rather contrary and domageable for the use of militarie combat: And we see our men do commonly employ particular weapons in their fence schools, and peculiarly appointed for that purpose. And I have seen it dis-allowed that a gentleman chalenged to fight with rapier and dagger should present himself in the equipage of a man at arms; or that another should offer to come with his cloake instead of a dagger. It is worthy the noting that Lachez in Plato, speaking of an apprentisage how to manage arms conformable to ours, says he could never see any notable warrior come of a school of fence, and especially from among the maisters. As for them our own experience confirmes as much. And for the rest we may at least say they are sufficiencies of no relation or correspondency. And in the institution of the children of this Commonwealth, Plato interdicts the artes of striking or playing with fists devised by Amycus and Epeius, and to wrestle invented by Antoeus and Cecyo: because they aime at another end then to adapt youth to warlike service, and have no afflilition with it. But I digresse much from my theame. The Emperor Mauricius being forwarned by dreames and sundry prognostications that one Phocas a souldier at that time yet unknown, should kill him, demanded of Philip his son in law who that Phocas was, his nature, his conditions and customs, and how amongst other things Philip told him he was a faint, cowardly, and timorous fellow. The Emperor thereby presently concluded that he was both cruel and a murtherer. What makes tyrants so blood-thirstie? it is the care of their securities and that their faint-hart yields them no other means to assure themselves then by rooting out those which may in any sort offend them; indeed, silly women, for fear that they should or bite or scratch them: Cuncta ferit dum cuncta timet. -- Claud. in Eutrop. i. 182. Of all things he afraide, At all things fiercely laide. The first cruelties are exercised by themselves, thence proceedeth the fear of a just revenge, which afterward produces that swarme of new cruelties; by the one to stifle the other. Philip, the King of Macedon, who had so many crowes to pul with the Romanes, agitated by the horror of so many murthers committed by his appointment, and unable to make his partie good, or to take any safe resolution against so many families, by him at severall times injured, resolved at last to seize upon al their children whom he had caused to be murthered, that so he might day by day one after another rid the world, of them, and so establish his safety. Matters of worth are not impertinent wherever they be placed. I, who rather respect the weight and benefite of discourses then their order and placing, need not fear to place here at randome a notable story. When they are so rich of their own beautie, and may very well uphold themselves alone, I am content with a haires end, to fitte or join them to my purpose. Amongst others who had been condemned by Philip was one Herodicus, Prince of the Thessalians: after whom he caused his two sons in lawe to be put to deathe, each of them leaving a young son behind. Theoxena and Arco were the two widdowes. Theoxena, although she were instantly urged thereunto, could never be induced to marry again. Arco took to husband Poris, a chief man amongst the Æneans, and by him had diverse children, all which she left very young. Theoxena, moved by a motherly charitie toward her young nephews, and so to have them in her protection and bringing up, wedded Poris. Vpon this came out the proclamation of the Kings edict. This noble-minded mother, distrusting the Kings crueltie and fearing the mercilesness of his satelities or officers towards these noble, hopefull and tender youths, feared not to say that she would rather kil them with her own hands then deliver them. Poris, amazed at her protestations, promiseth her secretly to convey them to Athens, there by some of his faithful friends to be kept safely. They take occasion of a yearly feast which to the honor of Æneas was solemnized at Ænea, and thither they go, where having all day long assisted at the ceremonies and public banket, night being come, they convay themselves into a shippe appointed for that purpose in hope to save themselves by sea. But the winde fell out so contrary that the next morning they found themselves in view of the town whence the night before they had hoisted sailes, where they were pursued by the garders and soldiers of the port. Which Poris perceiving, laboured to hasten and encourage the mariners to shift away: but Tbeoxena, engaged through love and revenge, remembring her first resolution, prepared both weapons and poisons, and presenting them to their sight, thus she bespake them: ’Oh my dear children, take a good heart; death is now the only meane of your defense and liberty, and shall be a just cause unto the Gods for their holy justice. These bright keen blades, these full cuppes shall free you the passage unto it. Courage therefore, and you my eldest child take this sword to die the strongest death.’ Who on the one side having so undaunted a perswader, and on the other their enemies ready to cut their throats in furious manner, ranne all to that which came next to his hand; and so all goared and panting were throwne into the sea. Theoxena, proud she had so gloriously provided for her children’s safety, lovingly embraced her husband, said thus unto him: ’Oh my dear heart, let us follow these boyes, and together with them enjoy one self-same grave;’ and so close-claspe together they flung themselves into the main: so that the ship was brought to shore again, but empty of her maisters. Tyrants, to act two things together, that is, to kill and cause their rage to be felt, have employed the utmost of their skill to devise lingering deaths. They will have their enemies die, yet not so soone but that they may have leisure to feel their vengeance. Wherin they are in great perplexity; for if the torments be over-violent, they are short; if lingring, not grevious enough. In this they employ their wits and devices, many examples whereof we see in antiquitie; and I wot not whether we retain some spice of that barbarisme. Whatsoever is beyond a simple death seems to me meere crueltie. Our justice cannot hope that he whom the terror of death cannot dismay, be he to be hanged or beheaded, can in any sort be troubled with the imagination of a languishing fire, of a wheele, or of burning pincers. And I wot not whether in that meane time we bring him to despair; for what plight can the soul of man be in that is broken up on a wheele, or, after the old fashion, nailed to a crosse, and 24 howres together expects his death! Josephus reporteth that whilst the Roman wars continued in Jewrie, passing by a place where certain Jewes had been crucified three dayes before, he knew three of his friends amongst them, and having gotten leave to remove them, two of them died, but the third lived long after. Chalcondylas, a man of credite, in the memories he left of matters happened in his time and thereabouts, maketh report of an extreme torment the Emperor Mechmed was often wont to put in practice, which was by one only blow of a cimitary, or broad Persian sword, to have men cut in two parts, by the waste of the body, about the diapbragma, which is a membrane lying overthwart the lower part of the breast, separating the heart and lights from the stomacke, which caused them to die two deaths at once: and affirmeth that both parts were seen full of life, to move and stir long time after, as if they had been in lingering torment. I do not think they felt any great torture in that moving. The gastliest torments to looke upon are not alwaies the greatest to be endured: and I find that much more fiercely-horrible, which other historians write, and which he used against certain Lords of Epirus, whom fair and leasurely he caused to be flayed all over, disposed by so malicious a dispensation that their lives continued fifteene days in that languor and anguish. And these two others: Croesus having caused a gentleman to be apprehended, greatly favoured by Pantaleon his brother, led him in a fullers or clothworkers shoppe, where with cards and teazles belonging to that trade, he made him to be carded, scraped, and teazled so long until he died of it. George Sechel, ring-leader of the countrymen of Polina, who under the title of a Croysada, wrought so many mischiefs, having been defeated in a battle by the Vayvoda of Transilvania and taken prisoner, was for three dayes together tyed naked to a wooden horse, exposed to all manner of tortures any man might devise against him; during which time diverse other prisoners were kept fasting. At last, he yet living, saw Lucat his dear brother, and for whose safety he sued and entreated, forced to drinke his blood, drawing all the envie and hatred of his misdeeds upon himself. And twenty of his most favoured captaines were compelled to feed upon his flesh, which with their teeth they must teare off and swallow their morsels. The rest of his body and entrailes, he being dead, were boiled in a pan, and given for food to other of his followers. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXVIII: ALL THINGS HAVE THEIR SEASON. CHAPTER XXVIII: ALL THINGS HAVE THEIR SEASON. HOSE who compare Cato the Censor to Cato the Younger that killed himself, compare two notable natures, and in form neare one unto another. The first exploited his sundrie waies and excelleth in military exploits and utilitie of his public vacations. But the youngers virtue (besides that it were blasphemy in vigor to compare any unto him) was much more sincere and unspotted. For who will discharge the Censors of envie and ambition that durst counterchecke the honor of Scipio in goodnes and all other parts of excellencie, far greater and better than him or any other man living in his age? Amongst other things reported of him, this is one, that in his eldest a he gave himself with so earnest a longing to the Greek tong, as if it had been to quench a long burning thirst, a thing in mine opinion not very honorable in him. It is properly that which we call doting, or to become a child again. All things have their season indeed the good and all. And I may say my Paternoster out of season. As T. Quintius Flaminius was accused, forasmuch as being general of an army, even in the hour of the conflict he was seen to withdraw himself apart, ammusing,himself to pray God, although he gained the battle. Imponit finem sapiens et rebus honestis. -- JUVEN. Sat. vi. 344 A wise-man will use moderation, Even in things of commendation. Eudemonidas seeing Xenocrates very old laboriously apply himself in his schoole- lectures, said, When will this man know something, since he is yet learning? And Philopoemen, to those who highly extolled King Ptolomey because he daily hardened his body to the exercise of arms: It is not (said he) a matter commendable in a King of his age in them to exercise himself, he should now really and substantially employ them. Wise men say that young men should make their preparations and old men enjoy them. And the greatest vice they note in us is, that our desires do uncessantly grow yonger and yonger. We are ever beginning anew to live. Our studies and our desires should sometimes have a feeling of age. We have a foote in the grave, and our appetites and pursuits are but new-borne. Tu secanda marmora Locas sub ipsum funus, et sepulcri Immemor, struis domos. -- HOR. Car. 1. ii. ed. xviii. You, when you should be going to your grave, Put marble out to work, in houses brave, Unmindfull of the burial you must have. The longest of my desseignes does not extend to a whole yeare: now I only apply my self to make an end: I shake off all my new hopes and enterprises: I bid my last farewell to all the places I leave, and daily dispossess my self of what I have. Olim jam nec perit quicquam mihi, nec acquiritur. Plus superest viatici quam viæ (17. 2 SEN. Epist. lxxvii.) ’It is a good while since I neither loose nor get any thing: I have more to bear my charges then way to go.’ Vixi, et quem de derat cursum fortuna peregi. --VIRG. Æn. 1. iv. 653. I have liv’d, and the race have past Wherein my fortune had me plac’t. To conclude, it is all the case I find in my age, and that it suppresseth many cares and desires in me wherewith life is much disquieted. The care of the worlds course, the care of riches, of greatness, of knowledge, of health, and of my self. This man learneth to speak when he should rather learne to hold his peace for ever. A man may alwaies continue his study, but not schooling. O fond-foolish for an old man to be ever an Abecedarian. Diversos diversa iuvant, non omnibus annis Omnia conveniunt. ----- CATUL. Eleg. i. 103. Diverse delights to diverse nor to all Do all things at all years convenient fall. If we must needs study, let us study something sorteable to our condition, that we may answer as he did, who being demanded what his studies would stead him in his decrepity, answered that he might the better and with more ease leave this world. Such a study was yong Catoes in forefeeling his approaching end, who lighted upon Platoes discourse on the soules immortality. Not as it may be supposed that long before he had not stored himself with all sorts of munition for such a dislodging. Of assurance, of constancy and instruction, he had more than Plato has in all his writings. His science and his courage were in this respect above all Philosophy. He undertook this occupation, not for the service of his death, but as one who did not so much as interrupt his sleep in a deliberation of such consequence, who ever without choice or change continued his wonted studies, and all other accustomed actions of his life. The same night wherein the Pretorship was refused him he passed over in play. That wherein he must die, he spent in reading. The loss of life or office was all one to him. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXIX: OF VERTUE CHAPTER XXIX: OF VERTUE FINDE by experience that there is great difference betweene the sodaine fits and fantasies of the soul, and a resolute disposition and constant habitude: and I see there is nothing but we may attaine unto, indeed, as some say, to exceed Divinitie itself; forasmuch as it is more to become impassible of himself, then to be so by his originall condition: and that one may join a resolution and assurance of God to mens imbecillitie. But it is by fits. And in the lives of those heroes or noble worthies of former ages, are often found wonderful parts, and which seems greatly to exceed our natural forces: but they are prankes or parts consonant to truth: and it may hardly be believed mans soul may so be tainted and fed with those so high-raised conditions, that onto it they may become as ordinary and natural. It happens unto ourselves, who are but abortive broods of men, sometimes to rowse our soul far beyond her ordinary pitch, as stirred up by the discourses or provoked by the examples of others. But it is a kind of passion which urgeth, mooveth, agitateth, and in some sort ravisheth her from out her self: for, that gust overblowne and storme past, we see it wil unawares unbend and lose itself, if not to the lowest pitch, at least to be no more the same she was, so that upon every slight occasion, for a bird lost or for a glasse broken, we suffer ourselves to be mooved and distempered very near as one of the vulgar sort. Except order, moderation, and constancy, I imagine all things may be done by an indifferent and defective man. Therefore say wise men, that directly to judge of a man, his common actions must specially be controuled, and he must every day be surprised in his work-day clothes. Pyrrho, who framed so pleasant a science of ignorance, assaied (as all other true philosophers) to fashion his life answerable to his doctrine. And forasmuch as he maintained the weaknesse of mans judgement to be so extreme as it could take nor resolution nor inclination: and would perpetually suspend it, ballancing, bebolding and receiving all things as indifferent: it is reported of him that he ever kept himself after one fashion, looke and countenance. If he had begunne a discourse, he would end it, though the party to whom he spake were gone: and if he went any where, he would not go an inche out of his path what let or obstacle soever came in his way; being kept from falls, from cartes, or other accidents by his friends. For, to fear or shunne any thing had been to shocke his propositions, which remooved all election and certainty from his very senses. He sometimes suffered himself to be cut and cautherized with such constancy as he was never seen so much as to shrug, twitch, move, or winke with his eyes. It is something to bring the mind to these imagination, but more to joine the effects unto it, yet is it not impossible. But to joine them with such perseverance and constancy as to establish it for an ordinary course; verily in these enterprises so far from common use, it is almost incredible to be done. The reason is this, that he was sometimes found in his house bitterly scolding with his sister for which being reproved as he that wronged his indifferencie; ’What!’ said he, ’must this seely woman also serve as a witness to my rules?’ Another time, being found to defend himself from a dog: ’It is,’ replied he, ’very hard altogether to dispoile and shake off man;’ and man must endeavor and enforce himself to resist and confront all things, first by effects, but if the worst befall, by reason and by discourse. It is now about seven or eight years since, that a country man yet living not above two leagues from this place, having long before been much vexed and troubled in mind for his wives jealousies one day coming home from his work, and she after her accustomed manner welcomming and entertaining him with brawling and scowlding, as, one unable to endure her any longer, fell into such a moodie rage that sodainely with a sickle which he held in his hand he clean cut off those parts that were the cause of her jealousies and flung them in her face. And it is reported that a yong gentleman of France, amorous and lustie, having by his perseverance at last mollified the heart of his fair mistresse, desperate, because coming to the point of his so long sued-for businesses he found himself unable and unprepared, and that as -----non viriliter Iners senile penis extulerat caput, --Tib. ad Priap. v. 4. soone as he came home he deprived himself of it, and sent it as a cruel and bloudy sacrifice for the expiation of his offence. Had he done it by discourse or for religions sake, as the priestes of Cybele were wont to do, what might we not say of so haughty an enterprise? Not long since at Bragerac, five leagues distance from my house, up the river of Dordaigne, a woman, having the evening before been grievously tormented and sore beaten by her husband, froward and skittish by complexion, determined, though it should cost her the price of her life, by one meane or other to escape his rudeness, and rising the next morning, went as she was accustomed to visite her neighbors, to whom in some sort she recommended the state of her affairs, then taking a sister of hirs by the hand, ledde her along until she came upon the bridge that crosseth the river, and having bid her hartily farewell, as in the way of sport, without shewing any manner of change or alteration, headlong threw hirselfe down into the river, where she perished. And which is more to be noted in her is, that this her determination ripened a whole night in her head. But the Indian wives may not here be forgotten as worthy the noting: whose custom is, that husbands have many wives, and for her that is dearest unto her husband to kill herself after him: every one in the whole course of her life endevoreth to obtaine this priviledge and advantage over all her fellow wives: and in the good offices and duties they show their husbands, respect no other recompence than to be preferred to accompany them in death. Ubi mortifero jacta est fax ultima lecto, ------Uxorem fusis, stat pia turba comis: Et certamen habent Læthi, quæ viva sequator ------Coniugium, pudor est non licuisse mori: Ardent victrices, et flammæ pectora præbent, -----Imponuntque suis ora perusta viris -- Propert. iii. El. xii. 17. When for his death-bed last flame is appli’d With loose haires many kind wives stand beside, And strive for death, which alive may be next Hir wedlocke, who may not, is sham’d and vex’t: They that orecome, are burn’d, to flames give way, Their bodies burnt on their burnt husbands lay. A late Writer affirrneth that himself has seen this custom highly reputed in the new discovered East Indiaes, where not only the wives are buried with their husbands, but also such slaves as he has enjoyed, which is done after this manner. The husband being deceased, the widdow may, if she will (but few do it, request two or three monthes space to dispose of her busines. The day come, adorned as a sumptuous bride, she mounteth on horsebacke, and with a cheereful countenance telleth everybody she is going to lie with her bridegroome, holding in her left hand a looking-glasse, and an arrow in the right. Thus having a while rid up and down in great pomp and magnificence, accompanied with her friends and kinsmen, and much concourse of people, in feast and jollitie, she is brought into a public place, purposely appointed for such spectacles; which is a large open place, in the middest whereof is a pit or grave full of wood, and near unto it an upraised scaffold, with foure or five steppes to ascend, upon which she is brought, and served with a stately and sumptuous banket, which ended, she beginneth to dance and sing, and when she thinks good, commandeth the fire to be kindled. That done, she commeth down again, and taking the nearest of her husbands kindred by the hand, they go together to the next river, where she strippes herself all naked and distributeth her jewels and cloathes among her friends, then plungeth herself in the water, as if she meant to wash away her sins; then coming out she enwrappeth herself in a yellow piece of linnen cloth, about the length of fourteene yards; and giving her band again unto her husbands kinsmen, they return unto the mount, where she speaks unto the people, to whom (if she have any) she recommendeth her children. Betweene the pitte and mount there is commonly a curtaine drawne, lest the sight of that burning furnace might dismay them: which many, to show the greater courage, wil not have it drawne. Her speech ended, a woman presenteth her with a vessell ful of oyl, therewith to annoint her head and body, which done, she casteth the rest into the fire, and therewithall sodainly flings herself into it: which is no sooner done but the people cast great stors of faggots and billets upon her, lest she should languish over-long: and all their joy is converted into grief and sorrow. If they be persons of meane quality, the dead mans body is carried to the place where they intend to bury him, and there he is placed sitting; his widdow kneeling before him with her arms close about his middle, and so keepeth hirself whilst a wall is erected up about them both, which raised to the height of her shoulders, some of her kindred taking her by the head behind, wrings her neck about, and having given the last gasp, the wall is immediately made up close over their heads, wherein they remain buried. In the same country there was something like to this in their Gymnosophists, or wise men, who not by menaces or compulsions of others, nor by the violence of a sodaine humor, but by the express and voluntary profession of their rule, their manner was according as they attained unto a certain age, or saw themselves threatned by some sicknesse, to cause a pile of wood to be erected and upon it a rich bedde; and having cheerfully feasted their friends and acquaintance, with such a resol ution laid themselves down in that bed, that fire set unto it, they were never seen to stir nor hand nor foot; and thus died one of them named Calanus in the presence of all the army of Alexander the Great. And who had not so made himself away was neither esteemed holy nor absolutely happy among them; sending his soul purged and purified by fire after it had consumed whatsoever was mortal and terrestrial in it. This constant premeditation of al the life is that which makes the wonder. Amongst our other disputation, that of Fatum has much entermedled itself: and to join future things and our wil itself unto a certain unavoydable necessitie, we yet stand upon that argument of former times: since God forseeth al things must thus happen, as undoubtedly he doeth: they must then necessarily happen so. To which our clarks and maisters answere, that to see any thing come to pass as we do, and likewise God (for he being present in ful essence rather seeth than foreseeth), is not to force the same to happen: indeed we see because things come to pass, but things happen not because we see. The hapning makes the science or knowledge, and not knowledge the happening. What we see come to pass, happeneth; but it might come to pass otherwise. And God in the eternall register of the causes of happenings, which he has in his prescience, has also those which are called casual; and the voluntary, which depend of the liberty he has given unto our free will, and knows we shall faile, because our will shall have been to faile. I have seen diverse encourage their troupes with this fatall necessitie; for, if our hour be tied unto a certain point neither the musket-shottes of our enemy, nor our courage, nor our flight and cowardice can either advance or recoyle the same. This may well be said, but seek you who shall effect it: and if it be so that a strong and lively faith does likewise draw action after it: truely this faith (wherewith we so much fil our mouthes) is marvelous light in our times, except the contempt it has of works, make her disdaine their company. So it is that to the same purpose the Lord of Joinville, as credible a witness as any other, tells us of the Bedoins, a nation intermingled with the Saracine, with whom our King Saint Lewis had to deale in the holy land who so confidently believed in their religion the dayes of every one to be prefixed and numbred from all eternity by an inevitable preordinance, that they went al bare and naked to the wars except a Turkish glaive in their hand, and their body covered but with a white linnen cloth: and for the bitterest curse, if they chanced to fall out one with another, they had ever in their mouth: ’Cursed be then as he that armeth himself for fear of death.’ Here is another manner of trial or a belief or faith then ours. In this rank may likewise be placed that which those two religious men of Florence not long since gave unto their countrymen. Being in some controversie betweene themselves about certain points of learning, they accorded to go both into the fire in the presence of al the people and in the open market place, each one for the verifying of his opinion; and all preparations were ready made and execution to be performed, but that by an unexpected accident it was interrupted. A yong Turkish Lord, having achieved a notable piece of service in arms and with his own person in ful view of the two battles between Ammurath and Huniades ready to be joined together, being demanded by Ammurath his prince, who being so yong and inexperienced (for it was the first war or service he had seen before) had replenished him with so generous and undanted vigor of courage, answered that a hare had been his soveraigue maister and only teacher of valor; and thus began his speech: Being one day a hunting, I found a hare sitting in her form, and although I had a brace of excellent good greyhounds with me in a slip or leash, I thought it good, because I would be sure of my same to use my bow; for she was a very fair marke. I begaune to shoot my arrows at her, which I did to the number of fortie (for in my quiver were just so many), yet could I never hurt her, no not so much as start her. After all this I let slip my grayhounds, who could do no more than I had done: by which I learnt that she had been sheltred and defended by her destinie; and that no glaives nor arrows never hit but by the permission of our fatalitie, which it lieth not in us to avoide or to advance. This story may serve to make us perceive by the way how flexible our reason is to all sorts of objects. A notable man, great in years, in name, in dignity, and in learning, vaunted himself unto me, that he was induced to a certain most important change of his religion by a strange and fantastical incitation: and in al things so il concluding that I deemed the same stronger and more forcible being taken contrary. He termed it a miracle, and so did I, but in a different sense. Their historians say that persuasion having popularly been scattered amongst the Turkes of the fatal and inflexible prescription of their dayes, does apparently aide to warrant and embolden them in dangers. And I know a great Prince who happily thrives by it, be it he believe it or take it for an excuse to hazard himself extraordinarily; provided fortune be not soone wearie to favor and backe him. There has not happened in our memory a more admirable effect of resolution than of those two villaines that conspired the death of the Prince of Orange: it is strange how the last who performed the same could be induced or encouraged to undergo such an enterprize, wherein his fellow (though he had resolutely attempted it and had all might be required for such an action) had so ill success and miscarried. And in those steps and with the same weapons to go and undertake a Lord, armed with so late an instruction of distrust; mighty in friends and followers, puissant of bodily strength, in his own hall, amiddest his servants and guarde, and in a city wholly at his devotion. It must of force be said that in performing it he employed a well-directed and resolute band and a dreadlesse courage, mooved by a vigorous passion. A poynard is more sure to wound a man, which forasmuch as it requireth more motion and vigor of the arm than a pistol, its stroke is more subject to be hindred or avoyded. That the first ranne not to an assured death I make no great doubt, for the hopes wherewith he might be entertained could not harbour in a well-setled and resolute midde, and the conduct of his exploit sheweth he wanted no more that then courage. The motions of so forcible a persuasion may be diverse, for our fantasia disposeth of herself and of us as she pleaseth. The execution committed near Orleans had no coherence with this wherein was more hazard than vigor; the blow was not mortal had not fortune made it so, and the enterprise to shoote on horsebacke and far-off, and to one who mooved still according to the motion of his horse, was the attempt of a man that rather loved to misse of his effect then faile to save himself. What followed did manifestly show it; for he was so amazed and drunken with the thought of so haughty an execution, as he lost all his senses, both to work his escape and direct his tongue in his answers. What needed he have done more then recover his friends by crossing of a river? It is a meane wherein I have cast my self in far less dangers; and which I think of small hazard, how broad soever, alwayes provided your horse find an easy entrance, and on the further side you forsee an easy and shallow landing, according to the course of the streame of the water. The second, when the horrible sentence was pronounced against him, answered stoutly: I was prepared for it, and I shall amaze you with my patience. The Assassines, a nation depending of Phoenicia, are esteemed among the Mahometists of a sovereign devotion and puritie of maners: they hold that the readiest and shortest way to gain Paradise is to kill some one of a contrary religion; therefore has it often been seen that one or two in their bare doublets have undertaken to assault mighty enemies with the price of an assured death and without any care of their own danger. And thus was our Earle Raymond of Tripoli murthered or assassinated (this word is borrowed from their name) in the middest of his citie, daring the time of our wars in the holy land; and likewise Conrade Marquis of Montferrat his murtherers being brought to their torture, were seen to swell with pride that they had performed so worthy an exploit. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXX: OF A MONSTROUS CHILD. CHAPTER XXX: OF A MONSTROUS CHILD. HIS discourse shall pass single, for I leave it to Physitians to treat of. I saw two dayes since a child whom two men and a nurse (which named themselves to be his father, his uncle, and his aunt) carried about with intent to get some money with the sight of him, by reason of his strangenesse. In all the rest he was as other children are: he stood upon his feete, went and prattled in a manner as all others of his age. He would never take nourishment but by his nurses breast; and what in my presence was offred to be put in his mouth he chewed a little and put it all out again. His puling differed somewhat from others: he was just fourteene monthes olde. Under his paps he was fastned and joined to another child, but had no head, and who had the conduite of his backe stopped; the rest whole. One of his arms was shorter than the other, and was by accident broken at their birth. They were joined face to face, and as if a little child would embrace another somewhat bigger. The joyning and space whereat they were closed together was but foure inches broad, or thereabouts; in such sort that if you thrust up the imperfect child you might see under the others navill; and the seame was betweene the paps and his navill. The navill of the imperfect one could not be seen, but all the rest of his belly might. Thus, what of the imperfect one was not joined, as arms, buttocks, thighes, and legs, did hang and shake upon the other, whose length reached to the middle-leg of the other perfect. His nurse told me he made water by both privities. The members of the little one were nourished, living, and in the same state as the others, except only they were less and thinner. This double body nd these different members, having reference to one only head, might serve for a favorable prognostication to our King to maintaine the factions and different parties of this our kingdome under a unitie of the laws. But least the success should prove it contrary, it is not amisse to let him run his course; for in things already past there need no divination. Vt quum facta sun t, tum ad conjecturam aliquid interpretatione revocantur:(Cic. Divin. ii.) ’So as when they are done they then by some construction should be revoked to conjecture.’ As it is reported of Epimenides, who ever devined backward. I come now from seeing of a shepherd at Medoc, of thirty years of age or thereabouts, who had no signe at all of genitorie parts, but where they should be are three little holes by which his water does continually tril from him. This poore man has a beard, and desires still to be fumbling of women. Those which we call monsters are not so with God, who in the immensitie of his work seeth the infinite of formes therein contained. And it may be thought that any figure does amaze us, has relation unto some other figure of the same kind, although unknown unto man. From out his all-seeing wisdom proceedeth nothing but good, common, regular, and orderly; but we neither see the sorting, nor conceive the relation. Quod crebro videt, non miratur, etiam si, cur fiat, nescit. Quod an te non vidit, id, si evenerit, ostentum esse censet (CIC. Div. 1. II.). ’That which he often seeth he does not wonder at, though he know not why it is done; but if that happen which he never saw before, he thinkes it some portentous wonder.’ We call that against nature which commeth against custom. There is nothing, whatsoever it be, that is not according to her. Let therefore this universall and natural reason chase from us the error, and expell the astonishment which noveltie breedeth and strangenes causeth in us. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXI: OF ANGER AND CHOLER CHAPTER XXXI: OF ANGER AND CHOLER LUTARKE is everywhere admirable, but especially where he judgeth of humane actions. The notable things he reporteth may be perceived in the comparison of Lycurgus and Numa, speaking of the great simplicity we commit in leaving long children under the government and charge of their fathers and parents. Most of our policies or commonwealths, says Aristotle (as the Cyclopes were wont) commit the conduct of their wives and charge of their children to all men, according to their foolish humor or indiscreete fantasies. And well-nigh none but the Lacedemonian and Cretensian have resigned the discipline of children to the laws. Who seeth not that in an estate all things depend of nurture and education? And all the while, without discretion, it is wholly left to the parents mercy how foolish and wicked soever they be. Amongst other things, how often (walking through our streets) have I desired to have a play or comedie made in revenge of young boyes, which I saw thumpt, misused, and well-nigh murthered by some harebrained, moodie, and through choler-raging fathers and mothers, from out whose eyes a man might see sparkles of rage to startle. ------ rabie jecur incendente feruntur Præcipites, ut saxa jugis abrupta, quibus mons Subtrahitur, clivoque latus pendente recedit: -- JUV. Sat. vi. 548. They headlong run with rage, which does enflame their livers Like stones that broken fall from mountaine tops in shivers, The hill withdrawes, and they are rould From hanging cliffe which leaves their hold (And according to Hypocrates, the most dangerous infirmities are those which disfigure the face), and with a loud thundring voice often to follow children that came but lately from nurse, which after prove lame, maimed, blockish and dull-pated with blowes; and yet our laws makes no accompt of it, as if these spraines and unjoyntings of limbes, or these maimes were no members of our commonwealth. Gratum est quod patrim civem populoque dedisti, Si facis ut patriæ sit idoneus, utilis aqris, Vtilis et bellorum et pacis rebus agendis. -- Juv. Sat. xiv. 70. That you to th’countrie give a man, ’tis acceptable, If for the countrie fit you make him, for fields able, Of peace and war for all achievements profitable. There is no passion so much transports the sinceritie of judgement as does anger. No man would make conscience to punish that judge by death who in rage or choler had condemned an offender. And why should fathers be allowed to beate or schoolmasters be suffered to whip children, or to punish them, being angry? It is no longer correction, but revenge. Punishment is unto children as physicke, and would any man endure a physician that were angrie and wroth against his patient? Our selves (did we well), during the time of our anger, should never lay hands on our servants. So long as our pulse panted, and we feel any concitation, so long remit we the partie: and things will seem far otherwise unto us if we once come to our senses again, and shall better bethinke us. Then is it passion that commandes. It is passion that speaks, and not we. Athwart it, faults seem much greater unto us, as bodies do athwart a foggy mist. Whoso is hungry useth meat, but whoso will use chastisement should never hunger nor thirst after it. Moreover, corrections given with discretion and moderation are more gently received, and with more good to him that receiveth them. Otherwise he shall never think to have been justly condemned by a man who is transported by rage and choler, and for his justification alleadgeth the extraordinary motions of his maister, the inflammation of his face, his unwonted oaths, his chafing, his unquietnesse, and his rash precipitation. Ora tument ira, nigrescunt sanguine venæ: Lumina Gorgoneo sævius igne micant. -- OVID. Art. Am. 1. iii. 53. The face with anger swelles, the veines grow blacke with blood, The eyes more fiercely shine than Gorgons fierie moode. Suetonius writeth that Caius Rabirius, having by Cæsar been condemned, nothing did him so much good towards the people (to whom he appealed) to make him obtain his suit, as the sharpnes and over-boldnes which Cæsar had declared in that judgement. Saying is one thing, and doing another. A man must consider the sermon apart and the preacher severall. Those have made themselves good sport who in our dayes have gone about to checke the veritie of our Church by the ministers vice: she fetcheth her testimony from elsewhere. It is a foolish manner of arguing, and which would soone reduce all things to a confusion. An honest man may sometimes have false opinions, and a wicked man may preach truth: indeed such a one as beleeves it not. Verily it is a pleasing harmonie when doing and saying go together. And I will not deny but saying when deeds follow is of more efficacie and authority: as said Eudamidas when he heard a philosopher discourse of war: these speeches are good, but he that speaks them is not to be beleeved, for his ears were never accustomed to hear the clang of trumpets nor rattling of drums. And Cleomenes, hearing a rhetoritian speak of valor, burst out into an extreme laughter; whereat the other being offended, he said unto him: ’I would do as much if it were a swallow should speak of it, but were be an eagle I should gladly hear him.’ Me seems I perceive in ancient mens writings that he who speaks what he thinketh toucheth nearer the quick than he who counterfeits. Heare Cicero speak of the love of liberty, then listen to Brutus: their wordes will tell you and sound in your eare, the latter was a man readie to purchase it with the price of his life. Let Cicero, that father of eloquence, treate of the contempt of death, and let Seneca discourse of the same; the first draws it on languishing, and would faine resolve you of a thing whereof he has not yet resolved himself. He gives you no heart, for himself has none: whereas the other does rowze, animate, and inflame you. I never looke upon an author, be they such as write of virtue and of actions, but I curiously endeavor to find out what he was himself. For the Ephori of Sparta, hearing a dissolute liver propose a very beneficial advise unto the people, commanded him to hold his peace, and desired an honest man to assume the invention of it unto himself, and to propound it. Plutarkes compositions, if they be well savored, do plainely manifest the same unto us: and I am persuaded I know him inwardly: yet would I be glad we had some memories of his own life: and by the way I am falne into this discourse, by reason of the thanks I owe unto Aulus Gellius, in that he has left us written this story of his manners, which fitteth my story of anger. A slave of his, who was a lewd and vicious man, but yet whose ears were somewhat fedde with philosophicall documents, having for some faults by him committed, by the commandement of Plutarke his master been stripped naked, whilst another servant of his whipped him, grumbled in the beginning that he was whipped without reason and had done nothing: but in the end mainly crying out, he fell to railing and wronging his master, upbraiding him that he was not a true Philosopher, as he vanted himself to be, and how he had often heard him say that it was an unseemely thing in a man to be angry. And that he had made a book of it: and now, all plunged in rage and engulf’ed in choler, to cause him so cruelly to be beaten was cleane contrary to his own writing. To whom Plutarke, with an unaltered and mild-setled countenance, said thus unto him: ’What, you raskall, whereby doest you judge I am now angrie? Does my countenance, does my voice, does my colour, or does my speech give you any testimony that I am either moved or cholericke? Mee seems mine eyes are not staringly wild, nor my face troubled, nor voice frightful or distempered. Doe I waxe red? Do I foame at the mouth? Does any word escape me I may repent hereafter? Doe I startle and quake? Doe I rage and ruffle with anger? For to tell you true, these are the right signes of choler and tokens of anger.’ Then turning to the party that whipped him: ’Continue still your work,’ quoth he, whilst this fellow and I dispute of the matter.’ This is the report of Gellius. Architas Tarentinus returning from a war where he had been captaine general, found his house all out of order, husbandrie all spoiled, and by the ill government of his bailiffe, his ground all waste and unmanured; and having called for him, said thus: ’Away, bad man, for if I were not angrie I would have you whipt for this.’ Plato likewise being vexed and angrie with one of his slaves, commanded Speusippus to punish him, excusing himself that now being angrie he would not lay hands upon him. Charilus the Lacedemonian, to an Helot who behaved himself over insolently and audaciously towards him, by the Gods (says he) if I were not now angrie I would presently make you die. It is a passion which pleaseth and flattereth itself. How many times being moved by any false suggestion, if at that instant we be presented with any lawfull defense or true excuse, do we fall into rage against truth and innocencie itself? Touching this purpose, I have retained a wonderful example of antiquitie. Piso, in diverse other respects a man of notable virtue, being angrie, and chafing with one of his soldiers, who returning from forage or boothbaling, could not give him an accompt where he had left a fellow-souldier of his, and thereupon concluding he had killed or made him away, forthwith condemned him to be hanged. And being upon the gallowes and ready to dye behold his companion who had stragled abroade, coming home, whereat all the army rejoiced very much, and after many embracings and signes of joy between the two soldiers, the hangman brought both unto Piso, all the company hoping it would be a great pleasure unto him; but it fell out cleane contrary, for through shame and spite, his wrath, still burning, was redoubled, and with a slie devise his passion instantly presented to his mind, he made three guiltie, forasmuch as one of them was found innocent, and caused them all three to be dispatched: the first souldier because he was alreadie condemned; the second, which had stragled abroade, by reason he was the cause of his fellowes death; and the hangman for that he had not fulfilled his generalls commandement. Those who have to deale with froward and skittish women have no doubt seen what rage they will fall into, if when they are most angrie and chafing a man be silent and patient, and disdains to foster their anger and wrath. Celius the orator was by nature exceedingly fretfull and cholerike. To one who was with him at supper, a man of a mild and gentle conversation, and who because he would not move him, seemed to approve whatever he said, and yield to him in every thing, as unable to endure his peevishness should so pass without some nourishment, burst out into a rage and said unto him: ’For the love of God, deny me something, that we may be two.’ So women are never angrie but to the end a man should again be angrie with them, therein imitating the laws of love. Phocion to a man who troubled his discourse with brawling and scolding at him in most injurious manner, did nothing else but hold his peace, and give him what leisure he would to vent his choler, which done, without taking any notice of it, began his discourse again where he had left it off. There is no reply so sharpe as such silent contempt. Of the most cholerlike and testie man of France (which is ever an imperfection, but more excusable in a military man, for it must needs be granted there are in that profession some men who cannot well avoyde it) I ever say he is the patientest man I knowe to bridle his choler; it mooveth and transporteth him with such fury and violence -- ------ magno veluti cum flamma sonore Virgea suggeritur costis undantis aheni, Exultantque æstu latices, furit intus aquai Fumidus atque alte spumis exuberat amnis, Nec jam se capit unda, volat vapor ater ad auras -- VIRG. Æn. 1. vii. 462. As when a fagot flame with hurring sounds Under the ribbes of boyling cauldron lies, The water swelles with heat beyond the bounds, Whence streaming streames raging and foaming rise, Water out-runs itself, blacke vapours flye to skies -- that he must cruelly enforce himself to moderate the same. And for my part I know noe passion I were able to smother with such temper and abide with such resolution. I would not set wisdom at so high a rate. I respect not so much what he does as how much it cost him not to do worse. Another boasted in my presence of his behaviours order and mildness, which in truth is singular. I tolde him that indeed it was much, namely, in men of so eminent a quality as himself was, on whom all eyes are fixed, alwaies to show himself in a good temper; but that the chiefest point consisted in providing inwardly and for himself; and that in mine opinion it was no discreet part inwardly to fret: which, to maintaine that marke and formall outward appearance, I feared he did. Choler is incorporated by concealing and smothering the same, as Diogenes said to Demosthenes, who fearing to be seen in a taverne withdrew himself into the same. The more you recoylest backe, the further you goest into it. I would rather persuade a man, though somewhat out of season, to give his boy a wherrat on the eare, then to dissemble this wise, sterile or severe countenance, to vex and fret his mind. And I would rather make show of my passions then smother them to my cost, which being vented and exprest, become more languishing and weake: better it is to let its pointe work outwardly, then bend it against ourselves. Omnia vitia in aperto leviora aunt: et tunc perniciosissima, quum simulata sanitate subsidunt; (SEN. Epist. lvi.) ’All vices are then less perilous when they lie open to be seen, but then most pernitious when they lurke under counterfeited soundenesse.’ I ever warne those of my household who by their offices-authority may sometimes have occasion to be angry, first to husband their anger, then not employ it upon every slight cause; for that impeacheth the effect and worth of it. Rash and ordinary brawling is converted to a custom, and thats the reason each man contemnes it. That which you employ against a servant for any theeving is not perceived, because it is the same he has sundry times seen you use against him if he have not washt a glasse well or misplaced a stoole. Secondly, that they be not angry in vain, but ever have regard their chiding come to his ears with whom they are offended; for commonly some will brawle before he come in their presence, and chide a good while after he is gone -- Et secure petulans amentia certat, -- CLAUD. in Eu. 1. i. 48. Madnesse makes with itself a fray, Which fondly does the wanton play -- and avenge their anger against his shadow, and make the storme fall where no man is either chastised or interested, but with the rumour of their voice, and sometimes with such as cannot do withall. I likewise blame those who being angry will brave and mutiny when the partie with whom they are offended is not by. These Rodomontados must be employed on such as fear them. Mugitus veluti cum prima in prælia taurus Terrificos ciet, atqui irasci in cornua tentat, Arboris obnixus trunco, ventosque lacessit Ictibus, et sparsa ad pugnam proludit arena. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. xii. 103. As when a furious bull to his first combats mooves His terror-breeding lowes, his horne to anger prooves, Striving against a trees trunke, and the wind with strokes, His preface made to fight with scattered sand, provokes. When I chance to be angrie it is in the earnestest manner that may be, but yet as briefly and as secretly as is possible. I lose my self in hastiness and violence, but not in trouble. So that let me spend all manner of injurious words at randome and without all heed, and never respect, to place my points pertinently, and where they may do most hurt: for commonly I employ nothing but my tongue. My boyes scape better cheape in great matters then in small trifles. Slight occasions surprise me, and the mischief is that after you are once falne into the pits it is no matter who thrusts in, you never cease till you come to the bottome. The fall presseth, hasteneth, mooveth, and furthereth itself. In great occasions I am pleased that they are so just, that every body expects a reasonable anger to insue. I glorify my self to deceive their expectation. Against these I bandy and prepare my self; they make me summon up my wits and threaten to carry me very far if I would follow them. I easily keep my self from falling into them, and if I stay for them I am strong enough to reject the impulsion of this passion, what violent cause soever it has. But if it seize upon and once preoccupate me, what vain cause soever it has, it does cleane transport me: I condition thus with those that may contest with me, when you perceive me to be first angry, be it right or wrong, let me hold on my course, I will do the like to you whenever it shall come to my lot. There is not engendred but by the concurrence of cholers, which are easily produced one of another, and are not borne at one instant. Let us allow every man his course, so shall we ever be in peace. Oh profitable prescription, but of an hard execution! I shall sometime seem to be angry for the order and direction of my house, without any just emotion. According as my age yieldeth my humors more sharp and peevish, so do I endeavor to oppose my self against them and if I can I will hereafter enforce my self to be less froward and not so testy, as I shall have more excuse and inclinations to be so; although I have heretofore been in their number that are least. A word more to conclude this chapter: Aristotle says choler does sometimes serve as arms unto Vertue and Valor. It is very likely: notwithstanding such as gainsay him, answer pleasantly, it is a weapon of a new fashion and strange use. For we moove other weapons but this mooveth us; our hand does not guide it, but it directeth our hand; it holdeth us, and we hold not it. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXII: A DEFENCE OF SENECA AND PLUTARKE. CHAPTER XXXII: A DEFENCE OF SENECA AND PLUTARKE. HE familiarity I have with these two men, and the aid they affoord me in my old age, and my book meerely framed of their spoiles, bindeth me to wed and maintaine their honor. As for Seneca, amongest a thousand petty pamphlets those of the pretended reformed religion have published, for the defense of their cause, which now and then proceede from a good hand, and which, pity it is, it should not be employed in more serious and better subjects, I have heretofore seen one who, to prolong and fill up the similitude he would find betweene the government of our unfortunate late King Charles the Ninth and that of Nero, compareth the whilom Lord Cardinall of Lorraine, unto Seneca; their fortunes to have been both chief men in the government of their Princes, and therewithall their manners, their conditions, and their demeanours. Wherein (in mine opinion) he does the said Lord Cardinall great honor: for although I be one of those that highly respect his spiri,t his worth, his eloquence, his zeale towards his religion, and the service of his King; and his good fortune to have been borne in an age wherein he was so new, so rare, and therewithall so necessary for the commonwealth, to have a clergie man of such dignitie and nobility, sufficient and capable of so weighty a charge; yet to confesse the truth, I esteeme not his capacitie such, nor his virtue so exquisitely unspotted, nor so entire or constante as that of Seneca. Now this book whereof I speak, to come to his intention, maketh a most injurious description of Seneca, having borrowed his reproaches from Dion the historian, to whose testimony I give no credit at all: for besides he is inconstant, as one who after he has called Seneca exceeding wise, and shortly after termed him a mortal enemy to Neroes vices, in other places makes him covetous, given to usurie, ambitious, base-minded, voluptuous, and under false pretences and feigned shewes, a counterfet philosopher; his virtue appeareth so lively, and wisdom so vigorous in his writings, and the defense of these imputations is so manifest, as well of his riches as of his excessive expences, that I believe no witness to the contrary . Moreover, there is great reason we should rather give credit to Roman historians in such things then to Græcians and strangers, whereas Tacitus and others speak very honourably of his life and death, and in other circumstance declare him to have been a most excellent and rarely vertuous man, I wil alleadge no other reproach against Dions judgement then this, which is unavoydable; that is, his understanding of the Roman affairs is so weake and il advised as he dareth defend and maintaine Juli us Cæsars cause against Pompey, and blusheth not to justify Antonius against Cicero. But let us come to Plutarke. John Bodin is a good modern author, and endowed with much more judgement then the common rabble of scriblers and blur-papers which now adayes stuffe stationers shops, and who deserveth to be judged, considered, and had in more then ordinary esteeme. Nevertheless I find him somewhat malapert and bolde in that passage of his ’Methode of Historie,’ when he accuses Plutarke, not onl y of ignorance (wherein I would have let him say his pleasure, for that is not within my element, but also that he often writeth things altogether incredible and meerely fabulous (these are his very words). If he had simply said things otherwise then they are, it had been no great reprehension; for what we have not seen we receive from others and upon trust; and I see him sometime, wittingly and in good earnest, report one and same story diversly; as the judgements of three best captaines that ever were, spoken by Hanibal, is otherwise in Flaminius his life, and otherwise in Pyrrhus. But to taxe him to have taken incredible and impossible things for ready payment is to accuse the most judicious author of the world of want of judgement. And see here his example: As, says he, when he reports that a child of Lacedemon suffered all his belly and gutts to be torn out by a cubbe or young foxe, which he had stolne and kept close under his garment, rather then he would discover his theft. First, I find this example ill chosen; forasmuch as it is hard to limit the powers of the soules faculties, whereas of corporall forces, we have more law to limite and know them; and therefore had I been to write of such a subject, I would rather have made choyce of an example of this second kind. And some there be less credible. As amongst others that which he reported of Pyrrhus, who being sore wounded, gave so great a blow with a sword unto one of his enemies, armed at all assayes and with all pieces, as he cleft him from the crowns of the head down to the groine, so that the body fell in two pieces. In which example I find no great wonder, nor do I admit of his excuse wherewith he cloaketh Plutarke: to have added this word (as it is said) to forewarn us and restraine our beliefe. For if it be not in things received by authority and reverence of antiquity or religion, neither would himself have received nor proposed to us to beli eve things in themselves incredible: and that (as it is said) he does not here sette down this phrase to that purpose, may easily be perceived by what himself in other places telleth us upon the subject of the Lacedemonian childrens patience, of examples happened in his time much harder to be persuaded: as that which Cicero has also witnessed before him, because (as he says) he had been there himself: that even in their times there were children found prepared to endure all manner of patience, whereof they made trial before Dianas altar, and which suffered themselves to be whipped till the blood trilled down all parts of their body, not only without crying, but also without sobbing; and some who voluntarily suffered themselves to be scourged to death. And what Plutarke also reporteth, and a hundred other witnesses averre, that assisting at a sacrifice, a burning coale happened to fall into the sleeve of a Lacedemonian child, as he was busie at incensing, suffered his arm to burne so long until the smel of his burnt flesh came to all the by standers. There was nothing, according to their custom, so much called their reputation in question, and for which they endured more blame and shame, than to be surprised stealing. I am so well instructed of those mens greatnes of courage, that this report does not only seem incredible to me as to Bodin, but I do not so much as deem it rare, or suppose it strange. The Spartane story is full of thousands of much more rare and cruel examples; then according to this rate, it containeth nothing but miracle. Concerning this point of stealing, Marcellinus reporteth that whilst he lived there could never be found any kind of torment that might in any sort compell the Egyptians surprised filching (which was much used amongst them) to confesse and tell but their names. A Spanish peasant being laide upon the racke about the complices of the murther of the, Pretor Lucius Piso, in the midst of his torments cried out his friends should not stir, but with all security assist him, and that it was not in the power of any grief or pain to wrest one word of confession from him: and the first day nothing else could possibly be drawn from him. The next morrow, as he was led towarde the racke to be tormented anew, he by strong violence freed himself from out his keepers bands, and so furiously ranne with his bead against a wall, that he burst his braines out, and presently fell down dead. Epicharis having glutted and wearied the moody cruelty of Neroes satellites or officers, and stoutly endured their fire, their beatings, and their engines a whole day long without any one voice or word of revealing her conspiracy, and the next day after, being again brought to the torture with her limbs bruised and broken, convayed the lace or string of her gowne over one of the pillars of the chair wherein she sate, with a sliding knot in it, into which sodainly thrusting her head she strangled herself with the weight of her body. Having the courage to dye so, and steale from the first torments, seems she not purposely to have lent her life to the trial of her patience of the precedent day only to mocke that tyrant and encourage others to attempt the like enterprise against him? And he that shall enquire of our argolettiers or freebooters what experiences they have had in these our late civil wars, shall no doubt find effects and examples of patience, of obstinacy and stif-necknednes in these our miserable dayes, and amidst the effeminate and puling wordlings far beyond the Egyptians, and well worthie to be compared to those alreadie reported of Spartan virtue. I know there have been found seely hoores who have rather endure to have their feet broild upon a gridyron, their finger ends crusht and wrung with the locke of a pistoll, their eyes all bloody to be thrust out of their heads with wringing and wresting of a cord about their foreheads, before they would so much as be ransomed. I have seen and spoken with one who had been left all naked in a ditch for dead, his necke all bruised and swolne, with a halter about it, wherewith he had been dragged a whole night at a horses tail through thick and thin, with a hundred thrusts in his body given him with daggers, not to kill him outright, but to grieve and terrifie him, and who had patiently endured all that, and lost both speech and sense, fully resolved (as himself told me) rather to die a thousand deaths (as verily, if you apprehend what he suffered, he past more than one full death) then promise any ransome; yet was he one of the wealthiest husbandman in all his country. How many have been seen who have patiently endured to be burnt and roasted for unknown and wilful opinions which they had borrowed of others; my self have known a hundred and a hundred women (for the saying is, Gaskoine heads have some prerogative in that) whom you might sooner have made to bite a red-hot piece of iron than recant an opinion they had conceived in anger. They will be exasperated and grow more fell against blowes and compulsion, and he who first invented the tale of that woman which by no threats or stripes would leave to call her husband pricke-lowse, and being cast into a pond and duckt under water, lifted up her hands and joyning her two thumb-nails in act to kill lice above her head, seemed to call him lousie still, devised a fable whereof in truth we dayly see the expres image in diverse womens obstinacy and wilfulnesse. And yet obstinacy is the sister of constancy, at least in vigor and stedfastnesse. A man must not judge that which is possible and that which is not according to that which is credible and incredible to our sense and understanding, as I have already said elsewhere. And it is a great fault, wherein the greater number of men do dayly fall (I speak not this of Bodin) to make a difficulty in believing that of others which themselves neither can nor would do. Every man perswades himself that the chief form of humane nature is in himself; according to her must all others be directed. The proceedings that have no reference to hers are false and feigned. Is any thing proposed unto him of another mans faculties or actions? The first thing he calls to the judgement of his consultation is his own examples; according as it goeth in him, so goeth the worlds order. Oh dangerous sottishnesse and intollerable foppery! I consider some men a far-off, beyond and above my self, namely amongst those ancient ones: and although I manifestly acknowledge my own insufficiency to follow or come near them by a thousand paces, I cease not to keep them still in view, and to judge of those wardes and springs that raise them so high the seedes whereof I somewhat perceive in my self as likewise I do of the mindes extreme basenes which amazeth me nothing at all, and I misbelieve no more. I see the turn those give to wind up themselves, and I admire their greatness, and those starts which I perceive to be so wondrous fair, I embrace them: and if with my strength I reach not unto them, at least my judgement does most willingly apply itself unto them. The other example he alledgeth of things incredible by Plutarke, is that reported by Plutarke, that Agesilaus was fined by the Ephories because he had drawne the he arts and good wills of all his fellow-citizens unto himself alone. I know not what marke of falsehood or show of impossibility he findes in it; but so it is that Plutarke speaks there of things which in all likelyhood were better known to him then to us: and as it was not strange in Greece, to see men punished and exiled only because they were too popular and pleased the common people over much. Witness the Ostracisme amongst the Athenians, and the Petalisme amongst the Siracusans. There is an other accusation in the same place which for Plutarkes sake does somewhat touch me, where he says that he has very well and in good truth sorted the Romanes with the Romanes, and the Græcians amongst themselves, but not the Romanes with the Greacians, witness (says he) Demosthenes and Cicero, Cato and Aristides, Sylla and Lysander, Marcellus and Pelopidas, Pompey and Agesilaus, deeming thereby that he has favoured the Græcians by giving them so unequall companions. It is a just reproving of that which is most excellent and commendable in Plutarke: for in his comparisons (which is the most admirable part of his work, and wherein in mine opinion he so much pleased himself) the faithfulnesse and sinceritie of his judgement equalleth their depth and weight. He is a Philosopher that teacheth us virtue. But let us see whether we can warrant him from this reproch of prevarication and falsehood. That which I imagine has given occasion or ground to this judgement is that great and far- spreading lustre of the Roman names, which still are tingling in our ears and never out of our mindes. We do not think Demosthenes may equall the glory of a consull, a proconsul and a questor, of this great commonwealth of Rome. But he that shall impartially consider the truth of the matter, and men in themselves, which Plutarke did cheiefly aime at, and more, to balance their custom, their natural dispositions and their sufficiencie, then their for tune: I am of a cleane opposite opinion to Bodin, and think that Cicero and old Cato are much behind or short of their parallels. For this purpose I would rather have chosen the example of yong Cato compared to Pbocion: for in that pair might well be found a more likely disparitie for the Romanes advantage. As for Marcellus, Sylla, and Pompey, I see very well how their exploits of war be more swolne, glorious and pompous then the Græcians, whom Plutarke compareth unto them; but the most vertuous and fairest actions, no more in war then elsewhere, are not alwaies the most famous. I often see the names of some captaines smothered under the brightnesse of other names of lesser desert, witness Labienus, Ventidius, Telesinus, and diverse others. And to take him in that sense, were I to complain for the Græcians, might not I say that Camillus is much less comparable unto Themistocles, the Gracchi to Agis and Cleomenes, and Numa to Lycurgus? But it is folly at one glance to judge of things with so many and diverse faces. When Plutarke compares them, he does not for all that equall them. Who could more eloquently and with more conscience note their differences? Does he compare the victories, the exploites of arms, the power of the armies conducted by Pompey and his triumphs unto those of Agesilaus? I do not believe (says he) that Xenophon himself (were he living) though it were granted him to write his pleasure of Agesilaus durst ever dare to admit any comparison betweene them: seems he to equall Lysander to Sylla? There is no comparison (says he) neither in number of victories nor hazard of battle betweene them: for Lysander only obtained two sea-battles, &c. This is no derogation from the Romanes. If he have but simply presented them unto the Græcians, what ever disparity may be between them, he has not in any sort wronged them. And Plutarke does not directly counterpoise them. In some there is none preferred before others; he compareth the parts and the circumstances one after another, and severally judgeth of them. If therefore any would go about to convince him of favor, he should narrowly sift out some particular judgement; or in general and plaine termes say, he has missed in sorting such a Græcian to such a Roman, forasmuch as there are other more sortable and correspondent, and might better be compared, as having more reference one unto another. Return to : Book II CHAPTER XXXIII: THE HISTORIE OF SPURINA CHAPTER XXXIII: THE HISTORIE OF SPURINA HILOSOPHY thinketh she has not il employed her means, having yielded the sovereign rule of our mind, and the authority to restraine our appetites, unto reason. Amongst which, those who judge there is none more violent than those which love begetteth, have this for their opinion, that they holde both of body and soul; and man is wholly possessed with them: so that health itself depended of them, and physick is sometimes constrained to serve them instead of a Pandership. But contrariwise, a man might also say that the comixture of the body does bring abatement and weaknesse unto them; because such desires are subject to satiety and capable of materiall remedies. Many who have endevored to free and exempt their mindes from the continuall alarumes which this appetite did assail them with, have used incisions, indeed cut-off the mooving, turbulent and unruly parts. Others have alayed the force and fervency of them by frequent applications of cold things, as snow and vinegar. The hair-cloths which our forefathers used to weare for this purpose, whereof some made shirts, and some waste-bands or girdles, to torment their reines. A prince told me not long since, that being very yong and waiting in the Court of King Francis the First, upon a solemn festival day, when all the Court endevored to be in their best clothes, a humor possessed him to put on a shirt of hair-cloth, which he yet keepoth, and had been his fathers: but what devotion soever possessed him, he could not possibly endure until night to put it off again, and was sick a long time after, protesting he thought no youthly heat could be so violent but the use of this receipt would coole and allay; of which he perhaps never assayed the strongest? For, experience sheweth us, that such emotion does often maintaine itself under base, rude, and slovenly cloathes: and hair cloathes do not ever make those poore that weare them. Zenocrates proceeded more rigorously; for his Disciples, to make trial of his continencie, having convayed that beauteous and famous curtizan Lais naked into his bed, saving the weapons of her beauty, wanton allurements, and amorous or love-procuring potions, feeling that, mugre all, philosophicall discourses and strict rules, his skittish body beganne to mutiny, he caused those members to be burned which had listened to that rebellion. Whereas the passions that are in the mind, as ambition, covetousnesse and others, trouble reason much more: for it can have no ayde but from its own means; nor are those appetites capable of satiety but rather sharpened by enjoying and augmented by possession. The example alone of Julius Cæsar may suffice to show us the disparitie of these appetites, for never was man more given to amorous delights. The curious and exact care he had of his body is an authentic witness of it, forasmuch as he used the most lascivious means that then were in use; as to have the haires of his body smeered and perfumed al over with an extreme and labored curiosity; being of himself a goodly personage, white, of a tall and comely stature, of a cheerful and seemely countenance, his face ful and round and his eyes browne lively, if at least Suetonius may be believed; for the statues which nowadaies are to be seen of him in Rome answere not altogether this portraiture we speak of. Besides his wives, which he changed foure times, without reckoning the bies or amours in his youth with Nicomedes King of Bythinia, he had the maiden-head of that so farr and highly-renowned Queene of Egypt, Cleopatra; witness yong Cæsarion whom he begotte of her. He also made love unto Eunoe, Queene of Mauritania, and at Rome to Posthumia, wife unto ServiusSulpitius: to Lolio, wife to Gabinius; to Tertulla, of Crassus; indeed unto Mutia, wife to great Pompey, which, as historians say, was the cause her Husband was divorced from her. Which thing Plutarke confesseth not to have known. And the Curions both father and son, twitted Pompey in the teeth, at what time he took Cæsars daughter to wife, that he made himself son in law to one who had made him cuckold, and himself was wont to call Egyptus. Besides all this number, he entertained Servilia, the sister of Cato and mother to Marcus Brutus, whence (as diverse hold) proceedeth that great affection he ever bare to Marcus Brutus; for his mother bare him at such a time as it was not unlikely he might be borne of him. Thus (as me seems) have I good reason to deem him a man extreamly addicted to all amorous licenciousnesse, and of a wanton-lascivious complexion. But the other passion of ambition, wherewith he was infinitely affected and much tainted, when he came once to withstand the same it made him presently to give ground. And touching this point, when I call Mahomet to remembrance (I meane him that subdued Constantinople, and who brought the final extermination of the name of Græcians) I know not where these two passions are more equal ballanced, equally an indefatigable letcher and a never-tired souldier; but when in his life they seem to strive and concurre one with another, the mutinous heate does ever gourmandize the amorous flame. And the latter, although out of natural season did never attain to a ful and absolute authority, but when he perceived himself to be so aged that he was utterly unable longer to undergoe the burden of war. That which is aleadged, as an example on the contrary side, of Ladislaus, King of Naples, as very well worth the noting, who, though he were an excellent, courageous and ambitious captaine, proposed unto himself, as the principal scope of his ambition, the execution of his sensuality, and enjoying of some rare and unmatched beauty. So was his death: having by a continuall tedious siege brought the city of Florence to so narrow a pinch that the inhabitants were ready to yield him the victory, he yielded the same to them upon condition they would deliver into his hands a wench of excellent beauty that was in the city, of whom he had heard great commendations, which they were enforced to graunt him, and so by a private injury to ward off the public ruine of the city. She was daughter of a notable rare phisician and while he lived chief of his profession who seeing himself engaged in so stuprous a necessitie, resolved upon an haughty enterprise. Whilst all were busie adorning his daughter, and besetting her with costly jewels, that she might the more delight and please this new kingly lover, he also gave her an exquisitively- wrought and sweetly-perfuimed handkercher, to use in their first approches and embracements, a thing commonly in use amongst the women of that country. This handkercher, strongly empoysonped according to the cunning Skill of his art, coming to wipe both their enflamed secret parts and open pores, did so readily convay and disperse its poyson, that having sodainly changed the heate into colde, they immediately deceased one in anothers arms. But I will now return to Cæsar. His pleasures could never make him lose one minute of an hour, nor turn one step from the occasions that might in any way further his advancement. This passion did so sovereignly oversway all others, and possessed his mind with so uncontrouled an authority, that she carryed him whither she list. Truely I am grieved when in other things I consider this mans greatness, and the wondrous parts that were in him; so great sufficiencie in all manner of knowledge and learning, as there is almost no science wherein he has not written. He was so good an orator, that diverse have preferred his eloquence before Ciceroes; and himself (in mine opinion) in that facultie thought himself nothing short of him. And his two Anti-Catoes were especially written to over-balance the eloquence which Cicero had emploied in his Cato. And for all other matters, was ever mind so vigilant, so active, and so patient of labor as his? And doubtlesse it was also embellished with sundry rare seedes of virtue - I meane lively, natural, and not counterfeits. He was exceeding sober, and so homely in his feeding, that Oppius reporteth how upon a time, through a certain cookes negligence, his meate being dressed with a kind of medicinable oyle instead of olive-oyle, and so brought to the boorde, although he found it, yet he fed hartily of it only because he would not shame his hoste: another time he caused his baker to be whipped because he had served him with other than common household bread. Cato himself was wont to say of him, that he was the first sober man had addrest himself to the ruine of his country. And whereas the same Cato called him one day drunkard, it hapned in this manner. Being both together in the Senate house, where Catelines conspiracie was much spoken of, wherein Cæsar was greatly suspected to have a hand, a note was by a friend of his brought, and in very secret sort delivered him, which Cato perceiving, supposing it might be something that the conspirators advertised him of, instantly summoned him to show it, which Cæsar, to avoid a greater suspicion, refused not: it was by chance an amorous letter which Servilia, Catoes sister, wrote to him: Cato having read it, threw it at him, saying, ’Hold it again, you drunkard.’ I say it was rather a word of disdaine and anger than a n reproch of this vice: as often we nickname that anger us with the first nicknames of reproaches that come into our mouth, though meerely impertinent to those with whom we fall out. Considering that the vice wherewith Cato charged him has neare coherencie unto that wherein he had surprised Cæsar: for Venus and Bacchus (as the vulgar he says) agree well together; but with me, Venus is much more blithe and gamesome, being accompanied with sobrietie. The examples of his mildenes and clemencie towards such as had offended him are infinite: I meane, besides those he showed during the civill wars, which (as by his own writing may plainly appeare) he used to blandish and allure his enemies, to make them fear his future domination and victories the less. But if any shall say those examples are not of validitie to witnes his genuine and natural affabilitie, we may lawfully answere, that at least they show us a wonderful confidence and greatnes of courage to have been in him. It has often befalne him to send whole armies backe again to his enemies after he had vanquished them, without dayning to binde them so much as with an oath, if not to favor, at least not to bear arms against him. He has three or foure times taken some of Pompeyes chief captaines prisoners, and as often set them at liberty again. Pompey declared all such as would not follow and accompany him in his wars to be his enemies; and he caused those to be proclaimed as friends who either would not stir at all, or not effectually arm themselves against him. To such of his captaines as fled from him, to procure other conditions, he sent them their weapons, their horses, and all other furniture. The citties he had taken by main force he freed to follow what faction they would, giving them no other garison then the memory of his clemencie and mildnes. In the day of his great battail of Pharsalia, he expresly inhibited that, unles they were driven to unavoydalle extremities no man should lay hands upon any Roman cittizen. In my judgement these are very hazardous partes, and it is no wonder if, in the civill wars tumultuous broiles we have now on foote, those that fight for the ancient laws and state of their country as he did, do not follow and imitate the example. They are extraordinary means, and which only belongs to Cæsars fortune, and to his admirable foresight, successfully to direct and happily to conduct them. When I consider the incomparable greatness and unvaluable worth of his mind, I excuse Victorie in that she could not well give him over in this most unjust and unnatural cause. But to return to his clemencie we have diverse genuine and lively examples, even in the time of his al swaying government, when all things were reduced into his hands, and be needed no longer to dissemble. Caius Memmius had written certain detracting and railing orations against him, which he at full and most sharpely had answered, nevertheless he shortly after helped to make him consul. Caius Calvus, who had composed diverse most injurious epigrams against him, having employed sundrie of his friendes to be reconciled to him again, Cæsar descended to write first unto him. And our good Catullus, who under the name of Mamurra had so rudely and bitterly railed against him, at last coming to excuse himself, Cæsar that very night made him to suppe at his own table. Having been advertised how some were overlavish in rayling against him, all he did was but in a public oration to declare how he was advertised of it. His enemies he feared less than he hated them. Certain conspiracies and conventicles were made against his life, which being discovered unto him, he was contented by an edict to publish how he was thoroughly informed of them, and never prosecuted the authors. Touching the respect he ever bare unto his friends, Caius Oppius travelling unto him, and falling very sick, having but one chamber, he resigned the same unto him, and himself was contented to lie all night abroade and upon the bare ground. Concerning his justice, he caused a servant of his whom he exceedingly loved, to be executed, forasmuch as he had laine with the wife of a Roman knight, although no man sued or complained of him. Never was man that showed more moderation in his victory or more resolution in his adverse fortune. But all these noble inclinations, rich gifts, worthy qualities, were altered, smothered, and eclipsed by this furious passion of ambition; by which he suffred himself to be so far misled that it may be well affirmed she, only, ruled the stern of all his actions. Of a liberall man she made him a common theefe, that so he might the better supply his profusion and prodigalitie; and made him utter that vile and most injurious speech, that if the wickedest and most pernicious men of the world had for his service and furtherance been faithfull unto him, he would to the utmost of his power have cherished and preferred them as well as if they had been the honestest: it so besotted and, as it were, made him drunke with so extreme vanity, that in the presence of his fellow-citizens, he durst vaunt himself to have made that great and far-spread Roman Commonwealth a shapelesse and bodilesse name, and pronounce that his sentences or answeres should thenceforward serve as laws; and sitting to receive the whole body of the Senate coming toward him, and suffer himself to be adored, and in his presence divine honors to be done him. To conclude, this only vice (in mine opinion) lost and overthrew in him the fairest natural and richest ingenuitie that ever was, and has made his memory abominable to all honest mindes, insomuch as by the ruine of his countrey and subversion of the mightiest state and most flourishing commonwealth that ever the world shall see, he went about to procure his glory. A man might contrariwise find diverse examples of greate persons, whom pleasure has made to forget the conduct of their own affairs, as Marcus Antonius and others: but where love and ambition should be in one equall balance and with like forces mate one another, I will never doubt but Cæsar would gain the prize and gole of the victory. But to come into my path again. It is much, by discourse of reason, to bridle our appetites, or by violence to force our members to containe themselv es within the bonds of dutie. But to whippe us, for the interest of our neighbors; not only to shake off this sweet pleasing passion, which tickleth us with self-lioving pleasure we apprehend and feel to see ourselves gratefull to others and of all men beloved and sued unto, but also to hate and scorne those graces which are the cause of it, and to condemne our beauty because some others will be set on fire with it, I have seen few examples like this. Spurina, a young gentleman of Thuscanie - Qualis gemma micat fulvum quæ dividit aurum, Aut collo decus aut capiti vel quale per artem Inclusum buxo, aut Ericia terebintho, Lucet ebur -- Virg. Æn. x. 134. As when a precious stone clear rayes does spread, Set in pure golde, adorning necke or head Or as fair iv’ry shines in boxe enclos’d, Or workemanly with mountaine gumme dispos’d - being endowed with so alluringly-excessive and singular beautie that the chastest eyes could not possibly gainstand or continently resist the sparkling glances thereof, not contented to leave so great a flame succourlesse or burning fever remedilesse, which he in all persons and every where enkindled, entered into so furious despite against himself, and those rich gifts nature had so prodigally conferred upon him (as if they must bear the blame of others faults that with gashes and skars he wittingly mangled and voluntarily cut that perfect proportion and absolute feature which nature had so curiously observed in his unmatched face; whereof, to speak my opinion, such outrages are enemies to my rules. I rather admire than honor such actions. His intent was commendable and his purpose consciencious, but in my seeming somewhat wanting of wisdom. What, if his deformitie or uglinesse was afterward an instrument to induce others to fall into the sinne of contempt and vice of hatred, or fault of envy for the glory of so rare commendation; or of slander, interpreting his humor to be a frauncke ambition. Is there any form whence vice (if so it please) may not wrest an occasion in some manner to exercise itself? It had been more just, and therewithall more glorious, of so rare gifts of God to have made a subject of exemplary virtue and orderly methode. Those which sequester themselves from public offices, and from this infinite number of thornie and so many-faced rules which in civile life binde a man of exact honesty and exquisite integrities in mine opinion reape a goodly commoditie, what peculiar sharpe-nesse soever they enjoin themselves. It is a kind of death to avoide the pain of well doing or trouble of well living. They may have another prise, but the prise of uneasiness methinks they never had. Nor that in difficulty there be anything that is amid the waves of the worldly multitude, beyond keeping himself upright and untainted, answering loyally and truely discharging al members and severall parts of his charge. It is happily more easy for one in honest sort to neglect and pass over all the sexe, than duely and wholly to maintaine himself in his wifes company. And a man may more incuriously fall into povertie then into plenteousnesse; being justly dispenced. Custome, according to reason, does leade to more sharpnesse than abstinence has. Moderation is a virtue much more toylesome than sufferance. The chaste and well living of yong Scipio has a thousand severall fashions; that of Diogenes but one. This does by so much more exceed all ordinary lives in innocencie and unspottednesse as those which are most exquisite and accomplished exceed in profit and out-go it in force. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXIV: OBSERVATIONS CONCERNlNG THE MEANES TO WARRE AFTER THE MANNER OF JULIUS CÆSAR Æ CHAPTER XXXIV: OBSERVATIONS CONCERNlNG THE MEANES TO WARRE AFTER THE MANNER OF JULIUS CÆSAR T IS reported of diverse chief Generals in war, that they have particularly affected some peculiar book or other, as Alexander the Great highly esteemed Homer; Scipio, Africanus, Xenophon; Marcus Brutus, Polybius; Charles the Fifth, Philip de Comines: and it is lately averred that in some places, and with some men, Machiavell is much accompted of: But our late Marshall Strozzi, who had made especiall choice to love Cæsar, without doubt I think of all other chose best, for truely he ought to be the breviary of all true soldiers, as being the absolute and perfect chief patterne of military profession. And God he knowes with what grace and with what decorum he has embellished this rich subject, with so pure a kind of speech, so pleasing and so absolutely perfect, that to my taste there are no writings in the world which in this subiect may be compared to his. I will here register certain particular and rare parts concerning his manner of war, which yet remaine in my memory. His army beeing somewhat afrighted upon the report that ranne of the great forces which K. Iuba brought against him, instead of abating the opinion his soldiers had conceived of it, and to diminish the means or forces of his enemy, having caused them to be assembled altogether, thereby to assure and encourage them, he took a cleane contrary course to that which in like cases we are accustomed to do, for he had them trouble themselves no more to find out the number of the forces which his enemies brought against him, for himself had already true knowledge and certain intelligence of them, and told them a number far exceeding both the truth and report of them: following what Cyrus commandeth in Xenophon. Forasmuch as the deceit is not of like interest, for a man to find his enemies in effect weaker than he hoped, then stronger indeed having once conceived an opinion of their weaknesse. He enured all his soldiers simply to obey, without controling, gain-saying, or speaking of their captaines desseignes, which he never communicated unto them, but upon the last point of execution; and was pleased, if by chance they had any inkling of them, so to deceive them. Presently to change his opinion: and having prefixed a place to quarter in at night, he has often been seen to march further, and lengthen his journey, namely if the weather were foul, or if it rained. The Swizzers in the beginning of his wars in Gaule, having sent toward him to give them free passage through the Roman countries, and he being resolved by force to empeach them, did notwithstanding show them very good looks, and took certain dayes respit to give them an answer. During which time he might have leisure to assemble his army together. These poore people knew not how well he could husband time: for he often repeated that the skill to embrace occasions in the nick is the chiefest part of an absolute captaine: and truly the diligence he used in his exploit is incredible, and the like was never heard of. If he were not over-consciencious in that under colour of some treatie, parle or accord, to take any advantage of his enemies, he was as little scrupulous in that he required no other virtue in his soldiers but valor; and except mutiny and disobedience he punished not greatly other vices. After his victories he often gave them the reines to all licenciousness, for a while dispencing them from all rules of military discipline; saying, moreover, his soldiers were so well instructed that though they were in their gayest clothes, pranked up, muskt and perfumed, they would, notwithstanding, run furiously to any combate. And in truth he loved to see them richly armed, and made them weare gilt, graven and silvered armours, that their care to keep them cleane and bright might make them more fierce and readie to defend themselves. Speaking to them, he ever called them by the name of fellow soldiers, a name used at this day by some captaines; which his successor Augustus afterward reformed, esteeming he had done it for the necessitie of his affairs, and to flatter the hearts of those which followed him but voluntarily; -----Rheni mihi Cæsar in undis, Dux erat, hic socius facinus quos inquinat, æquat. -- Lucan. v. 289. When Caasar past the Rheine he was my general, My fellow here; sinne whom it staines makes fellowes-all; but this custom was over-lowlie for the dignitie of an emperor and chief general of an army, and he brought up the fashion again to cal them only soldiers. To this curtesie, Cæsar did, notwithstanding intermixe a great severity to suppresse and keep them humble. His ninth legion having mutinied near unto Placentia, he presently cassiered the same with great ignominie unto it, notwithstanding that Pompey were yet on foot and strong; and would not receive it into favor but with humble petition and entreaties. He did more appease them by authority and audacitie than by mildness and affabilitie. Where he speaks of his passage over the river of Rheine, towards Germany, he says that, deeming it unworthy the honor of the Roman people his army should pass over in shippes, he caused a bridge to be built, that so it might pass over drie-foot. There he erected that admirable bridge whereof he so particularly describeth the same: for he never more willingly dilates himself in describing any of his exploites then where he endevoreth to represent unto us the subtilitie of his inventions in such kindes of manuall workes. I have also noted this his book, that he much accompteth of his exhortations he made his soldiers before any fight, for where he would show to have been either surprised or urged, he ever alledgeth this, that he had not so much leisure as to make an oration to his soldiers or army: before that great battle against those of Tournay, Cæser (says he) having disposed of the rest, ranne sodainely whither fortune carried him, to exhort his men, and meeting with the tenth legion, he had not leisure to say any thing else unto them but that they should remember their former wonted virtue, they should nothing be danted, they should stoutly resist the encounter of their adversaries; and forasmuch as the enemy was come within an arrow-shot unto him, he gave the signal of the battle; and sodainely going elsewere to encourage others, he found them already together by the ears: see here what himself says of it in that place. Verely his tongue has in diverse places much bestead, and done him notable service, and even whilst he lived his military eloquence was so highly regarded that many of his army were seen to copie and keep his orations; by which means diverse volumes were filled with them, and continued many ages after his death, his speech and particular graces, so that his familiar friends, and namely Augustus, hearing that rehearsed which had been collected of his, knew by the phrases and words what was his or not. The first time that with any public charge he issued out of Rome, he came in eight dayes to the river of Rhone, having ever one or two secretaries before him, who continually wrote what he endited, and one behinde him that carried his sword. And surely if one did nothing but run up and down, he could very hardly attaine to that promptitude wherewith ever being victorious, having left Gaule, and following Pompey to Brundusium, in eighteene dayes he subdued all Italie; returned from Brundusium to Rome, and thence went even to the heart of Spain, where he passed many extreme difficulties in the wars betweene Afranius and Petreius, and at the long siege of Marseille; from whence he returned into Macedon, overthrew the Roman army at Pharsalia; thence pursuing Pompey he passed into Egypt, which he subdued; from Egypt he came into Syria, and into the countrie of Pontus; where he fought with Pharnaces; thence into Affrica, where he defeated Scipio and Iuba; and thence through Italie he returned into Spain, where he overthrew Pompeyes children. Ocior et cæli flammis et tigride fæta, Ac veluti montis saxum de vertice præceps Cum ruit avulsum vento, seu turbidus imber Proluit, aut annis solvit sublapsa vetustas, Fertur in abruptum magno mons improbus actu, Exultatque solo, silvas, armenta, virosque, I nvolvens secum. -- Virg. Æn. xii. 684. Swifter then breed -yong tiger, or heav’ns flash, And as from mountaines top a headlong stone, Rent-off by winds, or by stormes troublous dash Washt-off, or loos’d by age of years are gone, Crosse-carried with great force that hill-like masse Bounds on the earth, and rowles with it in one Woods, herds, and men, and all that near it was Speaking of the siege of Avaricum, he says that it was his custom, both day and night, ever to be near and about such workemen as he had set a work. In all enterprises of consequence he was ever the first skout-man or surveyer of any place; and his army never approched place which he had not viewed or survayed himself. And if we may believe Suetonius, at what time he attempted to pass over into England he was the first man that sounded the passage. He was wont to say that he esteemed that victory much more which was conducted by advise and managed by counsell, then by main strength and force. In the war against Petreius and Afranius, fortune presenting an apparent occasion of advantage unto him, he says that he refused it, hoping, with a little more time, but with less hazard, to see the overthrow of his enemy. Where he also plaid a notable part, to command all his army to swimme over a river without any necessitie. ------ rapuitque ruens in prælia miles, Quod fugiens timuisset iter, mox uda receptis Membra fovent armis, gelisque a gurgite cursu Restituunt artus, -- Lucan. iv. 151. The Souldier rides that way in hast to fight Which yet he would have feared in haste of flight His limbs with water wet and cold before, With arms he covers, running does restore. I find him somewhat more warie and considerate in his enterprises then Alexander; for the latter seems to seek out, and by main force to run into dangers, as an impetuous or raging torrent, which without heede, discretion, or choise, shockes and checkinates whate’er it meeteth withall. Sic tauriformis volvitur Aufidus, Qui Regna Dauni perfluit Appuli, Dum sævit, horrendamque cultis Diluviem meditator agris. -- Hor. Car. iv. Od. xiv. 25. So Bull-fac’d Aufidas still rowling growes, Which through Apulias ancient kingdome flowes, When he does rage in threatning meditation To bring on fair fields fearefull inundation. And to say truth, his hap was to be most employed in the spring time and first heate of his age: whereas Cæsar was well strucken in years when he beganne to follow arms. Alexander was of a more cholerike, sanguine and violent constitution, while humor he stirred up with wine, whereof Cæsar was very abstinent. But where occasions of necessitie were offered, and where the subject required it, there was never man that so little regarded his person. As for me, me seems I read in diverse of his exploits a certain resolution rather to lose himself then to abide the brunt or shame to be overthrowne. In that great battle which he fought against those of Turnay, seeing the vanguard of his army somewhat enclining to route, even as be was, without shield or target, he ranne headlong to the front of his enemies; which many other times happened unto him. Hearing once how his men were besieged, he past disguised through the midst and thickest of his enemies campe, so to encourage and awe them with his presence. Having crossed the way to Dyrrhachium, with very few forces, and perceiving the rest of his army (the conduct whereof he had left unto Antonius, to be somewhat slow in coming, he undertook all alone to repasse the sea, notwithstanding a violent and raging tempest; and secretly stole himself away to fetch the rest of his forces: all the havens on that side, indeed all the sea, being possessed by Pompey. And concerning the enterprises he underwent with armed hand, there are diverse of them, which in respect of the hazard, exceed all discourse of military reason: for, with how weake means undertook he to subdue the kingdom of Egypt, and afterward to front the forces of Scipio and Iuba, which were tenne parts greater than his? Mee thinkes such men have had a kind of more than humane confidence of their fortune: and himself was wont to say that haughty enterprises were to be executed and not consuIted upon. After the battle of Pharsalia, having sent his army before into Asia and himself with only one ship passing through the strait of Hellespont, he met on the seas with Lucius Cassius, attended on with ten tall shippes of war; he was so far from shunning him, that he durst not only stay for him, but with all haste make toward and summon him to yield himself to his mercy, which he did. Having undertaken that furious siege of Alesia, wherein were fourescore thousand men of defense, and all France up in arms, with a resolution to run upon him and raise the siege, and having an army on foote of one hundred and nine thousand horse, and two hundred fortie thousand foote; what a foolhardy and outrageous confidence was it in him that he would never give over his attempt and resolve in two so great difficulties together? Which he notwithstanding underwent; and after he had obtained so notable a battle of those which were without, be soone reduced those that were besieged in the town to his mercy. The very like happened to Lucullus at the siege of Tigranocerta, against King Tigrane, but with an unlike condition, seeing his enemies demissenesse, with whom Lucullus was to deale. I will here note two rare and extraordinary events touching the siege of Alesia; the one, that the French men being all assembled together with a purpose to meet with Cæsar, having diligently survaied and exactly numbered all their forces, resolved in their counsell to cutte off a great part of this huge multitude for fear they might breed a confusion. This example is new, to fear to be over-many; yet if it be well taken, it is very likely that the body of an army ought to have a well-proportioned greatness, and ordered to indifferent bounds. Whether it he for the difficulty to feed the same or to lead it in order and keep it in awe, and we may easily verifle by examples that these numerous and infinite armies have seldom brought any notable thing to pass: according to Cyrus his saying in Xenophon. It is not the multitude of men, but the number of good men, that causeth an advantage: the rest rather breeding confusion and trouble than helpe or avail. And Bajazeth took the chiefest foundation of his resolution, against the advice of all his captaines, to join fight with Tamburlane, only because the innumerable number of men which his enemy brought into the field gave him an assured hope of rout and confusion. Skanderbeg, a sufficient and most expert judge in such a case, was wont to say that tenne or twelve thousand trusty and resolute fighting men ought to suffice any sufficient chieftaine of war to warrant his reputation in any kind of military exploite. The other point, which seems to be repugnant both unto custom and reason of war, is, that Vercingentorix, who was appointed chief general of all the forces of the revolted Gaules, undertook to immure and shutte himself into, Alesia. For he that has the commandement of a whole countrie ought never to engage himself, except in cases of extremities and where all his rest and last refuge goeth on it, and has no other hope left him but the defense of such a place. Otherwise he ought to keep himself free, that so he may have means to provide in all parts of his government. But to return to Cæsar: he became in time somewhat more slow, heedy, and considerate, as witnesseth his familiar friend Oppius; deeming he should not so easily hazard the honor of so many victories, which one only disaster or misencounter might make him lose. It is that the Italians are wont to say, when they will or blame or reproach any man with this overdaring or rash foolhardinesse, which is often seen in yong men, calling them bisognosi d’onore, as much to say as needy of honor: and that being yet hungrie r greedy, and voyd of reputation, they have reason to seek after it, whatsoever it may cost them; which they should never do that have already acquired the same. There may be some just moderation in this desire of glory, and some satietie in this appetite as well as in others; diverse do so practize it. He was far from that religion of the ancient Romans who in their wars would never prevaile but with meere and genuine virtue: but rather joined more conscience unto it than nowadaies we should do; and would never allow of all means were he never so certain to get the victory. In his wars against Ariovistus, while he was in parly with him, some tumult or insurrection happened between the two armies, which beganne by the fault or negligence of some of Ariovistus horsmen. In which hurlie- burlie Cæsar found himself to have a great advantage over his enemies, which notwithstanding he would not embrace, for fear he might be taxed or suspected to have proceeded falsly or consented to any trechery. At what time soever he went to fight, he was accustomed to weare a very rich garment, and of a sheene and garish colour, that so he might the better be marked. When his soldiers were neerest unto their enemies he restrained and kept them very short. When the ancient Græcians would accuse or taxe any man of extreme insufficiencies they used this common proverbe, that he could neither read nor swimme: and himself was of t his opinion, that the arte of swimming was most necessary and beneficiarie in war: and a souldier might reape diverse commodities by it, if he were in haste, and to make speed, he would ordinarily swimme over al the rivers he met withal; and loved greatly to travell on foote, as Alexander the great was wont. In Egypt, being on a time forced (to save himself) to leap into a little wherry or bote, and so many of his people following him that he was in danger to sink, he rather chose to fling himsel f into the sea, which he did; and swimming came into his fleete, that was more than two hundred paces from him, holding his writing tables in his left hand out of the water, and with his teeth drawing his coate of arms after him, that his enemies might not enjoy it: and this did he being well stricken in years. No general of war had ever so much credit with his soldiers. In the beginning of his civill wars, his centeniers offered him every one at their own charges to pay and find him a man at arms, and his footemen to serve him for nothing, and those that were best able, to defray the poore and needy. Our late admirall of France, Lord Chastillon, in our late civill wars showed such an example: for the Frenchmen of his army, at their proper cost and charges, helped to pay such strangers as followed him. Few examples of so loving and earnest affection may be found amongst those that follow the old manner of war, and strictly hold themselves under the ancient pollicie of their laws. Passion has more sway over us then reason: yet has it chanced in the war against Hannibal, that, imitating the example of the Roman peoples liberalitie in the citie, the soldiers and captaines refused their pay, and in Marcellus his campe, those were called mercenary that took any pay. Having had some defeate near unto Dyrrachium, his soldiers came voluntarily before him, and offered themselves to be punished; so that he was more troubled to comfort then to chide them. One only of his cohortes (whereof ten went to a legion) held fight above foure howres with foure of Pompeys whole legions, until it was well-nigh all defeated with the multitude and force of arrows: and in his trenches were afterward found one hundred and thirty thousand shafts. A souldier of his, named Scæva, who commanded one of the entrances, did so invincibly defend and keep himself, that he had one of his eyes thrust out, and one shoulder and one thigh thrust through, and his shield flawed and pearced in two hundred and thirty severall places. It has befallen to many of his soldiers, being, taken prisoners, to chuse rather to die then promise to follow any other faction, or receive any other entertainment. Granius Petronius, taken by Scipio in Affrike, after Scipio had caused all his fellowes to be put to death, sent him word that gave him his life, forasmuch as he was a man of rank and a questor: Petronius answered that Cæsars soldiers were wont to give life to others, and not accept it themselves; and therewithall with his own hands killed himself. Infinite examples there are of their fidelitie. That part which they, acted who were besieged in Salona, a citie which took part with Cæsar against Pompey, must not be forgotten, by reason of a rare accident that there hapned. Marcus Octavius, having long time beleagred the town, they within were reduced to such extreamitie and pinching necessitie of all things, that to supply the great want they had of men, most of them being alreadie or hurt or dead; they had set all their slaves at liberty, and for the beboofe of their engines were compelled to cut off all their womens haires, to make ropes with them; besides a wonderful lacke of victualls, resolving notwithstanding never to yield themselves: after they had a long time lingered the siege, and that Octavius was thereby become more carelesse, and less heeding or attentive to his enterprise, they one day about high noone (having first ranged their wives and children upon the walles, to set the better face upon the matter) rushed out in such a fury upon the besiegers, that having put to rout and defeated the first, the second, and third corps de garde, then the fourth and the rest, and having forced them to quit their trenches, chased them even to their shippes: and Octavius with much adoe saved himself in Dyrrachium, where Pompey was. I remember not at this time to have read of any other example where the beleagred do in grosse beate the beleagrers, and get the maistry and possession of the field nor that a sallie has drawne a meere and absolute victory of a battle into consequence. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXV: OF THREE GOOD WOMEN. CHAPTER XXXV: OF THREE GOOD WOMEN. HEY are not to be had by dozens, as each one knowes, namely, in rights and duties of mariage; for it is a bargaine full of so many thornie circumstances, that it is hard the will of a woman should long keep her self whole and perfect therein. And although men have somewhat a better condition in the same, yet have they much to do. The touchstone and perfect trial of a goode marriage respects the time that the societie continueth; whether it have constantly been mild, loyall and commodious. In our age they more commonly reserve to enstall their good offices, and set forth the vehemence of their affections toward their lost husbands: and then seek they at least to yield some testimony of their good wil. O late testimony and out of season, whereby they rather show they never love them but when they are dead! Our life is full of combustion and scolding, but our disease is full of love and of curtesie. As fathers conceal affection toward their children, so they, to maintaine an honest respect, cloake tbeir love toward their husbands. This mystery answereth not my taste. They may long enough scratch and dishevel themselves; let me enquire of a chamber-maide or of a secretarie how they were, how they did, and how they have lived together. I can never forget this good saying: Jactantius mærent, quæ minus dolent: ’They keep a howling with most ostentation who are less sorrowfull at heart.’ Their lowring and puling is hateful to the living and vain to the dead. We shall easily dispence with them to laugh at us when we are dead, upon condition they smile upon us while we live. Is not this the way to revive a man with spite; that he who has spitten in my face when I was living shall come and claw my feet when I am dead? If there be any honor for a woman to weepe for her husband, it belongs to her that has smiled upon him when she had him. Such as have wept when they lived, let them laugh when they are dead, as well outwardly as inwardly. Moreover, regard not those blubbred eyes, nor that pity moving voice, but view that demeanour, that colour and cheerful good plight of those cheekes under their great vailes ; thence it is she speaks plaine French. There are few whose health does not daily grow better and better; a quality that cannot lie. This ceremonious countenance looketh not so much backward as forward: it is rather a purchase than a payment. In mine infancie an honest and most fair ladie (who yet liveth) the widdowe of a prince, had somewhat more of I wot not what in her attires then the laws of widdowhood would well permit. To such as blamed her for it, it is (said she) I intend no more new acquaintances, and have no mind at all to marry again. Because I will not altogether dissent from our custom, I have here made choice of three women who have also employed the, utmost endeavor of their goodnes and affection about their husbands deaths. Yet are they examples somewhat different and so urging that they hardly draw life into consequence. Plinie the yonger had dwelling near to a house of his in Italie a neighbour wonderfully tormented with certain ulcers which much troubled him in his secret parts. His wife perceiving him to droope and languish away, entreated him she might leasurely search, and neerely view the quality of his disease, and she would more freely then any other tell him what he was to hope for: which having obtained and curiously considered the same, she found it impossible ever to be cured, and all he might expect was but to lead a long, dolorous, and languishing life: and therefore, for his more safetie and sovereign remedie, persuaded him to kill himself. And finding him somewhat nice and backeward to effect so rude an enterprise: ’Thinke not my dear friend (quoth she) but that the sorrowes and grief I see you feel, touch me as near and more, if more may be, as your self, and that to be rid of them I will applie the same remedie to my self which I prescribe to you. I will accompany you in your cure as I have done in your sickness: remoove all fear, and assure your self we shall have pleasure in this passage, which shall deliver us from all torments, for we will happily go together.’ That said, and having cheared up her husbands courage, she determined they should both headlong throw themselves into the sea from out a window of their house that overlooked the same: and to maintaine this loyall, vehement and never to be severed affection to the end, wherewith she had during his life embraced him, she would also have him die in her arms: and fearing they might faile her, and through the fall or fear or apprehension her bold-fast might be loosed, she caused herself to be fast bound unto him by the middle: and thus for the ease of her husbands life she was contented to foregoe her own. She was but of meane place and low fortune, and amidde such condition of people it is not so strange to see some parts of rare virtue and exemplar goodnesse. ------ extrema per illos Justitia excedens terris vestigia fecit. Virg. Georg. ii. 473. Justice departing from the earth did take Of them her leave, through them last passage make. The other two are noble and rich; where examples of virtue are rarely lodged. Arria, wife unto Cecinna Pætus, a man that had been consul, was mother of another Arria, wife to Thrasea Pætus, whose virtue was so highly renowned during the time of Nero; and by meane of his son-in-law, grandmother to Fannia. For the resemblance of these mens and womens names and fortunes has made diverse to mistake them. ’This first Arria, her husband Cecinna Pætus having been taken Prisoner by the soldiers of Claudius the Emperor, after the overthrow of Scribonianus, whose faction he had followed, entreated those who led him prisoner to Rome, to take her into their ship where for the service of her husband she should be of less charge and incommoditie to them then a number of other persons which they must necessarily have, and that she alone might supply and stead him in his chamber, in his kitchen and all other offices; which they utterly refused, and so hoisted sailes, but she leaping into a fishers boate that she immediately hired, followed him aloofe from the further shore of Sclavonia. Being come to Rome one day in the Emperours presence, Junia, the widdow of Scribonianus, by reason of the neerenesse and societie of their fortunes, familiarly accosted her, but she rudely, with these words, thrust her away. What (quoth she ) shall I speak to you, or shall I listen what you sayest? ’Thou, in whose lappe Scribonianus your husband was slain’ and you yet livest? and you breathest? These words with diverse other signes made her kinsfolk and friends perceive that she purposed to make herself away, as impatient to abide ber husbands fortune. And Thrasea her son in law, taking hold of her speeches, beseeching her that she would not so unheedily spoile herself, he thus bespake her: ’What, if I were in Cecinnæs f ortune or the like, would you have my wife your daughter to do so?’ ’What else? Make’ you a question of it?’ answered she. ’Yes, marry would I had she lived so long and in so good- agreeing sort with you as I have done with my husband.’ These and such like answers encreased the care they had of her and made them more heedful to watch and neerely to look unto her. One day after she had uttered these words to her keepers, ’You may looke long enough to me, well may you make me die worse, but you shall never be able to keep me from dying:’ and therewith furiously flinging herself out of a chaire (wherein she sate) with all the strength she had, she fiercely ranne her head against the next wall; with which blow having sore hurt herself, and falling into a dead swowne, after they had with much adoe brought her to herself again: ’Did I not tell you (quoth she) that if you kept me from an easy death I would choose another how hard and difficult soever?’ The end of so admirable a virtue was this. Her husband Pætus wanting the courage to do himself to death, unto which the Emperors cruelty reserved him, one day, having first employed discourses and exhortations befitting the counsell she gave him to make himself away, she took a dagger that her husband wore, and holding it right out in her hand for the period of her exhortation: Doe thus, Pætus (said she) and at that instant stabbing herself mortally to the heart, and presently pulling the dagger out again, she reached the same unto her husband and so yielded up the ghost, uttering this noble, generous, and immortal speech, Pæte non dolet, she had not the leisure to pronounce other than these three wordes, in substance materiall and worthy herself, ’Holde Pætus it has done me no hurt.’ Casta suo gladium cum traderet Arria Pæto, Ouem de visceribus traxerat ipsa suis; Si qua fides, vulnus quod feci, non dolet, inquit. Sed q uod tu facies, id mihi Pæte dolet. -- Mart. i. Epig. xiv. 1. Chast Arria, when she gave her Pætus that sharpe sword, Which from her bowells she had drawne forth bleeding new, The wound I gave and have, if you will trust my word Grieves not, said she, but that which shall be made by you. It is much more lively in his own natural and of a richer sense, for both her husbands wound and death, and her own hurts, she was so far from grieving to have been the counselor and motive of them, that she rejoiced to have performed so haughty and courageous an act, only for the behoofe of her dear husband; and at the last gasps of her life she only regarded him, and to remove all fear from him to follow her in death, which Pætus beholding, he immediately wounded himself with the same dagger, ashamed, as I suppose, to have had need of so dear an instruction and precious a teaching. Pompea Paulina, an high and noble borne yong Roman ladie, had wedded Seneca, being very aged. Nero, his fair disciple, having sent his satellites or officers toward him to denounce the decree of his death to him, which in those dayes was done after this manner: when the Roman Emperors had condemned any man of quality to death, they were wont to send their officers unto him to chuse what death he pleased, and to take it within such and such a time, which, according to the temper of their choler, they prescribed unto him sometimes shorter and sometimes longer, giving him that time to dispose of his affairs, which also by reason of some short warning they diverse times took from him: and if the condemned partie seemed in any sort to strive against their will, they would often send men of purpose to execute him, either cutting the veins of his arms and legs, or compelling him to take and swallow poison. But men of Honour stayed not that enforcement, but to that effect used their own Phisit ans or Surgeons, Seneca, with a reposed and undanted countenance, listned attentively to their charge, and presently demaunded for paper and inke to make his last wil and testament, which the captaine refusing him, he turned towards his friends and thus bespoke them: ’Sith, my loving friends, I cannot bequeath you any other thing in remembrance or acknowledgement of what I owe you, I leave you at least the richest and best portion I have, that is, the image of my maners and my life, which I beseech you to keep in memory; which doing you may acquire the glory and purchase the name of truly sincere and absolutely true friends.’ And therewithall, sometimes appeasing the sharpenes of the sorow he saw them endure for his sake, with mild and gentle speeches, sometimes raising his voice to chide them. ’Where are,’ said he ’those memorable precepts of Philosophy? What is become of those provisions which for so many years together we have laid up against the brunts and accidents of Fortune? Was Neroes innated cruelty unknown unto us? What might we expect or hope for at his hands, who had murdred his mother and massacred his brother, but that he would also do his tutor and governor that has fostred and brought him up? Having uttered these words to all the bystanders, he turned him to his wife, as she was ready to sink down, and with the burden of her grief to faint in heart and strength; he called and embraced her about the necke, and heartil y entreated her, for the love of him, somewhat more patiently to bear this accident; and that his hour was come, wherein be must show no longer by discourse and disputation, but in earnest effect, declare the fruit he had reaped by his studie; and that undoubtedly he embraced deathe, not only without grief but with exceeding joy. Wherefore; my dear dear heart, do not dishonour it by your tears, lest you seem to love yourself more than my reputation. Asswage your sorrowes and comfort your self, in the knowledge you hast had of me and of my actions, leading the rest of your life by the honest occupations to which you are addicted. To whom Paulina, having somewhat rouzed her drooping spirits, and by a thrice noble affection awakened the magnanimity of her high-setled courage, answered thus : ’No, Seneca, think not that in this necessitie I will leave you without my company. I would not have you imagine that the vertuous examples of your life have not also taught me to die; and when sha ll I be able to do it or better, or more honestly, or more to my own liking then with your self? And be resolved I wil go with you and be partaker of your fortune.’ Seneca taking so generous a resolve and glorious a determination of his wife in good part, and to free himself from the fear he had to leave her after his death to his enemies mercy and cruelty: ’Oh my dear Paulina, I had,’ quoth be, ’persuaded you what I thought was convenient, to leade your life more happily, and doest you then rather choose the honor of a glorious death? Assuredly I will not envy you. Be the constancy and resolution answerable to our common end, but be the beautie and glory greater on your side.’ That said, the veines of both their arms were cut, to the end they might bleede to death; but because Senecæs were somewhat shrunken up through age and abstinence, and his blood could have no speedy course, he commanded the veines of his thighes to be launced; and fearing lest the torments he felt might in some sort entender his wifes heart, as also to deliver himself from the affliction which greatly yearned him to see her in so pittious plight, after he had most lovingly taken leave of her, he besought her to be pleased she might be carried into the next chamber, which was accordingly performed. But all those incisions being unable to make him die, he willed Statius Anneus his phisitian to give him some poysoned potion which wrought but small effect in him for through the weaknesse and coldenesse of his members, it could not come unto his heart. And therefore they caused a warme has to be prepared, wherein they layd him, then perceiving his end to approach, so long as he had breath he continued his excellent discourses concerning the subject of the estate wherein he found himself, which his secretaries, so long as they could hear his voice, collected very diligently, whose last words continued long time after in high esteem and honor amongst the better sort of men, as oracles; but they were afterward lost, and great pittie it is they never came unto our handes. But when he once beganne to feel the last pangs of death, taking some of the water wherein he lay bathing, all bloody, he therewith washed his head, saying, ’I vow this water unto Jupiter the Deliverer.’ Nero being advertised of all this, fearing lest Paulinæs death (who was one of the best alied ladies in Rome, and to whom he bare no particular grudge) might cause him some reproach, sent in all poste baste to have her incisions closed up again, and if possible it could be, to save her life, which her servants by unwrithing her, performed, she being more than halfe dead and voyd of any sense. And that afterward, contrary to her intent, she lived, it was very honorable and as befitted her virtue, shewing by the pale hew and wanne colour of her face how much of her life she had wasted by her incisions. See here three true stories, which in my conceit are as pleasant and as tragical as any we devise at our pleasures to please the vulgar sort withall; and I wonder that those who invent so many fabulous tales do not rather make choise of infinite, excellent and quaint stories that are found in bookes, wherein they should have less trouble to write them, and might doubtlesse proove more pleasing to the hearer and profitable to the reader. And whosoever would undertake to frame a compleate and well- joynted, body of them neede neither employe nor adde any thing of his own unto it except the ligaments, as the soldring of another mettall, and by this means might compact sundry events of all kindes, disposing and diversifying them according as the beauty and lustre of the work should require; and very near, as Ovid has showen and contrived his Metamorphosis, with that strange number of diverse fables. In the last couple this is also worthy consideration, that Paulina offreth willingly to leave her life for her husband’s sake, and that her husband had also other times quit death for the love of her. There is no great counterpoyze in this exchange for us, but according to his Stoike humor I suppose he persuaded himself to have done as much for her, prolonging his life for her avail as if he had died for her. In one of his letters he writeth to Lucilius, after he had given him to understand how an ague having surprised him in Rome, contrary to his wives opinion who would needs have stayed him, he sodainly took his coach to go unto a house of his into the country; and how he told her that the ague he had was no bodily fever, but of the place; and followeth thus: ’At last she let me go, earnestly recommending my health unto me. Now I who know how her life lodgeth in mine, begin to provide for myself, that consequently I may provide for her the priviledge my age has bestowed on me making me more constant and more resolute in many things, I lose it whenever I call to mind that in this aged corps there harboureth a young woman to whom I bring some profit. Since I cannot induce her to love me more courageously, she induceth me to love my self more carefully; for something must be lent to honest affections, and sometimes, although occasions urge us to the contrary, life must be revoked again, indeed with torment. The soul must be held fast with ones teeth, since the lawe to live [in honest men] is not to live as long as they please, but so long as they ought. He who esteemeth not his wife or a friend so much as that he will not lengthen his life for them, and wil obstinately die, that man is over- nice and too effeminate: The soul must commaund that unto herself, when the utilitie of our friends requireth it we must sometimes lend ourselves unto our friend, and when we would die for us we ought for their sakes to interrupt our deseigne. It is a testimony of high courage to return to life for the respect of others , as diverse notable men have done; and to preserve age is a part of singular integritie (the cheifest commoditie whereof is the carelesnesse of her continuance, and a more courageous and disdainful use of life) if a man perceive such an office to be pleasing, acceptable and profitable to any well-affected friend. And who doeth it receiveth thereby a grateful meede and pleasing recompence; for what can be sweeter than to be so dear unto his wife, that in respect of her a man become more dear unt o himself. So my Paulina, has not only charged me with her fear, but also with mine. It has not been sufficient for me to consider how resolutely I might die, but I have also considered how irresolutely she might endure it, I have enforced my self to live. And to live is sometime magnanimity.’ Reade here his own wordes, as excellent as is his use. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXVI: OF THE WORTHIEST AND MOST EXCELLENT MEN CHAPTER XXXVI: OF THE WORTHIEST AND MOST EXCELLENT MEN If a man should demaund of me, which of all men that ever came to my knowledge I would make choise of, me seems I find three who have been excellent above all others. The one is Homer: not that Aristotle or Varro (for example sake) were not perhaps as wise and as sufficient as he: nor that Virgil (and possibly in his own arte) be not comparable unto him. I leave that to their judgements that know them both. I who know but one of then, according to my skill may only say this, that I cannot be persuaded the Muses themselves did ever go beyond the Roman. Tale facit carmen docta testudine, quale ---Cynthius impositis temperat articulis, -- PROPERT. 1. ii. Eleg. xxxiv. 79. He on his learned lute such verse does play As Phoebus should thereto his fingers lay. In which judgement this must notwitlistdnding not be forgotten, that Virgil does especially derive his sufficiency from Homer, and he is his guide and schoolemaster, and that but only glance or sentence of the Iliads has given both body and matter to that great and divine poem of the Æneid. My meaning is not to account so: I entermix diverse other circumstances which yield this man most admirable unto me, and as it were beyond humane condition. And truely I am often amazed that he who has produced, and by his authority brought so many deities in credit with the world, has’ not obtained to be reputed a god himself. Being blind and indigent, having lived before ever the sciences were redacted into strict rules and certain observations, he had so perfect knowledge of them, that all those which since his time have labored to establish pollicies or commonwealths, to manage wars, and to write either of religion or philosophy, in which sect soever or of all artes, have made use of him as of an absolutely perfect master in the knowledge of all things; and of his books, as of a seminary, a spring-garden or store-house of all kinds of sufficiency and learning. Qui quid sit pulchchrum, quid turpe, quid utile, quid non, Plenius ac melius, Chrysippo, ac Crantore dicit. -- HOR. 1. i. Epist. xxiii. What is fair, what is foul, what profit may, what not, Better than Crantor or Chrysippus, Homer wrot. And as another says: ------a quo ceu fonte perrenni Vatum Pieriis labra rigantur aquis. -- OVID. Am. 1. iii. Eleg. viii. 25. By whom, as by an ever-flowing-filling spring, With Muses liquor poets lippes are bath’de to sing. And another: Adde Heliconiadum comites, quoram unus Homerus, Astra potitus -- LUCR. 1. iii. 1081. Muses companions adde to these, of all One only Homer has in heav’n his stall. And another: ------ cujusque ex ore profuso Omnis posteritas latices in carmina duxit, Amnemque in tenues, ausa est deducere rivos: Unius faacunda bonis. -- MANIL. Ast. 1. ii. 8. From whose large mouth for verse all that since live Drew water, and grew bolder to derive Into thinne shallow rivers his deepe flood Richly luxuriant in one man’s good. It is against nature’s course that he bath made the most excelent production that may be: for the ordinary birth of things is imperfect: they are augmented by encrease and corroborated by growth. He has reduced the infancy of poesie and diverse other sciences to be ripe, perfect, and compleate. By which reason he may be termed the first and last of poets, following the noble testimony antiquity has left us of him, that having had no man before him whom he might imitate, so bath he had none after him could imitate him. His wordes (according to Aristotle) are the only words that have motion and action: they are the only substantiall wordes. Alexander the Great, having lighted upon a rich casket amongst Darius his spoils, appoynted the same to be safely kept for himself to keep his Homer in, saying he was the best adviser and faithfullest counselor he had in his military affairs. By the same reason said Cliomenes, son to Anaxandridas, that he was the Lacedemonians poet, for he was an excellent good teacher or master of warrelike discipline. This singular praise and particular commendation has also been given him by Plutarke, where he says that he is the only author in the world who yet never distasted reader, or glutted man, ever showing himself other and different to the readers, and ever flourishing with a new grace. That wagge Alcibiades, demanding one of Homers bookes of one who professed letters, because he had it not, gave him a whirrit on the eare, as if a man should find one of our Priests without a breviarie. Xenophanes one day made his moan to Hieron, the tyrant of Siracusa, that he was so poore as he had not wherewithall to find two servants. How commeth that to pass? (answered Hieron). Homer, who was much poorer than you are, dead as he is, findeth more than tenne thousand. What left Panætius unsaide when he named Plato the Homer of Philosophers? Besides, what glory may be compared to his? There is nothing liveth so in mens mouthes as his name and his workes; nothing so known and received as Troy, as Helen and her wars, which perhaps never were. Our children are yet called by the names he invented three thousand years since and more. Who knows not Hector? Who has not heard of Achilles? Not only some particular races, but most nations, seek to derive themselves from his inventions. Machomet, the second of that name, Emperor of Turkes, writing to Pope Pius the second: I wonder (says he) how the Italians will bandie against me, seeing we have our common offspring, from the Troians; and I as well as they have an interest to revenge the blood of Hector upon the Græcians whom they favor against me. Is it not a worthy comedie, whereof kings, commonwealths, principalities, and emperours have for many ages together played their parts, and to which this great universe serveth as a theatre? Seven cities of Greece strived amongst themselves about the places of his birth, so much honor his very obscuritie procured him. Smyrna, Rhodos, Colophon, Salamis, Chios, Argos, Athenæ. A. GEL. Noct. Att. 1. iii. c. 11. Rhodes, Salamis, Colophon, Chios, Argos, Smyrna, with Athens. The other is Alexander the great. For who shall consider his age, wherein he beganne his enterprises; the small means he had to ground so glorious a design upon, the authority he attained unto in his infancie amongst the greatest commanders and most experienced captaines in the world, by whom he was followed: the extraordinary favor wherwith fortune embraced him and seconded so many of his haughty-dangerous exploites, which I may in a manner call rash or foolhardie. Impellens quicquid sibi summa petenti Obstaret, gaudensque viam fecisse ruinæ. -- LUCAN 1. i. 148 . While he shot at the high’st, all that might stay He for’st and joyde with ruine to make way. That eminent greatness to have at the age of thirty years, passed victoriously through all the habitable earth and but with half the life of a man to have attained the utmost endeavour of human nature so that you cannot imagine his continuance lawfull, and the lasting of his increase in fortune, and progres in virtue even unto a just terme of age, but you must suppose something above man to have caused so many royal branches to issue from out the loines of his soldiers, leaving the world after his death to be shared between foure successors, only captaines of his army, whose successors have so long time since continued, and descendants maintained that large possession. So infinite, rare, and excellent vertues that were in him, as justice, temperance, liberalitie, integritie in words, love toward his, and humanitie toward the conquered. For in truth his maners seem to admit he no just cause of reproach: indeed some of his particular, rare, and extraordinary actions may in some sort be taxed. For it is impossible to conduct so great and direct so violent motion with the strict rules of justice. Such men ought to be judged in gross by the mistris end of their actions. The ruine of Thebes; the murder of Menander, and of Ephestions Physitian; the massacre of so many Persian prisoners at once; of a troupe of Indian soldiers, not without some prejudice unto his word and promise; and of the Cosæians and their little children, are escapes somewhat hard to be excused. For concerning Clitus, the fault was expiated beyond its merit; and that action, as much as any other, witnesseth the integritie and cheerfulness of his complexion, and that it was a complexion in itself exceedingly formed to goodnesse. And it was wittily said of one that he had vertues by nature and vices by accident. Concerning the point that he was somewhat too lavish a boaster, and over-impatient to hear himself ill spoken of; and touching those mangers, arms and bits, which he caused to be scattered in India, respecting his age and the prosperitie of his fortune, they are in my conceit pardonable in him. He that shall also consider his many vertues, as diligence, f oresight, patience, discipline, policy, magnanimity, resolution and good fortune, wherein though Haniballs authority had not taught it us, he has been the first and chief of men: the rare beauties, matchlesse features, and incomparable conditions of his person, beyond all comparison and wonder breeding; his carriage, demeanor, and venerable behaviour, in a face so young, so vermeill, and heart enflaming: Oualis ubi Occam perfusus Lucifer unda, Quem Venus ante alios astror um diligit ignes, Extulit os sacrum cælo, tenebrasque resolvit. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. viii. 589. As when the day-starre washt in ocean streames, Which Venus most of all the starres esteemes, Showes sacred light, shakes darkenesse off with beames. The excellencie of his wit, knowledge and capacity; the continuance and greatness of his glory unspotted, untainted, pure and free from all blame or envie: insomuch as long after his death it was religiously beleeved of many that the medalls or brooches representing his person brought good lucke unto such as wore or had them about them. And that more Kings and Princes have written his gests and actions then any other historians of what a quality soever, have registered the gests or collected the actions of any other King or Prince that ever was: and that even at this day the Mahometists, who contemne all other histories, by special priviledge allow, receive, and only honor his. All which premises duely considered together, he shall confesses I have had good reason to prefer him before Cæsar himself, who alone might have made me doubt of my choice. And it must needs be granted that in his exploites there was more of his own, but more of fortunes in Alexander’s achievements. They have both had many things mutually likewise, and Cæsar happily some greater. They were two quick and devouring fires, or two swift and surrounding streames, able to ravage the world by sundry ways. Et velut immissi diversis partibus ignes Arentem in silvam, et virgulta sonantia lauro: Aut ubi decursu rapido de montibus altis Dant sonitum spumosi amnes, et in æquora currunt, Quisque suum populatus iter. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. xii. 521. As when on diverse sides fire is applied To cracking bay-shrubs, or to woods sunne dried Or as when flaming streames from mountaines hie, With down-fall swift resound, and to sea flie Each one does havocke-out his way thereby. But grant Cæsar’s ambition were more moderate, it is so unhappy in that it met, with this vile subject of the subversion of his countrie, and universall empairing of the world; that all parts impartially collected and put together in the balance, I must necessarily bend to Alexander’s side. The third, and in my judgement most excellent man, is Epaminondas. Of glory he has not so much as some, and is far shorte of diverse (which well considered is no substantiall part of the thing) in resolution and true valor, not of that which is set on by ambition, but of that which wisdom and reason may settle in a well- disposed mind, he had as much as maybe imagined or wished for. He has in mine opinion made as great trial of his vertues as ever did Alexander or Cæsar, for although his exploites of war be not so frequent and so high raised, yet being throughly considered, they are as weightie, as resolute, as constant, indeed as authentic a testimony of hardnes and military sufficiencie as any man’s else. The Greacians, without any contradiction, affoorded him the honor to entitle him the chief and first man among themselves: and to be the first and chief man of Greece is without all question to be chief and first man of the world. Touching his knowledge and worth, this ancient judgement does yet remaine amongst us, that never was man who knew so much, nor never man that spake less than he. For he was by sect a Pythagorean, and what he spake no man ever spake better. An excellent and most perswasive orator was he. And concerning his maners and conscience therein be far outwent all that ever medled with managing affairs: for in this one part, which ought especially to be noted, and which alone declareth that we are, and which only I counterpoise to al others together, he gives place to no philosopher; no not to Socrates himself. In him innocencie is a qualities proper, chief, constant, uniform, and incorruptible; in comparison of which, it seems in Alexander subalternall, uncertaine, variable, effeminate and accidentall. Antiquitie judged that precisely to sift out, and curiously to prie into all other famous captaines, there is in every one severally some speciall quality which makes him renowned and famous. In this man alone it is a virtue and sufficiencie, every where compleate and likewise, which in all offices of humane life leaveth nothing more to be wished for. Be it in public or private, in peaceable negociations or warlike occupations, be it to live or die, greatly or gloriously, I know no form or fortune of man that I admire or regard with so much honor, with so much love. True it is, I find this obstinacy in povertie somewhat scrupulous, and so have his best friends portrayed it. And this only action (high notwithstanding and very worthy admiration) I find or deem somewhat sharpen so as I would not wish nor desire the imitation thereof in me, according to the form it was in him. Scipio Æmilianus alone (wold any charge him with as fierie and nobly-minded an end, and with as deepe and universall knowledge of sciences) might be placed in the other scale of the balance against him. Oh what a displeasure has swift-gliding Time done me, even in the nick, to deprive our eyes of the chiefest pair of lives, directly the noblest that ever were in Plutarke, of these two truly worthy personages: by the universall consent of the world, the one chief of Græcians, the other principal of Romanes. What a matter, what a workeman! For a man that was no saint, but as we say a gallant-honest man, of civil maners and common customs, of a temperate haughtinesse, the richest life I know (as the vulgar saying is) to have lived amongst the living, and fraughted with the richest qualities and most to be desired parts (all things impartially considered) in my humor, is that of Alcibiades. But touching Epaminondas, for a patterne of excessive goodness I will here insert certain of his opinions. The sweetest contentment he had in all his life he witnesseth to have been the pleasure he gave his father and mother of his victory upon Leuctra: he staketh much in preferring their pleasure before his content, so just and full of so glorious an action. He thought it unlawfull, indeed were it to recover the liberty of his countrey, for any one to kill a man except he knew a just cause. And therefore was he so backeward in the enterprise of Pelopidas his companion, for the deliverance of Thebes. He was also of opinion that in a battle a man should avoid to encounter his friend, being on the contrary part, and if he met him to spare him. And his humanitie or gentleness even towards his very enemies, having made him to be suspected of the Boeotians, forasmuch as after he had miraculously forced the Lacedemonians to open him a passage, which at the entrance of Morea, near Corinth, they had undertaken to make good, he was contented, without further pursuing them in fury, to have marched over their bellies, was the cause he was deposed of his office of Captain General. Most honorable for such a cause, and for the shame it was to them, soone after to be forced by necessitie to advance him to his first place, and to acknowledge how their glory, and confesse that their safetie, did only depend on him: victory following him as his shadow whither soever he went, and as the prosperitie of his countrie was borne by and with him, so it died with and by him. Return to : Book II. CHAPTER XXXVII: OF THE RESEMBLANCE BETWEENE CHILDREN AND FATHERS CHAPTER XXXVII: OF THE RESEMBLANCE BETWEENE CHILDREN AND FATHERS HIS hudling up of so much trash, or packing of so many severall pieces, is done so strangely, as I never lay hands on it but when an over lazie idlenesse urgeth me, and nowhere but in my own house. So has it been compact at sundry pauses, and contrived at severall intervalls, as occasions have sometime for many months together, here and there in other places detained me. Besides, I never correct my first imaginations by the second, it may happen I now and then alter some word rather to diversifie then take any thing away. My purpose is to represent the progress of my humors, that every part be seen or member distinguished as it was produced. I would to God I had begunne sooner, and knew the tracks of my changes and course of my variations. A boy whom I employed to write for me supposed he had gotten a rich bootie when he stole some parts which he best liked; but one thing comforts me, that he shall gain no more than I lost by them. I am grown elder by seven or eight years since I beganne them; nor has it been with-out some new purchase. I have by the liberality of years acquainted my self with the stone-chollike. Their commerce and long conversation is not easily past over without some such-like fruite. I would be glad that of many other presents they have ever in store, to bestow upon such as waite upon them long, they had made choice of some one that had been more acceptable unto me: for they could never possess me with any that, even from my infancy, I hated more. Of all accidents incident to age it was that I feared most. My self have many times thought I went on too far, and that to hold out so long a journey, I must of necessitie in the end stumble upon some such unpleasing chance. I perceived plainly and protested sufficiently it was high time to depart, and that according to the rule of skilfull chirurgions, who when they must cut off some members life must be seared to the quick and cut to the sound flesh. That nature is wont to make him pay untolerable usurie who does not yield or pay the same in due time. I was so far from being readie to make lawfull tender of it, that in eighteene months, or thereabouts, I have continued in so yrkesome and unpleasing plight, I have already learn’d to apply my self unto it; and am now entring into covenant with this chollicall kind of life; for therein I find matter wherewith to comfort me, and to hope better. So much are men enured in their miserable estate, that no condition is so poore but they will accept: so they may continue in the same. Heare Mæcenas - Debilem facito manu, Debilem pede, coxa. Lubricos quate dentes, Vita dum superego, bene est. -- SEN. Epist. ci. Make me be weake of hand, Scarce on my legs to stand, Shake my loose teeth with pain, ’Tis well so life remaine. And Tamburlane cloked the fantastic cruelty he exercised upon Lazars or Leprousmen with a foolish kind of humanitie, putting all he could find or hear of to death, (as he said) to ridde them from so painefull and miserable a life as they lived. For there was none so wretched amongst them that would not rather have been three times a leper than not to be at all. And Antisthenes the Stoic being very sicke, and crying out, ’Oh, who shall deliver me from my tormenting evils?’ Diogenes, who was come to visite him, foorthwith presenting him a knife: ’Mary, this,’ said he, ’and that very speedily, if you please’: ’I mean not of my life,’ replied be, ’but of my sickness.’ The sufferances which simply touch us in mind do much less afflict me then most men: partly by judgement; for the world deemeth diverse things horible, or avoydable with the loss of life, to me are in a manner indifferent: partly by a stupid and insensible complexion, I have in accidents that hit me not point-blancke: which complexion I esteeme one of the better partes of my natural condition. But the truely-essentiall and corporall sufferances, those I taste very sensibly: yet is it, having other times fore-apprehended them with a delicate and weake sight, and by the enjoying of this long health and happy rest, which God has lent me the better part of my age, somewhat impaired; I had by imagination conceived them so intolerable that, in good truth, I was more afraide than since I have found hurt in them: whereupon I dayly augment this opinion: that most of our soules faculties (as we employ them) do more trouble than stead the quiet repose of life. I am continually grapling with the worst of all diseases, the most grievous, the most mortal, the most remedilesse and the most violent. I have alreadie had trial of five or six long and painefull fittes of it. Nevertheless, either I flatter-my self, or in this plight there is yet something that would faine keep life and soul together, namely, in him whose mind is free from fear of death, and from the threats, conclusions and consequences which physicke is ever buzzing into our heads. But the effect of pain itself has not so sharpe a smarting, or so pricking a sharpenesse, that a setled man should enter into rage or fall into despaire. This commoditie at least I have by the chollicke, that what I could never bring to pass in my self, which was altogether to reconcile and thoroughly to acquaint my self with death, she shall atchieve, she shall accomplish, for by how much more she shall importune and urge me, by so much less shall death be fearefull unto me. I had already gotten, not to be beholding to life, but only in regard of life, and for lives sake: she shall also untie this intelligence and loose this combination. And God graunt, if in the end her sharpenesse shall happen to surmount my strength, she cast me not into other extremities no less vicious, no less bad, that is, to love and desire to die. Summum nec metuas diem, nec optes. -- MART. 1. x. Epig. xlvii. ult. Nor fear your latest doom, Nor wish it ere it come. They are two passions to be feared, but one has her remedy nearer than the other. Otherwi se I have ever, found that precept ceremonious which so precisely appoints a man to set a good countenance, a setled resolution, and disdainful carriage, upon the sufferance of evills. Why does Philosophy, which only respecteth livelinesse and regardeth effects, ammuze itself about these externall apparances? Let her leave this care to Mimikes, to Histrions, and to Rhetoricke Masters, who make so great accompt of our gestures. Let her hardly remit this vocall lithernesse unto evil, if it be neither cordiall nor stomacall. And let her lend her voluntary plaints to the kind of sighes, sobs, palpitations, and palenesse which nature has exempted from our puissance. Alwayes provided, the courage be without fear, and words sans despair: let her be so contented. ’What matter is it if we bend our arms, so we writhe not our thoughts?’ She frame thus for ourselves, not for others: to be, not to seem. Let her applie herself to governe our understanding, which she has undertaken to instruct. Let her in the pangs or fits of the chollike, still maintains the soul capable to acknowledge herself and follow her accustomed course, resisting sorrow and enduring grief, and not shamefully to prostrate herself at his feet: mooved and chafed with the combate, not basely suppressed nor faintly overthrowne: capable of entertainement and other occupations unto a certain limit. In so extreme accidents it is cruelty to require so composed a warde at our hands. If we have a good game it skills not, though we have an ill countenance. If the body be any whit eased by complaining, let him do it: if stirring or agitation please him, let him turn, rowle, and tosse himself as long as he list: if with raising his voice, or sending it forth with more violence, he think his grief any thing alayed or vented (as some physicians affirme it somewhat easeth women great with child, and is a meane of easy or speedy delivery) fear he not to do it; or if he may but entertaine his torment, let him mainly cry out. Let us not commaund our voice to depart; but if she will, let us not hinder it, Epicurus does not only pardon his wise-man to crie out, when he is grieved or vexed, but perswadeth him to it. Pugiles etiam quum feriunt, in jactandis cæstibus ingemiscunt, quia profundenda voce omne corpus intenditur venitque plaga vehementior: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ii.) ’Men when they fight with sand-bags, or such he avy weapons, in fetching their blow and driving it, will give a groan withall because by stretching their voice all their body is also strayned, and the stroke cometh with more vehemence.’ We are vexed and troubled enough with the evil, without troubling and vexing ourselves with these superfluous rules. This I say to excuse those which are ordinarily seen to rage in the fits, and storme in the assaults of this sicknesse, for, as for me, I have hitherto past it over with somewhat a better countenance, and am content to groan without braying and exclaiming. And yet I trouble not myself to maintaine this exterior decencie; for I make small reckoning of such an advantage, in that I lend my sicknesse what it requireth: but either my pain is not so excessive, or I bear it with more constancy than the vulgar sorte. Indeede I must confesse, when the sharpe fits or throwes assaile me, I complain and vexe my self, but yet I never fall into despaire, as that fellow: Eiulatu, questu, gemitu, fremitibus Resonando multum flebiles voces refert. -- Cic. ibid. With howling, growning and complaint of fates, Most lamentable cries he imitates. I feel my self in the greatest heate of my sicknesse and I ever found my self capable and in tune, to speak, to think, and to answer, as soundly as at any other time, but not so constantly, because my pain does much trouble and distract me. When I am thought to be at the lowest, and that such as are about me spare me, I often make a trial of my forces, and propose them such discourses as are furthest from my state. There is nothing impossible for me; and me thinkes I can do all things upon a sodaine fitte, so it continue not long. Oh, why have not I the gift of that dreamer mentioned by Cicero, who dreaming that he was closely embracing a yong wench, found himself ridde of the stone in his sheetes! Mine do strangely dis-wench me. In the intermission or respites of this outragious pain, when as my ureters (through which the urine passeth from the reines to the bladder) languish without gnawing me, I sodainely return into my ordinary form; forasmuch as my mind taketh no other allarume but the sensible and corporall. All which I certainely owe unto the care I have had to prepare my self by reason and discourse of such accidents: ----- laborum Nulla mihi nov a nunc facies inopinaque surgit, Omnia præcepi, atque animo mecum ante peregi. --VIRG. Æn. 1. vi. 103. No new or unexpected form is cast, Of travels in my breast: all I forecast, In my mind with my self I all forepast. I am handled somewhat roughly for a prentise, and with a violent and rude change; being at one instant falne from a very pleasing, calme, and most happy condition of life, unto the most dolorous, yrkesome, and painefull that can possibly be imagined: for, besides that in itself it is a disease greatly to be feared, its beginnings or approaches are in me sharper or more difficult than it is wont to trouble others withall. The pangs and fittes thereof do so often assaile me, that in a manner I have no more feeling of perfect health. Notwithstanding I hitherto keep my spirit so seated as, if I can but join constancy unto it, I find my self to be in a much better state of life than a thousand others, who have neither ague nor other infirmitie but such as for want of discourse they give themselves. There is a certain fashion of subtile humility which procedeth of presumption: as this, that in many things we acknowledge our ignorance, and are so curteous to avowe that in Natures workes there are some qualities and conditions which to us are imperceptible, and whereof our sufficiencie cannot discover the means nor find out the causes. By this honest and conscientious declaration, we hope to gain that we shall also be beleeved in those we shall say to understand. We neede not go to cull out miracles, and chuse strange difficulties: me seems, that amongst those things we ordinarily see there are such incomprehensible rarities as they exceed all difficulty of miracles. What monster is it that this teare or drop of seed whereof we are ingendred brings with it, and in it the impressions, not only of the corpor all form, but even of the very thoughts and inclinations of our fathers? Where does this droppe of water contains or lodge this infinite number of formes? And how bear they these resemblances of so rash and unruly a progresse, that the childes child shall be answerable to his grandfather, and the nephew to his uncle? In the family of the Lepidus the Roman, there have been three, not successively, but some between, that were borne with one same eye covered with a cartilage or gristle. There was a race in Thebes which from their mothers wombe bare the form of a burre, or yron of a launce; and such as had it not were judged as misbegotten and deemed unlawfull. Aristotle reporteth of a certain nation, with whom all women were common, where children were allotted their fathers only by their resemblances. It may be supposed that I am indebted to my father for this stonie-quality, for he died exceedingly tormented with a great stone in his bladder. He never felt himself troubled with the disease but at the age of sixtie-seaven years, before which time he had never felt any likelihood or motion of it, nor in his reines, nor in his sides, nor elsewhere: and until then had lived in very prosperous health, and little subject to infirmities, and continued seven years and more with that disease training a very dolorous lives-end. I was borne five and twenty years before his sickness and during the course of his healthy state, his third child. Where was al this while the propension or inclination to this defect hatched? And when he was so far from such a disease, that light part of his substance wherewith he composed me, how could it for her part bear so great an impression of it? And how so closely covered, that fortie-five years after, I have begunne to have a feeling of it? and hitherto alone, among so many brethren and sisters, and all of one mother. He that shal resolve me of this progresse I will believe him as many other miracles as he shall please to tell me: alwayes provided (as commonly they do) he go not about to pay me with a doctrine much more difficult and fantastical then the thing itself (let physicians somewhat excuse my liberty): for by the same infusion and fatall insinuation, I have received the hate and contempt of their doctrine. The antipathie which is betweene me and their arte is to me hereditarie. My father lived three score and fourteene years; my grandfather three score and nine; my great grandfather very near fourescore, and never tasted or took any kind of physicke. And whatsoever was not in ordinary use amongst them was deemed a drug. Physicke is grounded upon experience and examples. So is mine opinion. Is not this a manifest kind of experience, and very advantageous? I know not whether in all their registers they are able to find me three more, borne, bred, brought up, and deceased, under one roofe, in one same chimnie, that by their own direction and regiment have lived so long. Wherein they must needs grant me, that if it be not reason, at least it is fortune that is on my side. Whereas among physicians fortune is of more consequence then reason. Low-brought and weake as I am now, let them not take me at an advantage, nor let them not threaten me: for that were insulting arrogance. And to say truth, I have by my familiar examples gained enough upon them, although they take hold and stay there. Humane things have not so much constancy: it is now two hundred years, wanting but eighteene, that this essay continueth with us: for the first was borne in the yeare of our Lord one thousand foure hundred and two, some reason there is why this experience should now beginne to faile us. Let them not upbraide me with those infirmities which now have seized upon me: is it not sufficient to have lived seven and fortie years in good and perfect health for my part? Suppose it to be the end of my ca rriere, yet it is of the longest. Mine ancestors by some secret instinct and natural inclination have ever loathed al manner of physicke: for the very sight of drugs bred a kind of horror in my father. The Lord of Gaviac, mine unckle by the fathers side, a man of the church, sickish even from his birth, and who notwithstanding made his weake life to hold until sixtie seaven years, falling once into a dangerous and vehement continuall feaver, it was by the physicians concluded that unless he would aide himself (for they ofte terme that aide which indeede is impeachment) he was but a dead man. The good soul, afrighted as he was at that horrible sentence, answred thus, why then I am a dead man: but shortly after God made their prognostications to proove vain. The Lord of Bussaguet, last of the brethren (for they were foure), and by much the last, he alone submitted himself to that arte, as I imagine by reason of the frequence he had in other sciences; for he was a counsellor in the Court of Parliament, which prospered so ill with him that though he were in show of a very strong complexion, he died long before the others, except one, the Lord of Saint Michæl. It may well be I have received of them that natural dyspathie to physicke. Yet if there had been no other consideration but this, I would have endevoured to force it. For all these conditions, which without reason are borne in us, are vicious. It is a kind of maladie a man mu st fight withall. It may be I had such a propension, but I have settled and strengthened the same by discourses which in me have confirmed the opinion I have of it. For I have also the consideration to refuse physicke by reason of the sharpnesse of its taste. It would not easily agree with my humor, who think health worthy to be purchased with the price of all cauteries and incisions, how painefull soever. And following Epicurus, me seems that all manner of voluptuousness should be avoided, if greater griefes follow them, and griefes to be sought after, that have greater voluptuousness ensuing them. Health is a very precious jewell, and the only thing that in pursuite of it deserveth a man should not only employ time, labor, sweate and goods, but also life to get it; forasmuch as without it life becomes injurious unto us. Voluptuousnes, science and virtue, without it, tarnish and vanish away. And to the most constant and exact discourses that philosophy will imprint in our min ds to the contrary, we neede not oppose any thing against it but the image of Plato, being visited with the falling sickenesse, or an apoplexie; and in this presupposition chalenge him to call the richest faculties of his mind to helpe him. All means that may bring us unto health, cannot be esteemed of men either sharpe or dear. But I have some other apparances which strangely make me to distrust al his ware. I do not say but there may be some art of it: it is certain that amongst so m any of Natures workes there are some things proper for the preservation of our health. I know there are some simples which in operation are moistening and some drying. My self have found, by experience, that radish rootes are windie, and senie-leeves breede loosenes in the belly. I have the knowledge of diverse such experiments, as I know that mutton nourisheth, that wine warmeth me. And Solon was wont to say that eating was, as all other drugges are, a medicine against the disease of hunger. I disallow not the use we draw from the world, nor doubt I of natures power and fruitfulnesse, and other application to our need. I see that the pickrell-fish and the swallowes live well by her laws. I greatly distrust the inventions of our wit, of our arte and of our science, in favor of which we have forsaken nature, and abandoned her rules; wherein we can neither observe limitation nor keep moderation. As we term justice, the composition of the first laws that came unto our hands, and their practice and dispensation very often most wicked and inconvenient. And as those which mocke and condemne it, intend not nevertheless to wrong this noble virtue; but only to condemne the abuse and profanation of so sacred a title: so likewise in physicke, I know her glorious name, her proposition, and her promise, so profitable to mankinde: but what it desseigneth amongst us, I neither honor nor respect. First, experience makes me fear it, for of all I know, I see no kind of men so soone sicke, nor so late cured, as those who are under the jurisdiction of physicke: Their very health is distempered and corrupted by the constraint of their prescriptions. Physitians are not contented to have the government over sicknesses, but they make health to be sicke, lest a man should at any time escape their authority. Of a constant and perfect health, do they not frame an argument of some future daungerous sickenesse? I have often been sicke, and without any their helpe, I have found my sicknesses (though I never medled with the bitterness of their prescriptions) as easy to be tollerated and as short as any mans else, and yet I have felt diverse. My health is free and sound, without any rules or discipline) except of my own custom and pleasure. I find no difference in places, al are likewise to me to dwell in: for being sicke, I neede no other commodities then those I must have when I am in health. I am nothing passionated, though I be without physician, without apothecary, or without physical helpe; whereat I see some as much troubled in mind as they are with their disease. What, does the best physician of them all make us perceive any happinesse or continuance in his life, as may witness some manifest effect of his skill and learning? There is no nation but has continued many ages without physicke: indeed the first ages, which is as much to say, the best and most happy: and the tenth part of the world has as yet no use of it. Infinite nations know it not; where they live both more healthie and much longer than we do: indeed and amongst us the common sort live happily without it. The Romanes had been sixe hundred years before ever they received it: by means of interposition of Cato the censor, they banisht it their citie, who declared how easily man might live without it, having lived himself foure score and five yeeres, and his wife until she was extreamely old, not without physicke, but indeed without any physician. For whatsoever is by experience found healthy for our body and health may be termed physicke. He entertained (as Plutarke says) his familie in health by the use (as far as I remember) of hares milk: as the Arcadians (says Plinie) cure all maladies with cowes milke. And the Lybians (says Herodotus) do generally enjoy a perfect health by observing this custom, which is, so soone as their children are about foure yeeres old, to cautherize and seare the veines of their head and temples, whereby they cut off the way to all rumes and defluxions. And the countrie-people where I dwell use nothing against all diseases but some of the strongest wine they can get, with store of saffron and spice in it; and all with one like fortune. And to say true, of all this diversitie of rules and confusion of prescriptions, what other end or effect workes it but to evacuate the belly? which a thousand home-simples will do as well. And I know not whether it be as profitable (as they say) and whether our nature require the residents of her excrements, until a certain measure, as wine does his lees for his preservation. You see often men very healthy, by some strange accidents, to fall into violent vomites and fluxies, and voyd great store of excrements, without any precedent need or succeeding benefite: indeed, with some empairing and prejudice. I learnt of Plato not long since, that of three motions which belong to us, the last and worst is that of purgations, and that no man, except he be a foole, ought to undertake it, unless it be in great extremity. The evil is troubled and stirred up by contrary oppositions. It is the form of life that gently must diminish, consume and bring it to an end. Since the violent twinges of the drug and maladie are ever to our loss, since the quarrell is cleared in us, and the drug a trustlesse helpe; by its own nature an enemy to our health, and but by trouble has no accesse in our state. Let’s give them leave to go on. That order which provideth for fleas and moles, does also provide for men, who have the same patience to suffer themselves to be governed that fleas and moles have. We may fairely cry Bo-bo-boe; it may well make us hoarse, but will nothing advaunce it. It is a proud and impetuous order. Our fear and our despaire, in liew of enviting help from it, does distaste and delay it out of our helpe: it oweth his course to sickness as well as to health. To suffer itself to be corrupted in favor of one, to the prejudice of the others rights, it will not do it, so should they fall into disorder. Let us go on in the name of God; let us follow. That order leadeth on such as follow it: those that follow it not, it haleth on, both with their rage and physicke together. Cause a purgation to be prepared for your braine; it will be better emploied unto it then to your stomacke. A Lacedemonian being asked, what had made him live so long in health, answered, ’The ignorance of physicke.’ And Adrian the Emperor, as he was dying, ceased not to crie out that the number of physicians had killed him. A bad wrestler became a physician. ’Courage,’ said Diogenes to him, ’you hast reason to do so, for now shall you helpe to put them into the ground who have heeretofore ayded to lay you on it.’ But according to Nicocles, they have this happe, that the sunne does manifest their success, and the earth does cover their fault. And besides, they have a very advantageous fashion among themselves, to make use of all manner of events; for whatsoever either Fortune or Nature, or any other strange cause (whereof the number is infinite) produces in us or good or healthfull, it is the priviledge of physicke to ascribe it unto herself. All the fortunate successes that come to the patient which is under their government, it is from nature he has them. The occasions that have cured me, and which heale a thousand others who never send or call for physicians to helpe them, they usurpe them in their subjects. And touching ill accidents, either they utterly disavow them, in imputing the blame of them to the patient, by some vain reasons, whereof they never misse to find a great number; as he lay with his arms out of the bed, he has heard the noyse of a coach. ------rhedarum transitus arcto Vicorum inflexu. -- JUV. Sat. iii. 236. Coaches could hardly pass, The lane so crooked was. His window was left open all night: he has laine upon the left side, or troubled his head with some heavy thought. In some, a word, a dreame, or a looke, is of them deemed a sufficient excuse to free themselves from all imputation: or if they please, they will also make use of this emparing, and thereby make up their business, and as a meane which can never faile them, when by their applications the disease is grown desperate, to pay us with the assurance that, if their remedies had not been, it would have been much worse. He whom but from a cold they have brought to a quotidian ague, without them should have had a continuall feaver. They must needs thrive in their businesses since all ills redownd to their profit. Truely they have reason to require of the pacient an application of favourable confidence in them: which must necessarily be in good earnest and yielding to apply itself unto imaginations, over-hardly to be believed, Plato said very well and to the purpose, that freely to lie belonged only to physicians, since our health dependeth on their vanity and falsehood of promises. Æsope, an author of exceeding rare excellence, and whose graces few discover, is very pleasant in representing this kind of tyrannical authority unto us, which they usurpe upon poore soules, weakned by sickenes and overwhelmed through fear: for he reporteth how a sicke man, being demaunded by his physician what operation he felt by the physicke he had given him: ’I have sweate much,’ answered he. ’That is good,’ replied the physician. Another time he asked him again how he had done since: ’I have had a great cold and quivered much,’ said he. ’That is very well,’ quoth the physician again. The third time he demaunded of him how he felt himself, he answered: ’I swell and puffe up as it were with the dropsie.’ ’That’s not amisse,’ said the physician. A familiar friend of his coming afterward to visite him, and to know how he did. ’Verily,’ said be, ’my friend, I die with being too too well.’ There was a more equall law in Egypt by which for the first three dayes the physician took the patient in hand upon the patients perill and fortune; but the three dayes expired, it was at his own. For, what reason is there that Æsculapius their patrone must have been strucken with thunder, forasmuch as he recovered Hippolitus from death to life? Nam pater omnipotens aliquem indignatus ab umbris, Mortalem infernis ad lumina surgere vitæ, Ipse repertorem medicinæ talis, et artis Fulmine Phoebigenam Stygias detrusit ad undas. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. vii. 770. Jove, scorning that from shades infernall night, A mortal man should rise to lifes new light, Apolloes son to hell he thunder-threw, Who such an arte found out, such medicine knew, and his followers must be absolved that send so many soules from life to death? A physician boasted unto Nicocles that his arte was of exceeding great authority. It is true (quoth Nicocles) for it may kill so many people without fear of punishment by law. As for the rest, had I been of their counsell, I would surely have made my discipline more sacred and mysterious. They had begunne very well, but the end has not answered the beginning. It was a good ground to have made Gods and Dæmons authors of their science, to have assumed a peculiar language and writing to themselves. Howbeit, philosophy supposeth it to be folly to persuade a man to his profit by ways not understood: Ut si quis medicus imperet vt sumat. ’As if a physician should bid a man take. Terrigenam, herbigradam, domiportam, sanguine cassam. -- Cic. Divin. ii. One, earth-borne, go-by-grasse, house-bearing, slimie, blood-less.’ It was a good rule in their arte, and which accompanieth all fanaticall, vain, and supernaturall artes, that the patients beliefe must by good hope and assurance preoccupate their effect and operation. Which rule they hold so far forth, that the most ignorant and bungling horse-leach is fitter for a man that has confidence in him, than the skilfullest and learnedst physician. The very choyce of most of their drugges is somewhat mysterious and divine. The left foot of a tortoyze, the stale of a lizard; the dongue of an elephant, the liver of a mole, blood drawne from under the right wing of a white pigeon, and for us who are troubled with the stone-cholike (so disdainfully abuse they our misery) some rattes pounded to small powder, and such other foolish trash, which rather seem to be magike spells or charmes than effects of any solid science. I omit to speak of the odde number of their pilles, the destination of certain dayes and feastes of the yeare, the distinction of hours to gather the simples of their ingredients, and the same rewbarbative and severely- grave looke of theirs, and of their port and countenance, which Plinie himself mocketh at. But, as I was about to say they have failed, forasmuch as they have not added this to their fair beginning, to make their assemblies more religious, and their consultations more secret. No profane man should have access unto them, no more than to the secret ceremonies of Æsculapius. By which means it commeth to pass that their irresolution; the weaknesse of their arguments, divinations and grounds; the sharpenesse of their contestations, full of hatred, of jealousie and particular considerations, being apparant to all men; a man must needs be stark blinde if he who falleth into their hands see not himself greatly endangered. Who ever saw physician use his fellowes receipt without dimishing or adding somewhat unto it; whereby they greatly betraie their arte and make us perceive they rather respect their reputation, and consequently their profit, than the well- fare or interests of their patients. He is the wisest amongst their doctors who has long since prescribed them that one alone should meddle to cure a sicke man; for, if it prosper not with him, and he do no good, the reproach will not be great to the arte of physicke through the fault of one man alone; and on the other side, if it thrive well with him, the glory shall be the greater; where as if they be many, on every hand will they discredit their mysterie, because they oftner happen to do ill than well. They should have been content with the perpetuall disagreeing which is ever found in the opinions of the principal masters and chief authors of their science, known but by such as are conversant in bookes, without making apparent show of the controversies, and inconstancies of their judgement, which they foster and continue amongst themselves. Will we have an example of the ancient debate of physicke? Herophilus placeth the originall cause of sickenesse in the humors: Erasistratus, in the blood of the arteries: Asclepiades, in the invisible atomes that pass into our pores; Alcmeon, in the abundance or defense of corporall forces: Diocles, in the inequality of the bodies elements, and in the quality of the aire we breathe: Strabo, in the abundance, cruditie, and corruption of the nourishment we take: Hipocrates does place it in the spirits. There is a friend of theirs, whom they know better than I, who to his purpose crieth out that the most important science in use amongst us (as that which has charge of our health and preservation) is by il hap the most uncertaine, the most confused, and most agitated with infinite changes. There is no great danger to mistake the height of the sunne, or missereckon the fraction of some astronomical suppuration; but herein, whereon our being and chief freehold does wholly depend, it is no wisdom to abandon ourselves to the mercy of the agitation of so manifold contrary winds. Before the Peloponnesian war there was no great news of this science. Hipocrates brought it into credite. Whatsoever he established, Chrisippus overthrew. Afterward Erasistratus, grande-child to Aristotle, re-enverst what ever Chrysippus had written of it. After these, start up the Emperikes, who concerning the managing of this arte, took a new course altogether different from those ancient fathers. And when their credit began to growe stale, Herophilus brought another kind of physicke into use, which Asclepiades, when his turn came, impugned, and in the end subverted. Then came the opinions of Themison to be in great authority, then those of Musa, and afterward those of Vectius Valens, a famous physician, by reason of the acquaintance he had with Messalina. During the time of Nero, the soveraigntitie of physick fel to the hands of Thessalus, who abolished and condemned whatsoever had been held of it before his time. This mans doctrine was afterward wholly overthrowne by Crinas of Marseilles, who anew revived and framed that all men should direct and rule medicinable operations to the Ephemerides and motions of the starres, to eate, to drinke, to sleepe at what hour it should please Luna and Mercurie. His authority was soone after supplanted by Charinus, a physician of the same town of Marseilles, who not only impugned ancient physicke, but also the use of warme and public bathes, which had been accustomed to many ages before. He caused men to be bathed in cold water; indeed, were it in the deepe of winter he plunged and dived sicke men into the running streame of rivers. Untill Plinies time no Roman had ever dained to exercise the arte of physicke, but was ever used by strangers and Græcians as at this daie it is used in France by Latinizers. For as a famous physician says, we do not easily admit and allow that physicke, which we understand, nor those drugs we gather ourselves. If those nations from whom we have the wood guiacum, the sarsapareille, and the wood esquine, have any physician amongst them, how much think we by the same commendation of the strangenesse, rarenesse and dearth, they will rejoice at our coleworts and parsly? For, who dareth contemne things sought and fetcht so far- off with the hazard of so long and dangerous a peregrination? since these auncient mutations of physicke, there have been infinite others, that have continued unto our dayes, and most often entire and universal mutations; as are those which Paracelsus, Fioravanti and Argenterius have produced: for (as it is told me) they do not only change a receipt, but also the whole contexture and policy of physickes whole body, accusing such as hitherto have made profession thereof, of ignorance and cosinage. Now I leave to your imagination in what plight the poore patient findeth himself. If we could but he assured, when they mistake themselves, their physicke would do us no harme, although not profit us, it were a reasonable composition for a man to hazard himself to get some good, so he endangered not himself to lose by it. Æsope reporteth this story, that one who had sought a Moore-slave, supposing his blacke hew had come unto him by some strange accident, or ill usage of his former master, with great diligence caused him to be medicined with diverse ba thes and sundry potions; it fortuned the Moore did no whit mend or change his swarthy complexion, but lost his former health. How often commeth it to pass, and how many times see we physicians charge one another with their patients death. I remember a popular sickenesse which some years since greatly troubled the townes about me, very mortal and dangerous the rage whereof being overpast, which had carried away an infinite number of persons; one of the most famous physicians in all the country published a book concerning that disease, wherein he adviseth himself that they had done amisse to use phlebotomy, and confesseth it had been one of the principal causes of so great an inconvenience. Moreover, their authors hold that there is no kind of physicke, but has some hurtful part in it. And if those that fit our turn do in some sort harm us, what must those do which are given us to no purpose, and out of season? As for me, if nothing else belonged thereunto, I deem it a matter very dangerous, and of great prejudice for him who loathes the taste or abborres the smell of a potion, to swallow it at so unconvenient hours, and so much against his heart. And I think it much distempereth a sicke man, namely, in a season he has so much neede of rest. Besides, consider but the occasions on which they ordinarily ground the cause of our sickenesses; they are so light and delicate, as thence I argue that a very small error in compounding of their drugges may occasion as much detriment. Now if the mistaking in a physician be dangerous, it is very ill for us ; for it is hard if he fall not often into it. He has needs of many parts, diverse considerations, and severall circumstances to proportion his design justly. He ought to know the sicke man’s complexion, his temper, his humors, his inclinations, and his imaginations. He must be assured of external circumstances; of the nature of the place; the condition of the aire; the quality of the weather; the situation of the planets, and their influences. In sickenes, be ought to be acquainted with the causes, with the signes, with the affections and criticall days; in drugges, he should understand their weight, their virtue, and their operation, the country, the figure, the age, the dispensation. In all these parts be must know how to proportion and refer them one unto another, thereby to beget a perfect symmetric or due proportion of each part; wherein if he misse never so little, or if amongst so many wheeles and several motions, the least be out of tune or temper, it is enough to marre all. God knowes how hard the knowledge of most of these parts is: for example, how shall he find out the proper signe of the disease, every malady being capable of an infinite number of signes. How many debates, ad controversies have they amongst themselves about the interpretations of urine. Otherwise, whence should that continuall altercation come we see amongst them about the knowledge of the disease? How should we excuse this fault, wherein they fall so often, to take a martin for a fox? In those diseases I have had (so they admitted any difficulty) I could never yet find three agreeing in one opinion. I more willingly note examples that concerne my self. A gentleman in Paris was not long since cut for the stone by the appointment of physicians, in whose bladder they found no more stone then in his hand: where also a Bishop, who was my very good friend, had by his physicians been earnestly solicited to be cut; and my self, because they were of his counsell, upon their words, aided to persuade him to it; who being deceased and opened, it was found he had no infirmity but in his reines. They are less excusable in this disease, for so much as it is in some sort palpable. Whereby I judge the arte of chirurgery much more certain; for it seeth and handleth what it does, and therein is less conjecture and divination. Whereas phisitians have no speculum matrices to discover our braine, our lungs, and our liver unto them. The very promises of physicke are incredible. For being to provide for diverse and contrary accidents, which often trouble us together, and with a kind of necessary relation one unto another, as the heate of the liver and the cold of the stomacke, they will persuade us that with their ingredients this one shall warme the stomacke, and this other coole the liver; the one has charge to go directly to the reynes, indeed even to the bladder, without enstalling his operation anywhere else, and by reason of its secret propriety, keeping his force and virtue all that long way, and so full of stops or lets until it come to the place to whose service it is destinated. Another shall drie the braine, and another moisten the lungs. Of all this hotch-pot having composed a mixture or potion, is it not a kind of raving to hope their several virtues shall divide and separate themselves from out such a confusion or commixture, to run to so diverse charges? I should greatly fear they would loose or change their tickets and trouble their quarters. And who can imagine, that in this liquid confusion these faculties be not corrupted, confounded, and alter one another? For that the execution of this ordinance depends on another officer, to whose trust and mercy we must once more commit our lives? As we have doublet and hose-makers to make our cloths, and are so much the better fitted, inasmuch as each meddles with his own trade, and such have their occupation more strictly limited then a tailer that will make all; and as for our necessary foode, some of our great lords, for their more commodity and ease, have severall cookes, as some only to dresse boiled meates, and some to roste, others to bake; whereas if one cooke alone would supply all three in general he could never do it so exactly: In like sort for the curing of all diseases, the Egyptians had reason to reject this general mysterie of physicians, and to sunder this profession for every malady, allotting each part of the body his distinct workman. For every particular part was thereby more properly attended, and less confusedly governed, and for so much as they regarded but the same especially. Our physicians never remember that he who will provide for all provideth for nothing; and that the totall and summarie policy of this little world is unto them undigestible. Whilst they feared to stop the course of a bloody flux because he should not fal into an ague, they killed a friend of mine who was more worth then all the rabble of them, indeed, were they as many more. They balance their divinations of future things with present evils, and because they will not cure the braine in prejudice of the stomacke, they offend the stomacke and empaire the braine, and all by their seditious and tumultuary drugs. Concerning the variety and weaknes of the reasons of this Art, it is more apparent then in any other Art. Aperitive things are good for a man that’s troubled with the collike, because that opening and dilating the passages, they addresse this slimy matter whereof the gravel and stone is engendred, and so convay downeward whatsoever beginneth to harden and petrifie in the reines: aperitive things are dangerous for a man thats troubled with the collick, because that opening and dilating the passages, they addresse towards the reines the matter enger idring gravell, which by reason of the propensions they have with it, easily seizing on the same, must by consequence stay great store of that which is convaied unto them. Moreover, if by chance it fortune to meet with a body somewhat more grosse then it ought to be, to pass all those strait turnings, which to expel the same they must glide through; that body being moved by those soluble things, and cast in those strait chanels, and coming to stop them, it will doubtlesse hasten a certain and most dolorous death. They have a like constancy about the counsels they give us, touching the regiment of our life. It is good to make water often; for by experience we see that permitting the same idlely to ly still, we give it leisure to discharge itself of her lees and excrements, which may serve to breed the stone in the bladder. It is good to make water but seldom, for the weighty dregs it draws with it are not easily carried away except by violence: as by experience is seen in a torrent that runneth very swift, which sweepeth and clenseth the place through which he passeth, much more than does a slow-gliding streame. Likewise it is good to have often copulation with women, for that openeth the passages, and convaieth the gravell away: it is also hurtful, for it heateth, wearieth, and weakneth the reines. It is good for one to bathe himself in warme water, forasmuch as that looseth and moistneth the places where the gravel and stone lurketh: it is also bad, because this application of externall heat helpeth the reines to concoct, to harden and petrifie the matter disposed unto it. To such as are at the bathes, it is more healthful to eat but little at night, that the water they are to drink the next morning, finding the stomacke empty, and without any obstacle, it may work the greater operation: on the other side, it is better to eat but a little at dinner, lest a man might hinder the operation of the water, which is not yet perfect, and not to charge the stomacke so suddenly, after this other travell, and leave the office of digesting unto the night, which can better do it then the day; the body and spirit being then in continual motion and action. See here how they in all their discourses juggle, daily, and trifle at our charge, and are never able to bring me a proposition, but I can presently frame another to the contrary of like force and consequence. Let them then no longer rail against those who in any sicknes suffer themselves gently to be directed by their own appetite, and by the counsell of nature, and who remit themselves to common fortune. I have by occasion of my travels seen almost all the famous bathes of Christendome, and some years since have begun to use them: for in general I deem bathing to be very good and healthy, and I am persuaded we incur no small incommodities in our health by having neglected and lost this custom, which in former times were generally observed very near amongst all nations, and is yet with diverse at this time to wash their bodies every day. And I cannot imagine but that we are much the worse with keeping our bodies all over-crusted, and our pores stopt with grease and filth. And touching the drinking of them, fortune has first made it to agree very well with in taste; secondly, it is natural and simple, and though vain, nothing dangerous; whereof this infinity of people of al sorts and complexions, and of all nations that come to them, does warrant me. And although I have as yet found no extraordinary good or wondrous effect in them, but rather having somewhat curiously examined the matter, I find all the reports of such operations, which in such places are reported, and of many believed, to be false and fabulous. So easily does the world deceive itself, namely, in things it desires or faine would have come to pass. Yet have I seen but few or none at al whom these waters have made worse; and no man can without malice denie but that they stir up a mans appetite, make easy digestion, and except a man go to them overweake and faint (which I would have none do) they will adde a kind of new mirth unto him. They have not the power to raise men from desperate diseases. They may stay some light accident, or prevent the threats of some alteration. Whosoever goeth to them and resolveth not to be merry, that so he may enjoy the pleasure of the good company resorts to them, and of the pleasant walks or exercises which the beauty of those places, where bathes are commonly seated, does affoord and delight men withall; he without doubt loses the better part and most assured of their effect. And therefore have I hitherto chosen to stay my self and make use of those, where I found the pleasure of the situation most delightsome, most conveniencie of lodging, of victuals and company, as are in France the bathes of Banieres; those of Plombieres, on the frontiers of Germany and Loraine: those of Baden in Switzerland; those of Luca in Tuscanie; and especially those of della Villa, which I have used most often and at diverse seasons of the yeare. Every nation has some particular opinion concerning their use, and severall laws and formes how to use them, and all different: and as I have found by experience the effect in a manner all one. In Germany they never use to drinke of the waters, but bathe themselves for all diseases, and will lie paddling in them almost from sunne to sunne. In Italie, if they drinke nine dayes of the water, they wash themselves other thirty dayes with it. And commonly they drinke it mixt with other drugges, thereby to helpe the operation. Here, our physicians appoint us when we have drunke to walk upon it that so we may helpe to digest it: there, so soone as they have drunke, they make them lie a bed until they have voyded the same out again, continually warming their stomack and feete with warme clothes. All the Germanes while they lie in the water do particularly use cupping glasses and scarifications; and the Italians use their doccie, which are certain spouts running with warme waters convayed from the bathes-spring in leaden pipes, where, for the space of a month, they let it spout upon their heads, upon their stomacke, or upon any other part of the body, according as neede requireth, one hour in the forenoone and as long in the afternoone. There are infinit other differences of customs in every countrey, or, to say better, there is almost no resemblances betweene one and the other. See how this part of physicke by which alone I have suffered myself to be carried away, which, though it be least artificiall, yet has she the share of the confusion and uncertainty seen in all other parts and every where of this arte. Poets may say what they list, and with more emphasis and grace witness these two epigrammes: Alcon hesterno signum lovis attiqit. Ille Quamvis marmoreus, vim patitur medici. Ecce hodie jussus transferri ex æde vetusta, Efertur, quamvis sit Deus atque lapis.’ --LUCIL. Auson. Epig. 73. Alcon looked yesterday on carved Iove. Iove, though of marble, feeles the leeches force, From his old church to day made to remoove, Though god and stone, he’s carried like a corse. And the other: Lotus nobiscu m est hilaris, cænavit et idem, Inventus mane est mortuus Androgoras. Tam subitæ mortis causam Faustine requiris? Insomnis medicum viderat Hermocratem. -- Mart. vi. Epig. liii. Androgoras in health bath’d over night with us, And merry supt, but in the morne stark dead was found. Of his so sudden death the cause shall I discusse? Hermocrates the leech he saw in sleepe unsound. Upon which I will tell you two pretty stories. The Baron of Caupene in Chalosse and I have both in common the right of the patronage of a benefice, which is of a very large precinct, situated at the feet of our mountaines named Lahontan. It is with the inhabitants of that corner as it is said to be with those of the valley of Angrougne. They lead a kind of peculiar life; their attire and their customs apart and severall. They were directed and governed by certain particular policies and customs, received by tradition from father to child: whereto, without other laws or compulsion except the reverence and awe of their custom and use, they awefully tied and bound themselves. This petty state had from all antiquity continued in so happy a condition that no neighbouring severe judge had ever been troubled to enquire of their life and affairs, nor was ever atturny or petty-fogging lawyer called for to give them advice or counsel; nor stranger sought unto to determine their quarrels or decide contentions; neither were ever beggars seen among them. They alwaies avoyded commerce and shunned alliances with the other world, lest they should alter the purity of their orders and policy, until such time (as they say) that one amongst them in their fathers days, having a mind puft up with a noble ambition to bring his name and credit in reputation, devised to make one of his children Sir John Lacke-latine or Master Peter-an-oake: and having made him learne to write in some neigbbour town not far off, at last procured him to be a country Notary or petty-fogging clark. This fellow having gotten some pelfe and become great, began to disdaine their ancient customs and put the pompe and statelines of our higher regions into their heads. It fortuned that a chief gossip of his had a goate dis-horned, whom he so importunately solicited to sue the trespasser and demand law and right at the justices hands that dwelt thereabouts; and so never ceasing to sow sedition and breed suites amongst his neighbors, he never left till he had confounded and marred all. After this corruption or intrusion of law (they say) there ensued presently another mischief of worse consequence by means of a quacke-salver or empirike physician that dwelt amongst them who would needs be married to one of their daughters, and so endenizon and settle himself amongst them. This gallant began first to teach and instruct them in the names of agues, rheumes, and impostumes; then the situation of the heart, of the liver and other intrailes: a science until then never known or heard of among them. And in stead of garlike, wherewith they had learned to expell and were wont to cure all diseases of what quality and how dangerous soever they were, he induced and inured them, were it but for a cough or cold, to take strange compositions and potions: and thus beganne to trafficke not only their health but also their deaths. They sweare that even from that time they apparently perceived that the evening sereine or night-calme bred the head-ache and blasted them; that to drinke being hot or in a sweat empaired their healths; that autumne winds were more unwholesome and dangerous than those of the spring-time: and that since his slibber-sawces, potions, and physicke came first in use, they find themselves molested and distempered with legions of unaccustomed maladies and unknown diseases, and plainly feel and sensibly perceive a general weaknesse and declination in their ancient vigor, and that their lives are nothing so long as before they were. See here the first of my tales. The other is that before I was troubled with the stone-chollicke and gravell in the bladder, hearing diverse make especiall account of a he-goates blood as a heavenly manna sent in these latter ages for the good and preservation of mans life and hearing men of good understanding speak of it as of an admirable and much-good-working drug and of an infallible operation: I, who have ever thought my self subject to all accidents that may in any sort fall on man, being yet in perfect health, began to take pleasure to provide my self of this myracle, and forthwith gave order (according to the receipt) to have a buck-goate gotten and carefully fed in my own house. For the blood must be drawne from him in the hottest month of summer, and he must only be fed with soluble hearbes, and drincke nothing but white-wine. It was my fortune to come to my own house the very same day the Goate should be killed; where some of my people came in haste to tell me that my cooke found two or three great bowles in his pauncb, which in his maw amongst his meat shocked one against another. I was so curious as I would needs have all his garbage brought before me; the thicke and large skinne whereof I caused to be opened, out of which came three great lumps or bodies, as light as any spunge, so framed as they seemed to be hollow, yet outwardly hard and very firme, bemotled with diverse dead and wannish colours; the one perfectly as round as any bowle, the other two somewhat lesser, and not so round, yet seemed to grow towards it. I have found (after I had made diligent inquiry among such as were wont to open such beasts) that it was a seld-seen and unheard of accident. It is very likely they were such stones as ours be, and cozen-germanes to them; which if it be, it is but vain for such as be troubled with the stone or gravell to hope to be cured by means of a beasts blood, that was drawing near unto death, and suffered the same disease. For, to aleadge the blood cannot participate of that contagion, and does no whit thereby alter his accustomed virtue, it may rather be inferred that nothing engendreth in a body but by consent and communication of all the parts. The whole masse does work, and the whole frame agitate altogether, although one part, according to the diversitie of operations, does contribute more or less than another; whereby it manifestly appeareth that, in all parts of this bucke- goate, there was some grettie or petrificant quality. It was not so much for fear of any future chaunce, or in regard of my self, that I was so curious of this experiment; as in respect, that as well in my own house as elsewere in sundry other places, it commeth to pass that many women do often gather and lay up in store diverse such kindes of slight druggs to help their neighbors and other people with them in time of necessitie; applying one same remedie to an hundred severall diseases: indeed many times such as they would be very loath to take themselves; with which they often have good lucke, and well thrives it with them. As for me, I honor physicians, not according to the common-received rule, for necessitie sake (for to this passage another of the prophets may be alleged who reprooved King Asa, because he had recourse unto physicians) but rather for love I bear unto themselves; having seen some, and known diverse honest men amongst them, and worthy all love and esteeme. It is not them I blame, but their Arte; yet do I not greatly condemne them for seeking to profit by our foolishnesse (for most men do so) and it is a thing common to all worldlings. Diverse possessions and many vocations, both more and less worthie than theirs, subsist and are grounded only upon public abuses and popular errours. I send for them when I am sicke, if they may conveniently be found, and love to be entertained by them, rewarding them as other men do. I give them authority to enjoin me, to keep my self warme if I love it better so than otherwise. They may chuse, be it either leekes or lettuce, what my broth shall be made withall, and appoint me either white or claret to drink: and so of other things else, indifferent to my taste, humor or custom. I know well it is nothing to them, forasmuch as sharpnesse and strangenesse are accidents of physickes proper essence. Lycurgus allowed and appoynted the sicke men of Sparta to drinke wine. Why did he so? Because being in health they hated the use of it. Even as a gentleman who dwelleth not far from me useth wine as a sovereigns remedie against agews, because being in perfect health, he hateth the taste thereof as death. How many of them see we to be of my humor? That is, to disdaine all physicke for their own behoofe, and live a kind of formall free life, and altogether contrary to that which they prescribe to other? And what is that but a manifest abusing of our simplicitie. For, they hold their life as dear and esteeme their health as pretious as we do ours, and would apply their effects to their skill if themselves knew not the uncertainty and falsehood of it. It is the fear of pain and death; the impatience of the disease and grief: and indiscreet desire and headlong thirst of health, that so blindeth them and us. It is meere faintness that makes our conceit: and pusillanimitie forceth our credulitie to be so yielding, and pliable.. The greater part of whom do notwithstanding not believe so much as they endure and suffer of others; For I hear them complain, and speak of it no otherwise than we do. Yet in the end are they resolved. What should I do then? As if impatience were in itself a better remedie than patience. Is there any of them that has yielded to this miserable subjection, that does not likewise yielde to all manner of impostures? or dooth not subject himself to the mercy of whomsoever has the impudencie to promise him recoverie and warrant him health? The Babilonians were wont to carry their sicke people into the open streetes: the common sort were there physicians: where all such as passed by were by humanitie and civilitie to enquire of their state and maladie, and according to their skill or experience give them some sound advise and good counsell. We differ not greatly from them: there is no poore woman so simple whose mumbling and muttering, whose slibber-slabbes and drenches we do not employ. And as for me, were I to buy any medicine, I would rather spend my money in this kind of physicke than in any other, because therein is no danger or hurt to be feared. What Homer and Plato said of the Egyptians, that they were all physicians, may well be said of all people. There is neither man nor woman that vanteth not himself to have some receipt or other, and does not hazard the same upon his neighbour, if he will but give credite unto him. I was not long since in a company where I wot not who of my fraternity brought news of a kind of pilles, by true accompt, composed of a hundred and odde severall ingredients; whereat we laughed very heartily, and made ourselves good sport; for what rocke so hard were able to resist the shocke or withstand the force of so thicke and numerous a battery? I understand, nevertheless , of such as took of them, that the least graine of gravell dained not to stir at all. I cannot so soone give over writing of this subject, but I must needs say a word or two concerning the experience they have made of their prescriptions, which they would have us take as a warantice or assurance of the certainty of their drugges and potions. The greatest number, and, as I deem, more than the two thirds of medicinable vertues, consist in the quintessence or secret propriety of simples, whereof we can have no other instruction but use and custom. For quintessence is no other thing than a quality, whereof we cannot with our reason find out the cause. In such trials or experiments, those which they affirme to have acquired by the inspiration of some dæmon, I am contented to receive and allow of them (for touching myracles, I meddle not with them) or be it the experiments drawne from things, which for other respects fall often in use with us: as if in wooll, wherewith we wont to cloth ourselves, some secret exsiccating or drying quality have by accident been found, that cureth kibes and chilblaines in the heels and if in reddishes, we eat for nourishment, some opening or atentive operation have been discovered. Galen reporteth that a leprous man chanced to be cured by means of a cuppe of wine he had drunken forasmuch as a viper was by fortune fallen into the wine caske. In which example we find the meane and a very likely director to this experience. As also in those to which physicians affirme to have been addressed by the examples of some beasts. But in most of other experiences to which they say they came by fortune, and had no other guide but hazard, I find the progresse of this information incredible. I imagine man heedfully viewing about him the infinite number of things, creatures, plants and mettals. I wot not where to make him beginne his essay; and suppose he cast his first fantasie upon an elkes- horne, to which an easy and gentle credulity must be given; he will be as far to seek, and as much troubled in his second operation: so, many diseases and severall circumstances are proposed unto him, that before he come to the certainty of this point, unto which the perfection of his experience should arrive, mans wit shall be to seek, and not know where to turn himself; and before (amiddest this infinity of things) he find out what this horne is: amongst the numberlesse diseases that are, what an epilepsie is; the sundry and manifolde complexions in a melancholy man; so many seasons in winter: so diverse nations amongst Frenchmen; so many ages in age; so diverse celestiall changes and alterations in the conjunction of Venus and Saturne: so severall and many partes in a mans body, nay in one of his fingers. To all which being neither guided by Argument, nor by conjecture, nor by example or divine inspiration, but by the only motion of fortune, it were most necessary it should be by a perfectly artificiall, well-ordred, and methodicall fortune. Moreover, suppose the disease thorowly cured, how shall he rest assured but that either the evil was come to his utmost period, or that an effect of the hazard caused the same health? Or the operation of some other thing, which that day he had either eaten, drunke or touched? or whether it were by the merite of his grandmothers prayers? Besides, suppose this experiment to have been perfect, how many times was it applied and begun anew; and how often was this long and tedious web of fortunes and encounters woven over again, before a certain rule might be concluded? And being concluded, by whom is it I pray you I? Amongst so many millions of men you shall scarce meet with three or foure that will duely observe and carefully keep a register of their experiments: shall it be your or his happe to light truely or hit just with one of them three or foure? What if another man, nay, What if a hundred other men, have had and made contrary experiments, and yet have sorted well? We should perhaps discerne some show of light if all the judgements and consultations of men were known unto us. But that three witnesses and three doctors shall sway all mankind, there is no reason. It were requisite humane nature had appointed and made speciall choise of them, and that by express procuration and letter of atturny they were by her declared our judges and deputed our atturnies. TO MY LADY OF DURAS MADAME, the last time it pleased you to come and visite me, you found me upon this point. And because it may be these toyes of mine may happily come to your hands, I would have them witness their author reputeth himself highly honoured for the favors it shall please you to show them. Wherein you shall discerne the very same demeanor and self-countenance you have seen in his conversation. And could I have assumed unto my self any other fashion than my own e accustomed, or more honorable and better form, I would not have done it: for al I seek to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will naturally represent and to the life portray me to your remembrance. The very same condition and faculties it pleased your Ladyship to frequent and receive with much more honor and curteke to reape by my writings is, they will has the loving care, and careful love of your right Honorable and most prudent Parents (thrice-honored Lady Grey) as well in language for more knowledge, more knowledge for all virtue, as in high linage for rich dowrie, rich dowrie for great match provided for you. An acte most worthie their Progenitors, the olde Worthies of S HREVVSBVRIE , to make you so well worthie by your match to inherite a house no less ancient; the ancient house of K ENT . Whereof to wish you answerable joy, to the honor of both Houses, demerite of yourselves, comfort of all your friendes, let me but adde my wish: God give my wish effect, and yourselves shall wish no better. And so to you (my in-hart-honoured, since best-deserving Lady N EVILL ) I knowe not, if native inclination, proceeding from a Father, in wisdom none greater; a Mother, in goodnesse none better; or informing instruction, applied by his prudent direction, used by her kind discretion, received by your quick ingenuitie, or confirming example of both them above all example, and your noble husband excellently qualified, exquisitely languaged, and your as learned as well graced brothers; or all these in concourse have made-uppe such accomplishment, as again I knowe not, if you, or we all, owe more to them for you. This I knowe and acknowledge, as to your right Honorable Father, this ages Cato, our Englands Hospitalis, I owe and vow all service for many-many favors he has done me, more he may, and to those other for some other: So to your Ladieship for all, who not only with them, but many more, have not only wrought me credite to give countenance, but brought me kindenesse to afforde commoditie. As therefore of aught else I ever may, so of this I have here done, your Ladieship may challenge no small parte, since no small parte thereof was done under your Fathers roofe, under your regiment. Wherefore to both your Honors (renowmed G REY and N EVILL ) as to Iuno in Greece, or Vesta in new Rome on the Altare of your vertues, I consecrate without idolatrie, prophanenesse, or blasphemie, both the incense of Praise and Thankes, and the never-failing fire of and ever-faithfull affection, which the Vestall Virgins of pure thoughts shall still-still keep alive, that while I live, and when I die, I may be as I am Your Honors servant in true hart, I OHN F LORIO . To the Right Ho- norable Lady Elizabeth Grey. Of Honorable T ALBOT honor’d-far, The forecast and the fortune, by his W ORD Montaigne here descrives; what by his S WORD, What by his wit; this, as the guiding starre; That, as th’Ætolian blast, in peace, or war, At sea, or land, as cause did use afforde, A VANT L E V ENT , to tackle his sailes a borde, So as his course no orethwart crosse might barre; But he would sweetly saile before the wind; For Princes service, Countries good, his fame. Heire-Daughter of that prudent-constant kind, Joyning thereto of G REY as great a name, Of both chief glories shrining in your mind, Honor him, that your Honor does proclaime. Il Candido. To the Right Noble and vertuous Lady Marie Nevill. If ornaments to men, to Ladies more, If to meane persons, more to noble mind, Study and languages have been assignde; How should we then admire, applaude, adore You Madame, so adorn’d, as few before? As if your Fathers, Husbands, Brothers kind You were to equall or excel inclinde: Such knowledge keeping keyes of vertues store. Though this you know no better in your own, Then it you knew in French, or had it been, In Tuscane wrote, as well you had it known; Though lesser grace in this, than that, be seen; Yet, as your own, since you love public-weale, Take well, we unknown goods to all reveale. Il Candido. Renascence Editions Return to : Book III. CHAPTER I: OF PROFIT AND HONESTY CHAPTER I: OF PROFIT AND HONESTY O MAN living is free from speaking foolish things; the ill lucke is to speak them curiously: Næ iste magno conatu magnas nugas dixerit. -- Ter. Heaut. act. iv. sc. i. This fellow sure with much a do, Will tell great tales and trifles too. That concerneth not me; mine slip from me with as little care as they are of smal worth: whereby they speed the better. I would suddenly quit them, for the least cost were in them: Nor do I buy or sell them but for what they weigh. I speak unto paper as to the first man I meete. That this is true, marke well what followes. To whom should not treachery be detestable, when Tiberius refused it on such great interest? One sent him word out of Germany, that if he thought it good, Ariminius should be made away by poison. He was the mightiest enemy the Romans had, who had so vilely used them under Varus, and who only empeached the encrease of his domination in that country. His answer was, that the people of Rome were accustomed to be revenged on their enemies by open courses, with weapons in hand; not by subtill sleights , nor in hugger mugger: thus left he the profitable for the honest. He was (you will say) a cosener. I beleive it; that’s no wonder in men of his profession. But the confession of virtue is of no less consequence in his mouth that hateth the same, forasmuch as truth by force does wrest it from him, and if he will not admire it in him, at least, to adorn himself he will put it on. Our composition, both public and private, is full of imperfection; yet is there nothing in nature unserviceable, no not inutility itself; nothing thereof has been insinuated in this huge universe but holdeth some fit place therein. Our essence is cymented with crased qualities; ambition, jealosie, envy, revenge, superstition, despair, lodge in us, with so natural a possession, as their image is also discerned in beasts: indeed cruelty, so unnaturall a vice: for in the middest of compassion, we inwardly feel a kind of bitter-sweet-pricking of malicious delight to see others suffer; and children feel it also: Suave mari magno turbantibus æquora ventis, E terra magnum alterius spectare laborem. -- Lucr. ii. 1. ’Tis sweet on graund seas, when winds waves turmoyle, From land to see an others greevous toyle. The seed of which qualities, who should roote out of man, should ruine the fundamental conditions of our life: In matter of policy likewise some necessary functions are not only base, but faulty: vices find therein a seate and employ themselves in the stitching up of our frame; as poysons in the preservations of our health. If they become excusable because we have neede of them, and that common necessity effaceth their true property; let us resigne the acting of this part to hardy Citizens, who sticke not to sacrifice their. honors and consciences, as those of old, their lives, for their Countries avail and safety. We that are more weake had best assume taskes of more ease and less hazard. The Common-wealth requireth some to betray, some to lie, and some to massaker: leave we that commission to people more obedient and more pliable. Truly, I have often been vexed to see our judges, by fraude or false hopes of favor or pardon, draw on a malefactor, to bewray his offence; employing therein both cousenage and impudencie. It were fit for justice, and Plato himself, who favoureth this custom, to furnish me with means more suitable to my humor. ’Tis a malicious justice, and in my conceit no less wounded by itself then by others. I answered not long since, that hardly could I betray my Prince for a particular man, who should be very sory to betray a particular man for my Prince. And loath not only to deceive, but that any be deceived in me; whereto I will neither furnish matter nor occasion. In that little busines I have managed betweene our Princes, amid the divisions and subdivisions which at this day so teare and turmoile us, I have curiously heeded, that they mistake me not, nor muffled themselves in my maske. The professors of that trade hold themselves most covert; pretending and counterfeiting the greatest indifference and neernes to the cause they can. As for me, I offer my self in my liveliest reasons, in a form most my own: A tender and young Negotiator, and who had rather faile in my businesses then in my self. Yet has this been hitherto with so good hap (for surely fortune is in these matters a principal actor) that few have dealt betwene party and party with less suspition and more inward favor. I have in all my proceedings an open fashion, easy to insinuate and give itself credit at first acquaintance. Sincerity, plainenesse, and naked truth, in what age soever, find also their opportunity and employment. Besides, their liberty is little called in question, or subject to hate, who deale without respect of their own interest. And they may truely use the answer of Hyperides unto the Athenians, complaining of his bitter invectives and sharpenesse of his speech: Consider not, my masters whether I am free, but whether I be so, without taking ought, or bettering my state by it. My liberty also has easily discharged me from all suspition of faintnesse, by its vigor (for forbearing to speak any thing, though it bit or stung them; I could not have said worse in their absence) and because it carrieth an apparant show of simplicity and carelesnesse. I pretend no other fruit by negotiating then to negotiate; and annex no long pursuites or propositions to it. Every action makes his particular game, win he if he can. Nor am I urged with the passion of love or hate unto great men; nor is my wil shackled with anger, or particular respect. I regard our Kings with an affection simply lawfull and meerely civil, neither mooved nor unmoov’d by private interest: for which I like my self the better. The general and just cause bindes me no more then moderately, and without violent fits. I am not subject to these piercing pledges and inward gages. Choller and hate are beyond the duty of justice, and are passions fitting only those whose reason is not sufficient to hold them to their duty, Utatur motu animi, qui uti ratione non potest: ’Let him use the motion of his mind that cannot use reason.’ All lawfull intentions are of themselves temperate: if not, they are altered into sedicious and unlawful. It is that makes me march every where with my head aloft, my face and heart open. Verily (and I fear not to avouch it) I could easily for a neede bring a candle to Saint Michæll, and another to his Dragon, as the good old woman. I will follow the best side to the fire, but not into it, if I can choose. If neede require, let Montaigne my Mannor-house be swallowed up in public ruine: but if there be no such necessity, I will acknowledge my self beholding unto fortune if she please to save it; and for its safety employ as much scope as my endevours can affoord me. Was it not Atticus, who, cleaving to the right (but losing side), saved himself by his moderation, in that general Shipwracke of the world, amidst so many changes and diverse alterations? To private men, such as he was, it is more easy. And in such kind of business I think one dealeth justly not to be too forward to insinuate or invite himself. To hold a staggering or middle course, to bear an unmooved affection, and with out inclination in the troubles of his country and public divisions, I deem neither seemely nor honest: Ea non media, sed nulla via est, velut eventum expectantium, quo fortunæ consilia sua applicant: ’That is not the mid-way, but a mad has the loving care, and careful love of your right Honorable and most prudent Parents (thrice-honored Lady Grey) as well in language for more knowledge, more knowledge for all virtue, as in high linage for rich dowrie, rich dowrie for great match provided for you. An acte most worthie their Progenitors, the olde Worthies of S HREVVSBVRIE , to make you so well worthie by your match to inherite a house no less ancient; the ancient house of K ENT . Whereof to wish you answerable joy, to the honor of both Houses, demerite of yourselves, comfort of all your friendes, let me but adde my wish: God give my wish effect, and yourselves shall wish no better. And so to you (my in-hart-honoured, since best-deserving Lady N EVILL ) I knowe not, if native inclination, proceeding from a Father, in wisdom none greater; a Mother, in goodnesse none better; or informing instruction, applied by his prudent direction, used by her kind discretion, received by your quick ingenuitie, or confirming example of both them above all example, and your noble husband excellently qualified, exquisitely languaged, and your as learned as well graced brothers; or all these in concourse have made-uppe such accomplishment, as again I knowe not, if you, or we all, owe more to them for you. This I knowe and acknowledge, as to your right Honorable Father, this ages Cato, our Englands Hospitalis, I owe and vow all service for many-many favors he has done me, more he may, and to those other for some other: So to your Ladieship for all, who not only with them, but many more, have not only wrought me credite to give countenance, but brought me kindenesse to afforde commoditie. As therefore of aught else I ever may, so of this I have here done, your Ladieship may challenge no small parte, since no small parte thereof was done under your Fathers roofe, under your regiment. Wherefore to both your Honors (renowmed G REY and N EVILL ) as to Iuno in Greece, or Vesta in new Rome on the Altare of your vertues, I consecrate without idolatrie, prophanenesse, or blasphemie, both the incense of Praise and Thankes, and the never-failing fire of and ever-faithfull affection, which the Vestall Virgins of pure thoughts shall still-still keep alive, that while I live, and when I die, I may be as I am Your Honors servant in true hart, I OHN F LORIO . To the Right Ho- norable Lady Elizabeth Grey. Of Honorable T ALBOT honor’d-far, The forecast and the fortune, by his W ORD Montaigne here descrives; what by his S WORD, What by his wit; this, as the guiding starre; That, as th’Ætolian blast, in peace, or war, At sea, or land, as cause did use afforde, A VANT L E V ENT , to tackle his sailes a borde, So as his course no orethwart crosse might barre; But he would sweetly saile before the wind; For Princes service, Countries good, his fame. Heire-Daughter of that prudent-constant kind, Joyning thereto of G REY as great a name, Of both chief glories shrining in your mind, Honor him, that your Honor does proclaime. Il Candido. To the Right Noble and vertuous Lady Marie Nevill. If ornaments to men, to Ladies more, If to meane persons, more to noble mind, Study and languages have been assignde; How should we then admire, applaude, adore You Madame, so adorn’d, as few before? As if your Fathers, Husbands, Brothers kind You were to equall or excel inclinde: Such knowledge keeping keyes of vertues store. Though this you know no better in your own, Then it you knew in French, or had it been, In Tuscane wrote, as well you had it known; Though lesser grace in this, than that, be seen; Yet, as your own, since you love public-weale, Take well, we unknown goods to all reveale. Il Candido. Renascence Editions Return to : Book III. CHAPTER I: OF PROFIT AND HONESTY CHAPTER I: OF PROFIT AND HONESTY O MAN living is free from speaking foolish things; the ill lucke is to speak them curiously: Næ iste magno conatu magnas nugas dixerit. -- Ter. Heaut. act. iv. sc. i. This fellow sure with much a do, Will tell great tales and trifles too. That concerneth not me; mine slip from me with as little care as they are of smal worth: whereby they speed the better. I would suddenly quit them, for the least cost were in them: Nor do I buy or sell them but for what they weigh. I speak unto paper as to the first man I meete. That this is true, marke well what followes. To whom should not treachery be detestable, when Tiberius refused it on such great interest? One sent him word out of Germany, that if he thought it good, Ariminius should be made away by poison. He was the mightiest enemy the Romans had, who had so vilely used them under Varus, and who only empeached the encrease of his domination in that country. His answer was, that the people of Rome were accustomed to be revenged on their enemies by open courses, with weapons in hand; not by subtill sleights , nor in hugger mugger: thus left he the profitable for the honest. He was (you will say) a cosener. I beleive it; that’s no wonder in men of his profession. But the confession of virtue is of no less consequence in his mouth that hateth the same, forasmuch as truth by force does wrest it from him, and if he will not admire it in him, at least, to adorn himself he will put it on. Our composition, both public and private, is full of imperfection; yet is there nothing in nature unserviceable, no not inutility itself; nothing thereof has been insinuated in this huge universe but holdeth some fit place therein. Our essence is cymented with crased qualities; ambition, jealosie, envy, revenge, superstition, despair, lodge in us, with so natural a possession, as their image is also discerned in beasts: indeed cruelty, so unnaturall a vice: for in the middest of compassion, we inwardly feel a kind of bitter-sweet-pricking of malicious delight to see others suffer; and children feel it also: Suave mari magno turbantibus æquora ventis, E terra magnum alterius spectare laborem. -- Lucr. ii. 1. ’Tis sweet on graund seas, when winds waves turmoyle, From land to see an others greevous toyle. The seed of which qualities, who should roote out of man, should ruine the fundamental conditions of our life: In matter of policy likewise some necessary functions are not only base, but faulty: vices find therein a seate and employ themselves in the stitching up of our frame; as poysons in the preservations of our health. If they become excusable because we have neede of them, and that common necessity effaceth their true property; let us resigne the acting of this part to hardy Citizens, who sticke not to sacrifice their. honors and consciences, as those of old, their lives, for their Countries avail and safety. We that are more weake had best assume taskes of more ease and less hazard. The Common-wealth requireth some to betray, some to lie, and some to massaker: leave we that commission to people more obedient and more pliable. Truly, I have often been vexed to see our judges, by fraude or false hopes of favor or pardon, draw on a malefactor, to bewray his offence; employing therein both cousenage and impudencie. It were fit for justice, and Plato himself, who favoureth this custom, to furnish me with means more suitable to my humor. ’Tis a malicious justice, and in my conceit no less wounded by itself then by others. I answered not long since, that hardly could I betray my Prince for a particular man, who should be very sory to betray a particular man for my Prince. And loath not only to deceive, but that any be deceived in me; whereto I will neither furnish matter nor occasion. In that little busines I have managed betweene our Princes, amid the divisions and subdivisions which at this day so teare and turmoile us, I have curiously heeded, that they mistake me not, nor muffled themselves in my maske. The professors of that trade hold themselves most covert; pretending and counterfeiting the greatest indifference and neernes to the cause they can. As for me, I offer my self in my liveliest reasons, in a form most my own: A tender and young Negotiator, and who had rather faile in my businesses then in my self. Yet has this been hitherto with so good hap (for surely fortune is in these matters a principal actor) that few have dealt betwene party and party with less suspition and more inward favor. I have in all my proceedings an open fashion, easy to insinuate and give itself credit at first acquaintance. Sincerity, plainenesse, and naked truth, in what age soever, find also their opportunity and employment. Besides, their liberty is little called in question, or subject to hate, who deale without respect of their own interest. And they may truely use the answer of Hyperides unto the Athenians, complaining of his bitter invectives and sharpenesse of his speech: Consider not, my masters whether I am free, but whether I be so, without taking ought, or bettering my state by it. My liberty also has easily discharged me from all suspition of faintnesse, by its vigor (for forbearing to speak any thing, though it bit or stung them; I could not have said worse in their absence) and because it carrieth an apparant show of simplicity and carelesnesse. I pretend no other fruit by negotiating then to negotiate; and annex no long pursuites or propositions to it. Every action makes his particular game, win he if he can. Nor am I urged with the passion of love or hate unto great men; nor is my wil shackled with anger, or particular respect. I regard our Kings with an affection simply lawfull and meerely civil, neither mooved nor unmoov’d by private interest: for which I like my self the better. The general and just cause bindes me no more then moderately, and without violent fits. I am not subject to these piercing pledges and inward gages. Choller and hate are beyond the duty of justice, and are passions fitting only those whose reason is not sufficient to hold them to their duty, Utatur motu animi, qui uti ratione non potest: ’Let him use the motion of his mind that cannot use reason.’ All lawfull intentions are of themselves temperate: if not, they are altered into sedicious and unlawful. It is that makes me march every where with my head aloft, my face and heart open. Verily (and I fear not to avouch it) I could easily for a neede bring a candle to Saint Michæll, and another to his Dragon, as the good old woman. I will follow the best side to the fire, but not into it, if I can choose. If neede require, let Montaigne my Mannor-house be swallowed up in public ruine: but if there be no such necessity, I will acknowledge my self beholding unto fortune if she please to save it; and for its safety employ as much scope as my endevours can affoord me. Was it not Atticus, who, cleaving to the right (but losing side), saved himself by his moderation, in that general Shipwracke of the world, amidst so many changes and diverse alterations? To private men, such as he was, it is more easy. And in such kind of business I think one dealeth justly not to be too forward to insinuate or invite himself. To hold a staggering or middle course, to bear an unmooved affection, and with out inclination in the troubles of his country and public divisions, I deem neither seemely nor honest: Ea non media, sed nulla via est, velut eventum expectantium, quo fortunæ consilia sua applicant: ’That is not the mid-way, but a mad way, or no way, as of those that expect the event with intent to apply their dessignes as fortune shall fall out.’ That may be permitted in the affairs of neighbors. So did Gelon, the tyrant of Siracusa, suspend his inclination in the Barbarian wars against the Greeks, keeping Ambasdours at Delphos, with presents, to watch on what side the victory would light, and to apprehend the fittest occasion of reconcilement with the victors. It were a kind of treason to do so in our own affairs and domesticall matters, wherein of necessity one must resolve and take a side; but for a man that has neither charge nor express commandement to urge him, not to busie or entermedle himself therein, I holde it more excusable: (Yet frame I do not this excuse for my self), then in forraine and strangers wars, wherewith, according to our laws, no man is troubled against his will. Nevertheless, those who wholly ingage themselves into them, may carry such an order and temper, as the storme (without offending them) may glide over their head. Had we not reason to hope as much of the deceased Bishop of Orleans, Lord of Morvilliers? And I know some who at this present worthily bestirre themselves, in so even a fashion or pleasing a manner, that they are likely to continue on foote, whatsoever iniurious alteration or fall the heavens may prepare against us. I holde it only fit for Kings to to be angry with Kings: And mocke at those rash spirits, who from the braverie of their hearts offer themselves to so unproportionate quarrels. For one undertaketh against a Prince, in marching courageously for his honor, and according to his duty: If he love not such a man, he does better: at least he esteemeth him. And the cause of laws especially, and defense of the auncient state, has ever found this priviledge, that such as for their own interest disturbe the same, excuse (if they honor not) their defenders. But we ought not terme duty (as now a dayes we do) a sower rigour and intestine carbbednesse, proceeding of private interest and passion: nor courage a treacherous and malicious proceeding. Their disposition to frowardnesse and mischiefs, they entitle Zeale: That’s not the cause does heate them, ’tis their own interest: They kindle a war, not because it is just, but because it is war. Why may not a man bear himself betweene enemies featly and faithfully? Doe it, if not altogether with an equall (for it may admit different measure at least with a sober affection, which may not so much engage you to the one, that he looke for al at your bands. Content your self with a moderate proportion of their favor, and to glide in troubled waters without fishing in them. Th’ other manner of offering ones uttermost endevours to both sides, implyeth less discretion then conscience. What knows he to whom you betray another, as much your friend as himself, but you will do the like for him, when his turn shall come. He takes you for a villaine: whilst that he heares you, and gathers out of you, and makes his best use of your disloyalty. For double fellowes are only beneficiall in what they bring, but we must looke they carry away as little as may be. I carry nothing to the one which I may not (having opportunity) say unto the other, the accent only changed a little: and report either but indifferent or known or common things. No benefit can induce me to lie unto them: what is entrusted to my silence I conceal religiously, but take as little in trust as I can. Princes secrets are a troublesome charge to such as have nought to do with them. I ever by my good will capitulate with them, that they trust me with very little: but let them assuredly trust what I disclose unto them. I alwayes knew more than I wold. An open speach opens the way to another, and draws all out, even as Wine and Love. Philippedes, in my mind, answered King Lysimachus wisely when he demaunded of him, what of his wealth or state he should empart unto him: Which and what you please (quoth he) so it be not your secrets. I see every one mutiny, if another conceal the deapth or mysterie of the affairs from him, wherein he pleaseth to employ him, or have but purloyned any circumstance from him. For my part, I am content one tell me no more of his business then he will have me know or deale in; nor desire I that my knowledge exceed or strain my word. If I must needs be the instrument of cozinage it shall at least be with safety of my conscience. I will not be esteemed a servant, nor so affectionate, nor yet so faithfull, that I be judged fit to betray any man. Who is unfaithfull to himself may be excused if he be faithlesse to his Master. But Princes entertaine not men by halfes, and despise bounded and conditionall service. What remedy? I freely tell them my limits; for a slave I must not be but unto reason, which yet I cannot compasse; And they are to blame, to exact from a free man the like subjection unto their service, and the same obligation, which they may from those they have made and bought, and whose fortune dependeth particularly and expresly on theirs. The laws have delivered me from much trouble; they have chosen me a side to followe, and appointed me a maister to obey; all other superiority and duty ought to be relative unto that, and be restrained. Yet, may it not be concluded, that if my affection should otherwise transport me, I would presently afforde my helping hand unto it. Will and desires are a lawe to themselves, actions are to receive it of public institutions: All these procedings of mine are somewhat dissonant from our formes. They should produce no great effects, nor holde out long among us. Innocencie itself could not in these times nor negotiate without dissimulation, nor trafficke without lying. Neither are public functions of my diet; what my profession requires thereto, I furnish in the most private manner I can. Being a child, I was plunged into them up to the ears, and had good success; but I got loose in good time. I have often since shunned medling with them, seldom accepted, and never required; ever holding my back toward ambition; but if not as rowers, who go forward as it were backeward: Yet so, as I am less beholding to resolution, then to my good fortune, that I was not wholly embarked in them. For there are courses less against my taste, and more comfortable to my carriage, by which, if heretofore it had called me to the service of the common-wealth, and my advancement unto credit in the world: I know that in following the same I had exceeded the reason of my conceite. Those which comm only say against my profession that what I terme liberty, simplicity and plainenesse in my behaviour, is arte, cunning and subtilty; and rather discretion then goodnesse, industry then nature, good wit then good hap, do me more honor then shame. But truely they make my cunning overcunning. And whosoever has traced me and nearely looked into my humors, Ile loose a good wager if he confesse not that there is no rule in their schoole, could, a midde such crooked pathes and diverse windings, square and report this natural motion, and maintaine an apparance of liberty and licence so equall and inflexible: and that all the attention and wit is not of power to bring them to it. The way to trueth is but one and simple, that of particular profit and benefit of affairs a man has in charge, double, uneven and accidentall. I have often seen these counterfet and artificiall liberties in practise, but most commonly without success. They favor of Aesopes Asse, who in emulation of the dogge, layde his two fore- feete very jocondly upon his masters shoulders but looke how many blandishments the prety dogge received, under one, so many bastinadoes were redoubled upon the poore Asses backe. Id maxime quemque decet: quod est cuiusque suum maxime: (Cic. Off. i.) ’That becomes every man especially which is his own especially.’ I will not deprive cousinage of her rank, that were to understand the world but ill: I know it has often done profitable service, it supporteth, indeed nourisheth the greatest part of mens vacations. There are some lawfull vices: as many actions, or good or excusable, unlawfull. Iustice in itself natural and universall is otherwise ordered, and more nobly distributed, then this other especiall and nationall justice, restrained and suted to the neede of our pollicie: Veri juris germanæque iustitiæ solidam et excess effigiem nullam tenemus: umbra et imaginibus utimur: (Cic. Off. iii.) ’We have no lively nor life-like portraiture of upright law and natural justice: we use but the shaddowes and colours of them.’ So that wise Dandamys, hearing the lives of Socrates, Pythagoras and Diogenes repeated, in other things judged them great and worth men, but overmuch subjected to the reverence of the laws: which to authorize and second, true virtue is to decline very much from his natural vigor: and not only by their permission, but persuasions, diverse vicious actions are committed and take place. Ex Senatus consultis plebisque scitis scelera exercentur: ’Even by decrees of counsell and by statute-laws are mischiefes put in practise.’ I follow the common phrase, which makes a difference betweene profitable and honest things: terming some natural] actions which are not only profitable but necessary, dishonest and filthy. But to continue our examples of treason. Two which aspired unto the kingdome of Thrace were falne into controversie for their right. The Emperor hindred them from falling together by the ears: the one, under colour of contriving some friendly accord by an enterview inviting the other to a feast in his house, imprisoned and murthred him. Justice required that the Romanes should be satisfied for this outrage: some difficulties empeached the ordinary course. What they could not lawfully do without war and hazard, they attempted to accomplish by treason; what they coulde not honestly atchieve, they profitably compassed. For exployting whereof, Pomponius Flaccus was thought most fitte; who trayning the fellow into his Nettes by feigned wordes and sugred assurances, in liew of the favor and honor he promised him, sent him bound hand and foote to Rome. One traytor over-reached another against common custom; For, they are all full of distrust, and ’tis very hard to surprise them in their own arte: witness the heavy and dismall experience we have lately felt of it. Let who liste be Pomponius Flaccus; and there are too-too many that will be so. As for my part, both my word and faith are as the rest, pieces of this common body; their best effect is the publicke service: that’s ever presupposed with me. But as if one should command me to take the charge of the Rolles or Recordes of the Pallace, I would answere, I have no skill in them; or to be a leader of Pioners, I would say, I am called to a worthier office. Even so, who would go about to employ me, not to murther or poyson, but to lie, betraye and forsweare my self, I would tell him, If I have robbed or stolne any thing from any man, send me rather to the Gallies. For a Gentleman may lawfully speak, as did the Lacedemonians, defeated by Antipater, upon the points of their agreement: ’You may impose as heavy burdens, and harmfull taxes upon us as you please, but you lose your time to command us any shamefull or dishonest things.’ Every man should give himself the oath, which the Aegyptian Kings solemnly and usually presented to their judges: Not to swarve from their consciences, what command soever they should receive from themselves to the contrary. In such commissions there is an evident note of ignominie and condemnation. And whosoever gives them you, accuses you; and if you conceive them right, gives you them as a trouble and burden. As much as the public affairs amend by your endevours, your own empaireth; the better you d o, so much the worse do you. And it shall not be newe, nor perhaps without shadowe of justice, that he who setteth you a work, becomes your ruine. If treason be in any case excusable, it is only then, when ’tis employed to punish and betray treason. We shall find many treacheries to have been not refused, but punished by them, in whose favor they were undertaken. Who knowes not the sentence of Fabritius against Pyrrus his Physition? And the commaunder has often severely revenge d them on the partie be employed in them, refusing so unbridled a credite and power, and disavowing so lewde and so vile an obedience. Iaropelc, Duke of Russia, sollicited an Hungarian Gentleman to betraye Boleslaus, King of Polonia, in contriving his death or furnishing the Russians with means to work him some notable mischief. This gallant presently bestirres him in it, and more than ever applying himself to the Kings service, obtained to be of his counsell, and of those he most trusted. By which advantages, and with the opportunity of his masters absence, he betrayed Vicilicia, a great and rich citie, to the Russians: which was whollie sakt and burnt by them, with a general slaughter, both of the inhabitants, of what sexe or age soever, and a great number of nobility thereabouts, whom to that purpose be had assembled. Iaropelc, his anger thus asswaged with revenge, and his rage mitigated (which was not without pretext, for Boleslaus had mightily wronged and in like manner incensed him) and glutted with the fruite of treason, examining the uglinesse thereof, naked and alone, and with impartiall eyes beholding the same, not distempered by passion, conceived such a remorse, and took it so to heart that he forthwith caused the eyes of his instrumentall executioner to be pulled out, and his tongue and privy parts to be cut off. Antigonus persuaded the Argiraspides soldiers to betray Eumenes their general, and his adversaries unto him, whom when they had delivered, and he had caused to be slain, himself desired to be the Commissary of divine justice, for the punishment of so detestable a trecherie: and resigning them into the hands of the Governor of the Province, gave him express charge, in what manner soever it were, to rid himself of them, and bring them to some mischievious end. Whereby, of that great number they were, not one ever after sawe the smoake of Macedon. The better they served his turn, the more wicked he judged them, and the more worthie of punishment. The slave that betraied the corner wherein his master P. Sulpicius lay hid, was set at liberty, according to the promise of Syllas proscription: but according to the promise of common reason, being freed, he was throwne headlong from off the Tarpeyan rocke. And Clovis, King of France, in liew of the golden arms he had promised the three servants of Cannacre, caused them to be hanged, after they had by his sollicitation betraide their maister unto him. They hang them up with the purse of their reward about their neckes. Having satisfied their second and speciall faith, they also satisfie the general and first. Mahomet the second, desirous to rid himself of his brother (through jealousie of rule, and according to the stile of that race) employed one of his officers in it; who stifled him, by in much water powred down his throate all at once: which done, in expiation of the fact, he delivered the murtherer into the hands of his brothers mother (for they were brethren but by the father’s side) she, in his presence, opened his bosome, and with her own revenging handes searching for his heart, pluckt it out and cast it unto dogges to eate. Even unto vile dispositions (having made use of a filthy action) it is so sweet and pleasing, if they may with security, as it were, in way of recompence and holy correction, sowe one sure stitch of goodnesse and justice unto it. Besides, they respect the ministers of such horrible crimes as people that still upbraide them with them, and covet by their deaths to smother the knowledge and cancell the testimony of their practises. Now if, perhaps, not to frustrate the public neede of that last and desperate remedy, one rewarde you for it: yet he who does it (if he be not as bad himself), will hould you a most accursed and execrable creature. And deemeth you a greater traytor than he whom you have betrayed; for with your own han des he touched the lewdnesse of your disposition, without disavowing, without object. But employeth you, as we do out- cast persons in the executions of justice; an office as profitable as little honest. Besides the basenesse of such commissions, there is in them a prostitution of conscience. The daughter of Sejanus could not in Rome, by any true formall course of lawe, be put to death, because she was a virgine: that laws might have their due course, she was first deflowred by the common hang-man and then strangled. Not his hand only, but his soul is a slave unto public commodity. When Amurath the first to agravate the punishment of his subjects who had given support unto his son’s unnatural rebellion, appointed their neerest kinsmen to lend their hands unto this execution: I find it very honest in some of them, who rather chose unjustly to be held guiltie of anothers parricide then to serve justice with their own. And whereas in some paltrie townes forced in my time, I have seen base varlets for the savegard of their own lives, yeild to hang their friends and companions, I ever thought them of worse condition then such as were hanged. It is reported that Witoldus Prince of Lituania, introduced an order with that nation, which was that the party condemned to die should, with his own hands, make himself away; finding it strange that a third man, being guiltlesse of the fact, shoulde be employed and charged to commit a murther. When an urgent circumstance, or any violent and unexpected accident, induceth a Prince for the necessitie of his estate, or as they say for state matters, to breake his worde and faith, or otherwise forceth him out of his ordinary duty, he is to ascribe, that necessity unto a lash of Gods rod. It is no vice, for he has quit his reason unto a reason more public and more powerfull, but surely ’tis ill fortune. So that to one who asked me what remedy? I replyde, none; were he truely rackt betweene these two extreames (Sed videat ne quæretur latebra periurio: (Cic. Off. iii.) ’But let him take heede he seek not a starting hole for perjurie’) he must have done it; but if he did it sans regret or scruple, if it greeved him not to do it, ’tis an argument his conscience is but in ill tearmes. Now were there any one of so tender or cheverell a conscience, to whome no cure might seem worthy of so extreme a remedy, I should prise or regard him no whit the less. He cannot loose himself more handsomely nor more excusablie. We cannot do every thing, nor be in every place. When all is done, thus and thus must we often, as unto our last Anker and sole refuge, resigne the protection of our vessell unto the only conduct of heaven. To what juster necessity can hoe reserve himself? What is less possible for him to do, then what he cannot effect, without charge unto his faith, and imputation to his honor? things which perhaps should be dearer to him then his own salvation and the safety of his people. When with enfoulded arms he shall devoutly call on God for his ayde, may he not hope that his fatherlie mercy shall not refuse the extraordinary favor and sinne-forgiving grace of his all powerfull hand, unto a pure and righteous hand? They are dangerous examples, rare and crased exceptions to our natural rules: we must yielde unto them, but with great moderation and heedie circumspection. No private commodity may any way deserve we should offer conscience th is wrong; the common-wealth may, when it is most apparant and important. Timoleon did fitlie warrant and ward the strangenes of his exploite by the tears he shed, remembering it was with a brotherlie hand he slew the tyrant. And it neerely pinched his self gnawne conscience that he was compelled to purchas the common good at the rate of his honestie. The sacred Senate itself, by his means delivered from thraldome, durst not definitively decide of so haughtie an action and rend in two so urgent and different semblances. But the Siracusans having opportunely and at that very instant sent to the Corinthians to require their protection, and a governour able to reestablish their town in former majestie, and deliver Sicilie from a number of petty tyrants, which grievously oppressed the same, they appointed Timoleon, with this new caveat and declaration: That according as he should well or ill demeane himself in his charge, their sentence should incline either to grace him as the redeemer of his country or disgrace him as the murtherer of his brother. The fantastic conclusion has some excuse upon the danger of the example and importance of an act so different, and they did well to discharge their judgement of it, or to embarke him some where else, and on their considerations. Now the proceedings of Timoleon in his renowned journie did soone yielde his cause the cleerer, so worthily and vertuously did he every way bear himself therein. And the good hap which ever accompanied him in the encombrances and difficulties he was to subdue in the atchievement of his noble enterprise, seemed to be sent him by the Gods, conspiring to second, and consenting to favor his justification. This mans end is excusable, if ever any could be. But the encrease and profit of the public revenues, which served the Roman Senate for a pretext of the ensuing-foul conclusion I purpose to relate, is not of su fficient force to warrant such injustice. Certain cities had by the order and permission of the Senate, with mony purchased their liberty at the hands of L. Sylla. The matter coming in question again, the Senate condemned them to be fineable and taxed as before; and the mony they had employed for their ransome should be deemed as lost and forfeited. Civill wars do often produce such enormous examples, That we punish private men, for so much as they have beleeved us when we were other then now we are. And one same magistrate does lay the penalty of his change on such as cannot do withal. The scboole-master whippeth his scholler for his docility, and the guide striketh the blind man he leadeth. A horrible image of justice. Some rules in philosophy are both false and faint. The example proposed unto us of respecting private utility before faith given, has not sufficient power by the circumstance they adde unto it. Theeves have taken you, and on your oath to pay them a certain sum of money, have set you at liberty again. They erre that say an honest man is quit of his worde and faith without paying, beeing out of their hands. There is no such matter. What fear and danger has once forced me to will and consent unto, I am bound to will and performe, being out of danger and fear. And although it have but forced my tongue and not my will, yet am I boun to make my word good and keep my promise. For my part, when it has somet imes unadvisedly over-run my thought, yet have I made a conscience to disavowe the same. Otherwise we should by degrees come to abolish all the right a third man taketh and may challenge of our promises. Quasi vero forti viro vis possit adhiberi: (Cic. Off. iii.) As though any force could be used upon a valiant man.’ ’Tis only lawfull for our private interest to excuse the breache of promise, if we have rashlie promised things in themservles wicked and unjust. For, the right of virtue ought to overrule the right of our bond. I have heretofore placed Epaminondas in the first rank of excellent men, and now recant it not. Unto what high pitch raised he the consideration of his particular duty? who never slew man he had vanquished, who for that unvaluable good of restoring his country her liberty, made it a matter of conscience to murther a Tyrant or his complices, without a due and formall course of lawe: and who judged him a bad man, how good a citizen soever, that amongst his enemies and in the fury of a battle, spared not his friend or his hoste. See here a mind of a rich composition. He matched unto the most violent and rude actions of men, goodnesse and courtesy, indeed the most choise and delicate that may be found in the scboole of Philosophie. This so high-raised courage, so swelling and so obstinate against sorow, death and povertie, was it nature or arte made it relent, even to the utmost strai ne of exceeding tenderness and debonarety of complexion? Being cloathed in the dreadfull livery of steele and blood, he goeth on crushing and brusing a nation, invincible to all others but to himself: yet mildely relenteth in the midst of a combat or confusion, when he meets with his host or with his friend. Verily this man was deservedly fit to command in war, which in the extremest fury of his innated rage, made him to feel the sting of courtesys and remorse of gentlenesse then when, all inflamed, it foamed with fury and burned with murder. ’Tis a miracle to be able to join any show of justice with such actions. But it onIy belongeth to the unmatched courage of Epaminondas, in that confused plight, to join mildness and facility of the most gentle behaviour that ever was unto them, indeed, and pure innocency it self. And whereas one told the Mamertins, that statutes were of no force against armed men: another to the Tribune of the people, that the time of justice and war were two: a third, that the confused noise of war and clangor of arms bindred him from understanding the sober voice of the laws: This man was not so much as empeached from conceiving the mild sound of civilitie and kindness. Borroived he of his enemies the custom of sacrificing to the muses (when he went to the wars) to qualifie by their sweetness and mildness that martiall fury and hostile surlinesse? Let us not fear, after so great a master, to hold that some things are unlawfull, even against our fellest enemies: that public interest ought not to challenge all of all against private interest: Manente memoria etiam in dissidio publicorum foederum privati juris: ’Some memory of private right continuing even in disagreement of public contracts.’ -----et nulla potentia vires Præstandi, ne quid peccet amicus, habet: -- Ovid. Pont. i. El. viii. 37. No power has so great might, To make friends still go right. And that all things be not lawfull to an honest man, for the service of his King, the general cause and defense of the laws. Non enim patria præstat omnibus officiis, et ipsi conducit pios habere cives in parentes: (Cic. Off. iii.) ’For our countrey is not above all other duties: it is good for the country to have her inhabitans use pietie toward their parents.’ ’Tis an instruction befitting the times: we need not harden our hearts with these plates of iron and steele; it sufficeth our shoulders be armed with them: it is enough to d’ipe our pens in inke, too much to die them in blood. If it be greatness of courage, and th’ effect of a rare and singular virtue, to neglect friendship, despise private respects and bonds; ones word and kindred, for the common good and obedience of the Magistrate: it is verily able to excuse us from it, if we but alledge that it is a greatness unable to lodge in the greatness of Epaminondas his courage. I abhorre the enraged admonitions of this other unruly spirit. ----- dum tela micant, non vos pietatis imago Ulla, nec adversa conspecti fronte parentes Commoveant, vultus gladio turbante verendos. -- Lucan. vii. 320. Cæs. While swords are brandisht, let no show of grace Once moove you, nor your parents face to face, But with your swords disturb their reverend grace. Let us bereave wicked, bloody and traiterous dispositions of this pretext of reason: leave we that impious and exorbitant justice, and adhere unto more humane imitations. Oh, what may time and example bring to pass! In an encounter of the civill wars against Cinna, one of Pompeyes soldiers, having unwittingly slain his brother, who was on the other side, through shame and sorrow presently killed himself; And some yeeres after, in another civill war of the said people, a souldier boldly demanded a reward of his Captains for killing his own brother. Falsly do we argue honor, and the beautie of an action, by it’s profit: and conclude as ill, to think every one is bound unto it, and that it is honest if it be commodious. Omnia non pariter rerum sunt omnibus apta. -- Prop. iii. El. viii. 7. All things likewise to all Do not well-fitting fall. Choose we out the most necessary and most beneficiall matter of humane society, it will be a mariage; yet is it that the Saints counsell findeth and deemeth the contrary side more honest, excluding from it the most reverend vocation of men; as we to our races assigne such beasts as are of least esteeme. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER II: OF REPENTING CHAPTER II: OF REPENTING THERS fashion man, I repeat him; and represent a particular one, but ill made; and whom were I to form a new, he should be far other than he is; but he is now made. And though the lines of my picture change and vary, yet loose they not themselves. Th e world runnes all on wheeles. All things therein moove without intermission; indeed, the earth, the rockes of Caucasus, and the Pyramides of Egypt, both with the public and their own motion. Constancy itself is nothing but a languishing and wavering dance. I cannot settle my object; it goeth so unquietly and staggering, with a natural drunkennesse; I take it in this plight as it is at the instant I ammuse my self about it, I describe not the essence but the passage; not a passage from age to age, or as the people reckon, from seaven years to seaven, but from day to day, from minute to minute. My history must be fitted to the present. I may soone change, not only fortune, but intention. It is a counter-roule of diverse and variable accidents or irresolute imaginations, and sometimes contrary; whether it be that my self am other, or that I apprehend subjects by other circumstances and considerations. Howsoever, I may perhaps gain-say my self, but truth (as Demades said) I never gain-say. Were my mind setled, I would not essay, but resolve my self: It is still a Prentise and a probationer. I propose a meane life and without luster; ’Tis all one. They fasten all Morall Philosophy as well to a popular and private life as to one of richer stuffe. Every man beareth the whole stampe of humane condition. Authors communicate themselves unto the world by some speciall and strange marke; I the first, by my general disposition; as Michel de Montaigne, not as a Grammarian, or a Poet or a Lawyer. If the world complain I speak too much of my self. I complain it speaks no more of itself. But is it reason, that being so private in use, I should pretend to make my self public in knowledge? Or is it reason I should produce into the world, where fashion and arte have such sway and command, the raw and simple effects of nature, and of a nature as yet exceeding weak? To write bookes without learning is it not to make a wall without stone or such like thing? Conceits of music are directed by arte, mine by hap. Yet have I this according to learning, that never man handled subject he understood or knew better then I do this I have undertaken, being therein the cunningest man alive. Secondly, that never man waded further into his matter, nor more distinctly sifted the parts and dependances of it, nor arrived more exactly and fully to the end he proposed unto himself. To finish the same, I have neede of naught but faithfulnesse; which is therein as sincere and pure as may be found. I speak truth, not my belly-full, but as much as I dare; and I dare the more the more I grow into years, for it seems, custom alloweth old age more liberty to babbel, and indiscretion to talk of itself. It cannot herein be, as in trades, where the Crafts-man and his work do often differ. Being a man of so sound and honest conversation, wrote he so foolishly? Are such learned writings come from a man of so weake a conversation? who has but an ordinary conceit, and writeth excellently, one may say his capacitie is borrowed, not of himself. A skilfull man is not skilfull in all things; But a sufficient man is sufficient every where, even unto ignorance. Here my books and my self march together, and keep one pace. Else-where one may commend or condemne the work without the work-man, here not; who toucheth one toucheth the other. He who shall judge of it without knowing him shal wrong himself more then me, he that knows it has wholly satisfied me. Happie beyond my merite, if I get this only portion of public approbation, as I may cause men of understanding to think I had been able to make use and benefit of learning, had I been endowed with any, and deserved better helpe of memory; excuse we here what I often say that I seldom repent my self, and that my conscience is contented with itself; not of an Angels or a horses conscience, but as of a mans conscience. Adding ever this clause, not of ceremony, but of true and essentiall submission; that I speak enquiring and doubting, meerely and simply referring my self, from resolution, unto common and lawfull opinions. I teach not; I report: No vice is absolutely vice, which offendeth not, and a sound judgement accuses not: For, the deformitie and incommoditie thereof is so palpable, as perhaps they have reason who say it is chiefly produced by sottishnesse and brought forth by ignorance; so hard is it to imagine one should know it without hating it. Malice sucks up the greatest part of her own venome, and therewith impoysoneth herself. Vice leaveth, as an ulcer in the flesh, a repentance in the soul, which still scratcheth and bloodieth itself. For reason effaceth other griefes and sorrowes, but engendereth those of repentance: the more yrkesome because inward: as the colde and heate of agues is more offensive then that which comes outward. I account vices (but each according to their measure) not only those which reason disalowes and nature condemnes, but such as mans opinion has forged as false and erroneous, if laws and custom authorize the same. In like manner there is no goodnesse but gladdeth an honest disposition. There is truely I wot not what kind or congratulation of well doing which rejoyceth in ourselves, and a generous jollitie that accompanieth a good conscience. A mind courageously vicious may happily furnish itself with security, but she cannot be fraught with this self-[joying] delight and satisfaction. It is no smal pleasure for one to feel himself preserved from the contagion of an age so infected as ours, and to say to himself; could a man enter and see even into my soul, yet shold he not find me guilty either of the affliction or ruine of any body, nor culpable of envie or revenge, nor of public offence against the laws, nor tainted with innovation, trouble or sedition; nor spotted with falsifying of my word: and although the liberty of times slowed and taught it every man, yet could I never be induced to touch the goods or dive into the purse of any French man, and have alwayes lived upon my own as well in time of war as peace: nor did I ever make use of any poore mans labor without reward. These testimonies of an unspotted conscience are very pleasing, which natural joy is a great benefit unto us: and the only payment never faileth us. To ground the recompence of vertuous actions upon the approbation of others is to undertake a most uncertaine or troubled foundation, namely in an age so corrupt and times so ignorant as this is: the vulgar peoples good opinion is is injurious. Whom trust you in seeing what is commendable? God keep me from being an honest man, according to the description I dayly see made of honor, each one by himself. Quæ fuerant vitia, mores sunt. ’What earst were vices are now grown fashions.’ Some of my friends have sometimes attempted to schoole me roundly, and sift me plainly, either of their own motion, or envited by me, as to an office, which to a well composed mind, both in profit and lovingnesse, exceedeth all the duties of sincere amity. Such have I ever entertained with open arms of curtesie and kind acknowledgement. But now to speak from my conscience I often found so much false measure in their reproaches and praises, that I had not greatly erred if I had rather erred then done well after their fashion. Such as we especially, who live a private life not exposed to any gaze but our own, ought in our hearts establish a touch-stone, and there to touch our deedes and try our actions; and accordingly, now cherish and now chastise ourselves. I have my own laws and tribunall, to judge of me, whither I addresse my self more then any where els. I restraine my actions according to other, but extend them according to my self. None but yourse lf knows rightly whether you be demiss and cruel, or loyal and devout. Others see you not, but ghesse you by uncertaine conjectures. They see not so much your nature as your arte. Adhere not then to their opinion, but hold unto your own. Tuo tibi judicio est utendum, Virtutis et viciorum grave ipsius conscientiæ pondus est: qua sublata jacent omnia: (Cic. Nat. Deor. iii.) ’You must use your own judgement. The weight of the very conscience of vice and vertues is heavy: take that away and al is down.’ But whereas it is said that repentance neerely followeth sin, seems not to imply sinne placed in his rich array, which lodgeth in us as in his proper mansion. One may disavow and disclaime vices that surprise us, and whereto our passions transport us; but those which by long habite are rooted in a strong and ankred in a powerfull will, are not subject to contradiction. Repentance is but a denying of our will, and an opposition of our fantasies which diverts us here and there. It makes some disavow his former virtue and continencie. Quæ mens est hodie, cur eadem non puero fuit, Vel cur his animis incolumes non redeunt genæ? --Hor. Car. iv. Od. x. 7. Why was not in a youth same mind as now? Or why bears not this mind a youthfull brow? That is an exquisite life which even in his own private keepeth itself in awe and order. Every one may play the jugler and represent an honest man upon the stage; but within, and in bosome, where all things are lawfull, where all is concealed; to keep a due rule or formall decorum, that’s the point. The next degree is to be so in ones own home, and in his ordinary actions, whereof we are to give accoumpt to nobody, wherein is no study, nor art; and therefore Bias describing the perfect state of a family whereof (says he) the maister be such inwardly by himself, as he is outwardly, for fear of the laws, and respect of mens speaches. And it was a worthy saying of Iulius Drusus to those work- men, which for three thousand crownes offered so to reforme his house that his neighbors should no more over looke into it. I will give you sixe thousand (said he) and contrive it so that on all sides every man may looke into it. The custom of Agesilaus is remembred with honor, who in his travaile was wont to take up his lodging in churches, that the people and Gods themselves might pry into his private actions. Some have been admirable to the world, in whom nor his wife, nor his servants ever noted anything remarkeable. ’Few men have been admired of their familiars. No man has been a Prophet, not only in his house, but in his own country,’ says the experience of histories. Even so in things of nought. And in this base example is the image of greatness discerned. In my climate of Gascoigne they deem it a jest to see me in print. The further the knowledge which is taken of me is from my home, of so much more woorth am I. In Guyenne I pay Printers, in other places they pay me. Upon this accident they ground, who living and present keep close-lurking, to purchase credit when they shall be dead and absent. I had rather have less. And I cast not my self into the world, but for the portion I draw from it. That done I quit it. The people attend on such a man with wonderment, from a public act, unto his own doores; together with his roabes he leaves of his part: falling so much the lower by how much higher he was mounted. View him within, there all is turbulent, disordered and vile. And were order and formality found in him, a lively, impartiall and well sorted judgement is required to perceive and fully to discerne him in these base and private actions. Considering that order is but a dumpish and drowsie virtue: to gain a Battaile, perfourme an Ambassage, and governe a people, are noble and woorthy actions; to chide, laugh, sell, pay, love, hate, and mildely and justly to converse both with his own and with himself; not to relent, and not gain-say himself, are thinges more rare, more difficult and less remarkeable. Retired lives sustain that way, whatever some say, offices as much more crabbed and extended than other lives do. And private men (says Aristotle) serve virtue more hardly and more highly attend her, then those which are magistrates or placed in authority. We prepare ourselves unto eminent occasions, more for glory then for conscience. The nearest way to come unto glory were to do that for conscience which we do for glory. And me seems the virtue of Alexander representeth much less vigor in her large Theater then that of Socrates in his base and obscure exercitation. I easily conceive Socrates in the roome of Alexander; Alexander in that of Socrates I cannot. If any aske the one what he can do, he will answer, ’Conquer the world’: let the same question be demanded of the other, he will say, ’Leade my life conformably to its natural condition’; A science much more generous, more important, and more lawfull. The woorth of the mind consisteth not in going high, but in marching orderly. Her greatness is not exercised in greatness; in mediocritye it is. As those which judge and touch us inwardely make no great accoumpt of the brightnesse of our public actions, and see they are but streakes and poyntes of clear Water surging from a bottome otherwise slimie and full of mud: So those who judge us by this gay outward apparance conclude the same of our inward constitution, and cannot couple popular faculties as theirs are, unto these other faculties, which amaze them so far from their levell. So do we attribute savage shapes and ougly formes unto divels. As who doeth not ascribe high- raised eye-browes, open nostrils, a stern frightfull visage and a huge body unto Tamberlaine, as is the form or shape of the imagination we have fore-conceived by the bruite of his name? had any heretofore showed me Erasmus, I could hardly had bin induced to think but whatsover he had said to his boy or hostes, had been Adages and Apothegmes. We imagine much more fitly an Artificer upon his close stoole or on his wife, then a great judge, reverend for his carriage and regardfull for his sufficiencie; we think, that from those high thrones they should not abase themselves so low, as to live. As vitious mindes are often incited to do well by some strange impulsion, so are vertuous spirits mooved to do ill. They must then be judged by their settled estate, when they are neare themselves, and as we say, at home, if at any time they be so; or when they are nearest unto rest, and in their natural seate. Naturall inclinations are by institution helped and strengthned, but they neither change nor exceed. A thousand natures in my time have a thwart, a contrary discipline escaped toward virtue or toward vice. Sic ubi desuetæ silvis in carcere clausæ Mansuevere feræ, et vultus posuere minaces, Atque hominem didicere pati, si torrida parvus Venit in ora cruor, redeunt rabiesque furorque, Admonitæque tument gustato sanguine fauces, Fervet, et a trepido vix abstinet ira magistro. -- Lucan. iv. 237. So when wild beasts, disused from the wood, Fierce looks laid-down, grow tame, closde in a cage, Taught to bear man, if then a little blood Touch their hot lips, fury returnes and rage; Their jawes by taste admonisht swell with vaines, Rage boyles, and from faint keeper scarse abstaines. These originall qualities are not grubd out, they are but covered and hidden. The Latine tongue is to me in a manner natural; I understand it better then French: but it is now fortie years I have not made use of it to speak, nor much to write; yet in some extreme emotions and suddaine passions, whe rein I have twice or thrice falne, since my years of discretion, and namely once, when my father being in perfect health, fell all along upon me in a swoune, I have ever, even from my very hart uttered my first words in latine: nature rushing and by force expressing itself, against so long a custom; the like example is alleadged of diverse others. Those which in my time have attempted to correct the passions of the world by new opinions, reforme the vices of apparance; those of essence they leave untouched if they encrease them not. And their encrease is much to be feared. We willingly protract al other well- doing upon these externall reformations of less cost and of greater merit; whereby we satisfie good cheape, other natural consubstantiall and intestine vices. Looke a little into the course of our experience. There is no man (if he listen to himself) that does not discover in himself a peculiar form of his, a swaying form, which wrestleth against the institution, and against the tempests of passions, which are contrary unto him. As for me, I feel not my self much agitated by a shocke; I commonly find my self in my own place, as are sluggish and lumpish bodies. If I am not close and neare unto my self, I am never far-offe; My debauches or excesses transport me not much. There is nothing extreme and strange; yet have I sound fits and vigorous lusts. The true condemnation, and which toucheth the common fashion of our men, is that their very retreate is full of corruption and filth. The Idea of their amendment blurred and deformed; their repentance crazed and faultie very near as much as their sinne. Some, either because they are so fast and naturally joined unto vice, or through long custom have lost all sense of its uglinesse. To others (of whose rank I am) vice is burthenous, but they counter-balance it with pleasure or other occasions, and suffer it, and at a certain rate lend themselves unto it though basely and viciously. Yet might happily so remote a disposition of measure be imagined, where with justice, the pleasure might excuse the offence, as we say of profit. Not only being accidentall, and out of sinne, as in thefts, but even in the very exercise of it, as in the acquaintance or copulation with women; where the provocation is so violent, and as they say, sometime unresistible. In a town of a kinsman of mine, the other day, being in Armignac, I saw a country man, commonly sirnamed the Theefe, who himself reported his life to have been thus. Being borne a begger, and perceiving that to get his bread by the sweate of his browe and labor of his bands, would never sufficiently arm him against penury, he resolved to become a Theefe; and that trade had employed all his youth safely, by means of his bodily strength: for he ever made up Harvest and Vintage in other mens grounds: but so far off, and in so great heapes, that it was beyond imagination one man should in one night carry away so much upon his shoulders: and was so careful to equall the pray and disperce the mischief he did, that the spoile was of less import to every particular man. He is now in old years indifferently rich; for a man of his condition (Godamercy his trade) which he is not ashamed to confesse openly. And to reconcile himself with God, he affirmeth; to be dayly ready, with his gettings, and other good turnes, to satisfie the posterity of those he has heretofore wronged or robbed; which if himself be not of abilitie to performe (for he cannot do all at once) he will charge his heirs withall, according to the knowledge he has of the wrongs by him done to every man. By this description, be it true or false, he respecteth theft, as a dishonest and unlawfull action, and hateth the same: yet less then pinching want: He repents but simply; for in regard it was so counterballanced and recompenced, he repenteth not. That is not that habit which incorporates us unto vice, and confirmeth our understanding in it; nor is it that boysterous winde, which by violent blastes dazeleth and troubleth our mindes, and at that time confoundes and overwhelmes both us, our judgement, and all into the power of vice. What I do is ordinarily full and compleate, and I march (as we say) all in one pace: I have not many motions, that hide themselves and slinke away from my reason, or which very neare are not guided by the consent of all my partes, without division, or intestine sedicion: my judgement has the whole blame or commendation; and the blame it has once, it has ever: for almost from it’s birth it has been one of the same inclination, course and force. And in matters of general opinions, even from my infancy, I ranged my self to the point I was to hold. Some sinnes there are outrageous, violent and suddaine; leave we them. But those other sinnes, so often reassumed, determined and advised upon, whether they be of complexion, or of profession and calling, I cannot conceive how they should so long be settled in one same courage, unless the reason and conscience of the sinner were thereunto inwardly privie and constantly willing. And how to imagine or fashion the repentance thereof, which, he vanteth, does some times visit him, seems somewhat hard unto me. I am not of Pythagoras Sect, that men take a new soul, when to receive Oracles they approach the images of Gods, unless he would say with all, that it must be a strange one, new, and lent him for the time: our own, giving so little signe of purification, and cleanesse worthie of that office. They do altogether against the Stoycall precepts, which appoint us to correct the imperfections and vices we find in ourselves, but withall forbid us to disturbe the quiet of our mind. They make us believe they feel great remorse, and are inwardly much displeased w ith sinne; but of amendment, correction or intermission, they show us none. Surely there can be no perfect health, where the disease is not perfectly remooved. Were repentance put in the scale of the balance, it would weigh down sinne. I find no humor so easy to be counterfeited as Devotion: If one conforme not his life and conditions to it, her essence is abstruse and concealed, her apparance gentle and stately. For my part, I may in general wish to be other then I am; I may condemne and mislike my universall form, I may beseech God to grant me an undefiled reformation, and excuse my natural weakenesse: but meeseemeth I ought not to tearme this repentance, no more then the displeasure of being neither Angell nor Cato. My actions are squared to what I am and confirmed to my condition. I cannot do better: And repentance does not properly concern what is not in our power; sorrow does. I may imagine infinite dispositions of a higher pitch, and better governed then myne, yet do I nothing better my faculties; no more then mine arm becomes stronger, or my wit more excellent, by conceiving some others to be so. If to suppose and wish a more nobler working then ours, might produce the repentance of our own, we should then repent us of our most innocent actions: for so much as we judge that in a more excellent nature, they had been directed with greater perfection and dignity; and ourselves would do the like. When I consult with my age of my youthes proceedings, I find that commonly (according to my opinion), I managed them in order. This is all my resistance is able to performe. I flatter not myself: in like circumstances, I should ever be the same. It is not a spot, but a whole dye that staynes me. I acknowledge no repentance, this is superficiall, meane, and ceremonious. It must touch me on all sides before I can terme it repentance. It must pinch my entrailes, and afflict them as deepely a nd throughly as God himself beholds me. When in negotiating, many good fortunes have slipt me for want of good discretion, yet did my projects make good choice, according to the occurrences presented unto them. Their manner is ever to take the easier and surer side. I find that in my former deliberations, I proceeded, after my rules, discreetely for the subjects state propounded to me; and in like occasions, would proceede likewise a hundred years hence. I respect not what now it is, but what it was, when I consulted of it. The consequence of all dessignes consists in the seasons; occasions pass, and matters change uncessantly. I have in my time run into some grosse, absurde, and important errors; not for want of good advise, but of good happe. There are secret and indivinable parts in the objects men do handle, especially in the nature of men and mute conditions without show, and sometimes unknown of the very possessors, produced and stirred up by suddaine occasions. If my wit could neyther find nor presage them, I am not offended with it; the function thereof is contained within it’s own limits. If the success bear me, and favor the side I refused, there is no remedy; I fall not out with my self: I accuse my fortune, not my endeavor: that’s not called repentance. Phocion had given the Athenians some counsell, which was not followed: the matter, against his opinion, succeeding happily: ’How now, Phocion (quoth one), art you pleased the matter has thrived so well?’ ’Yea (said he) and I am glad of it; yet repent not the advise I gave.’ When any of my friends come to me for counsell, I bestow it francklie and clearelie, not (as well-nigh all the world does) wavering at the hazard of the matter, whereby the contrary of my meaning may happen that so they may justly find fault with my advise for which I care not greatly. For they shall do me wrong, and it became not me to refuse them that dutie. I have no body to blame for my faults or misfortunes but my self. For in effect I seldom use the advise of other unless it be for complement sake, and where I have need of instruction or knowledge of the fact. Marry in things wherein nought but judgement is to be employed; strange reasons may serve to sustain, but not to divert me. I lend a favourable and courteous care unto them all. But (to my remembrance) I never beleeved any but my own. With me they are but Flyes and Moathes, which distract my wil. I little regard my own opinions, other mens I esteeme as little: Fortune payes me accordingly. If I take no counsell I give as little. I am not much sought after for it, and less credited when I give it: Neither know I any enterprise, either private or public, that my advise has directed and brought to conclusion. Even those whom fortune had some- way tyde thereunto, have more willingly admitted the direction of others conceits then mine. As one that am as jealous of the rights of my quiet, as of those of my autthority; I would rather have it thus. Where leaving me, they jumpe with my profession, which is wholly to settle and containe me in my self. It is a pleasure unto me to be disinteressed of other mens affayres, and disingaged from their contentions. When sutes or businesses be over-past, however it be, I greeve little at them. For, the imagination that they must necessarily happen so, puts me out of pain; Behould them in the course of the Universe, and enchained in Stoycall causes, Your fantazie cannot by wish or imagination remoove one point of them, but the whole order of things must reverse both what is past and what is to come. Moreover, I hate that accidentall repentance which olde age brings with it. He that in ancient times said be was beholden to years because they had ridde him of voluptuousness, was not of mine opinion. I shall never give impuissance thankes for any good it can do me : Nec tam aversa unquam videbitur ab opere suo providential ut debilitas inter optima inventa sit: ’Nor shall fore-sight ever be seen so averse from her own work, that weakenesse be found to be one of the best things.’ Our appetites are rare in olde-age: the blowe overpassed, a deepe saciety seazeth upon us: therein see no conscience. Fretting care and weakenesse imprint in us an effeminate and drowzie virtue. We must not suffer ourselves so fully to be carried into natural alterations as to corrupt or adulterate our judgement by them. Youth and pleasure have not heretofore prevailed so much over me, but I could ever (even in the midst of sensualities) discerne the ugly face of sinne: nor can the distaste which years me from discerning that of voluptuousness in in vice. Now I am no longer in it, I judge of it as if I were still there. I who lively and attentively examine my reason, find it to be the same that possessed me in my most dissolute and licentious age; unless, perhaps, they being enfeebled and empayred by years, do make some difference: And find, that what delight it refuseth to affoorde me in regarde of my bodilie health, it would no more denie me, then in times past, for the health of my soul. To see it out of combate, I holde it not the more couragious. My temptations are so mortified and crazed as they are not worthy of it’s oppositions: holding but my hand before me, I becalme them. Should one present that former concupiscence unto it, I fear it would be of less power to sustain it than heretofore it has been. I see in it, by itself no increase of judgement, nor accesse of brightnesse; what it now judgeth, it did then. Wherefore if there be any amendment, ’tis but diseased. Oh miserable kind of remedie to be beholden unto sicknesse for our health. It is not for our mishap, but for the good success of our judgement to performe this office. Crosses and afflictions make me do nothing but curse them. They are for people that cannot be awaked but by the whip, the course of my reason is the nimbler in prosperity. It is much more distracted and busied in the digesting of mischiefes than of delights. I see much clearer in fair weather. Health forewarneth me as with more pleasure, so to better purpose than sicknesse. I approached the nearest I could unto amendment and regularity, when I should have enjoyed the same; I should be ashamed and vexed that the misery and mishap of my old age could exceed the health, attention, and vigor of my youth: and that I should be esteemed, not for what I have been, but for what I am leaft to be. The happy life (in my opinion), not (as said Antisthenes) the happy death, is it that makes mans happinesse in this world. I have not preposterously busied my self to tie the tail of a Philosopher unto the head and body of a varlet: nor that this paultrie end should disavow and belie the fairest, soundest, and longest part of my life. I will present my self and make a general muster of my whole, every where uniformally. Were I to live again it should be as I have already lived. I neither deplore what is past, nor dread what is to come: and if I be not deceived, the inward parts have neerely resembled the outward. It is one of the chiefest points wherein I am beholden to fortune, that in the course of my bodies estate, each thing has been carried in season. I have seen the leaves, the blossomes, and the fruit; and now see the drooping and withering of it. Happily, because naturally. I bear my present miseries the more gently because they are in season, and with greater favor make me remember the long bappinesse of my former life. In like manner my discretion may well be of like proportion in the one and the other time: but sure it was of much more performance, and had a better grace, being fresh, jolly, and full of spirit, then now that it is worne, decrepite, and toylesome. I therefore renounce these casual and dolourous reformations. God must touch our heartes; our conscience must amende of itself, and not by re-inforcement of our reason, nor by the enfeebling of our appetites. Voluptuousnesse in itself is neither pale nor discoloured to be discerned by bleare and troubled eyes. We should affect temperance and chastity for itself, and for Gods cause, who has ordained them unto us: that which Catars bestow upon us, and which I am beholden to my chollicke, is for neither temperance nor chastitie: A man cannot boast of contemning or combating sensuality if he see her not, or know not her grace, her force, and most attractive beauties. I know them both, and therefore may speak it. But me thinks our soules in age are subject unto more importunate diseases and imperfections then they are in youth. I said so, being young, when my beardlesse chinne was upbraided me; and I say it again now that my gray beard gives me authority. We entitle wisdom, the frowardnesse of our humors, and the distaste of present things; but in truth we abandon not vices so much as we change them; and in mine opinion for the worse. Besides a sillie and ruinous pride, combersome tattle, wayward and unsotiable humors, superstition, and a ridiculous carking for wealth, when the use of it is well-nigh lost, I find the more envie, injustice, and leaudnesse in it. It sets more wrinckles in our minds then on our foreheads: nor are there any spirits, or very rare ones, which in growing old taste not sowrely and mustily. Man marcheth entirely towards his increase and decrease. View but the wisdom of Socrates, and diverse circumstances of his condemnation. I dare say he something lent himself unto it by prevarication of purpose: being so near, and at the age of seventy, to endure the benumming of his spirits richest pace and the dimming of his accustomed brightnesse, What Metamorphoses have I seen it daily make in diverse of mine acquaintances? It is a powerfull maladie which naturally and imperceptibly glideth into us: There is required great provision of study, heed, and precaution to avoid the imperfections wherewith it chargeth us; or at least to weaken their further progresse. I find that notwithstanding all my entrenchings, by little and little it getteth ground upon me: I hold out as long as I can, but know not whither at length it will bring me. Happe what happe will, I am pleased the world know from what height I tumbled. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER III: OF THREE COMMERCES OR SOCIETIES CHAPTER III: OF THREE COMMERCES OR SOCIETIES E MUST not cleave so fast unto our humors and dispositions. Our chiefest sufficiency is to apply ourselves to diverse fashions. It is a being, but not a life, to be tied and bound by necessity to one only course. The goodliest mindes are those that have most variety and pliablenesse in them. Behold an honorable testimony of old Cato. Huic versatile ingenium sic pariter ad omnia fuit, ut natum ad id unum diceres, quodcunque ageret: (LIV. Bel. Mac. ix.) ’He had a wit so turneable for all things likewise, as one would say he had been only borne for that he went about to do.’ Were I to dresse my self after my own manner, there is no fashion so good whereto I would be so affected or tied as not to know how to leave and loose it. Life is a motion unequall, irregular, and multiforme. It is not to be the friend (less the master) but the slave of ones self to follow uncessantly, and be so addicted to his inclinations, as he cannot stray from them, nor wrest them. This I say now, as being extreamly pestred with the importunity of my mind, forasmuch as she cannot ammuse herself, but whereon it is busied; nor employ itself, but bent and whole. How light soever the subject is one gives it, it willingly amplifiethl and wire-draws the same, even unto the highest pitch of toile. Its idlenesse is therefore a painefull trade unto me, and offensive to my health. Most wits have neede of extravagant stuffe, to un-benumme and exercise themselves: mine has neede of it rather to settle and continue itself. Vitia otii negotio discutienda sunt: (Sen. Ep. lvi.) ’The vices of idlenesse should be shaken off with business.’ For, the most laborious care and principal studie of it is to studie itself. Bookes are one of those businesses that seduce it from studie. At the first thoughts that present themselves, it rouzeth up and makes proofe of all the vigor it has. It exerciseth its function sometimes toward force, sometimes towards order and comelinesse, it rangeth, moderates and fortifieth. It has of itself to awaken the faculties of it: Nature having given it, as unto all other, matter of its own for advantage, subjects fit enough whereon to devise and determine. Meditation is a large and powerfull study to such as vigorously can taste and employ themselves therein. I had rather forge then furnish my mind. There is no office or occupation either weaker or stronger then that of entertaining of ones thoughts according to the mind, whatsoever it be. The greatest make it their vacation, Quibus vivere est cogitate, to whom it is all one to live and to meditate. Nature has also favoured it with this priviledge, that there is nothing we can do so long, nor action whereto we give ourselves more ordinarily and easily. It is the work of Gods (says Aristotle) whence both their happinesse and ours proceedeth. Reading serves me especially to awake my conceit by diverse objects: to busie my judgement, not my memory. Few entertainements then stay me without vigor and force. ’Tis true that courtesy and beautie possesse me as much or more then waight and depth. And because I slumber in all other communications, and lend but the superficiall parts of my attention unto them, it often befalleth me in such kind of weake and absurd discourses (discourses of countenance) to blurt out and answer ridiculous toies and foolish absurdities, unworthy a child; or wilfully to hold my Peace; therewithall more foolishly and incivilly. I have a kind of raving fancie-full behaviour, that retireth me into my self; and on the other side, a grosse and childish ignorance of many ordinary things; by means of which two qualities, I have in my days committed five or six as sottish trickes as any one whosoever; which to my derogation may be reported. But to follow my purpose, this harsh complexion of mine makes me me nice in conversing with men (whom I must picke and cull out for the nonce) and unfit for common actions. We live and negotiate with the people: If their behaviour importune us, if we disdaine to lend ourselves to base and vulgar spirits, which often are as regular as those of a finer mould; and all wisdom is unsavourie that is not conformed to common insipience. We are no longer to inter- meddle either with our or other mens affairs; and both publicke and private forsake such kind of people. The least wrested and most natural proceedings of our mind are the fairest; the best occupations, those which are least forced. Good God, how good an office does wisdom unto those whose desires she squareth according to their power! There is no science more profitable. As one may, was the burden and favoured saying of Socrates: A sentence of great substance. We must addresse and stay our desires to things most easy and neerest. Is it not a fool-peevish humor in me to disagree from a thousand to whom my fortune joineth me, without whom I cannot live, to adhere unto one or two that are out of my commerce and conversion; or rather to a fantastic conceit, or fanciefull desire, for a thing I cannot obtaine? My soft behaviours and mild manners, enemies to all sharpenesse and foes to all bitternesse, may easily have discharged me from envie and contention: To be beloved, I say not, but not to be hated, never did man give more occasion. But the coldnesse of my conversation has with reason robd me of the good will of many; which may be excused if they interpret the same to other or worse sense. I am most capable of getting rare amities, and continuing exquisite acquaintances. For so as with so greedie hunger I snatch at such acquaintances as answer my taste and square with my humor. I so greedily produce and headlong cast my self upon them, that I do not easily misse to cleave unto them, and where I light on, to make a steady impression; I have often made happie and successefull trial of it. In vulgar worldly friendships, I am somewhat cold and barren: for my proceeding is not natural, if not unresisted and with hoised- full sailes. Moreover, my fortune having enured and allured me, even from my infancie, to one sole singular and perfect amitie, has verily, in some sort, distasted me from others: and over deeply imprinted in my fantasies that it is a beast sociable and for companies and not of troupe, as said an ancient writer. So that it is naturally a pain unto me to communicate my self by halves and with modification: and that servile or suspicious wisdom which in the conversation of these numerous and imperfect amities, is ordained and proposed unto us: Prescribed in these dayes especially, wherein one cannot speak of the world but dangerously or falsely. Yet I see, that who (as I do) makes for his ende, the commodities of his life (I meane essentiall commodities) must avoide as a plague these difficulties and quaintness of humor. I should commend a high-raysed mind, that could both bende and discharge itself: that where-ever her fortune might transport her, she might continue constant: that could discourse with her neighbors of all matters, as of her building, of her bunting and of any quarrell; and entertaine with delight a Carpenter or a Gardiner. I envie those which can be familiar with the meanest of their followers, and vouchsafe to contract friendship and frame discourse with their own servants. Nor do I like the advise of Plato, ever to speak imperiously unto our attendants, without blithnesse and sance any familiarity: be it to men or women servants. For, besides my reason, it is inhumanity and injustice to attribute so much unto that prerogative of fortune and the governement: where less inequality is permitted betweene the servant and master, is in my conceite the more indifferent. Some other study to rouze and raise their mind, but I to abase and prostrate mine: it is not faulty but in extension. Narras et genus Aeaci, Et pugnata sacro bella sub Ilio. Quo Chium pretio cadum Mercemur, quis aquam temperet ignibus, Quo præbente domum, et quota Pelignis caream frigoribus, taces. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. xix. 3. You tell of Æacus the pedegree - The wars at sacred Troye you do display. You tell not at what price a hogs-head we May buy of the best Wine; who shall allaye Wine-fire with water, at whose house to holde At what a-clock I may be kept from colde. Even as the Lacedemonian valor had neede of moderation and of sweet and pleasing sounds of Flutes, to flatter and allay it in time of war, least it should run head-long into rashnesse and fury: whereas all other nations use commonly pearcing sounds and strong shouts, which violently excite and enflame their soldiers courage: so think I (against ordinary custom) that in the employment of our spirit, we have for the most part more need of leade then wings; of coldnesse and quiet, then of heate and agitation. Above all, in my mind, the only way to play the foole well is to seem wise among fooles: to speak as though ones tongue were ever bent to Favelar’ in punta di forchetta: (Italian prov.) ’To syllabize or speak minsingly.’ One must lend himself unto those he is with, and sometimes affect ignorance. Set force and subtiltie aside; In common employments ’tis enough to reserve order; dragge your self even close to the ground, they will have it so. The learned stumble willingly on this blocke: making continuall muster and open show of their skill, and dispersing their bookes abroade: And have in these dayes so filled the closets, and possessed the ears of Ladyes, that if they retaine not their substance, at least they have their countenance: using in all sorts of discourse and subject how base or popular soever, a newe, an affected and learned fashion of speaking and writing. Hoc sermone pavent, hoc iram, gaudia, curas, Hoc cuncta effundunt animi secreta, quid ultra? Concumbunt docte. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 189. They in this language fear, in this they fashion Their joyes, their cares, their rage, their inward passion; What more? they learned are in copulation. And alledge Plato and Saint Thomas for things, which the first man they meete would decide as well, and stand for as good a witness. Such learning as could not enter into their mind, has stayed on their tongues. If the well-borne will give any credit unto me, they shall be pleased to make their own and natural riches to prevaile and be of worth: They hide and shroud their formes under forraine and borrowed beauties: It is great simplicity for any body to smoother and conceal his own brightnesse, to shine with a borrowed light: They are buried and entombed under the Arte of CAPSVLA TOTÆ. It is because they do not sufficiently know themselves: the world containes nothing of more beauty: It is for them to honor artes, and to beautifie embellishment. What neede they more then to live beloved and honoured: They have, and know but too much in that matter. There needs but a little rouzing and enflaming of the faculties that are in them. When I see them medling with Rhetoricke, with Law, and with Logicke, and such like trash, so vain and unprofitable for their use, I enter into fear that those who advise them to such things, do it that they may have more law to governe them under that pretence. For what other excuse can I devise for them? It is sufficient, that without us, they may frame, or roule the grace of their eyes, unto cheerefulnesse, unto severity, and unto mildness: and season a ’No’ with frowardnesse, with doubt and with favor; and require not an interpreter in discourses made for their service. With this learning they command without controule, and over-rule both Regents and Schooles. Yet if it offend them to yield us any preheminence, and would for curiosity sake have part in bookes also: Poesie is a study fit for their purpose, being a wanton, ammusing, subtill, disguised, and pratling Arte; all in delight, all in show, like to them-selves. They may also select diverse commodities out of History. In Morall Philosophy they may take the discourses which enable them to judge of our humors, to censure our conditions, and to avoid our guiles and treacheries; to temper the rashnesse of their own desires, to husband their liberty: lengthen the delights of life, gently to bear the inconstancy of a servant, the peevishnesse of rudenesse of a husband, the importunity of years, the unwelcomnesse of wrinkles, and such like mind-troubling accidents. See here the most and greatest share of learning I would assigne them. There are some particular, retired and close dispositions. My essentiall form is fit for communication and proper for production: I am all outward and in apparance; borne for society and unto friendship. The solitude I love and commend is especially but to retire my affections and redeeme my thoughts unto my self to restraine and close up, not my steppes, but my desires and my cares, resigning all forraigne solicitude and trouble, and mortally shunning all manner of servitude and obligation; and not so much the throng of men as the importunity of affairs. Locall solitarinesse (to say trueth) does rather extend and enlarge me outwardly; I give my self to State-business and to the world more willingly when I am all alone. At the court, and in press of people, I close and slinke into my own skinne. Assemblies thrust me again into my self. And I never entertaine my self so fondly, so licentiously, and so particularly, as in places of respect and ceremonious discretion. Our follies make me not laugh, but our wisdomes do. Of my own complexion, I am no enemy to the agitations and stirrings of our Courts: I have there past great part of my life and am inured to be merry in great assemblies so it be by intermission, and suitable to my humor. But this tenderness and coinesse of judgement (whereof I speak) does perforce tie me unto solitarinesse. Yea even in my own house, in the middest of a numerous family and most frequented houses, I see people more then a good many, but seldom such as I love to converse or communicate withall. And there I reserve, both for my self and others, an unaccustomed liberty; making truce with ceremonies, assistance, and invitings, and such other troublesome ordinances of our courtesys (O servile custom and importunate manner) there every man demeaneth himself as he pleaseth, and entertaineth what his thoughts affect: whereas I keep my self silent, meditating and close, without offence to my guests or friends. The men whose familiarity and society I hunt after, are those which are called honest, vertuous, and sufficient: the image of whom does distaste and divert me from others. It is (being rightly taken) the rarest of our formes; and a form or fashion chiefly due unto nature. The end or scope of this commerce is principally and simply familiarity, conference and frequentation: the exercise of mindes, without other fruite. In our discourses all subjects are likewise to me: I care not though they want either waight or depth; grace and pertinency are never wanting; all therein is tainted with a ripe and constant judgement, and commixt with goodnesse, liberty, cheerefulnesse, and kindness. It is not only in the subject of Laws and affairs of Princes, that our spirit sheweth its beauties grace and vigor: It sheweth them as much in private conferences. I know my people by their very silence and smyling, and perhaps discover them better at a Table then sitting in serious counsell. Hippomacus said, he discerned good Wrestlers but by seeing them march through a Street. If learning vouchsafe to step into our talk, she shall not be refused; yet must not she be stern, mastring, imperious and importunate, as commonly she is; but assistant and docile of hirselfe. Therein we seek for nothing but recreation and pastime: when we shall looke to be instructed, taught and resolved, we will go seek and sue to her in her throne. Let her if she please keep from us at that time; for, as commodious and pleasing as she is. I presume that for a neede we could spare her presence, and do our business well enough without her. Wits well borne, soundly bred and exercised in the practise and commerce of men, become gracious and plausible of themselves. Arte is but the Checke- roule and Register of the Productions uttered and conceites produced by them. The company of fair and society of honest women is likewise a sweet commerce for me: Nam nos quoque oculos eruditos habemus: (Cic. Parad.) ’For we also have learned eyes.’ If the mind have not so much to solace hirselfe as in the former, the corporall sences, whose part is more in the second, bring it to a proportion near unto the other: although in mine opinion not equall. But it is a society wherein it behooveth a man somewhat to stand upon his guard: and especially those that are of a strong constitution, and whose body can do much, as in me. In my youth I heated my self therein and was very violent: and indured all the rages and furious assaults which Poets say happen to those who, without order or discretion, abandon themselves over-loosly and riotously unto it. True it is indeed, that the same lash has since stood me instead of an instruction. Quicunque Argolico de classe Capharea fugit, Semper ab Euboicis vela retorquet aquis. -- Ovid. Trist. i. El. 83. Greeke Sailers that Capharean Rockes did fly From the Euboean Seas their sailes still ply. It is folly to fasten all ones thoughts upon it, and with a furious and indiscret affection to engage himself unto it: But on the otherside, to meddle with it without love or bond of affection, as Comedians do, to play a common part of age and manners, without ought of their own but bare-conned words, is verily a provision for ones safety: and yet but a cowardly one; as is that of him who would forgoe his honor, his profit or his pleasure, for fear of danger; for it is certain that the practisers of such courses cannot hope for any fruite able to moove or satisfie a worthy mind. One must very earnestly have desired that whereof he would enjoy an absolute delight. I meane, though fortune should unjustly favor their intention: which often happens, because there is no woman, how deformed or unhandsome soever, but thinkes herself lovely, amiable and praiseworthy, either for her age, her hair or gate (for there are generally no more fair then foul ones): and the Brachmanian maides wanting other commendations, by Proclamation for that purpose, made show of their matrimoniall parts unto the people assembled, to see if thereby at least they might get them husbands. By consequence there is not one of them, but upon the first oath one maketh to serve her, will very easily be persuaded to think well of herself. Now this common treason and ordinary protestations of men in these dayes must needs produce the effects experience already discovereth: which is, that either they join together, and cast away themselves on themselves to avoid us, or on their side follow also the example we give them; acting their part of the play without passion, without care, and without love, lending themselves to this enter course: Neque affectui suo, aut alieno obnoxiæ: ’Neither liable to their own nor other folkes affection.’ Thinking, according to Lysias persuasions in Plato, they may so much the more profitably and commodiously yield unto us, by how much less we love them: Wherein it will happen as in Comedies, the spectators shall have as much or more pleasure as the Comedians. For my part, I no more acknowledge Venus without Cupid, then a mother-hood without an off-spring: They are things which enterlend and enter-owe one another their essence. Thus does this cozening rebound on him that useth it, and as it cost him little, so gets he not much by it. Those which made Venus a goddesse, have respected that her principal beautie was incorporeall and spirituall. But she whom these kind of people hunt after is not so much as humane, nor also brutal; but such as wild beasts would not have her so filthy and terrestriall. We see that imagination enflames them, and desire or lust urgeth them, before the body: We see in one and other sex, even in whole heards, choise and distinctions in their affections, and amongst themselves, acquaintances of long continued good-will and liking: And even those to whom age denieth bodily strength, do yet bray, neigh, roare, skip and wince for love. Before the deed we see them full of hope and heat; and when the body has plaid his part, even tickle and tingle themselves with the sweetenesse of that remem brance: some of them swell with pride at parting from it, others all weary and glutted, ring out songs of glee and triumph. Who makes no more of it but to discharge his body of some natural necessitie, has no cause to trouble others with so curious a preparation. It is no food for a greedy and clownish hunger. As one that would not be accounted better than I am, thus much I will display of my youths wanton-errors: Not only for the danger of ones health that followes that game (yet could I not avoid two, although light and cursorie assaults) but also for contempt, I have not much been given to mercenarie and common acquaintances. I have coveted to set an edge on that sensuall pleasure by difficultie, by desire, and for some glory. And liked Tiberius his fashions, who in his amours was swaied as much by modesty and noblenesse as by any other quality. And Floras humor, who would Prostitute her self to none worse then Dictators, Consuls, or Censors, and took delight in the dignitie and greatness of her lovers, does somewhat sute with mine. Surely glittering pearles and silken cloathes adde some-thing unto it, and so do titles, nobility and a worthie traine. Besides which, I made high esteeme of the mind, yet so as the body might not justly be found fault withall: For, to speak my conscience, if either of the two beauties were necessarily to be wanting, I would rather have chosen to want the mentall, whose use is to be emploied in better things. But in the subject of love, a subject that chiefly has reference unto the two senses of seeing and touching, some thing may be done without the graces of the mind, but little or nothing without the corporall. Beautie is the true availefull advantage of women: It is so peculiarly theirs, that ours, though it require some features and different allurements, is not in her right kue or true bias, unless confused with theirs: childish and beardlesse. It is reported that such as serve the great Turke under the title of beautie (whereof the number is infinite) are dismissed at furthest when they once come to the age of two and twenty yeeres. Discourse, discretion, together with the offices of true amitie, are better found amongst men: and therefore governe they the worlds affairs. These two commerces or societies are accidentall and depending of others; the one is troublesome and tedious for its raritie, the other withers with old age: nor could they have sufficiently pro vided for my lives necessities. That of bookes, which is the third, is much more solid-sure and much more ours, some other advantages it yieldeth to the two former, but has for her share constancy and the facilite of her service. This accosteth and secondeth all my course, and every where assisteth me: It comforts me in age and solaceth me in solitarinesse; It easeth me of the burden of a weary-some sloth and at all times rids me of tedious companies: it abateth the edge of fretting sorrow, on condition it be not extreme and over-insolent. To divert me from any importunate imagination or insinuating conceit, there is no better way then to have recourse unto books; with ease they allure me to them, and with facility they remoove them all. And though they perceive I neither frequent nor seek them, but wanting other more essential, lively, and more natural commodities, they never mutiny or murmur at me; but still entertaine me with one and self-same visage. He may well walke a foote that leades his horse by the bridle, says the proverbe. And our James king of Naples and Sicili, being fair, young, healthy and in good plight, caused himself to be caried abroad in a plaine wagon or skreene, lying upon an homely pillow of course feathers, cloathed in a sute of home spunne gray, and a bonet of the same, yet royally attended on by a gallant troupe of Nobles, of Litters, Coches, and of all sorts of choice led-horses, a number of gentlemen and officers, represented a tender and wavering austerity. The sicke man is not to be moaned that has his health in his sleeve. In the experience and use of this sentence, which is most true, consisteth all the commoditie I reape of bookes. In effect I make no other use of them then those who know them not. I enjoy them, as a miser does his gold; to know that I may enjoy them when I list, my mind is setled and satisfied with the right of possession. I never travel without bookes, nor in peace nor in war: yet do I pass many dayes and moneths without using them. It shall be anon, say I, or to-morrow, or when I please; in the meane while the time runnes away, and passeth without hurting me. For it is wonderful what repose I take, and how I continue in this consideration, that they are at my elbow to delight me when time shall serve; and in acknowledging what assistance they give unto my life. This is the best munition I have found in this humane peregrination, and I extremely bewaile those men of understanding that want the same. I accept with better will all other kindes of ammusements, how slight soever, forasmuch as this cannot faile me. At home I betake me somewhat the oftner to my library, whence all at once I command and survey all my houshold. It is seated in the chief entrie of my house, thence I behold under me my garden, my base court, my yard, and looke even into most roomes of my house. There without order, without method, and by peece-meales I turn over and ransacke, now one book and now another. Sometimes I muse and rave; and walking up and down I endight and enregister these my humors, these my conceits. It is placed on the third story of a tower. The lowermost is my Chapell; the second a chamber with other lodgings, where I often lie, because I would be alone. Above it is a great ward-robe. It was in times past the most unprofitable place of all my house. There I pass the greatest pa t of my lives dayes, and weare out most hours of the day. I am never there a nights. Next unto it is a handsome neat cabinet, able and large enough to receive fire in winter, and very pleasantly windowen. And if I feared not care more then cost (care which drives and diverts me from all business), I might easily join a convenient gallerie of a hundred paces long and twelve broad on each side of it, and upon one floore; having already, for some other purpose, found all the walles raised unto a convenient height. Each retired place requireth a walke. My thoughts are prone to sleepe if I sit long. My mind goes not alone, as if [legs] did moove it. Those that studie without bookes are all in the same case. The form of it is round, and has no flat side, but what serveth for my table and chaire: In which bending or circling manner, at one looke it offereth me the full sight of all my books, set round about upon shelves or desks, five rancks one upon another. It has three bay-windowes of a far-extending, rich and unresisted prospect, and is in diameter sixteene paces void. In winter I am less continually there: for my house (as the name of it importeth) is pearched upon an over-pearing hillocke; and has no part more subject to all wethers then this: which pleaseth me the more, both because the accesse unto it is somwhat troublesome and remote, and for the benefit of the exercise which is to be respected; and that I may the better seclude my self from companies and keep incrochers from me: There is my seat, that is my throne. I endeavor to make my rule therein absolute, and to sequester that only corner from the communitie of wife, of children and of acquaintance. Else-where I have but a verball authority, of confused essence. Miserable in my mind is he who in his own home has no where to be to himself; where he may particularly court, and at his pleasure hide or withdraw self. Ambition paieth h r followers well to keep them still in open view, as a statue in some conspicuous place. Magna servitus est magna fortuna: (Sen. Cons. ad Pol. c. xxvi. p.) ’A great fortune is a great bondage.’ They cannot be private so much as at their privie. I have deemed nothing so rude in the austerity of the life which our Church-men affect as that in some of their companies they institute a perpetuall societie of place, and a numerous assistance amongst them in anything they do. And deem it somewhat more tolerable to be ever alone, then never be able to be so. If any say to me, It is a kind of vilifying the Muses to use them only for sport and recreation, he wots not as I do, what worth, pleasure, sport and pass-time is of: I had well nigh termed all other ends rediculous. I live from hand to mouth, and, with reverence be it spoken, I live but to my self: there end all my designes. Being young I studied for ostentation ; then a little to enable my self and become wiser; now for delight and recreation, never for gain. A vain conceit and lavish humor I had after this kind of stuffe; not only to provide for my need, but somewhat further to adorn and embellish my self withall: I have since partlie left it. Bookes have and containe diverse pleasing qualities to those that can duly choose them. But no good without paines; no Roses with out prickles. It is a pleasure not absolutely pure and neate; no more then all others; it has his inconveniences attending on it, and sometimes waighty ones: The mind is the rein exercised, but the body (the care whereof I have not yet forgotten) remaineth there-whilst without action, and is wasted, and ensorrowed. I know no excess more hurtful for me, nor more to be avoided by me, in this declining age. See here my three most favoured and particular employments. I speak not of those I owe of dutie to the world. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER IV: OF DIVERTING AND DIVERSIONS CHAPTER IV: OF DIVERTING AND DIVERSIONS WAS once employed in comforting of a truely-afflicted Lady: the greatest part of their discourses are artificial and ceremonious. Uberibus semper lachrimis, semperque paratis, In statione sua, atque expectantibus illam Quo jubeat manare modo. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 273. With plenteous tears; still readie in their stand, Expecting still their Mistresses commaund, How they must flow, when they must go. Men do but ill in opposing themselves against this passion; for opposition does but incense and engage them more to sorrow and quietnesse: The disease is exasperated by the jealousie of debate. In matters of common discourse we see that what I have spoken without heede or care, if one come to contest with me about it, I stifly maintaine and make good my own, much more if it be a thing wherein I am interessed. Besides, in so dooing you enter but rudely into your matter, whereas a physicians first entertainment of his patient should be gracious, cheereful, and pleasing. An uglie and froward Physition wrought never any good effect. On the contrary then, we must at first assist and smoothe their laments, and witness some approbation and excuse thereof. By which means you get credit to go on, and by an easy and insensible inclination you fall into more firme and serious discourses and fit for their amendment. But I, who desired chiefly to gull the assistants, that had their eyes cast on me, meant to salve their mischief: I verily find by experience that I have but an ill and unfruitfull vain to persuade. I present my reasons either too sharpe, or too drie, or too stirringly, or too carelesly. After I had for a while applyed myself to her torment, I attempted not to cure it by strong and lively reasons: either because I want them, or because I suppose I might otherwise effect my purpose the better. Nor did I cull out the severall fashions of comfort prescribed by philosophy: That the thing lamented is not ill, as Cleanthes: or but a little ill, as the Peripatetikes: that to lament is neither just nor commendable, as Chrysippus: Nor this Epicurus, most agreeing with my manner, to translate the conceit of yrkesome into delightsome things: Nor to make a loade of all this masse, dispensing the same, as one has occasion, as Cicero. But fair and softly declining our discourses, and by degrees bending them unto subjects more neare, then a little more remote, even as she more or less enclined to me. I unperceivably remooved those dolefull humors from her: so that as long as I was with her, so long I kept her in cheerful countenance and untroubled fashion, wherein I used diversion. Those which in the same service succeeded me, found her no whit amended; the reason was, I had not yet driven my wedge to the roote. I have perhaps else where glaunced at some kindes of public diversions. And the militairie customs used by Pericles in the Peloponesian war, and a thousand others else where, to divert or withdrawe the army of an enemy from their own country, is too frequent in histories. It was an ingenious diverting wherewith the Lord of Himbercourt saved both himself and others in the town of Liege, into which the Duke of Burgondie, who beleagred the same, had caused him to enter, to performe the covenante of their accorded yielding. The inhabitants thereof, to provide for it, assembled by night, and began to mutiny against their former agreement, determining upon this advantage to set upon the Negotiators, now in their power. He perceiving their intent, and noise of this shoure readie to fall upon him, and the danger his lodging was in, forth-with rushed out upon them two cittizens (whereof he had diverse with him furnished with most plausible and new offers to be propounded to their counsell but indeed forged at that instant to serve his turn withall, and to ammuse them. These two stayes the first approaching storme, and carryed this incensed Hydra-headed-monster multitude backe to the townehouse, to hear their charge, and accordingly to determine of it. The conclusion was short, when lo a second tempest came rushing on, more furiously inraged then the former; to whom he immediately dispatched foure new and semblable intercessors, with protestations that now they were in earnest to propose and declare new and far more ample conditions unto them, wholly to their content and satisfaction; whereby this disordered rout was again drawne to their Conclave and senate-house. In summe, he by such a dispensation of amusements, diverting their headlong fury, and dissipating the same with vain and frivolous consultations, at length lulled them into so secure a sleep, that he gained the day, which was his chiefest drift and only aymed scope. This other story is also of the same predicament. Atalanta, a maid of rare surpassing beautie and of a wondrous strange disposition, to ridde herself from the importunate pursuit of a thousand amorous sutors, who sollicited her for mariage prescribed this law unto them, that she would accept of him that should equall her in running; on condition those she shold overcome might lose their lives. Some there were found who deemed this prize worthie the hazard, and who incurred the penaltie of so cruel a match. Hippomenes coming to make his assay after the rest, addressed himself to the divine protectress of all amorous delights, earnestly invoking her assistance, who gently listening to his hearty prayers, furnished him with three golden Apples, and taught him how to use them. The scope of the race being plaine, according as Hippomenes perceived his swift-footed mistresse to approch his heels, he let fall (as at unawares) one of his Apples: the heedlesse maiden gazing and wondring at the alluring beautie of it, failed not to turn and take it up. Obstupuit virgo, nitidique cupidine pomi, Dectinat cursus, aurumque volubile tollit. -- Ovid. Met. x. 666. The maid amaz’d, desiring that fair gold, Turnes by her course, takes it up as it rold. The like he did (at his need) with the second and third, until by this disgressing and diverting, the goale and advantage of the course was judged his. When Physitians cannot purge the rheume, they divert and remoove the same unto some less dangerous part. I also perceive it to be the most ordinary receit for the mindes diseases. Ab ducendus etiam nonnunquam animus est ad aliena studia, sollicitudines, curas negotia: Loci denique mutatione, tanquam ægroti non convalescentes, sæpe curandus est: ’Our mind also is sometimes to be diverted to other studies, cogitations, cares, and businesses: and lastly to be cured by chance of place, as sicke folkes use that otherwise cannot get health.’ We make it seldom to shocke mischiefes with direct resistance; we make it neither to bear nor to break, but to shun or divert the blow. This other lesson is too high and over-hard. It is for him of the first rank meerely to staye upon the thing itself, to examine and judge it. It belongth to one only Socrates, to accost and entertaine death with an undaunted ordinary visage, to become familiar and play with it. He seeketh for no comfort out of this thing itself. To die seems unto him a natural and indifferent accident: thereon be wishly fixeth his right, and thereon he resolveth without looking else where. Hegesias his disciples, who with hunger starv’d themselves to death, incensed thereunto with the perswading discourses of his lessons; and that so thicke as King Ptolomey forbad him any longer to entertaine his schoole with such murtherous precepts. Those considered not death in itself they judged it not: This was not the limit of their thoughts, they run on, and ayme at another being. Those poore creatures we see on scaffolds, fraught with an ardent devotion, therein to the uttermost of their power, employing al their sences; their ears attentive to such instructions as Preachers give them, their hands and eyes lift up towards heaven; their voice uttering loud and earnest praiers: all with an eager and continuall ruth-mooving motion; do verily what in such an unavoydable exigent is commendable and convenient. One may well commend their religion, but not properly their constancy. They shunne the brunt, they divert their consideration from death; as we use to dandle and busie children, when we would lance them or let them blood. I have seen some, who if by fortune they chanced to cast their eyes towards the dreadful preparations of death which were round about them, fal into trances, and with fury cast their cogitations else where. We teech those that are to pass over some steep downefall or dreadfull abisse, to shut or turn aside their eyes. Subrius Flavius, being by the appointment of Nero to be put to death by the hands of Niger, both chief commanders in war: when he was brought unto the place where the execution should be performed, seeing the pit Niger had caused to be digged for him uneven and unhandsomely made: "Nor is this pit (quoth he to the soldiers that stood about him) according to the true discipline of war’: and to Niger, who willed him to hold his head steddy, ’I wish you would stricke as steddily.’ He guessed right; for Nigers arm trembling, he had diverse blowes at him before be could strike it off. This man seemed to have fixed his thoughts surely and directly on the matter. He that dies in the fury of a battle, with weapons in band, thinkes not then on death, and neither feeleth nor considereth the same: the heate of the fight transports him. An honest man of my acquaintance, falling down in a single combate, and feeling himself stab’d nine or ten times by his enemy, was called unto by the by standers to call on God and remember his conscience: but he told me after, that albeit those voices came unto his ears, they had no whit mooved him, and that he thought on nothing but how to discharge and revenge himself. In which combat he vanquished and slew his adversary. He who brought L. Syllanus his condemnation, did much for him, in that when he heard him answer he was prepared to die, but not by the hands of base villaines, ran upon him with his soldiers to force him; against whom obstinately defending himself, though unarmed, with fists and feet, he was slain in the conflict; dispercing with a ready and rebellious choller the painefull sence of a long and fore- prepared death to which he was assigned. We ever think on somewhat else: either the hope of a better life does settle and support us, or the confidence of our childrens worth, or the future glory of our name, or the avoyding of this lives mischieves, or the revenge banging over their heads that have caused and procured our death: Spero equidem mediis, si quid pia numina possunt, Supplcia hausurum scopulis, et nomine Dido Sæpe vocaturum. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 382. Audiam, et hæc manes veniet mihi fama sub imos. --387. I hope, if powers of heaven have any power, On rockes he shall be punisht, at that hour He oft on Didoes name shall pittilesse exclaime, This shall I hear, and this report, shall to me in my grave resort. Xenophon sacrificed with a crowne on his head, when one came to tell him the death of his son Gryllus in the battle of Mantinea. At the first hearing whereof he cast his crowne to the ground, but finding upon better relation how valiantly he died, he took it up and put it on his head again. Epicurus also at his death comforted himself in the eternitie and worth of his writings. Omnes clari et nobilitati labores fiunt tolerabiles: (Cic. Tusc. iii.) ’All glorious and honorable labours are made tolerable.’ And the same wound and the same toile (says Xenophon) toucheth not a General of an army as it does a private souldier. Epaminondas took his death much the more cheerfully, being informed that the victory remained on his side. Hæc sunt solatia, hæc fomenta summorum dolorum: (Ibid.) ’These are the comforts, these the eases of most grievous paines.’ And such other like circumstances ammuse, divert and remoove us from the consideration of the thing in itself. Even the arguments of Philosophie, at each clappe wrest and turn the matter aside, and scarcely wipe away the scabbe thereof. The first man of the first Philosophicall School and Superintendent of the rest, that great Zeno, against death cried out: ’No evil is honorable; death is: therefore is death no evil.’ Against drunkennesse: ’No man entrusts his secrets to a drunkard; every one to the wise: therefore the wise will not be drunke.’ Is this to hit the white? I love to see that these principal wits cannot rid themselves of our company. As perfect and absolute as they would be, they are still but grosse and simple men. Revenge is a sweet-pleasing passion, of a great and natural impression: I perceive it well, albeit I have made no trial of it. To divert of late a young prince from it, I told him not, he was to offer the one side of his cheeke to him who had strooke him on the other, in regard of charity; nor displaid I unto him the tragical events Poesie bestoweth upon that passion. There I left him, and strove to make him taste the beautie of a contrary image; the honor, the favor and the good-will he should acquire by gentlenesse and goodnesse: I diverted him to ambition. Behold how they deale in such cases. If your affection in love be over-powerfull, disperse or dissipate the same, say they; and they say true, for I have often, with profit, made trial of it: Breake it by the virtue of severall desires, of which one may be Regent or chief Master, if you please; but for fear it should misuse or tyrannize you, weaken it with dividing, and protract it with diverting the same. Cum morosa vago singultiet inguine vena, Conjicito humorem collectum in corpora quæque. -- Pers. Sat. vi. 73. Lucr. iv. 1056. When raging lust excites a panting tumor, To diverse parts send that collected humor. And looke to it in time, lest it vex you, if it have once seized on you. Si non prima novis conturbes vulnera plagis, Volgivagaque vagus Venere ante recentia cures. -- Lucr. iv. 1061. Unless the first wounds with new wounds you mix, And ranging cure the fresh with common tricks. I was once neerely touched with a heavy displeasure, according to my complexion, and yet more just then heavy: I had perhaps lost my self in it, had I only relied upon my own strength. Needing a vehement diversion to withdraw me from it. I did by Arte and studie make my self a Lover, whereto my age assisted me; love discharged and diverted me from the inconvenience which good-wil and amitie had caused in me. So is it in all things else. A sharpe conceit possesseth, and a violent imagination holdeth me; I find it a shorter course to alter and divert, then to tame and vanquish the same: if I cannot substitute a contrary unto it, at least I present another unto it. Change ever easeth, Varietie dissolveth, and shifting dissipateth. If I cannot buckle with it, I flie from it: and in shunning it, I stray and double from it. Shifting of place, exercise and company, I save my self amid the throng of other studies and ammusements, where it loses my tracke, and so I slip away. Nature proceedeth thus, by the benefit of inconstancy: for the time it has bestowed on us, as a sovereigns physition of our passions chiefly obtaines his purpose that way, when fraughting our conceits with other and different affairs, it dissolveth and corrupteth that first apprehension, how forcible soever it be. A wise man seeth little less his friend dying at the end of five and twenty yeeres, then at the beginning of the first yeere; and according to Epicurus, nothing less: for he asscribed no qualification of perplexities, either to the foresight or antiquitie of them. But so many other cogitations crosse this that it languisheth, and in the end groweth weary. To divert the inclination of vulgar reports, Alcibiades cut off his fair dogs ears, and so drove him into the market place; that giving this subject of prattle to the people, they might not meddle with his other actions. I have also seen some women, who to divert the opinions and conjectures of the babling people, and to divert the foolish tatling of some, did by counterfet and dissembled affections overshadow and cloak true affections. Amongst which I have noted some, who in dissembling and counterfeiting have suffered themselves to be intrapped wittingly and in good earnest; quitting their true and originall humor for the feigned: of whom I learne that such as find themselves well seated are very fooles to yielde unto that maske. The common greetings, and public entertainements being reserved unto that set or appointed servant, believe there is little sufficiency in him, if in the end he usurpe not your roome and send you unto his. This is properly to cut out and stitch up a shoe for another to put on. A little thing does divert and turn us; for a small thing holds us. We do not much respect subjects in grosse and alone: they are circumstances, or small and superficiall images that moove and touch us; and vain rindes which rebound from subjects. Folliculos ut nunc teretes æstate cicadas Linquunt. -- Lucr. v. 812. As grasse-hoppers in summer now forsake The round-grown sheafes, which they in time should take. Plutarke himself bewailes his daughter by the fopperies of his childehood. The remembrance of a farewell, of an action, of a particular grace, or of a last commendation, afflict us. Cæsars gowne disquieted all Rome, which his death had not done: The very sound of names, which gingleth in our ears, as, ’Oh, my poore master; or ’Alas, my dear friend;’ ’Oh, my daughter.’ When such like repetitions pinch me, and that I looke more nearely to them, I find them but grammaticall laments, the word and the tune wound me. Even as Preachers exclamations do often move their auditory more then their reasons: and as the pitiful groan of a beast yerneth us though it be killed for our use: poising or entring there-while into the true and massie essence of my subject. His se stimulis dolor ipse lacessit. -- Lucan. ii. 42. Griefe by these provocations, Puts itself in more passions. They are the foundations of our mourning. The conceipt of the stone, namely in the yard, has sometime for three or foure dayes together so stopped my urine, and brought me so neare deaths-doore, that it had been meere folly in me to hope, nay to desire, to avoyd the same, considering what cruel pangs that painefull plight did seaze me with. Oh how cunning a master in the murthering arte or hangmans trade was that good Emperor who caused malefactors yards to be fast-tide, that so he might make them dye for want of pissing. In which ill plight finding my self, I considered by how slight causes and frivolous objects, imagination nourished in me the grief to lose my life: with what atomes the consequence and difficulty of my dislodging was contrived in my mind: to what idle conceits and frivolous cogitations we give place in so waighty a case or important affaire. A Dogge, a Horse, a Hare, a Glasse, and what not, were corrupted in my loss. To others, their ambitious hopes, their purse, their learning: In my mind as sottishly. I view death carelessely when I behould it universally as the end of life. I overwhelme and contemne it thus in great, by retayle it spoiles and proules me. The tears of a Lacquey, the distributing of my cast sutes, the touch of a known hand, an ordinary consolation, does disconsolate and intender me. So do the plaints and fables of trouble vex our mindes: and the wailing laments of Dydo and Ariadne passionate even those that believe them not in Virgill nor in Catullus: It is an argument of an obstinate nature and indurate hart, not to be moved therewith: as for a wonder, they report of Polemon: who was not so much as appaled at the biting of a Dog, who took away the braun or calfe of his leg. And no wisdom goeth so far, as by the due judgement to conceive aright the evident cause of a Sorrow and grief, so lively and wholly, that it suffer or admit no accession by presence, when eyes and ears have their share therein: parts that cannot be agitated but by vain accidents. Is it reason that even arts should serve their purposes, and make their profit of our imbecillity and natural blockishnes? An Orator (says Rhetorick) in the play of his pleading, shall be moved at the sound of his own voice, and by his feigned agitations: and suffer himself to be cozoned by the passion he representeth: imprinting a lively and essentiall sorrow, by the jugling he acteth, to transferre it into the judges, whom of the two it concerneth less: As the persons hired at our funerals who to aide the ceremony of mourning make sale of their tears by measure, and of their sorrow by waight. For although they strive to act it in a borrowed form, yet by habituating and ordering their countenance, it is certain they are often wholly transported into it, and entertaine the impression of a true and untamed melancholly. I assisted, amongst diverse others of his friends, to convay the dead corpse of the Lord of Grammont from the siege of Laffere, where he was untimely slain, to Soissons. I noted that every where as we passed along we filled with lamentation and tears all the people we met, by the only show of our convoies mourning attire; for the deceased mans name was not so much as known or heard of about those quarters. Quintilian reporteth to have seen Comedians so far ingaged in a sorrowfull part, that they wept after being come to their lodgings: and of himself, that having undertaken to move a certain passion in another, he had found himself surprised not only with shedding of tears, but with a palenesse of countenance, and behaviour of a man truly dejected with grief. In a country neare our Mountaines the women say and unsay, weepe and laugh with one breath, as Martin the Priest; for, as for their lost husbands, they encrease their waymentings by repeti tion of the good and gracefull parts they were endowed with, there withall under one they make public relation of those imperfections, to work, as it were, some recompence unto themselves and transchange their pity unto disdaine; with a much better grace then we, who when we loose a late acquaintance, strive to loade him with new and forged prayses, and to make him far other, now that we are deprived of his sight, then he seemed to be when we enjoied and beheld him; as if mourning were an instructing party, or tears cleared our understanding by washing the same. I renounce from this time forward all the favourable testimonies any man shall affoord me, not because I shall deserve them, but because I shall be dead. If one demand that fellow, what interest he has in such a siege; The interest of example (will he say) and common obedience of the Prince; I nor looke nor pretend any benefit thereby, and of glory I know how small a portion commeth to the share of a private man such as I am. I have neither passion nor quarrell in the matter. Yet the next day shall you see him all changed, and chafing, boiling, and blushing with rage in his rank of battaile, ready for the assault. It is the glaring reflecting of so much steele, the flashing thundering of the Canon, the clang of trumpets, and the ratling of Drummes, that have infused this new fury, and rankor in his swelling vaines. A frivolous cause, will you say. How a cause? There needeth none to excite our mind. A doating humor without body, without substance, overswayeth and tosseth it up and down. Let me think of building Castles in Spayne, my imagination will forge me commodities and afford me means and delights wherewith my mind is really tickled and essentially gladded. How often do we pester our spirits with anger or sadnesse by such shaddowes, and entangle ourselves into fantastic passions which alter both our mind and body? What astonished, flearing, and confused mumpes and mowes does this dotage stir up in our visages? what skippings and agitations of members and voice, seems it not by this man alone, that he has false visions of a multitude of other men with whom he does negotiate; or some inwarde Goblin that torments him? Enquire of your self where is the object of this alteration? Is there any thing but us in nature, except subsisting nullity, over whom it has any power? Because Cambyses dreamed that his brother should be King of Persia, he put him to death: a brother whom be loved and ever trusted. Aristodemus, King of the Messenians, killed himself upon a conceite he took of some ill presage, by I know not what howling of his Dogs. And King Midas did as much, being troubled and vexed by a certain unpleasing dreame of his own. It is the right way to prize ones life at the right worth of it to forgo it for a dreame. Here notwithstanding our mindes triumph over the bodies weakenesses and misery: in that it is the prey and marke of all wrongs and alterations to feede on and aime at. It has surely much reason to speak of it. O prima infoelix fingenti terra Prometheo: Ille parum cauti pectoris egit opus. Corpora disponens, mentem non vidit in arte: Recta animi primum debuit esse via. -- Prop. iii. El. iv. 7. Unhappy earth first by Prometheus formed, Who of small providence a work performed. He framing bodies saw in arte no mind: The mindes way first should rightly be assign’d. Return to : Book III CHAPTER V: UPON SOME VERSES OF VIRGIL CHAPTER V: UPON SOME VERSES OF VIRGIL ROFITABLE thoughts, the more full and solid they are, the more combersome and heavy are they; vice, death, poverty, and diseases, are subjects that waigh and grieve. We must have our mind instructed with means to sustain and combate mischiefes, and furnished with rules how to live well and believe right: and often rouze and exercise it in this goodly study. But to a mind of the common stampe it must be with intermission and moderation; it groweth weake by being continually over-wrested. When I was young I had neede to be advertised and sollicited to keep my self in office: Mirth and health (saies one) sute not so well with these serious and grave discourses. I am now in another state. The conditions of age do but over-much admonish, instruct, and preach unto me. From the excess of jollity, I am falne into the extreme of severity: more peevish and more untoward. Therefore, I do now of purpose somewhat give way unto licentious allurements; and now and then employ my mind in wanton and youthfull conceits, wherein she recreates herself. I am now but too much setled; too heavy and too ripe. My years read me daily a lesson of coldnesse and temperance. My body shunneth disorder and feares it: it has his turn to direct the mind toward reformation; his turn also to rule and sway; and that more rudely and imperiously. Be I awake or a sleepe, it does not permit me one hou re but to ruminate on instruction, on death, on patience, and on repentance. As I have heretofore defended my self from pleasure, so I now ward my self from temperance: it haleth me too far back, and even to stupidity. I will now every way be master of my self. Wisdome has her excesses, and no less need of moderation then folly.So that least I should wither, I varnish and over cloy my self with prudence, in the intermissions my evils afoord me; Mens intenta suis ne siet: usque malis. Ovid. Trist. iv. El. i. 4. Still let not the conceit attend, The ils that it too much offend. I gently turn aside, and steale mine eyes from viewing that tempestuous and cloudy skie I have before me; which (thankes be to God) I consider without fear, but not without contention and study. And ammuse my self with the remembrance of past youth-tricks: -----animus quod perdidit, optat, Atque in præterita se totas imagine versat. -- Petron. Arb. Sat. The mind, what it has lost, does wish and cast, And turn and winde in Images forepast. That infancy looketh forward, and age backward was it not that which Janus his double visage signified? years entrains me if they please: but backward. As far as mine eyes can discerne that fair expired season, by fits I turn them thitherward. If it escape my blood and veines, yet will I not roote the image of it out of my memory: ------ hoc est, Vivere bis, vita posse priore frui. -- Mart. x. Epig. xxiii. 7. This is the way for any to live twise, Who can of former life enjoy the price. Plato appoints old men to be present at youthfull exercises, dances, and games, to make them rejoice at the bodies agility and comlinesse of others, which is now no longer in them, and call to their remembrance the grace and favor of that blooming age; and wills them to give the honor of the victory to that young-man who has gladded and made most of them mery. I was heretofore wont to note sullen and gloomy days as extraordinary: now are they my ordinary ones: the extraordinary are my fair and clear dayes. I am ready to leape for joy, as at the receaving of some unexpected favor, when nothing grieveth me. Let me tickle my self, I can now hardly wrest a bare smile from this wretched body of mine. I am not pleased but in conceite an dreaming, by sleight to turn aside the way-ward cares of age: but sure there is need of other remedies then dreaming. A weake contention of arte against nature. It is meere simplicity, as most men do, to prolong and anticipate humane incommodities. I had rather be less while olde, then old before my time. I take hold even of the least occasions of relight I can meet withall. I know now by hear-say diverse kindes of wise, powerfull and glorious pleasures: but opinion is not of sufficient force over me to make me long for them. I would not have them so stately, lofty, and disdainfully as pleasant, gentle, and ready. A natura discedimus; populo nos damus, nullius rei bono auctori: (Sen. Ep. xcix.) ’We forsake nature; We follow the people author of no good.’ My Philosophy is in action, in natural and present, little in conceit. What if I should be pleased to play at cob-nut or whip a top? Non ponebat enim rumores ante salutem. -- Ennius. He did not prize what might be said, Before how all might safe be laid. Voluptuousnesse is a quality little ambitious; it holds itself rich enough of itself without any accesse of reputation; and is best affected where it is most obscured. That young man should deserve the whip who would spend his time in choosing out the neatest Wine and best sauces. There is nothing I ever knew or esteemed less: I now beginne to learne it. I am much ashamed of it, but what can I do with all? and am more ashamed and vexed at the occasions that compell me to it. It is for us to dally, doate, and trifle out the time; and for youth to stand upon nice reputation, and hold by the better end of the staffe. That creepeth towards the world and marcheth toward credite; we come from it. Sibi arma, sibi equos, sibi hastas, sibi clavam, sibe pilam, sibi nationes et cursus habeant: nobis senibus, ex lusionibus multis, talos relinquant, et tesseras: (Cic. De Sene.) ’Let them keeps their armor, their horses, their lances, their polaxes, their tennis, their swimming, and their running; and of their many games, let them put over to us old men the tables and the cards." The very laws send us home to our lodgings. I can do no less in favor of this wretched condition, whereto my age forceth me, then furnish it with somewhat to dandle and ammuse itself, as it were childehood, for when all is done we fall into it again. And both wisdom and folly shall have much a do, by enterchange of offices to support and succour me in this calamity of age. Misce stultitiam conciliis brevem. -- Hor. iv. Od. xii. 27. With short-like-foolish tricks, Thy gravest counsels mixe. Withal I shun the lightest pricklings; and those which heretofore could not have scratcht me, do now transpearce me. So wilingly my habite does now begin to apply itself to evil; in fragili corpore odiosa omnis offensio est: (Cic. De Sene.) ’all offence is yrkesome to a crased body.’ Mensque pati durum sustinet ægra nihil. -- Ovid.Pont. i. El. vi. 18. A sicke mind can endure, No hard thing for her cure. I have ever been ticklish and nice in matters of offence; at this present I am more tender and every where open. Et minimæ vires frangere quassa valent. -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. xi. 22. Least strength can breake Things worne and weake. Well may my judgement hinder me from spurning and repining at the inconveniences which nature allots me to endure: from feeling them it cannot. I could find in my heart to run from one ende of the world to another, to searche and purchase one yeare of pleasing and absolute tranquillity; I who have no other scope then to live and be mery. Drouzie and stupide tranquillity is sufficiently to be found for me, but it makes me drouzy and dizzie, therefore I am not pleased with it. If there be any body or any good company in the country, in the citty, in France, or any where els, resident, travelling, that likes of my conceites, or whose humors are pleasing to me, they neede but hold up their hand, or whistle in their fiste, and I will store them with Essayes of pithe and substance, with might and main. Seeing it is the mindes priviledge to renew and recover itself on old age, I earnestly advise it to do it; let it bud, blossome, and flourish if it can as Misle-toe on a dead tree. I fear it is a traitor; so straightly is she clasped, and so hard does she cling to my body, that every hand-while she forsakes me; to follow her in her necessities. I flatter her in private, I urge her to no purpose, in vain I offer to divert her from this combination, and bootlesse it is for me to present her Seneca, or Catullus, or Ladies, or stately dances: if her companion have the chollicke, it seems she also has it. The very powers or faculties that are particular and proper to her, cannot then rouze themselves: they evidently seem to be enrheumed: there is no blithnes in her productions, if there be none in the body. Our schollers are to blame, who serching the causes of our mindes extraordinary fits and motions, besides they ascribe some to a divine fury, to love, to war-like fiercenesse, to Poesie, and to Wine, if they have not also allotted health her share: a health, youthfull, lusty, vigorous, full, idle, such as heretofore the Aprill of my years and security offered me by fittes. That fire of jocondnesse stirreth up lively and bright sparkles in our mind beyond our natural brightnesse and amongst the most working, if not the most desperate Enthusiasmes or inspirations. Well, it is no wonder if a contrary estate clogge and naile my spirit, and drawe from it a contrary effect. Ad nullum consurgit opus, cum corpore languet. -- Cor. Gal. El. i. 125. It to no work does rise, When body fainting lyes. And yet would have me beholden to him for lending (as he sayth) much less to this consent then beareth the ordinary custom of men. Let us at least, whilst we have time, chase and expell all difficulties from our society. Dum licet obducta solvatur fronte senectus; -- Hor. Epod. xiii. 7. With wrinckled wimpled forhead let old years, While we may, be resolv’d to merrie cheere. Tetrica sunt amænanda jocularibus: ’Unpleasant things and sowre matters should be sweetned and made pleasant with sportefull mixtures.’ I love a lightsome and civill discretion, and loathe a roughnes and austerity of behaviour: suspecting every peevish and way ward countenance. Tristemque vultus tetrici arrogantiam. -- Mart. vii. Epig. lvii. 9. Of austere countenance, The sad soure arrogance. Et habet tristis quoque turba cynædos. Fidlers are often had, Mongst people that are sad. I easily believe Plato, who saieth that easy or hard humors are a great prejudice unto the mindes goodnesse or badnesse. Socrates had a constant countenance, but light-some and smyling; not frowardly constant, as old Crassus, who was never seen to laugh. Vertue is a pleasant and buxom quality. Few I know will snarle at the liberty of my writings, that have not more cause to snarle at their thoughts-loosenes. I conforme my- self unto their courage, but I offend their eyes. It is a well ordered humor to wrest Platos writings and strain his pretended negotiations with Phedon, Dion, Stella, Archeanassa. Non pudeat dicere, quod non pudeat sentire. ’Let us not be ashamed to speak what we shame not to think.’ I hate a way ward and sad disposition, that glided over the pleasures of his life, and fastens and feedes on miseries. As flyes that cannot cleave to smooth and sleeke bodies, but seaze and holde on rugged and uneven places; or as Cupping glasses, that affect and suck none but the worst blood. For my part I am resolved to dare speak whatsoever I dare do: And am displeased with thoughts not to be published. The worst of my actions or condicions seem not so ugly unto me as I find it both ugly and base not to dare to avouch them. Every one is wary in the confession; we should be as heedy in the action. The bouldnes of offending is somewhat recompensed and restrained by the bouldnes of confessing. He that should be bound to tell all, should also bind himself to do nothing which one is forced to conceal. God graunt this excess of my licence draw men to freedom, beyond these cowardly and squeamish vertues, sprung from our imperfections; that by the expence of my immoderation I may reduce them unto reason. One must survay his faultes and study them, ere he be able to repeat them. Those which bide them from others, commonly conceal them also from themselves; and esteme them not sufficiently hidden if themselves see them. They withdraw and disguise them from their own consciences. Quare vicia confitetur? Quia etiam nunc in illis est, somnium narrare vigilantes est: (SEN. Epist. 53 m.) ’Why does no man confesse his faults? Because he is yet in them: and to declare his dreame, is for him that is waking.’ The bodies evils are discerned by their increase. And now we find that to be the gout which we termed the rheume or a bruse. The evils of the mind are darkened by their own force; the most infected feeleth them least: Therefore is it that they must often a day be handled, and violently be opened and rent from out the hollow of our bosome. As in the case of good, so of bad offices, only confession is sometimes a satisfaction. Is there any deformity in the error which dispenseth us to confesse the same? It is a pain for me to dissemble, so that I refuse to take charge of other men’s secrets, as wanting hart to disavow my knowledge. I can conceal it; but deny it I cannot, without much ado and some trouble. To be perfectly secret, one must be so by nature, not by obligation. It is a small matter to be secret in the Princes service, if one be not also a liar. He that demanded Thales Milesius, whether he should solemnly deny his lechery; had he come to me, I would have answered him, he ought not do it, for a ly is in mine opinion worse than lechery. Thales advised him otherwise, bidding him sweare, thereby to warrant the more by the less. Yet was not his counsell so much the election as multiplication of vice. Whereupon we sometimes use this by-word, that we deale well with a man of conscience, when in counterpoise of vice we propose some difficulty unto him: but when he is inclosed betweene two vices, he is put to a hard choise. As Origen was dealt with al, either to commit idolatry, or suffer himself to be Sodomatically abused by a filthy Egiptian slave that was presented unto him, he yeilded to the first condition, and viciously, says one. Therefore should not those women be distasted according to their error, who of late protest that they had rather charge their conscience with ten men then one Masse. If it be indiscretion so to divulge ones errors, ther is no danger though it come into example and use; for Ariston said, that ’The winds men fear most are those which discover them.’ We must tuck up this homely rag that cloaketh our manners. They send their conscience to the stews, and keep their countenance in order. Even traitors and murtherers observe the laws of complements, and thereto fix their endevors. So that neither can injustice complain of incivility nor malice of indiscretion. Tis pity a bad man is not also a foole, and that decency should cloak his vice. These pargettings belong only to good and sound wals, such as deserve to be whited, to be preserved. In favor of Hugonots, who accuse our auricular and private confession, I confesse my self in public, religiously and purely. Saint Augustine, Origine, and Hippocrates have published their errors of their opinions; I likewise of my maners. I greedily long to make my self known, nor care I at what rate, so it be truly; or, to say better, I hunger for nothing; but I hate mortally to be mistaken by such as shall happen to know my name. He that does all for honor and glory, what thinks he to gain by presenting himself to the world in a maske, hiding his true being from the peoples knowledge? Commend a crook-back for his comely stature, he ought to take it as an injury: if you be a coward, and one honoreth you for a valiant man, is it of you he speaks? you are taken for another: I should like as well to have him glory in the courtesys and lowtings that are showed him, supposing himself to be ring-leader of a troupe when he is the meanest folower of it. Archelaus, King of Macedon, passing through a street, som body cast water upon him, was advised by his followers to punish the party. ’Yea, but,’ quoth he, ’who ever it was, he cast not the water upon me, but upon him he thought I was.’ Socrates to one that told him he was railed upon and ill spoken of: ’Tush,’ said he, ’there is no such thing in me.’ For my part, should one commend me to be an excellent Pilote, to be very modest, or most chaste, I should owe him no thanks. Likewise should any man call me traitour, theefe or drunkard, I would deem my self but little wronged by him. Those who misknow themselves may feed themselves with false approbations; but not I, who see and search my self into my very bowels, and know full well what belongs unto me. I am pleased to be less commended, provided I be better known. I may be esteemed wise for such conditions of wisdom that I account meere follies. It vexeth me that my Essayes serve Ladies in liew of common ware and stuffe for their hall; this Chap. wil prefer me to their cabinet: I love their society somewhat private, their public familiarity wants favor and savor. In farewels we heate above ordinary our affections to the things we forgo. I here take my last leave of this worlds pleasures: lo here our last embraces. And now to our theame. Why was the acte of generation made so natural, so necessary and so just, seeing we fear to speak of it without shame, and exclude it from our serious and regular discourses we prononce boldly to rob, to murther, to betray and this we dare not but betweene our teeth. Are we to gather by it, that the less we breath out in words the more we are allowed to furnish our thoughts with? For words least used, least writen, and least concealed should best be understood, and most generally known. No age, no condition are more ignorant of it then of their bread. They are imprinted in each one, without expressing, without voice or figure. And the sexe that does it most, is most bound to suppresse it. It is an action we have put in the precincts of silence, whence to draw it were an offence: not to accuse or judge it. Nor dare we bear it but in circumlocution and picture. A notable favor, to a criminal offender, to be so execrable, that justice deem it injustice to touch and behold him, freed and saved by the benefit of this condemnations severity. It is not herein as in matters of books, which being once called-in and forbidden, become more saleable and publik? As for me, I will take Aristotle at his word, that bashfallnesse is an ornament to youth, but a reproach to age. These verses are preached in the old schoole, a schoole of which I hold more then of the modern: her vertues seem greater unto me, her vices less. [Ceux] qui par trop fuiant Venus estrivent Faillent autant que ceux qui trop la suivent. Who strive ore much Venus to shunne, offends Alike with him that wholy her intends. Tu dea, tu rerum naturam sola gubernas, Nec sine te quicquam dias in luminis oras Exoritur, neque fit lætum, nec amabile quicquam. -- Lucr. i. 22. Goddesse, you rul’st the nature of all things. Without you nothing into this light springs, Nothing is lovely, nothing pleasures brings. I know not who could set Pallas and the Muses at oddes with Venus, and make them cold and slow in affecting of love; as for me, I se no Deities that better sute together, nor more endebted one to another. Who-ever shal go about to remove amourous imaginations from the Muses, shall deprive them of the best entertainement they have, and of the noblest subject of their work and who shall debarre Cupid the service and conversation of Poesie, shall weaken him of his best weapons. By this means they caste upon the God of acquaintance, of amitie and goodwill; and upon the Goddesses, protectresses of humanity and justice, the vice of ingratitude, and imputation of churlishnesse. I have not so long been cashiered from the state and service of this God, but that my memory is still acquainted with the force of his worth and valor. ------ agnosco veteris vestigia flammæ. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 23. I feel, and feeling know, How my old flames regrow. There commonly remaine some reliques of shivering and heate after an ague: Nec mihi deficiat color hic, hyemantibus annis. When Winter years com-on, Let not this heate be gon. As drie, as sluggish and unwieldy as I am, I feel yet some warme cinders of my passed heate. Qual l’alto Ægeo, perche Aquiloneo Noto Cessi, che tuto prima il volse e scosse, Non s’accheta ei pero, ma il suono e ’l moto, Ritien deli onde anco agitate e grosse. As graund Ægean Sea, because the voice Of winds does cease, which it before enraged Yet does not calme, but stil retaines the noise And motion of huge billowes; unasswaged. But for so much as I know of it, the power and might of this God are found more quick and lively in the shadowe of the Poesie then in their own essence. Et versus digitos habet. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 197. Verses have full effect. Of fingers to erect. It representeth a kind of aire more lovely then love itself. Venus is not so fair, nor so alluring, all naked, and quick panting, as she is here in Virgill. Dixerat, et niveis hinc atque hinc diva lacertis Cunctantem amplexu molli fovet: Ille repente Accepit solitam flammam, notusque medullas Intravit calor, et labe facta per ossa cucurrit Non secus atque olim tonitru cum rupta corusco Ignea rima micans percurrit lumine nimbos.-- Virg. Æn. viii. 387. So said the Goddesse, and with soft embrace Snow-white arms, the grim-fire does enchase, He straight took wonted fire, known heate at once His marrow pearc’t, ranne through his weakned bones; As fierie flash with thunder does divide, With radient lightning through a storme does glide. ----- ea verba loquutus, Optatos dedit amplexus, placidumque petivit Conjugis infusus gremio per membra soporem. -- Ibid. 404. A sweet embrace, when he those words had said, He gave, and his lims pleasing-rest he praid To take in his wives bosome lolling laid. What therein I find to be considered is, that he depainteth her somewhat stirring for a maritall Venus. In this discreete match, appetites are not commonly so fondling, but drowsie and more sluggish. Love disdaineth a man should hold of other then himself, and dealeth but faintly with acquaintances begun and entertained under another title as marriage is. Alliances, respects and means, by all reason, waigh as much or more as the grace and beauty. A man does not marry for himself, whatsoever he aleageth, but as much or more for his posterity and families. The use and interest of mariage concerneth our offspring a great way beyond us. Therefore does this fashion please me, to guide it rather by a third hand, and by anothers sence, then our own: All which, how much does it dissent from amorous conventions? Nor is it other then a kind of incest in this reverend alliance and sacred bond to employ the efforts and extravagant humor of an amorous licentiousness as I think to have said else-were. One should (says Aristotle) touch his wife soberly, discreetly and severely, least that tickling too lasciviously pleasure transport her beyond the bounds of reason. What he speaks for conscience, Phisitions alledge for health: saying that pleasure excessively whotte, voluptuous and continuall, altereth the seede and hindereth conception. Some other say, besides, that to a languishing congression (as naturally that is) to store it with a convenient and fertile heat, one must but seldom and by moderate intermissions present himself unto it. Quo rapiet sitiens venerem, interjusque recondant. -- Virg. Georg. iii. 137. Thirsting to snatch a fit, And inly harbour it. I see no mariages faile sooner or more troubled then such as are concluded for beauties sake, and hudled up for amorous desires. There are required more solid foundations and more constant grounds, and a more warie marching to it: this earnest youthly heate serveth to no purpose. Those who think to honor marriage by joyning love unto it (in mine opinion) do as those who, to do virtue a favor, holde that nobility is no other thing then Vertue. Indeed, these things have affinitie, but therewithall great difference: their names and titles should not thus be commixt; both are wronged so to be confounded. Nobilitie is a worthy, goodly quality, and introduced with good reason, but inasmuch as it dependeth on others, and may fall to the share of any vicious and worthless fellowe, it is in estimation far shorte of virtue. If it be a virtue, it is artificiall and visible; relying both on time and fortune; diverse in form, according unto countries living and mortal; without birth, as the river Nilus genealogicall and common; by succession and similitude; drawne along by consequence, but a very weake one. Knowledge, strength, goodnesse, beauty, wealth and all other qualities fall within compasse of commerce and communication; whereas this consumeth itself in itself, of no emploiment for the service of others. One proposed to one of our Kings the choice of two mentors in one office, the one a Gentleman, the other a Yeoman: he appointed that without respect unto that quality, he who deserved best shold be elected; but were their valor or worth fully likewise, the Gentleman should be regarded, this was justlie to give nobility her right and rank. Antigonus, to an unknown young-man who sued unto him for his fathers charge, a man of valor and who was lately deceased: ’My friend (quoth he) in such good turnes I waigh not my soldiers noble birth so much as their sufficiencie.’ Of truth it should not be herein as with the officers of Spartan kings; Trumpeters, Musitions, Cookes, in whose roome their children succeeded, how ignorant soever, before the best experienced in the trade. Those of Calicut make of their nobility a degree above humane. Marriage is interdicted them, and all other vocations saving war. Of Concubines they may have as many as they list, and women as many lechardes, without Jealousie one of another. But it is a capital crime and unremissible offence to contract or marry with any of different condition: Nay, they deem themselves disparaged and polluted if they have but touched them in passing by: And as if their honor were much injured and interressed by it they kil those who approach somewhat too neare them. In such sort that the ignoble are bound to cry as they walke along, like the Gondoliers or Water men of Venice along the streetes, least they should jostle with them: and the nobles command them to what side of the way they please. Thereby do these avoyde an obloquie which they esteeme perpetual, and those an assured death. No continuance of time, no favor of Prince, no office, no virtue, nor any wealth can make a clown to become a gentleman; which is much furthered by this custom, that marriages of one trade with another are strictly forbidden. A Shoo-maker cannot marry with the race of a Carpenter, and parents are precisely bound to traine up orphanes in their fathers trade, and in no other. Thereby the difference, the distinction an d continuance of their fortune is maintained. A good marriage (if any there be) refuseth the company and conditions of love; it endevoureth to present those of amity. It is a sweet society of life, full of constancy, of trust, and an infinite number of profitable and solid offices, and mutual obligations: No woman that throughly and impartially tasteth the same, (Optato quamjunxit lumine tæda -- Catul. Com. Ber. 79. Whom loves-fire joined in double band, With wished light of marriage brand) would foregoe her estate to be her husbands master. Be she lodged in his affection as a wife, she is much more honourably and surely lodged. Be a man passionately entangled in any unlawfull lust or love, let them then be damned on whom he would rather have some shame or disgrace to alight; either on his lawfull wife, or on his lechard mistris, whose misfortune would afflict him most, and to whom he wisheth greater good or more honor. These questions admit no doubt in an absolute sound [marriage]. The reason we see so few good, is an apparant signe of its worth, and a testimony of its price. Perfectly to fashion and rightly to take it, is the worthiest and best part of our societie. We cannot be without it, and yet we disgrace and vilifie the same. It may be compared to a cage, the birds without despair to get in, and those within despair to get out. Socrates being demanded whether was most commodeous to take or not to take a wife: ’Which soever a man does (quoth he), he shall repent it.’ It is a match wherto may well be applied the common saying, Homo homini aut Deus, aut lupus: (Eras. Chil. i. cent. i. 69, 70.) ’Man unto man is either a God or a Wolfe,’ to the perfect erecting whereof are the concurrences of diverse qualities required. It is, now a dayes, found most fit or commodious for simple mindes and popular spirits whom dainties, curiosity and idleness do not so much trouble. Licentious humors, debaushed conceits (as are mine), who hate all manner of duties, bondes, or observances are not so fit, so proper, and so suitable for it. Et mihi dulce magis resoluto vivere collo. -- Cor. Gal. El. i. 61. Sweeter it is to me, With loose necke to live free. Of my own disposition, would wisdom itself have had me, I should have refused to wed her. But we may say our pleasure; the custom and use of common like overbeareth us. Most of my actions are guided by example, and not by election; yet, did I no t properly envite my self unto it, I was led and brought thereunto by strange and unexpected occasions; for, not only incommodious things, but foul, vicious and inevitable, may by some condition and accident become acceptable and allowed. So vain is mans posture and defense; and truely I was then drawne unto it, being but ill prepared and more backeward then now I am that have made trial of it. And as licencious as the world reputes me, I have (in good truth) more stricktly observed the laws of wedlock then either I had promised or hoped. It is no longer time to wince when one has put on the shackles. A man ought wisely to husband his liberty, but after he has once submitted himself unto bondage, he is to stick unto it by the laws of common duty, or at least enforce himself to keep them. Those which undertake that covenant to deale therein with hate and contempt, do both injustly and incommodiously; and that goodly rule I see pass from hand to hand among women, as a sacred oracle, Sers ton mary comme ton maistre: Et t’en garde comme un traistre. Your husband as your master serve yee: From him as from false friend preserve yee. which is as much to say, Beare your self toward him with a constrained enemy and distrustfull reverence (a stile of war, and cry of defiance) is likewise injurious and difficult. I am to mild for such crabbed dessignes. To say truth, I am not yet come to that perfection of sufficiency and quaintness of wit, as to confound reason with injustices and laugh or scoffe at each order or rule that jumps not with my humor. To hate superstition, I do not presently cast my self into irreligion. If one do not alwaies discharge his duty, yet ought he at least ever love, ever acknowledge it. It is treason for one to marry unless he wed. But go we on. Our Poet describeth a marriage full of accord and good agreement, wherein notwithstanding there is not much loyalty. Did he meane it was not possible to performe loves rights, and yet reserve some rights toward marriage; and that one may bruse it, without altogether breaking it? A servant may picke his masters purse, and yet not hate him. Beauty, opportunity, destiny (for destiny, has also a hand therin) --------fatum est in partibus illis. Quas sinus abscondit; nam si tibi sidera cassent, Nil faciet longi mensura incognita nervi. Juven. Sat. ix. 32. In those parts there is fate, which hidden are; If then you be not wrought-for by your starre, The measure of long nerves unknown to nothing serves. have entangled a woman to a stranger, yet perhaps not so absolutely, but that some bond may be left to hold her to her husband. They are two dissignes, having severall and unconfounded pathes leading to them. A woman may yield to such a man whom in no case she would have married. I meane not for the conditions of his fortune, but for the qualities of his person. Few men have wedded their sweet hearts, their paramours or mistresses, but have come home by Weeping Crosse, and ere long repented their bargaine. And even in the other world, what an unquiet life leades Jupiter with his wife, whom before he had secretly knowen and lovingly enjoyed? This is as they say, ’to beray the panier, and then put it on your head.’ My self have seen in some good place love shamefully and dishonestly cured by mariage, the considerations are too much different. We love without disturbance to ourselves; two diverse and in themselves contrary things. Isocrates said, that the town of Athens pleased men, even as Ladies do whom we serve for affection. Every one loved to come thither, to walke and pass away the time, but none affected to wed it; that is to say: to endenison, to dwell and habituate himself therein. I have (and that to my spight and grief), seen husbands hate their wives, only because themselves wronged them. Howsoever, we should not love them less for our faults; at least for repentance and compassion they ought to be dearer unto us. These are different ends (says he), and yet in some sort compatible. Wedlocke has for his share, honor, justice, profit and constancy, a plaine but more general delight. Love melts in only pleasure and truly it has it more ticklish, more lively, more quaint, and more sharpe, a pleasure inflamed by difficulty; there must be a kind of stinging, tingling and smarting. It is no longer love, be it once without Arrowes or without fire. The liberality of Ladies is to profuse in marriage, and blunts the edge of affection and desire. To avoide this inconvenience, see the punishment inflicted by the laws of Lycurgus and Plato. But Women are not altogether in the wrong, when they refuse the rules of life prescribed to the World, forasmuch as only men have established them without their consent. There is commonly brauling and contention between them and us; and the nearest consent we have with them is but stormy and tumultuous. In the opinion of our Authour, we heerin use them but inconsiderately. After we have knowen, that without comparison they are much more capable and violent in Loves-effects then we, as was testified by that ancient Priest who had been both man and woman, and tried the passions of both sexes. Venus huic erat utraque nota: -- Ovid. Meta. iii. 323. Tiros. Of both sortes he knew venery. We have moreover learned by their own mouth, what tryall was made of it, though in diverse ages, by an Emperor and an Empresse of Rome, both skilful and famous masters in lawlesse lust and unruly wantonnesse; for he in one night deflowred ten Sarmatian virgines that were his captives; but she really did one night night also answer twenty severall assaults, changing her assailants as she found cause to supply her neede to fit her taste, ------adhuc ardens rigidæ tentigine vulvæ Et lassata viris, nondum satiata necessit. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 127. and that upon the controversie happened in Catalogne betweene a wife and a husband; she complaining on his over-violence and continuance therein not so much in my conceit, because she was thereby over-labored, (for but by faith I believe not miracles), as under this pretext, to abridge and bridle the authority of husbands over their wives, which is the fundamental part of marriage: and to show that their frowning, sullennesse and peevishnesse exceed the very nuptiall bed, and trample under-foote the very beauties, graces and delights of Venus (to whose complaint her husband, a right churlish and rude fellow answered, that even on fasting dayes he must needs do it ten times at least) was by the Queene of Aragon given this notable sentence: by which after mature deliberation of counsel, the good Queen to establish a rule and imitable example unto all posterity, for the moderation and required modesty in a lawfull marriage, ordained the number of sixe times a day as a lawfull, necessary and competent limit. Releasing and diminishing a great part of her sexes neede and desire, to establish (quoth she) an easy form, and consequently permanent and immutable. Hereupon doctors cry out; what is the appetite and lust of women, when as their reason, their reformation and their virtue, is retailed at such a rate? considering the diverse judgement of our desires: for Solon, master of the lawiers schoole alloweth but three times a month because this matrimoniall entercourse should not decay or faile. Now after we beleeved (say I) and preached thus much, we have for their particular portion allotted them continency, as their last and extreme penalty. There is no passion more importunate then this, which we would have them only to resist; not simply as a vice in itself, but as abbomination and execration, and more then irreligion and parricide; whilst we ourselves without blame or reproach offend in it at our pleasure. Even those amongst us who have earnestly labored to overcome lust, have sufficiently viewed what difficulty, or rather unresistable impossibilitie they found in it, using nevertheless materiall remedies, to tame, to weaken and coole the body. And we on the other side would have them sound, healthy, strong, in good liking, well-fed and chaste together, that is to say, both hot and colde. For marriage, which we averre should hinder them from burning, affords them but smal refreshing, according as our manners are. If they meet with a husband whose force by reason of his age is yet boyling, he will take a pride to spend it else-where. Sit tandem pudor, aut eamus in ius, Multis mentula millibus redempta, Non est hæc tua, Basse, vendidisti. -- Mart. xii. Epig. xcix. 10. The philosopher Polemon was iustly called in question by his wife, for sowing in a barren fielde the fruit due to the fertile. But if they match with broken stuffe in ful wedlocke, they are in worse case then either virgins or widowes. We deem them sufficiently furnished if they have a man lie by them. As the Romans reputed Clodia Leta a vestall-virgin defloured, whom Caligula had touched, although it was manifestly prooved he had but approached her; But on the contrary, their need or longing is thereby encreased; for but the touch or company of any man whatsoever stirreth up their heate, which in their solytude was husht and quiet, and lay as cinders raked up in ashes. And to the end, as it is likely, to make by this circumstance and consideration their chastitie more meritorious: Boleslaus and Kinge his wife, King and Queene of Poland, lying together, the first day of their mariage vowed it with mutual consent, and in despight of all wedlocke commoditie of nuptiall delightes maintained the same. Even from their infancy we frame them to the sports of love: their instruction, behaviour, attire, grace, learning and all their words aimeth only at love, respects only affection. Their nurces and their keepers imprint no other thing in them, then the lovelinesse of love, were it but by continually presenting the same unto them, to distaste them of it: my daughter (al the children I have) is of the age wherein the laws excuse the forwardest to marry . She is of a slowe, nice and mild complexion, and has accordingly been brought up by her mother in a retired and particular manner: so that she beginneth but now to put-off childish simplicitie. She was one day reading a French book before me, an obscene word came in her way (more bawdie in sound then in effect, it signifieth the name of a Tree and another thing), the woman that looks to her stayed her presently, and somwhat churlishly making her step over the same: I let her alone, because I would not crosse their rules, for I medle nothing with this government: womens policy has a mysticall proceeding, we must be content to leave it to them. But if I be not deceived, the conversation of twenty lacqueis could not in six moneths have setled in her thoughts, the understanding, the use and consequences of the sound belonging to those filthy sillables as did that good olde woman by her checke and interdiction. Motus doceri gaudet Ionicos. Matura virgo, et fingitur artubus Jam nunc, et incestos amores De tenero meditatur ungui. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. vi. 21. Maides mariage-ripe straight to be taught delight Ionique daunces, fram’de by arte aright In every joint, and ev’n from their first hair Incestuous loves in meditation bear. Let them somwhat dispence with ceremonies, let them fal into free liberty of speach; we are but children, we are but gulles, in respect of them, about any such subject. Heare them relate how we sue, how we wooe, how we sollicitie, and how we entertaine them, they will soone give you to understand that we can say, that we can do, and that we can bring them nothing but what they already knew, and had long before digested without us. May it be (as Plato says) because they have one time or other been themselves wanton, licentious and amorous lads? Mine ears hapned one day in a place, where without suspicion they might listen and steale some of their private, lavish and bould discourses; O why is it not lawful for me to repeat them? Birlady (quoth I to my self), It is high time indeed for us to go studie the phrases of Amadis, the metaphors of Aretine, and eloquence of Boccace, thereby to become more skilfull, more ready and more sufficient to confront them: surely we bestow our time well; there is nor quaint phrase nor choise word, nor ambiguous figure, nor patheticall example, nor love-expressing gesture, nor alluring posture, but they know them all better then our bookes: it is a cunning bred in their vaines and will never out of the flesh, Et mentem Venus ipsa dedit. -- Virg. Georg. iii. 267. Venus herself assign’de To them both means and mind, which these skill infusing School-mistresses nature, youth, health and opportunity, are ever buzzing in their ears, ever whispering in their minds: they need not learn, nor take paines about it; they beget it, with them it is borne. Nec tantum niveo gavisa est nulla columbo Compar, vel si quid dicitur improbius, Oscula mordenti semper decerpere rostro: Quantum præcipue multivola est mulier. -- Catul. Eleg. iv. 125. No pigeons hen, or pair, or what worse name You list, makes with her Snow-white cock such game, With biting bill to catch when she is kist, As many-mind ed women when they list. Had not this natural violence of their desires been somwhat held in awe by fear and honor, wherewith they have been provided, we had all been defamed. All the worlds motions bend and yield to this conjunction, it is a matter every-where infused; and a Centre whereto all lines come, all things looke. The ordinances of ancient and wise Rome, ordained for the service, and instituted for the behoofe of love, are yet to be seen: together with the precepts of Socrates to instruct courtizans. Nec non libelli Stoici inter sericos Iacere paluillos amant. -- Hor. Epod. viii. 15. Ev’n Stoics books are pleas’d Amidst silke cushions to be eas’d. Zeno among other laws, ordered also the struglings, the opening of legs, and the actions, which happen in the deflowring of a virgin. Of what sense was the book of Strato the philosopher, of carnall copulation? And whereof treated Theophrastus in those he entitled, one The Lover, the other Of Love? Whereof Aristippus in his volume Of ancient deliciousnesse or sports? What implied or what imported the ample and lively descriptions in Plato, of the loves practised in his dayes? And the lover of Demetrius Phalereus? And Clinias, or the forced lover of Heraclides Ponticus? And that of Antisthenes, of the getting of children, or of weddings? And the other, Of the Master, or of the lover? And that of Aristo, Of amorous exercises? Of Cleanthes, one of love, another of the Art of love? The amorous dialogues of Spherus? And the filthy intolerable, and without blushing not to be uttered fable of Jupiter and Iuno, written by Chrysippus? And his so lascivious fifty Epistles? I will omit the writings of some Philosophers who have followed the sect of Epicurus, protectresse of all manner of sensuality and carnall pleasure. Fifty severall Deities were in times past allotted to this office. And there has been a nation found, which to allay and coole the lustfull concupiscence of such as came for devotion, kept wenches of purpose in their temples to be used; and it was a point of religion to deale with them before one went to prayers. Nimirum propter continentiam incontinentia necessaria est, incendium ignibus extinguitur: ’Belike we must be incontinent that we may be continent, burning is quenched by fire.’ In most places of the world that part of our body was deified. In that same province some flayed it to offer, and consecrated a peece thereof; others offred and consecrated their seed: In another the young men did publikely pierce and in diverse places open their yard between flesh and skin, and through the holes put the longest and biggest stickes they could endure, and of those stickes made afterwards a fire, for an offring to their Gods, and were esteemed of small vigor and less chastity if by the force of that cruel pain they showed any dismay. Else- where the most sacred magistrate was reverenced and acknowledged by those parts. And in diverse ceremonies the portraiture thereof was carried and showed in pompe and state, to the honor of sundry Deities. The Egyptian dames in their Bacchanalian feasts wore a wodden one about their necks, exquisitely fashioned, as huge and heavy as every one could conveniently bear: besides that which the statue of their God represented, which in measure exceeded the rest of his body. The maried women here-by, with their Coverchefs frame the figure of one upon their forheads; to glory, themselves with the enjoying they have of it; and coming to be widowes, they place it behind, and hide it under their quoifes. The greatest and wisest matrons of Rome were honoured for offring flowers and garlands to God Priapus. And when their Virgins were maried, they (during the nuptials) were made to sit upon their privities. Nor am I sure whether in my time I have not seen a glimps of like devotion. What meant that laughter-moving, and maids looke-drawing peece our fathers wore in their breeches, yet extant among the Switzers? To what end is at this present day the show of our formall under our Gascoine hoses? and often (which is worse) above their natural greatness, by falshood and imposture? A little thing would make me believe that the said kind of garment was invented in the best and most upright ages, that the world might not be deceived, and all men should yield a public account of their sufficiency. The simplest nations have it yet somewhat resembling the true form. Then was the work-mans skill instructed, how it is to be made, by the measure of the arm or foot. That good-meaning man, who in my youth, thorowout his great city, caused so many fair, curious and ancient statues to be guelded, lest the sense of seeing might be corrupted, following the advice of that other good ancient man, Flagitii principium est nudare inter cives corpora. -- Cic. Tusc. iv. En. Mongst civill people sinne, By baring bodies we beginne, should have considered, how in the mysteries of the good Goddesse, all apparance of man was excluded; that he was no whit nearer, if he did not also procure both horses and asses, and at length nature herself to be guelded. Omne adeo qenus in terris, hominumque ferarumque, Et genus æquoreum, pecuæs, pictæque volucres, Infurias ignemque ruunt. -- Virg. Georg iii. 244. All kindes of things on earth, wild beast, mankinde, Field-beasts, fair-fethered fowle, and fish (we find) Into loves fire and fury run by kind. The Gods (says Plato) have furnished man with a disobedient, skittish, and tyrannical member; which like an untamed furious-beast, attempteth by the violence of his appetite to bring all things under his becke. So have they allotted women another as insulting, wild and fierce; in nature like a greedy, devouring, and rebellious creature, who if when he craveth it, he be refused nourishment, as impatient of delay, it enrageth; and infusing that rage into their bodies stoppeth their conduicts, hindreth their respiration, and causeth a thousand kindes of inconveniences; until sucking up the fruit of the general thirst, it have largely bedewed and enseeded the bottome of their matrix. Now my law-giver should also have considered that perhaps it were a more chaste and commodiously fruitfull use betimes to give them a knowledgeand taste of the quick, then according to the liberty and heate of their fantasies suffer them to ghesse and imagine the same. In lieu of true essentiall parts they by desire surmise and by hope substitute others, three times as extravagant. And one of my acquaintance was spoiled by making open show of his in place, where yet it was not convenient to put them in possession of their more serious use. What harme cause not those huge draughts or pictures, which wanton youth with chalke or coales draw in each passage, wall, or staires of our great houses, whence a cruel contempt of our natural store is bred in them? Who knows whether Plato, ordaining amongst other well-instituted Commonwealths, that men and women, old and yoong, should in their exercises or Gymnastickes present themselves naked one to the sight of another, aimed at that or no? The Indian women, who daily without interdiction view their men all over, have at least wherewith to assuage and coole the sense of their seeing. And whatsoever the women of that great kingdome of Pegu say, who from their waist downward, have nothing to cover themselves but a single cloth slith before; and that so straight that what nice modesty or ceremonious decencie soever they seem to affect, one may plainly at each step see what God has sent them: that it is an invention or shift devised to draw men unto them, and withdraw them from other men or boies, to which unnaturall brutish sinne that nation is wholly addicted: it might be said, they lose more than they get: and that a full hunger is more vehement then one which has been glutted, be it but by the eyes. And Livia said, that to an honest woman a naked man is no more then an Image. The Lacedemonian women, more virgin-wives then are our maidens, saw every day the young men of their citie naked at their exercises: themselves nothing precise to hide their thighes in walking, esteeming themselves (says Plato) sufficiently cloathed with their virtue, without vardingall. But those of whom S. Augustine speaks, have attributed much to nakednesse, who made a question, whether women at the last day of judgement should rise again in their proper sex, and not rather in ours, lest even then they tempt us in that holy state. In summe, we lure and every way flesh them: we uncessantly enflame and encite their imagination: and then we cry out, But oh, but oh, the belly. Let us confesse the truth, there are few amongst us that fear not more the same they may have by their wives offences, than by their own vices; or that cares not more (oh wondrous charity) for his wives, then his own conscience; or that had not rather be a theefe and church-robber, and have his wife a murderer and an heretike, then not more chaste than himself. Oh impious estimation of vices! Both we and they are capable of a thousand more hurtful and unnaturall corruptions then is lust or lasciviousnesse. But we frame vices and waigh sinnes, not according to their nature, but according to our interest; whereby they take so many different unequall formes. The severity of our laws makes womens inclination to that vice more violent and faulty then its condition beareth; and engageth it to worse proceedings then is their cause. They will readily offer rather to follow the practise of law, and plead at the barre for a fee, or go to the wars for reputation, then in the midst of idlenesse and deliciousnesse be tied to keep so hard a Sentinell, so dangerous a watch. See tbey not plainly, how there is neither Merchant, Lawyer, Souldier, or Church-man, but will leave his accounts, forsake his client, quit his glory and neglect his function, to follow this other business. And the burden-bearing porter, souterly cobbler and toilefull labourer, all harassed, all besmeared and all bemoiled through travell, labor and trudding, will forget all, to please himself with this pleasing sport. Num tu quæ tenuit dives Achæmenes, Aut pinguis Phryqiæ Mygdonias opes, Permutare velis crine Liciniæ, Plenas aut Arabum domos, Dum fragrantia detorquet ad oscula Cervicem aut facili sævitia negat, Quæ poscente magis gaudeat eripi, Interdum rapere occupet? -- HOR. Car. ii. Od. xii. 21. Would you exchange for your fair mistresse hair, All that the rich Achæmenes did hold, Or all that fertill Phrygias soile does bear, Or all th’Arabians store of spice and gold? Whilst she to fragrant kisses turnes her head, Or with a courteous coinesse them denies; Which more then he that speeds she would have sped, And which sometimes to snatch she formost hies? I wot not whether Cæsars exploits, or Alexanders atchivements exceed in hardinesse the resolution of a beauteous young woman, trained after our manner in the open view and uncontrolled conversation of the world,sollicited and battered by so many contrary examples, exposed to a thousand assaults and continuall pursuits, yet still holding herself good and unvanquished. There is no point of doing more thorny nor more active then this of not doing. I find it easier to bear all ones life a combersome armour on his backe then a maiden-head. And the vow of virginity is the noblest of all vows, because the hardest. Diaboli virtus in lumbis est: (Hieron.) ’The divel’s master-point lies in our loines,’ says St. Jerome. Surely we have resigned the most difficult and vigorous devoire of mankinde unto women, and quit them the glory of it, which might stead them as a singular motive to opinionate themselves therein, and serve them as a worthy subiect to brave us, and trample under feet that vain preheminence of valor and virtue we pretend over them. They shall find (if they but heed it) that they shall thereby not only be highly regarded, but also more beloved. A gallant undaunted spirit leaveth not his pursuits for a bare refusall; so it be a refusall of chastitie, and not of choise. We may sweare, threaten and wailingly complain; we lie, for we love them the better. There is no enticing lure to wisdom and secret modesty; so it be not rude, churlish, and froward. It is blockishnesse and basenesse to be obstinately willfull against hatred and contempt. But against a vertuous and constant resolution matched with an acknowledging mind, it is the exercise of a noble and generous mind. They may accept of our service unto a certain measure, and make us honestly perceive how they disdaine us not, for the law which enjoineth them to abhorre us because we adore them, and hate us forasmuch as love them, is doubtlesse very cruel, were it but for its difficultie. Why may they not listen to our offers and not gain-say our requests, so long as they containe themselves within the bounds of modesty? Wherefore should we imagine they inwardly affect a freer meaning? A Queene of our time said wittily, that ’to refuse mens kind summons is a testimony of much weaknesse, and an accusing of ones own facility; and that an unattempted Lady could not vaunt of her chastitie.’ Honours limits are not restrained so short; they may somewhat be slacked, and withoutoffending somewhat dispensed withall. At the end of his frontiers there is left a free, indifferent, and newter space. He that could drive and force his mistresse into a corner and reduce her into her fort, has no great matter in him if he be not content with his fortune. The price or honor of the conquest is rated by the difficultie. Will you know what impression your merits, your services and worth have made in her heart? Iudge of it by her behaviour and disposition. Some one may give more that (all things considered) gives not so much. The obligation of a benefit has wholly reference unto the will of him that gives; other circumstances which fall within the compasse of good-turnes, are dumbe, dead and casual. That little she gives may cost her more then all her companion has. If rarenesse be in any thing worthy estimation, it ought to be in this. Respect now how little it is, but how few have it to give. The value of money is changed according to the coine, stampe or marke of the place. Whatsoever the spight or indiscretion of some may upon the excess of their discontentment make them say: Vertue and truth do ever recover their advantage. I have knowen some whose reputation has long time been impeached by wrong and interessed by reproach, restored unto all mens good opinion and general approbation without care or art, only by their constancy, each repenting and denying what he formerly beleeved. From wenches somewhat suspected, they now hold the first rank amongst honorable ladies. Some told Plato that all the world spake ill of him: ’Let them say what they list,’ quoth he, ’I will so live that Ile make them recant and change their speeches.’ Besides the fear of God and the reward of so rare a glory which should incite them to preserve themselves, the corruption of our age enforceth them unto it, and were I in their clothes, there is nothing but I would rather do then commit my reputation into so dangerous hands. In my time the leisure of reporting and blabbing what one has done (a pleasure not much short of the act itself in sweetness) was only allowed to such as had some assured, trustie, and singular friend; whereas now-a-days the ordinary entertainements and familiar discourses of meetings and at tables are the boastings of favors received, graces obtained, and secret liberalities of Ladies. Verily, it is too great an abjection and argueth a basenesse of heart, so fiercely to suffer these tender, daintie, delicious joyes to be persecuted, pelted, and foraged by persons so ungrateful, so undiscreet, and so giddy-headed. This our immoderate and lawlesse exasperation against this vice, proceedeth and is bred of jealousie; the most vain and turbulent infirmitie that may afflict mans mind. Quis vetat apposito lumen de lumine sumi? Dent licet assidue, nil tamen inde perit. -- Ovid. Art. Amand. iii. 93. To borrow light of light, who would deny? Though still they give, nothing is lost thereby. That, and Envie her sister, are (in mine opinion) the fondest of the troupe. Of the latter, I cannot say much; a passion which how effectuall and powerfull soever they set forth, of her good favor she meddles not with me. As for the other I know it only by sight. Beasts have some feeling of it. The shepheard Cratis being fallen in love with a she Goat, her Bucke for jealousie beat out his braines as he lay asleepe. We have raised to the highest strain the excess of this moodie feaver, after the example of some barbarous nations: The best disciplines have therewith been tainted, it is reason, but not carried away by it: Ense maritali nemo confossus adulter, Purpureo stygias sanguine tinxit aquas. With husbands sword yet no adulter slain, With purple blood did Stygian waters staine. Lucullus, Cæsar, Pompey, Anthony, Cato, and diverse other gallant men were Cuckolds, and knew it, though they made no stir about it. There was in all that time but one gullish coxcombe Lepidus, that died with the anguish of it. Ah tum te miserum malique fati, Quæm attractis pedibus patente porta. Percurrent mugilesque raphanique. -- Catul. Lyr. Epig. xv. 17. Ah you then wretched, of accursed fate, Whom Fish-wives, Redish-wives of base est ate, Shall scoffing over-run in open gate. And the God of our Poet, when he surprised one of his companions napping with his wife, was contented but to shame them: Atque aliquis de dis non tristibus optat, Sic fieri turpis. -- Ovid. Met. iv. 187. Some of the merier Gods does wish in heart To share their shame, of pleasure to take part. And yet forbeareth not to be enflamed with the gentle dalliances and amorous blandishments she offereth him, complaining that for so slight a matter he should distrust her to him dear-dear affection: Quid causes petis ex alto? fiducia cessit Quo tibi Diva mei -- Virg. Æn. viii. 395. So far why fetch you your pleas pedigree? Whither is fled the trust you had in me? And which is more, she becomes a suiter to him in the behalfe of a bastard of hers, Arma rogo genitrix nato. -- Ibid. 382. A mother for a son, I crave, An armor he of you may have. Which is freely granted her: and Vulcan speaks honourably of Aeneas, Arma acri facienda viro. -- Ibid. 441. An armour must be hammered out, For one of courage stern and stout. In truth with an humanity more then humane. And which excess of goodnesse by my consent shall only be left to the Gods: Nec divas hominis componier æquum est. -- Catul. Eleg. iv. 141. Nor is it meet, that men with Gods Should be compar’d, there is such ods. As for the confusion of children, besides that the gravest law-makers appoint and affect it in their Common-wealths, it concerneth not women with whom this passion is, I wot not how in some sort better placed, fitter seated. Sæpe etiam Iuno maxima coelicolum Conjugis inculpa flagravit quotidiana. -- Catul. Eleg. iv. 138. Ev’n Juno, chief of Goddesses, oft-time, Hath grown hot at her husbands daily crime. When jealousie once seazeth on thesesilly, weake, and unresisting soules, ’tis pitiful to see how cruelly it tormenteth, insultingly it tyrannizeth them. It insinuateth itself under colour of friendship; but after it once possesseth them, the same causes which served for a ground of good-will, serve for the foundation of mortal hatred. Of all the mindes diseases, that is it, whereto most things serve for sustenance, and fewest for remedy. The virtue, courage, health, merit and reputation of their husbands are the firebrands of their despight, and motives of their rage. Nullæ sunt inimicitiæ nisi amoris acerbæ. -- Prop. ii. El. viii. 3. No enmities so bitter prove And sharpe, as those which spring of love. This consuming feaver blemisheth and corrupteth all that otherwise is good and goodly in them. And how chaste or good a huswife soever a jealous woman is, there is no action of hers but tasteth of sharpnesse and smaks of importunity. It is a furious perturbation, a moody agitation, which throwes them into extremities altogether contrary to the cause. The success of one Octavius in Rome was strange, who, having layen with and enjoied the love of Pontia Posthumia, increased his affection by enjoying her, and instantly sued to mary her;but being unable to persuade her, his extreme passionate love precipitated him into effects of a most cruel, mortal and inexorable hatred, whereupon he killed her. Likewise the ordinary Symptomes or passions of this other amorous disease are intestine hates, slie Monopolies, close conspiracies: Notumque, furens quid foemina possit. -- Virg. Æn. v. 6. It is known what a woman may, Whose raging passions have no stay. And a raging spight, which so much the more fretteth itself by being forced to excuse it self under pretence of good-will. Now the duty of chastitie has a large extension and far-reaching compasse. Is it their will we would have them to bridle? That’s a part very pliable and active. It is very nimble and quick-rolling to be staied. What? If dreames do sometimes engage them so far as they cannot dissemble nor deny them; It lieth not in them (nor perhaps in chastitie itself, seeing she is a female) to shield themselves from concupiscence and avoid desiring. If only their will interesse and engage us, where and in what case are we? Imagine what great throng of men there would be in pursuit of this privilege, with winged speed (though without eyes and without tongue) to be conveied upon the point of every woman that would buy him. The Scythian women were wont to thrust out the eyes of all their slaves and prisoners taken in war, thereby to make more free and private use of them. Oh what a furious advantage is opportunity ! He that should demand of me what the chief or first part in love is, I would answer, To know how to take fit time; even so the second, and likewise the third. It is a point which may do all in all. I have often wanted fortune, but sometimes also enterprise. God shield him from harme that can yet mocke himself with it. In this age more rashnesse is required; which our youths excuse under colour of heat. But should our women looke nearer unto it, they might find how it rather proceedeth of contempt. I superstitiously feared to offend; and what I love I willingly respect. Besides that, who depriveth this merchandize of reverence, defaceth all luster of it. I love that a man should therein somewhat play the child, the dastard and the servant. If not altogether in this, yet in some other things I have some aires or motives of the sottish bashfulness, whereof Plutarch speaks; and the course of my life has diversly been wounded and tainted by it: a quality very ill beseeming my universall form. And what is there amongst us but sedition and jarring? Mine eyes be as tender to bear a refusall as to refuse; and it does so much trouble me to be troublesome to others, that where occasions force me or dutie compelleth me to trie the will of any one, be it in doubtfull things, or of cost unto him, I do it but faintly and much against my will but if it be for my own private business (though Homer say most truly, that in an indigent or needy man, bashfulness is but a foolish virtue) I commonly substitute a third party, who may blush in my roome: and direct them that employ me, with like difficulty: so that it has sometimes befallen me to have the will to deny when I had not power to refuse. It is then folly to go about to bridle women of a desire so fervent and so natural in them. And when I hear them bragge to have so virgin-like a will and cold mind, I but laugh and mocke at them. They recoile too far backward. If it be a toothlesse beldame or decrepit grandame, or a young drie pthisicke starveling; if it be not altogether credible, they have at least some colour or apparence to say it. But those which stir about and have a little breath left them, marre but their market with such stuffe: forasmuch as inconsiderate excuses are no better then accusations. As a Gentleman my neighbour, who was suspected of insufficiencie, Languidior tenera cui pendens sicula beta, Nunquam se mediam sustulit ad tunicam, -- Catul. El. iii. 21. to justify himself, three or foure dayes after his mariage, swore confidently that the night before he had performed twenty courses, which oath has since served to convince him of meere ignorance, and to divorce him from his wife. Besides, this allegation is of no great worth; for there is nor continencie nor virtue where no resistance is to the contrary. It is true, may one say, but I am not ready to yield. The Saints themselves speak so. This is understood of such as boast in good earnest of their coldnesse and insensibility, and would be credited with a serious countenance: for, when it is from an affected looke (where the eyes give words the lie) and from the faltring speech of their profession (which ever workes against the wooll) I allow of it. I am a duteous servant unto plainnesse, simplicity and liberty; but there is no remedie, if it be not meerely plaine, simple, or infantine; it is foolish, inept and unseemely for Ladies in this commerce; it presently inclineth and bendeth to impudence. Their disguisings, their figures and dissimulations cozen none but fooles; there lying sitteth in the chaire of honor; it is a by-way, which by a false posterne leads us unto truth. If we cannot containe their imaginations, what require we of them? the effects? Many there be who are free from all strangers communication, by which chastitie may be corrupted and honestie defiled. Illud sæpe facit, quod sine teste facit. -- Mart. vii. Epig. lxi. 6. What she does with no witness to it, She often may be found to do it. And those whom we fear least are perhaps most to be feared; their secret sins are the worst. Ofendor moecha simpliciore minus. -- Ibid. vi. Epig. vii. 6. Pleas’d with a whores simplicity. Offended with her nicitie. There are effects which without impuritie may lose them their pudicitie, and which is more, without their knowledge. Obstetrix virginis cuiusdam integritatem manu velut explorans, sive malevolentia, sive inscitia, sive casu, dum inspicit, perdidit: ’A Midwife searching with her finger into a certain maiden’s virginity, either for ill will, or of unskilfulnesse, or by chance, while she seekes and looks into it, she lost and spoiled it.’ Some one has lost or wronged her virginity in looking or searching for it; some other killed the same in playing with it. We are not able precisely to circumscribe them the actions we forbid them: Our law must be conceived under general and uncertaine termes. The very Idea we forge unto their chastity i ridiculous. For amongst the extremest examples or patternes I have of it, it is Fatua, the wife of Faunas, who, after she was maried, would never suffer herself to be seen of any man whatsoever. And Hierons wife, that never felt her husbands stinking breath, supposing it to be a quality common to all men. It were necessary, that to satisfie and please us, they should become insensible and invisible. Now let us confesse that the knot of the judgement of this duty consisteth principally in the will. There have been husbands who have endured this accident, not only without reproach and offence against their wives, but with singular acknowledgment, obligation and commendation to their virtue. Some one that more esteemed her honestie then she loved her life, has prostituted the same unto the lawlesse lust and raging sensuality of a mortal hateful enemy, thereby to save her husbands life; and has done that for him which she never could have been induced to do for herself. This is no place to extend these examples; they are too high and over-rich to be presented in this luster: let us therefore reserve them for a nobler seat. But to give you some examples of a more vulgar stampe. Are there not women daily seen amongst us, who for the only profit of their husbands, and by their express order and brokage, make sale of their honesty? And in old times Phaulius the Argian, through ambition offred his to King Philip. Even as that Galba, who bestowed a supper on Mecenas, perceiving him and his wife beginne to bandy eye-trickes and signes, of civility shrunke down upon his cushion, as one expressed with sleepe, to give better scope unto their love: which he avouched as pretily: for at that instant a servant of his, presuming to lay hands on the plate which was on the table, he cried outright unto him: ’How now varlet? seest you not I sleepe only for Mecenas?’ One may be of loose behaviour, yet of purer will and better reformed then another who frameth herself to a precise apparance. As some are seen complain because they vowed chastitie before yeeres of discretion or knowledge, so have I seen others unfainedly bewaile and truly lament that they were vowed to licentiousnesse and dissolutenes before the age of judgement and distinction. The parents leaudnesse may be the cause of it; or the force of impulsive necessity, which is a shrewd counsellor and a violent perswader. Though chastity were in the East Indias of singular esteeme, yet the custom permitted that a maried wife might freely betake herself to what man soever did present her an Elephant: and that which some glory to have been valued at so high a rate. Phedon the philosopher, of a noble house, after the taking of his country Elis, professed to prostitute the beauty of his youth to all commers, so long as it should continue, for money to live with and bear his charges. And Solon was the first of Grece (say some), who by his laws gave women liberty, by the price of their honestie, to provide for their necessities: A custom which Heroditus reporteth to have been entertained before him in diverse commonwealths. And moreover, what fruit yields this careful vexation? For, what justice soever be in this passion, yet should we note whether it harrie us unto our profit or no. Thinkes any man that he can ring them by his industrie? Pone seram, cohibe; sed quis custodiet ipsos Custodes? cauta est, et ab illis incipit uxor. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 247. Keepe her with locke and key: but from her who shall keep Her Keepers? She begins with them, her wits so deepe. What advantage sufficeth them not in this so skilfull age? Curiosity is everywhere vicious, but herein pernicious. It is meere folly for one to seek to be resolved of a doubt, or search into a mischief, for which there is no remedie, but makes it worse, but festereth the same: the reproach whereof is increased, and chiefely published by jealousie; and the revenge whereof does more wound and disgrace our children then it helpeth or graceth us. You waste away and die in pursuit of so concealed a mysterie, of so obscure a verification. Whereunto how piteously have they arrived, who in my time have attained their purpose? If the accuser or intelligencer present not withall the remedy and his assistance, his office is injurious, his intelligence harmefull, and which better deserveth a stabbe then does a lie. We flout him no less that toileth to prevent it, then laugh at him that is a Cuckold and knowes it not. The character of cuckoldrie is perpetuall; on whom it once fastneth it holdeth for ever. The punishment bewraieth it more then the fault. It is a goodly sight to our private misfortunes from out the shadow of oblivion or the dungeon of doubt, for to blazon and proclaime them on Tragicall Stages; and misfortunes which pinch us not, but by relation. For (as the saying is) she is a good wife, and that a good marriage, not that is so indeed, but whereof no man speaks. We ought to be wittly-wary to avoid this irksome, this tedious and unprofitable knowledge. The Romans were accustomed, when they returned from any journey, to send home before, and give their wives notice of their coming, that so they might not surprise them. And therefore has a certain nation instituted the Priest to open the way unto the Bridegroome, on the wedding day, thereby to take from him the doubt and curiosity of searching in this first attempt, whether she come a pure virgin to him, or be broken and tainted with any former love. But the world speaks of it. I know a hundred Cockolds which are so honestly and little undecently. An honest man and a gallant spirit is moaned, but not disesteemed by it. Cause your virtue to suppresse your mishap, that honest-minded men may blame the occasion and curse the cause; that he which offends you may tremble with only thinking of it. And, moreover, what man is scot-free, or who is not spoken of in this sense, from the meanest unto the highest? ------tot qui legionibus imperitavit, Et melior quam to multis fuit, improbe, rebus. -- Lucr. iii. 1070. He that so many bands of men commanded, Thy better much, sir knave, wasmuch like branded. Seest then not how many honest men, even in your presence, are spoken of and touched with this reproach? Imagine then they will be as bold with you, and say as much of you else-where. For no man is spared. And even Ladies will scoffe and prattle of it. And what do they now adaies more willingly flout at, then at any well composed and peaceable mariage? There is none of you all but has made one Cuckold or other. Now nature stood ever on this point, Kæ me Ile kæ you, and ever ready to be even alwaies on recompences and vicissitude of things, and to give as good as one brings. The long- continued frequence of this accident should by this time have seasoned the bitter taste thereof: It is almost become a custom. Oh miserable passion, which has also this mischief, to be incommunicable. Fors etiam nostris invidit quæstibus aures. -- Catul. her. Argon. 170. Fortune ev’n ears envied, To hear us when we cried. For to what friend dare you entrust your grievances, who, if he laugh not at them, will not make use of them, as a direction and instruction to take a share of the quarie or bootie to himself? As well the sowrenesse and inconveniences, as the sweetness and pleasures incident to mariage, are secretly concealed by the wiser sort. And amongst other importunate conditions belonging to wedlocke, this one, unto a babling fellow as I am, is of the chiefest; that tyrannous custom makes it uncomely and hurtful for a man to communicate with any one all he knowes and thinkes of it. To give women advice to distaste them from jealousies were but time lost or labor spent in vain.Their essence is so infected with suspicion, with vanity and curiosity, that we may not hope to cure them by any lawfull meane. They often recover of this infirmitie by a form of health, much more to be feared then the disease itself. For even as some inchantment cannot ridde away an evil but with laying it on another, so when they lose it, they transferre and bestow this maladie on their husbands. And to say truth, I wot not whether a man can endure anything at their hands worse then jealousie; of all their conditions it is most dangerous, as the head of all their members. Pittacus said, that ’every man had one imperfection or other, his wives curst pate was his;’ and but for that, he should esteeme himself most happy. It must needs be a weightie inconvenience, wherewith so just, so wise and worthy a man, felt the state of his whole life distempered: what shall we petie fellowes do then? The Senate of Marceille had reason to grant and enroll his request who demanded leave to kill himself, thereby to free and exempt himself from his wives tempestuous scolding humor; for it is an evil that is never cleane rid away but by removing the whole peece: and has no other composition of worth, but flight or sufferance; both too-too hard, God knowes. And in my conceit, he understood it right that said, a good mariage might be made betweene a blinde woman and a deafe man. Let us also take heed, lest this great and violent strictnesse of obligation we enjoine them, produce not two effects contrary to our end: that is to wit, to set an edge upon their suiters stomacks, and make women more easy to yield. For, as concerning the first point, enhancing the price of the place, we raise the price and endeare the desire of the conquest. Might it not be Venus herself, who so cunningly enhanced the market of her ware by the brokage or pandarizing of the laws? knowing how sottish and tasteless a delight it is, were it not enabled by opinion and endeared by dearnes. To conclude, it is all but hogges flesh, varied by sauce, as said a roguish Flaminius his hoast. Cupid is a roguish God; his sport is to wrestle with devotion and to contend with justice. It is his glory, that his power checketh and copes all other might, and that all other rules give place to his. Materiam culpæ prosequiturque suæ. -- Ovid. Trist. iv. El. i. 34. He prosecutes the ground, Where he is faulty found. And as for the second point; should we not be less Cuckolds if we less feared to be so; according to womens conditions: whom inhibition inciteth, and restraint inviteth. Ubi velis nolunt, ubi nolis volunt ultro: -- Ter. Eunuc. act. iv. sc. 6. They will not when you will, When you will not, they will; Concessa pudet ire via. -- Lucan. ii. 445. They are asham’d to pass The way that granted was. What better interpretation can we find concerning Messalinas demeanor? In the beginning she made her silly husband Cuckold secretly and by stealth (as the fashion is) but perceiving how uncontrolled and easily she went on with her matches, by reason of the stupidity that possessed him, she presently contemned and forsooke that course, and began openly to make love, to avouch her servants, to entertaine and favor them in open view of all men; and would have him take notice of it, and seem to be distasted with it: but the silly gull and senselesse coxcombe awaked not for all this, and by his over-base facility, by which he seemed to authorize and legitimate her humors, yielding her pleasures weerish, and her amours tastelesse: what did she? Being the wife of an Emperor, lustie in health and living; and where? In Rome, on the worlds chief theater, at high noone-day, at a stately feast, in a public ceremony; and which is more, with one Silius, whom long time before she had freely enjoied, she was solemnly maried one day that her husband was out of the City. Seemes it not that she took a direct course to become chaste, by the retchlesnesse of her husband? or that she sought another husband, who by jealousie might whet her appetite, and who insisting might incite her? But the first difficultie she met with was also the last. The drowzie beast rouzed himself and suddenly started up. One has often the worst bargaines at the hands of such sluggish logger heads. I have seen by experience, that this extreme patience or long-sufferance, if it once come to be dissolved, produces most bitter and outragious revenges: for, taking fire all at once, choller and fury hudling all together, becomming one confused chaos, clattereth foorth their violent effects at the first charge. Irarumque omnes effundit habenas. -- Virg. Æn. xii. 499. It quite lets loose the raine, That anger should restraine. He caused both her and a great number of her instruments and abettors to be put to death; indeed such as could not do withall, and whom by force of whipping she had allured to her adulterous bed. What Virgill says of Venus and Vulcan, Lucretius had more sutably said it of a secretly-stolne enjoying betweene her and Mars, -----belli fera munera Mavors Armipotens regit, in gremium qui sæpe tuum se Reiicit, æterno devinctus vulnere amoris: Pascit amore avidos inhians in te Dea visus, Eque tuo endet resupini spiritus ore: Hunc tu Diva tuo recubantem corpore sancto Circumfusa super, suaveis ex ore loquelas Funde. -- Lucret. i. 33. Mars, mighty arm’d, rules the fierce feats of arms, Yet often casts himself into thine arms, Oblig’d thereto by endlesse wounds of love, Gaping on you feeds greedy sight with love, His breath hangs at your mouth who upward lies, Goddesse you circling him, while he so lies, With your celestiall body, speeches sweet Powre from your mouth (as any Nectar sweet). When I consider this, reiicit, pascit, inhians, molli, fovet, medullas, labefacta, pendet, percurrit, and this noble circumfusa, mother of gentle infusus, I am vexed at these small points and verball allusions, which since have sprung up. To those well-meaning people there needed no sharpe encounter or witty equivocation: their speech is altogether full and massie, with a natural and constant vigor: they are all epigram, not only tail, but head, stomacke, and feet. There is nothing forced, nothing wrested, nothing limping; all marcheth with like tenour. Contextus totus virilis est, non sunt circa flosculos occupati. The whole composition or text is manly, they are not bebusied about Rhetorike flowers. This is not a soft quaint eloquence, and only without offence; it is sinnowie, materiall, and solid; not so much delighting, as filling and ravishing, and ravisheth most the strongest wits, the wittiest conceits. When I behold these gallant formes of expressing, so lively, so nimble, so deepe, I say not this is to speak well, but to think well. It is the quaintness or livelinesse of the conceit that elevateth and puffes up the words. Pectus est quod disertum facit: ’It is a mans own brest that makes him eloquent.’ Our people terme judgement, language; and full conceptions, fine words. This pourtraiture is directed not so much by the hands dexterity as by having the object more lively printed in the mind. Gallus speaks plainly because he conceiveth plainly. Horace is not pleased with a sleight or superficiall expressing, it would betray him; he seeth more clear and further into matters: his spirit pickes and ransaketh the whole store of words and figures, to show and present himself; and he must have them more then ordinary, as his conceit is beyond ordinary. Plutarch says that he discerned the Latine tongue by things. Here likewise the sense enlighteneth and produces the words: no longer windy or spongy, but of flesh and bone. They signifie more then they utter. Even weake ones show some image of this. For, in Italie, I spake what I listed in ordinary discourses, but in more serious and pithy I durst not have dared to trust to an Idiome which I could not winde or turn beyond it’s common grace or vulgar bias. I will be able to adde and use in it somewhat of my own. The managing and emploiment of good wits endeareth and gives grace unto a tongue: not so much innovating as filling the same with more forcible and diverse services, wresting, straining and enfolding it. They bring no words unto it, but enrich their own, waigh- down and cramme-in their signification and custom; teaching it unwonted motions; but wisely and ingenuously. Which skill how little it is given to all, may plainly be discerned by most of our modern French Writers. They are over-bold and scornefull, to shunne the common trodden path: but want of invention and lacke of discretion looseth them. There is nothing to be seen in them but a miserable strained affectation of strange Inke-pot termes; harsh, cold and absurd disguisements, which in stead of raising, pull down the matter. So they may gallantize and flush it in novelties they care not for efficacie. To take hold of a new far-fetcht word, they neglect the usual, which often are more significant, forcible and sinnowie. I find sufficient store of stuffs in our language, but some defect of fashion. For there is nothing but could be framed of our Hunters gibbrish words or strange phrases, and of our Warriours peculiar tearmes; a fruitfull and rich soile to borrow of. And as hearbes and trees are bettered and fortified by being trans-planted, so formes of speach are embellished and graced by variation. I find it sufficiently plenteous, but not sufficiently plyable and vigorous. It commonly faileth and shrinketh under a pithy and powerfull conception. If your march therein be far extended, you often feel it droope and languish under you, unto whose default the Latine does now and then present his helping hand, and the Greeke to some others. By some of these words which I have culled out, we more hardly perceive the Energie or effectuall operation of them, forasmuch as use and frequencie have in some sort abased the grace and made their beauty vulgar. As in our ordinary language we shall sometimes meete with excellent phrases and quaint metaphors, whose blithenesse fadeth through age, and colour is tarnish by too common using them. But that does nothing distaste those of sound judgement, nor derogate from the glory of those ancient Authors, who, as it is likely, were the first that brought these words into luster, and raised them to that strain. The sciences handle this over finely with an artificiall manner, and different from the vulgar and natural form. My Page makes love, and understands it feelingly; Read Leon Hebræus or Ficinus unto him; you speak of him, of his thoughts and of his actions, yet understands he nothing what you meane. I nor acknowledge nor discerne in Aristotle the most part of my ordinary motions. They are clothed with other robes, and shrouded under other vestures for the use of Academicall schooles. God send them well to speed; but were I of the trade, I would naturalize Arte as much as they Artize nature. [Farewell,] Benbo and Equicola. When I write I can well omit the company, and spare the remembrance of books; for fear they interrupt my form. And in truth good Authours deject me too-too much, and quaile my courage. I willingly imitate that Painter who, having bungler-like drawne and fondly represented some Cockes forbad his boies to suffer any live Cocke to come into his shop. And to give my self some luster or grace have rather neede of some of Antinonides the Musicians invention; who, when he was to play any musick , gave order that before or after him, some other bad musicians should cloy and surfet his auditory. But I can very hardly be without Plutark, he is so universall and so full, that upon all occasions, and whatsoever extravagant subject you have undertaken, he intrudeth himself into your work, and gently reacheth you a helpe-affording hand, fraught with rare embelishments and inexhaustible of precious riches. It spights me that he is so much exposed unto the pillage of those which haunt him. He can no sooner come in my sight, or if I cast but glance upon him, but I pull some legge or wing from him. For this my dissignement, it much fitteth my purpose that I write in my own house, in a wild country, where no man belpeth or releeveth me; where I converse with no body that understands the Latine of his Pater noster, and as little of French. I should no doubt have done it better else where, but then the work had been less mine, whose principal drift and perfection is to be exactly mine. I could mend an accidentall error, whereof I abound in mine unwary course; but it were a kind of treason to remove the imperfections from me, which in me are ordinary and constant. When any body else, or my self have said unto my self: Thou art too full of figures or allegories; here is a word meerely-bred Gaskoyne; that’s a dangerous phrase: (I refuse none that are used in the frequented streets of France, those that will combat use and custom by the strict rules of Grammar do but jest) there’s an ignorant discourse, that’s a paradoxicall relation: or there’s a foolish conceit: you doest often but dally: one will think you speakest in earnest what you hast but spoken in jest. Yea (say I), but I correct unadvised, not customarie errors. Speake I not so every where? Doe I not lively display my self? That sufficeth: I have my will: All the world may know me by my book, and my book by me: but I am of an Apish and imitating condition. When I medled with making of verses (and I never made any but in Latine), they evidently accused the poet I came last from reading. And of my first Essayes, some taste a little of the stranger. At Paris I speak somewhat otherwise then at Montaigne. Whom I behold with attention, does easily convay and imprint something of his in me. What I heedily consider, the same I usurpe: a foolish countenance, a crabbed looke, a ridiculous manner of speach. And vices more: because they pricke me, they take fast hold upon me, and leave nice not, unless I shake them off. I have more often been heard to sweare by imitation then by complexion. Oh injurious and dead-killing imitation: like that of those huge in greatness and matchlesse in strength Apes, which Alexander met withall in a certain part of India: which otherwise it had been hard to vanquish. But by this their inclination to counterfeit whatsoever they saw done, they afforded the means. For, thereby the Hunters learn’t in their sight to put on shooes, and tie them with many strings and knots; to dresse their heads with diverse strange attires, full of sliding-knots and dissemblingly to rub their eyes with Glew or Bird- lime; so did those silly harmlesse beasts indiscreetly employ their Apish disposition. They ensnared, glewed, entrameled, haltred and shackled themselves. That other faculty of Extempore and wittily representing the gestures and words of another, which often causeth sport and breedeth admiring, is no more in me then in a blocke. When I sweare after my own fashion, it is only by God; the directest of all oathes. They report that Socrates swore by a Dogge; Zeno by that interjection (now a days used amongst the Italies) Capari; and Pithagoras by water and by aire. I am so apt at unawares to entertaine these superficiall impressions, that if but for three days together I use myself to speak to any Prince with your Grace or your Highnesse, for eight days after I so forget myself, that I shall still use them for your Honour or your Worship: and what I am wont to speak in sport or jest, the next day after I shall speak in good serious earnest. Therefore in writing I assume more unwillingly much beaten arguments, for fear I handle them at others charges. All arguments are likewise fertile to me. I take them upon any trifle. And I pray God this were not under-taken by the commandement of a mind as fleeting. Let me begin with that likes me best, for all matters are linked one to another. But my conceit displeaseth me, for somuch as it commonly produces most foolish dotages from deepest studies, and such as content me on a suddaine, and when I least looke for them; which as fast fleete away, wanting at that instant some holde fast. On horse-backe, at the table, in my bed; but most on horse-backe, where my amplest meditations and my farthest reaching conceits are. My speach is somewhat nicely jealous of attention and silence; if I be in any earnest talk, who interrupteth me, cuts me off. In travell, even the necessity of waies breakes off discourses. Besides that I most commonly travell without company, which is a great helpe for continued reasonings: whereby I have sufficient leisure to entertaine my self. I thereby have that success I have in dreames: In dreaming I commend them to my memory (for what I dream I do it willingly), but the next morning I can well call to mind what colour they were of, whether blith, sad or strange; but what in substance, the more I labor to find out, the more I overwhelme them in oblivion. So of casual and unpremeditated conceits that come into my braine, nought but a vain image of them remaineth in my memory; so much only as sufficeth unprofitably to make me chafe, spight and fret in pursuite of them. Well, then, leaving bookes aside, and speaking more materially and simply, when all is done I find that love is nothing else but an insatiate thirst of enjoying a greedily desired subject. Nor Venus that good huswife, other then a tickling delight of emptying ones seminary vessels: as is the pleasure which nature gives us to discharge other parts, which becomes faulty by immoderation and defective by indiscretion. To Socrates love is an appetite of generation by the mediation of beauty. Now, considering oftentimes the ridiculous tickling or titilation of this pleasure, the absurd giddy, and hare-braind motions wherwith it tosseth Zeno and agitates Cratippus: that unadvised rage, that furious and with cruelty enflamed visage in loves lustfull and sweetest effects: and then a grave, stern, severe, surly countenance in so fond-fond an action, that one has pell-mell lodged our joyes and filthes together, and that the supremest voluptuous-nesse both ravisheth and plaineth, as does sorrow: I believe that which Plato saies to be true, that man was made by the Gods for them to toy and play withall. ----- quænam ista jocandi Sæuitia? What cruelty is this, so set on jesting is? And that Nature in mockery left us the most troublesome of our actions, the most common: thereby to equall us, and without distinction to set the foolish and the wise, us and beasts all in one rank; no barrel better Hering. When I imagine the most contemplative and discreetly-wise-men in these tearmes in that humor, I hold him for a cozener, for a cheater to seem either studiously contemplative or discreetly wise. It is the foulenesse of the peacockes feete which does abate his pride, and stoop his gloating-eyed tayle: -----ridentem dicere verum, Quid vetat? -- Hor. Ser. i. Sat. ii. 24. What should forbid you sooth to say, Yet be as mery as we may. Those which in playes refuse serious opinions, do as one reporteth, like unto him who dreadeth to adore the image of a Saint, if it want a cover, an apr one or a tabernacle. We feed full well and drinke like beasts; but they are not actions that hinder the offices of our mind. In those we hold good our advantage over them, whereas this brings each other thought under subjection, and by its imperious authority makes brutish and dulleth all Platoes philosophy and divinity of it. In all other things you may observe decorum and maintaine some decency: all other operations admit some rules of honesty; this cannot only be imagined, but vicious or ridiculous. See whether for example sake you can but find a wise or discreete proceeding in it. Alexander said that he knew himself mortal chiefly by this action and by sleeping; sleepe does stifle and suppresseth the faculties of our soul, and that both [devoureth] and dissipates them. Surely it is an argument not only of our originall corruption, but a badge of our vanity and deformity. On the one side nature urgeth us unto it; having thereunto combined, indeed fastned the most noble, the most profitable, and the most sensually-pleasing of all her functions; and on the other suffereth us to accuse, to condemne and to shunne it, as insolent, as dishonest and as lewde, to blush at it, and allow, indeed to commend abstinence. Are not we most brutish to terme that work beastly which begets and which maketh us? Most people have concurred in diverse ceremonies of religion, as sacrifices, luminaries, fastings, incensings, offrings, and amongst others, in condemnation of this action. All opinions agree in that, besides the so far-extended use of circumcision. We have perhaps reason to blame ourselves for making so foolish a production as man, and to entitle both the deed and parts thereto belonging shamefull (mine are properly so at this instant). The Esseniens, of whom Plinie speaks, maintained themselves a long time without nurces or swathling clothes by the arrival of strangers that came to their shoares, who seconding their foolish humor, did often visit them. A whole nation hazarding rather to consume then engage themselves to feminine embracements, and rather lose the succession of all men then forge one. They report that Zeno never dealt with woman but once in all his life, which he did for civility, least he should over obstinately seem to contemne the sex. Each one avoideth to see a man borne, but all run hastily to see him dye. To destroy him we seek a spacious field and a full light, but to construct him we hide ourselves in some darke corner and work as close as we may. It is our dutie to conceal ourselves in making him; it is our glory, and the originall of many vertues to destroy him being framed. The one is a manifest injury, the other a greater favor, for Aristotle says that in a certain phrase, where he was borne, to bonifie or benefit was as much to say as to kill one. The Athenians, to equall the disgrace of these two actions, being to cleanse the Ile of Delos and justify themselves unto Apollo forbad within that precinct all burial and births, Nostri nosmet poenitet; (Ter. Phor.) ’We are weary of ourselves.’ There are some nations that when they are eating they cover themselves. I know a Lady (indeed one of the greatest) who is of opinion that to chew is an unseemly thing, which much empaireth their grace and beauty, and therefore by her will she never comes abroad with an appetite; And a man that cannot endure one should see him eate, and shunneth all company more when he filleth then when he emptieth himself. In the Turkish Empire there are many who to excel the rest will not be seen when they are feeding, and who make but one meale in a weeke, who mangle their face and cut their limbs, and who never speak to anybody, who think to honor their nature by disnaturing themselves: oh fantastic people that prize themselves by their contempt and mend [by] their empairing. What monstrous beast is this that maks himself a horror to himself, whom his delights displease, who tyes himself unto misfortune? Some there are that conceal their life, Exilioque domos et dulcia limina mutant, -- Virg. Georg. ii. 511. They change for banishment, The places that might best content, and steale it from the sight of other men; That eschew health and shunne mirth as hateful qualities and harmefull. Not only diverse Sects but many people curse their birth and blesse their death. Some there be that abborre the glorious Sunne and adore the hidious darkenesse. We are not ingenious but to our own vexation; It is the true foode of our spirits force; a dangerous and most unruly implement. O miseri quorum gaudia crimen habent. -- Cor. Gal. El. i. 188. O miserable they, whose joyes in fault we lay. Alas, poore silly man, you hast but too-too necessary and unavoidable incommodities, without increasing them by thine own invention, and are sufficiently wretched of condition without any arte; you aboundest in reall and essentiall deformities, and need not forge any by imagination. Doest you find your self too well at ease, unless the moiety of thine ease molest you? Findest you to have supplied or discharged al necessary offices wherto nature engageth you, and that she is idle in you, if you bind not your self unto new offices? Thou fearest not to offend her universall and undoubted laws, and art mooved at thine own partiall and fantastic ones. And by how much more particular, uncertaine, and contradicted they are, the more endevours you bestowest that way. The positive orders of your parish tie you, those of the world do nothing concerne you. Runne but a little over the examples of this consideration, your life is full of them. The verses of these two poets, handling lasciviousnesse so sparingly and so discreetly as they do in my conceit, seem to discover and display it nearer; ladies cover their bosome with networke, priests many sacred things with a veil, and painters shadow their workes to give them the more luster and to adde more grace unto them. And they say that the streakes of the Sunne and force of the winde are much more violent by reflection then by a direct line. The Egyptian answered him wisely that asked him what he had hidden under his cloake? ’It is,’ quoth he, ’hidden under my cloake that you mayest not know what it is.’ But there are certain other things which men conceal to show them. Hear this fellow more open: Et nudam pressi corpus ad usque meum. -- Ovid. Am. i. El. v. 24. My body I applide, Even to her naked side. Methinkes he baffles me. Let Martiall at his pleasure tuck-up Venus he makes her not by much appeare so wholly. He that speaks all he knows, does cloy and distaste us. Who feareth to express himself, leadeth our conceite to imagine more then happily he conceiveth. There is treason in this kind of modesty, and chiefly as these do in opening us so fair a path unto imagination. Both the action and description should taste of purloyning. The love of the Spaniards and of the Italians pleaseth me; by how much more respective and fearefull it is, the more nicely close and closely nice it is, I wot not who in ancient time wished his throat were as long as a Cranes neck that so he might the longer and more leasurely taste what he swallowed. That wish were more to purpose than this suddaine and violent pleasure: Namely, in such natures as mine, who am faulty in suddainenesse. To stay her fleeting and delay her with preambles, with them all serveth for favor, all is construed to be a recompence, a wink, a cast of the eye, a bowing, a word, or a signe, a becke is as good as a Dew guard. He that could dine with the smoake of roste-meat, might he not dine at a cheape rate? would he not soone be rich? It is a passion that commixeth with small store of solid essence, great quantity of doating vanity and febricitant raving: it must therefore be requited and served with the like. Let us teach Ladies to know how to prevaile, highly to esteeme themselves, to ammuse, to circumvent and cozen us. We make our last charge the first; we show ourselves right French men, ever rash, ever headlong. Wire-drawing their favors and enstalling them by retaile, each one, even unto miserable old age, findes some listes end, according to his worth and merite. He who has no jovissance but in enjoying, who shootes not but to hit the marke, who loves not hunting but for the prey; it belongs not to him to entermedle with our School. The more steps and degrees there are, the more delight and honor is there on the top. We should be pleased to be brought unto it as unto stately Pallaces by diverse porches, severall passages, long and pleasant Galleries, and well contrived turnings. This dispensation would in the end redound to our benefite; we should stay on it, and longer love to lie at Racke and Manger, for these snatches and away marre the grace of it. Take away hope and desire, we grow faint in our courses, we come but lagging after. Our mastery and absolute possession is infinitely to be feared of them. After they have wholy yielded themselves to the mercy of our faith and constancy, they have hazarded something. They are rare and difficult vertues: so soone as they are ours, we are no longer theirs. -----postquam cupidæ mentis satiata libido est. Verba nihil metuere, nihil perjuria curant. -- Catul. Arg. v. 147. The lust of greedy mind once satisfied, They fear no words; nor reke othes falsified. And Thrasonides, a young Greek, was so religiously amorous of his love, that having after much suit gained his mistris hart and favor, he refused to enjoy her, least by that jovissance he might or quench, or satisfie, or languish that burning flame and restlesse heat wherwith he gloried, and so pleasingly fed himself. Things far fetcht and dearly bought are good for Ladyes. It is the dear price makes viands savour the better. See but how the form of salutations, which is peculiar unto our nation, does by its facility bastardize the grace of kisses, which Socrates says, to be of that consequence, waight and danger, to ravish and steale our hearts. It is an unpleasing and injurious custom unto Ladies, that they must afford their lips to any man that has but three Lackies following him, how unhandsome and lothsome soever he be: Cuius livida naribus caninis, Dependet glacies, rigetque barba? Centum occurrere malo culilingis. -- Mart. v. Epig. xciv. 10. From whose dog-nosthrils black-blew Ise depends, Whose beard frost-hardned stands on bristled ends, &c. Nor do we ourselves gain much by it: for as the world is divided into foure parts, so for foure fair ones we must kisse fiftie foul: and to a nice or tender stomack, as are those of mine age, one ill kisse does, surpay one good. In Italy they are passionate and languishing sutors to very common and mercinarie women; and thus they defend and excuse themselves, saying, That even in enjoying there be certain degrees, and that by humble services they will endeavor to obtaine that which is the most absolutely perfect. They sell but their bodyes, their willes cannot be put to sale; that is too free, and too much its own. So say these, that it is the will they attempt, and they have reason: It is the will one must serve and most solicite. I abhor to imagine mine, a body voide of affection. And me seems this frenzie has some affinity with that boyes foolish humor, who for pure love would wantonize with that fayre Image of Venus which Praxiteles had made; or of the furious Egyptian who lusted after a dead womans corpes, which he was embaulming and stitching up: which was the occasion of the lawe that afterward was made in Egypt, that the bodies of fair, young, and nobly borne women should be kept three dayes before they should be delivered into the hands of those who had the charge to provide for their funerals and burials. Periander did more miraculously, who extended his conjugall affection (more regular and lawfull) unto the enjoying of Melissa his deceased wife. Seemes it not to be a lunatique humor in the Moone, being otherwise unable to enjoy Endimion her favorite darling, to lull him in a sweet slumber for many moneths together; and feed hirselfe with the jovissance of a boye, that stirred not but in a dreame? I say likewise, that a man loves a body without a soul when he loves a body without his consent and desire. All enjoyings are not likewise. There are some hecticke, faint and languishing ones. A thousand causes, besides affection and good will, may obtaine us this graunt of women. It is no sufficient testimony of true affection: therein may lurke treason, as elsewhere: they sometime go but faintly to work, and as they say with one buttocke Tanquam thura merumque parent; -- Ibid. xi. Epi. civ. 12. As though they did dispense Pure Wine and Frankincense. Absentem marmoreamve putes. -- Ibid. Epig. lxi. 8. Of Marble you would think she were, Or that she were not present there. I knowe some that would rather lend that then their coach, and who empart not themselves, but that way: you must also marke whether your company pleaseth them for some other respect or for that end only as of a lustie-strong grome of a stable: as also in what rank and at what rate you are there lodged or valued; -----tibi si datur uni Quo lapide illa diem candidiore notet. -- Catul. Eleg. iv. 147. If it afforded be to you alone, Where by she counts that day of all dayes one. What if she eate your bread with the sauce of a more pleasing imagination? Te tenet, absentes alios suspirat amores. -- Tibul. iv. El. v. 11. Thee she retaines, yet sigheth she For other loves that absent be. What? have we not seen some in our dayes to have made use of this action for the execution of a most horrible revenge, by that means murthering and empoysoning (as one did) a very honest woman? such as know Italie will never wonder if for this subject I seek for no examples elsewhere. For the said nation may in that point be termed Regent of the world. They have commonly more fair women, and fewer foul then we; but in rare and excellent beauties I think we match them. The like I judge of their wits, of the vulgar sort they have evidently many more. Blockishnes is without all comparison more rare amongst them: but for singular wits, and of the highest pitch, we are no whit behinde them. Were I to extend this comparison, I might (me thinkes) say, touching valor, that on the other side, it is in regard of them popular and natural amongst us: but in their hands one may sometimes find it so compleate and vigorous, that it exceedeth all the most forcible examples we have of it. The mariages of that countrie are in this somewhat defective. Their custom does generally impose so severe observances and slavish laws upon wives, that the remotest acquaintance with a stranger is amongst them as capital as the nearest. Which law causeth that all aproaches prove necessarily substanciall; and seeing all commeth to one reckoning with them, they have an easy choise: and have they broken down their hedges? Beleeve it, they will have fire: Luxuria ipsis vinculis, sicut fera bestia, irritata, deinde emissa: ’Luxurie is like a wild beast, first made fiercer with tying, and then let loose.’ They must have the reynes given them a little. Vidi ego nuper equum contra sua frena tenacem Ore reluctante fulminis ire modo. -- Ovid. Am. iii. El. iv. 13. I saw, spite of his bit, a resty colt, Runne head-strong headlong like a thunder-bolt. They allay the desire of company by giving it some liberty. It is a commendable custom with our nation that our children are entertained in noble houses there, as in a schoole of nobility to be trained and b rought up as Pages. And ’tis said to be a kind of discourtesy to refuse it a gentleman. I have observed (for so many houses so many severall formes and orders) that such Ladies as have gone about to give their waiting women the most austere rules, have not had the best successes. There is required more then ordinary moderation: a great part of their government must be left to the conduct of their discretion: For, when all comes to all, no discipline can bridle them in each point. True it is that she who escapeth safe and unpolluted from out the schoole of fredome, gives more confidence of hirselfe than she who commeth sound out of the schoole of severity and restraint. Our forefathers framed their daughters countenances unto shamefastnesse and fear (their inclinations and desires alwaies likewise), we unto assurance. We understand not the matter. That belongeth to the Sarmatian wenches, who by their laws may lie with no man, except with their own hands they have before killed another man in war. To me that have no right but by the ears, it sufficeth if they retaine me to be of their counsell, following the priviledge of mine age, I then advise both them and us to embrace abstinence, but if this season be too much against it, at least modesty and discretion. For as Aristippus (speaking to some young men who blushed to see him go into a bawdy house) said, ’The fault was not in entring, but in not coming out again.’ She that will not exempt her conscience, let her exempt her name; though the substance be not of worth, yet let the apparance hold still good. I love gradation and prolonging in the distribution of their favors. Plato sheweth that in all kindes of love, facility and readinesse is forbidden to defendants. ’Tis a trick of greedinesse which it behoveth them to cloake with their arte, so rashly and foolhardily to yield themselves in their distributions of favors, holding a and moderate course, they much better deceive our desires and conceal theirs. Let them ever be flying before us: I meane even those that intend to be overtaken as the Scithians are wont, though they seem to run away they heate us more, and sooner put us to route. Verily according to the lawe which nature gives them, it is not fit for them to will and desire: their part is to bear, to obey, and to consent. Therefore has nature bestowed a perpetual capacity; on us a seld and uncertaine ability. They have alwaies their hour, that they may ever be ready to let us enter. And whereas she has willed our appetites should make apparant show and declaration, she caused theirs to be concealed and inward: and has furnished them with parts unfit for ostentation, and only for defense. Such prankes as this we must leave to the Amazonian liberty. Alexander the great, marching through Hircania, Thalestris, Queen of the Amazones, came to meet him with thre hundred lances of her sex, all well mounted and compleately armed, having left the residue of a great army, that followed her, beyond the neighbouring mountaines. And thus aloud, that all might hear, she bespake him: That the far-resounding fame of his victories and matchles valor had brought her thither to see him, and to offer him her means and forces for the advancing and furthering of his enterprises. And finding him so fair, so young and strong, she, who was perfectly accomplished in all his qualities, advised him to lie with her, that so there might be borne of the most valiant woman in the world, and only valiant man then living, some great and rare creature for posterity. Alexander thanked her for the rest, but to take leisure for her last demands accomplishment, he staide thirteene days in that place, during which he revelled with as much glee, and feasted with as great jollity, as possibly could be devised, in honor and favor of so courageous a Princess. We are well-nigh in all things parciall and corrupted Judges of their action, as no doubt they are of ours. I allow of truth as well when it hurts me as when it helps me. It is a foul disorder, that so often urgeth them unto change, and hinders them from setting their affection on any one subject: as we see in this Goddesse, to whom they impute so many changes and severall friends. But withall it is against the nature of love not to be violent, and against the condition of violence to be constant. And those who wonder at it exclaime it against it, and in women search for the causes of this infirmity, as incredible and unnaturall: why see they not how often without any amazement and exclaiming, themselves are possessed and infected with it? I[t] might happily seem more strange to find any constant stay in them. It is not a passion meerely corporeall. If no end be found in coveteousnesse, nor limit in ambition, assure your self there is nor end nor limit in letchery. It yet continueth after saciety: nor can any man prescribe it or end or constant satisfaction. It ever goeth on beyond its possession, beyond it’s bounds. And if constancy be perhaps in some sort more pardonable in them then in us, They may readily alleage against us our ready inclination unto daily variety and new ware; And secondly alleage without us, that they buy a pigge in a poake. Ione, Queene of Naples caused Andreosse her first husband to be strangled and hanged out of the bars of his window, with a corde of Silke and golde woven with her own hands; because in bed business she found neither his members nor endevours answerable the hope she had conceived of him, by viewing his stature, beauty, youth, and disposition, by which she had formerly been surprised and abused. That action has in it more violence then passion; so that on their part at least necessity is ever provided for: on our behalfe it may happen otherwise. Therefore Plato by his laws did very wisely establish, that before marriages, the better to decide its opportunity, competent Judges might be appointed to make view of young men which pretended the same, all naked: and of maidens but to the waste: in making trial of us, they happily find us not worthy their choise: Experta latus, madidoque simillima loro Inguina, nec lassa stare coacta manu Deserit imbelles thalamos. -- Marti. vii. Epig. lvii. 3. It is not sufficient that will keep a lively course: weakenesse and incapacity may lawfully breake wedlock: Et quærendum aliunde foret neruosius illud Quod posset Zonam soluere virgineam. -- Catul. Eleg. iii. 27. Why not, and according to measure, an amorous intelligence, more licentious and more active? Si blando nequeat superesse labori. -- Virg. Georg. iii. 127. If it cannot outlast, labor with pleasure past. But is it not great impudency to bring our imperfections and weakenesse, in place where we desire to please, and leave good report and commendation behind us? for the little I now stand in need of, ------ ad unum Mollis opus. Unable to hold out, one only busie bout, I would not importune any one whom I am to reverence. -----fuge suspicari, Cuius undenum trepidavit ætas Claudere lustrum. -- Hor. Car. ii. Od. iv. 22. Him of suspition clears, Whom age has brought well neare To five and fifty yeare. Nature should have been pleased to have made this age miserable, without making it also ridiculous. I hate to see one for an inch of wretched vigor, which enflames him but thrice a week, take-on and swagger as fiercely as if he has some great and lawfull dayes-work in his belly; a right blast or puffe of winde: and admire his itching, so quick and nimble, all in a moment to be lubberly squat and benumbed. This appetite should only belong to the blossom of a prime youth. Trust not unto it, thogh you see it second that indefatigable, full, constant and swelling heate, that is in you: for truly it will leave you at the best, and when you shall most stand in neede of it. Send it rather to some tender, irresolute and ignorant girle, which yet trembleth for fear of the rod, and that will blush at it, Indum sanguineo veluti violaverit ostro Si quis ebur, vel mista rubent ubi lilia, multa Alba rosa. -- Virg. Æn. xii. 67. As if the Indian Ivory one should taint With bloody Scarlet-graine, or Lillies paint, White entermixt with red with Roses enter-spred. Who can stay until the next morrow, and not die for shame, the disdaine of those love sparkling eyes, privie to his faintnesse, dastardise and impertinencie: El taciti fecere tamen conuitia vultus: -- Ovid. Am. i. El. vii. 21. The face though silent, yet silent upbraydes it: he never felt the sweet contentment, and the sense-mooving earnestness to have beaten and tarnished them by the vigorous exercise of an officious and active night. When I have perceived any of them weary of me, I have not presently accused her lightnes: but made question whether I had not more reason to quarrell with nature, for handling me so unlawfully and uncivilly, Si non longa satis, si non bene mentula crassa: Nimirum sapiunt videntque paruam Matronæ quoque mentuiam illibenter, -- Lus. Priap. penul. 1. ibid. viii. 4. and to my exceeding hurt. Each of my pieces are equally mine, one as another: and no other does more properly make me a man then this. My whole pourtraiture I universally owe unto the world. One wisdom and reach of my lesson is all in truth, in liberty, in essence: disdaining in the catalogue of my true duties, these easy, faint, ordinary and provinciall rules. All natural; constant and general; whereof civility and ceremony are daughters, but bastards. We shall easily have the vices of apparance, when we shall have had those of essence. When we have done with these, we run upon others, if we find need of running. For there is danger that we devise new offices, to excuse our negligence toward natural offices, and to confound them. That is so, we see that in places where faults are bewitchings, bewitchings are but faults. That among nations, where laws of seemelinesse are more rare and slacke, theprimitive laws of common reason are better observed: The innumerable multitude of so manifold duties, stifling, languishing and dispersing our care. The applying of ourselves unto sleight matters, withdraweth us from such as be just. Oh how easy and plausible a course do these sperficiall men undertake, in respect of ours. These are but shadowes under which we shroud, and wherwith we pay one another. But we pay not, but rather heape debt on debt, unto that great and dreadfull judge, who tucks up our clouts and rags from about our privie parts, and is not squeamish to view all over, even to our most inward and secret deformities: a beneficiall decencie of our maidenly bashfulness, could it debar him of this tainted discovery. To conclude, he that could recover or un-besot man, from so scrupulous and verball a superstition, should not much prejudice the world. Our life consisteth partly in folly and partly in wisdom. He that writes of it but reverently and regularly, omits the better moitie of it. I excuse me not unto my self, and if I did, I would rather excuse my excuses then any fault else of mine: I excuse my self of certain humors, which in number I hold stronger then those which are on my side: In consideration of which I will say thus much more (for I desire to please all men, though it be a hard matter: Esse unum hominem accommodatum ad tantam morum ac sermonum et voluntatum varietatem: ’That one man should be applyable to so great variety of manners, speeches and dispositions’) that they are not to blame me, for what I cause auctorities received and approved of many ages, to utter: and that it is not reason, they should for want of ryme deny me the dispensation; which ever some of our churchmen usurpe and enjoy in this season, whereof behold here two, and of the most pert and cocket amongst them: Rimula dispeream, ni mono qramma tua est. Un vit d’amy la contents et bien traicte. How many others more? I love modesty; nor is it from judgement that I have made choise of this kind of scandalous speech: ’tis nature has chosen the same for me; I commend it no more then all formes contrary unto received custom: only I excuse it: and by circumstances as well general as particular, would qualifie the imputation. Well, let us proceed. Whence commeth also the usurpation of sovereign auctority, which you assume unto yourselves, over those that favor you to their cost and prejudice, Si furtiva dedit nigra munuscula nocte, -- Catul. El. iv. 145. If she have giv’n by night, The stolne gift of delight, that you should immediately invest withall the interest, the coldness and a wedlock authority? It is a free bargaine, why do you not undertake it on those termes you would have them to keep? There is no prescription upon voluntarie things. It is against form, yet it is true that I have in my time managed this match (so far as the nature of it would allow) with as much conscience as any other whatsoever, and not without some colour of justice: and have given them no further testimony of mine affection then I sincerely felt: and have lively displaide unto them the declination, vigor and birth of the same; with the fits and deferring of it: A man cannot alwayes keep an even pace, nor ever go to it likewise. I have bin so sparing to promise, that (as I think) I have paid more then either I promised or was due. They have found me faithfull, even to the service of their inconstancy: I say an inconstancy avowed, and sometimes multiplied. I never broke with them, as long as I had any hold, were it but by a threds-end: and whatsoever occasion they have given me by their ficklenes, I never fell off unto contempt and hatred: for such famliarities, though I attaine them on most shamefull conditions, yet do they bind me unto some constant good- will. I have sometime given them a taste of choller and indiscret impatience, upon occasions of their wiles, sleights, close-convayances, controversies and contestations betweene us; for, by complexion, I am subject to hastie and rash motions, which often empeach my traffick, and marre my bargaines, though but meane and of small worth. Have they desired to essay the liberty of my judgement, I never dissembled to give them fatherly counsell and biting advise, and showed myself ready to scratch them where they itched. If I have given them cause to complain of me, it has bin most for finding a love in me, in respect of our modern fashion, foolishly conscientious. I have religiously kept my word in things that I might easily have bin dispensed with. They then yielded sometimes with reputation, and under conditions, which they would easily suffer to be infringed by the conqueror. I have more then once made pleasure in her greatest efforts strike saile unto the interest of their honor: and where reason urged me, armed them against me, so that they guided themselves more safely and severely by my prescriptions, if they once freely yielded unto them, then they could have done by their own. I have as much as I could endevored to take on my self the charge and hazard of our appointments, therby to discharge them from all imputation; and ever contrived our meetings in most hard, strange and unsuspected manner, to be the less mistrusted, and (in my seeming) the more accessible. They are opened, especially in those parts where they suppose themselves most concealed. Things lest feared are lest defended and observed. You may more securely dare what no man thinks you would dare, which by difficulty becometh easy. Never had man his approches more impertinently genitale. This way to love is more according to discipline. But how ridiculous unto our people, and of how small effect, who better knowes then I? I will not repent me of it: I have no more to lose by the matter. -----me tabula sacer Votiva paries, indicat uvida, Suspendisse potenti Vestimenta maris Deo. -- Hor. Car. i. Od. v. 13. By tables of the vows which I did owe Fastened thereto the sacred wall does showe; I have hung up my garments water-wet, Unto that God whose power on seas is great. It is now high time to speak plainely of it. But even as to another, I would perhaps say: My friend you dotest, the love of your times has small affinity with faith and honesty: -----hæc si tu postules Ratione certa facere, nihilo plus agas, Quam si des operam; ut cum ratione insanias. -- Ter. Eunuc. act. i. sc. 1. If this you would by reason certain make, You do no more then if the paines you take To be stark mad, and yet to think it reason fit. And yet if I were to beginne anew, it should be by the very same path and progresse, how fruitlesse soever it might proove unto me, Insufficiency and sottishnesse are commendable in a discommendable action. As much as I separate my self from their humor in that, so much I approach unto my own. Moreover, I did never suffer my self to be wholly given over to that sport; I therewith pleased, but forgot not my self. I ever kept that little understanding and discretion which nature has bestowed on me, for their service and mine; some motion towards it, but no dotage. My conscience also was engaged therein, even unto incontinency and excess, but never unto ingratitude, treason, malice, or cruelty. I bought not the pleasure of this vice at all rates, and was content with its own and simple cost. Nullum intra se vitium est: (Sen. Epi. xcv.) ’There is no vice contained in itself.’ I hate almost likewise a crouching and dull lasinesse and a toilesome and thorny working. The one pincheth, the other dulleth me. I love wounds as much as bruses, and blood wipes as well as dry-blowes. I had in the practice of this solace, when I was fitter for it, an even moderation betweene these two extremities. Love is a vigilant, lively, and blithe agitation: I was neither troubled nor tormented with it; But heated and distempred by it. There we must make a stay; It is only hurtful unto fooles. A young man demanded of the Philosopher Panetius, whether it would beseeme a wise man to be in love; Let wise men alone (quoth he) but for you and me that are not so, it were best not to engage our selves into so stirring and violent a humor, which makes us slaves to others and contemptible unto ourselves. He said true, for we ought not entrust a matter so dangerous unto a mind that has not wherewith to sustain the approaches of it, nor effectually to quaile the speach of Agesilaus, That wisdom and love cannot live together. It is a vain occupation (’tis true), unseemely, shamefull and lawlesse: But using it in this manner, I esteeme it wholsome and fit to rouze a dull spirit and a heavy body: and as a physician experienced, I would prescribe the same unto a man of my complexion and form, as soone as any other receipt to keep him awake and in strength, when he is well in years; and delay him from the gripings of old age. As long as we are but in the suburbes of it, and that our pulse yet beateth, Dum nona canines, dum prima et recta senectus, Dum superest Lachesi quod torqueat, et pedibus me Porto meis, nullo dextram subeunte bacillo. -- Juven. Sat. iii. 26. While hoarie haires are new, and ould-age fresh and straight, While Lachesis has yet to spin, while I my waight Beare on my feete, and stand, without staffe in my hand. We had need to be solicited and tickled, by some biting agitation, as this is. See but what youth, vigor and jollity it restored unto wise Anacreon. And Socrates, when he was elder then I am, speaking of an amourous object: leaning (saies he) shoulder to shoulder, and approaching my head unto his, as [we] were both together looking upon a book, I felt, in truth, a sudden tingling or prickling in my shoulder, like the biting of some beast, which more then five days after tickled me, whereby a continuall itching glided into my heart. But a casual touch, and that but in a shoulder, to enflame, to distemper and to distract a mind, enfeebled, tamed and cooled through age; and of all humane mindes the most reformed. And why not I pray you? Socrates was but a man, and would neither be nor seem to be other. Philosophie contends not against natural delights, so that due measure be joined therewith; and alloweth the moderation, not the shunning of them. The efforts of her resistance are employed against strange and bastard or lawlesse ones. She says that the bodies appetites ought not to be encreased by the mind; and wittily adviseth us, that we should not excite our hunger by saciety; not to stuffe, insteed of filling our bellies: to avoide all jovissance that may bring us to want: and shunne the meat and drink which may make us hungry or thirstie. As in the service of love, she appoints us to take an object that only may satisfie the bodies neede without once moving the mind, which is not there to have any doing, but only to follow and simply to assist the body. But have I not reason to think that theseprecepts, which (in mine opinion are elsewhere somewhat rigorous) have reference unto a body which does his office; and that a dejected one, as a weakned stomack, may be excused if he cherish and sustain the same by arte, and by the entercouse of fantazie, to restore it the desires, the delights and blithnesse, which of itself it has lost. May we not say that there is nothing in us, during this earthly prison, simply corporall, or purely spirituall? and that injuriously we dismember a living man? thatthere is reason we should carrie ourselves in the use of pleasure, at least as favourably as we do in the pangs of grief? For example, it was vehement, even unto perfection, in the soules of Saints, by repentance. The body had naturally a part therein, by the right of their combination, and yet might have but little share in the cause: and were not contented that it should simply follow and assist the afflicted soul: they have tormented the body itself with convenient and sharpe punishments; to the end that one with the other, the body and the soul might a vie plunge man into sorrow so much the more saving, by how much the more smarting. In like case, in corporal pleasures, is it not injustice to quaile and coole the mind, and say, it must thereunto be entrained, as unto a forced bond or servile necessity? She should rather hatch and cherish them, and offer and invite itself unto them; the charge of swaying rightly belonging to her. Even as in my conceit, it is her part, in her proper delights, to inspire and infuse into the body all sense or feeling which his condition may bear, and indevour that they may be both sweet and healthy for him. For, as they say, ’tis good reason, that the body follow not his appetites to the mindes prejudice or dammage. But why is it not likewise reason that the mind should not follow hers to the bodies danger and hurt? I have no other passion that keeps me in breath. What avarice, ambition, quarels, sutes in law, or other contentions work and effect in others who as my self have no assigned vacation or certain leisure, love would performe more commodiously: it would restore me the vigilancy, sobriety, grace and care of my person; and assure my countenance against the wrinckled frowns of age (those deformed and wretched frownes) which else would blemish and deface the same; it would reduce me to serious, to sound and wise studies, whereby I might procure more love, and purchase more estimation: it would purge my mind from despaire of itself, and of its use, acquainting the same again with it self: It would divert me from thousands of irksome tedious thoughts, and melancholy carking cares, wherewith the doting idlenesse and crazed condition of our age does charge and comber us: It would restore and heat, though but in a dreame, the blood which nature forsaketh: It would uphold the drooping chinne, and somewhat strengthen or lengthen the shrunken sinews, decaied vigor, and dulled lives-blithenesse of silly wretched man, who gallops apace to his ruine. But I am not ignorant how hard a matter it is to attaine to such a commodity: through weakenesse and long experience, our taste is grown more tender, more choise, and more exquisite. We challenge most when we bring least; we are most desirous to choose when we least deserve to be accepted: And knowing ourselves to be such, we are less hardy and more distrustfull: Nothing can assure us to be beloved, seeing our condition and their quality. I am ashamed to be in the companie of this greene, blooming and boyling youth; Cujus in indomito constantior inguine nervus, Quam nova collibus arbor inhæret: -- Hor. Epod. xii. 19. Why should we present our wretchednesse amid this their jollity? Possint ut juvenes visere fervidi Multo non sine risu, Dilapsam in cineres facem, -- Hor. Car. iv. Od. xiii. 26. That hot young men may go and see, Not without sport and mery glee, Their firebrands turn’d to ashes be. They have both strength and reason on their side; let us give them place: we have no longer holde fast. This bloome of budding beauty loves not to be handled by such nummed and so clomsie bands, nor would it be dealt-with by means purely materiall or ordinary stuffe. For, as that ancient Philosopher answered one that mocked him because he could not obtaine the favor of a yongling, whom he suingly pursued: ’My friend,’ quoth he, ’the hooke bites not at such fresh cheese.’ It is a commerce needing relation and mutual correspondency: other pleasures that we receive may be requitted by recompences of different nature; but this cannot be repaid but with the very same kind of coyne. Verily, the pleasure I do others in this sport does more sweetly tickle my imagination then that is done unto me. Now if no generous mind can receive pleasure where he returneth none, it is a base mind that would have all duty and delights to feed with conference those under whose charge he remaineth. There is no beauty, nor favor, nor familiarity so exquisite, which a gallant mind should desire at this rate. Now, if women can do us no good but in pittie, I had much rather not to live at all then to live by almes. I would I had the priviledge to demande of them, in the same stile I have heard some beg in Italy: Fate beno per voi. ’Do some good for your self’; or after the manner that Cyrus exhorted his soldiers: ’Whosoever loves me, let him follow me.’ Consort your self, will some say to me, with those of your own condition, whom the company of like fortune will yield of more easy accesse. Oh sottish and wallowish composition! -----nolo Barbam vellere mortito leoni. -- Mar. x. Epig. xc. 9. I will not pull (though not a fearde), When he is dead, a Lion’s beard. Xenophon useth for an objection and accusation against Menon, that in his love he dealt with fading objects. I take more sensuall pleasure by only viewing the mutual, even- proporcioned and delicate commixture of two yong beauties; or only to consider the same in mine imagination, then if my self should be second in a lumpish, sad and disproporcioned conjunction. I resigne such distasted and fantastic appetites unto the Emperor Galba, who medled with none but cast, worne, hard-old flesh; And to that poore slave, O ego dii faciant talem te cernere possim, Charaque mutatis oscula ferre comis, Amplectique meis corpus non pingue lacertis. -- Ovid. Pont. i. El. v. 49. Gods graunt I may beholde you in such case, And kisse your chang’d locks with my dearest grace, And with mine arms your limbs not fat embrace. And amongst blemishing-deformities, I deem artificiall and forced beautie to be of the chiefest. Emanez, a young lad of Chios, supposing by gorgeous attires to purchase the beauty which nature denied him, came to the philosopher Arcesilaus, and asked of him whether a wise man could be in love or no. ’Yes, marrie,’ quoth he, ’so it were not with a painted and sophisticate beauty, as thine is.’ The fowlenesse of an old known woman is, in my seeming not so aged or so ill-favoured as one that’s painted and sleeked. Shall I bouldly speak it, and not have my throate cut for my labor? Love is not properly nor naturally in season but in the age next unto infancy. Quam si puellarum insereres choro, Mire sagaces falleret hospites. Discrimen obscurum solutis Crinibus, ambiguoque vultu. -- Hor. Car. ii. Od. v. 12. Whom if you should in crue of wenches place, With hair loose-hanging, and ambiguous face, Strangely the undiscern’d distinction might Deceive a thousand strangers of sharpe sight. No more is perfect beauty. For, whereas Homer extends it until such time as the chinne begins to bud, Plato himself has noted the same for very rare, and the cause for which the Sophister Dion termed youthes budding hayres, Aristogitons and Harmodii is notoriously known. In man-hoode I find it already to be somewhat out of date, much more in old age. Importunus enim transuolat aridas Qærcus. -- Ibid. iv. Od. xiii. 9. Importune love does ever flie The Okes with withered old-age drie. And Margaret, Queen of Navarre, lengthens much (like a woman) the priviledge of women; Ordaining thirty years to be the season for them to change the title of fair into good.The shorter possession we allow it over our lives the better for us. Behold its behaviour. It is a prin-cock boy, who, in his schoole, knows not how far one proceeds against all order: study, exercise, custom and practise, are paths to insufficiency: the novices bear all the sway. Amor ordinem nescit: ’Love knowes or keeps no order.’ Surely its course has more garbe when it is commixt with unadvisednes and trouble: faults and contrary successes give it edge and grace: so it be eager and hungry, it little importeth whether it be prudent. Observe but how he staggers, stumbleth and fooleth; you fetter and shackle him when you guide him by arte and discretion, and you force his sacred liberty when you submit him to those bearded, grim, and tough-hard hands. Moreover, I often hear them display this intelligence as absolutely spiritual, disdaining to draw into consideration the interest which all the sences have in the same. All serveth to the purpose. But I may say that I have often seen some of us excuse the weaknesse of their minds in favor of their corporall beauties; but I never saw them yet, that in behalfe of the mindes-beauties, how sound and ripe soever they were, would afford an helping hand unto a body that never so little falleth into declination. Why does not some one of them long to produce that noble Socraticall brood; or breed that precious gem between the body and the mind, purchasing with the price of her thighes a Philosophicall and spirituall breed and intelligence, which is the highest rate she can possibly value them at? Plato appointeth in his laws that he who performeth a notable and worthy exploite in war, during the time of that expedition, should not be denied a kisse or refused any other amorous favor of whomsoever he shall please to desire it, without respect either of his ill-favourdnes, deformity, or age. What he deemeth so just and allowable in commendation of Military valor, may not the same be thought as lawfull in commendation or some other worth? and why is not some one of them possessed with the humor to preoccupate on her companions the glory of this chaste love? chaste I may well say: -----nam si quando ad prælia ventum est, Ut quondam stipulis magnus sine viribus ignis In cassum furit. -- Virg. Georg. iii. 98. If once it come to handy-gripes; as great, But forcelesse fire in stubble; so his heate Rageth amaine, but all in vain. Vices smothered in ones thought are not the woorst. To conclude this notable commentarie, escaped from me by a flux of babling, a flux sometimes as violent as hurtful, Ut missum sponsi furtivo munere malum, Procurrit casto virginis e gremio: Quod miseræ oblitæ molli sub veste locatum, Dum adventu matris prosilit, excutitur, Atque illud prono præceps agitur decursu, Huic manat tristi conscius ore rubor. -- Catul. El. i. 19. As when some fruit by stealth sent from her friend, From chaste lap of a virgin does descend, Which by her, under her soft aprone plast, Starting at mothers coming thence is cast: And trilling down in haste does head-long go, A guilty blush in her sad face does flo. I say that both male and female are cast in one same moulde; instruction and custom excepted, there is no great difference betweene them. Plato calleth them both indifferently to the society of all studies, exercises, charges and functions of war and peace in his Commonwealth. And the Philosopher Antisthenes took away al distinction betweene their virtue and ours. It is much more easy to accuse the one sexe then to excuse the other. It is that which some say proverbially: Ill may the Kill call the Oven burnt tail. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER VI: OF COACHES CHAPTER VI: OF COACHES T IS easy to verifie, that excellent authors’ writing of causes, do not only make use of those which they imagine true, but eftsoones of such as themselves believe not: always provided they have some invention and beautie. They speak sufficiently, truly and profitably, if they speak ingeniously. We cannot assure ourselves of the chief cause: we hudle up a many together, to see whether by chance it shall be found in that number: Namque unam dicere causam, Non satis est, verum plures, unde una tamen sit. -- LUCR 1. vi. 700. Enough it is not one cause to devise, But more, whereof that one may yet arise. Will you demand of me whence this custom arises, to blesse and say God helpe to those that sneese? We produce three sortes of winde: that issuing from belowe is too undecent; that from the mouth implieth some reproach of gourmandise; the third is sneesing: and because it commeth from the head, and is without imputation, we thus kindly entertaine it: smile not at this subtilty, it is (as some say) Aristotles. Me seems to have read in Plutarch (who of all the authors I know, has best commixt arte with nature, and coupled judgement with learning), where he yieldeth a reason why those which travell by sea do sometimes feel such qualmes and risings of the stomack, saying, that it proccedeth of a kind of fear: having found-out some reason by which he prooveth that fear may cause such an effect. My self, who am much subject unto it, know well that this cause does nothing concerne me. And I know it, not by argument, but by necessary experience without alleging what some have tolde me, that the like does often happen unto beasts, namely, unto swine, when they are farthest from apprehending any danger: and what an acquaintance of mine has assured me of himself, and who is greatly subject unto it, that twice or thrice in a tempestous storme, being surprised with exceeding fear, all manner of desire or inclination to vomit had left him. As to that ancient good fellow; Peius vexabat quam ut periculum mihi succurreret: ’I was worse vexed then that danger could helpe me.’ I never apprehended fear upon the water, nor any where else (yet have I often had just cause offred me, if death itself may give it) which either might trouble or astony me. It proceedeth sometimes as well from want of judgement as from lacke of courage. All the dangers I have had have been when mine eyes were wide-open, and my sight clear, sound and perfect. For even to fear, courage is required. It has sometimes steaded me, in respect of others, to direct and keep my flight in order, that so it might be, if not without fear, at least without dismay and astonishment. Indeed, it was moved, but not amazed nor distracted. Undanted mindes march further, and represent flight, not only temperate, setled and sound, but also fierce and bold. Report we that which Alcibiades relateth of Socrates his companion in arms. I found (says he) after the rout and discomfiture of our army, both him and Lachez in the last rank of those that ranne away, and with all safety and leisure considered him, for I was mounted upon an excellent good horse, and he on foote, and so had we combated all day. I noted first, how in respect of Lachez, he showed both discreet judgement and undanted resolution: then I observed the undismaide bravery of his march, nothing different from his ordinary pace: his looke orderly and constant, duly observing and heedily judging what ever passed round about him: sometimes viewing the one, and sometimes looking on the other both friends and enemies, with so composed a manner, that he seemed to encourage the one and menace the other, signifying, that whosoever should attempt his life must purchase the same or his blood at a high-valued rate; and thus they both saved themselves, for men do not willingly graple with these, but follow such as show or fear or dismay. See here the testimony of that renowned Captain, who teacheth us what we daily find by experience, that there is nothing does sooner cast us into dangers then an inconsiderate greedinesse to avoide them. Quo timoris minus est, eo minus ferme periculi est: ’The less fear there is, most commonly the less danger there is.’ Our people is to blame to say such a one feareth death, when it would signifie that he thinkes on it and does foresee the same. Foresight does equally belong as well to that which concerneth us in good as touch us in evil. To consider and judge danger is in some sort not to be danted at it. I do not find my self sufficiently strong to withstand the blow and violence of this passion of fear, or of any other impetuosity; where I once therewith vanquished and deterred, I could never safely recover my self. He that should make my mind forgoe her footing could never bring her unto her place again. She does over lively sound and over deepely search into her self, and therefore never suffers the wound which pierced the same to be throughly cured and consolidated. It has been happy for me that no infirmity could ever yet displace her. I oppose and present myself in the best ward I have against all charges and assaults that beset me. Thus the first that should bear me away would make me unrecoverable. I encounter not two which way soever spoile should enter my hold, there am I open and remedilesly drowned. Epicurus says that a wise man can never pass from one state to its contrary. I have some opinion answering his sentence, that he who has once been a very foole shall at no time proove very wise. God sends my cold answerable to my cloths, and passions answering the means I have to endure them. Nature having discovered me on one side, has covered me on the other. Having disarmed me of strength, she has armed me with insensibility, and a regular or soft apprehension. I cannot long endure (and less could in my youth) to ride either in coach or litter, or to go in a boat; and both in the citty and country I hate all manner of riding but a horse-back; And can less endure a litter then a coach, and by the same reason more easily a rough agitation upon the water, whence commonly proceedeth fear, then the soft stirring a man shall feel in calme weather. By the same easy gentle motion which the oares give, convaying the boat under us, I wot not how I feel both my head intoxicated and my stomacke distempered, as I cannot likewise abide a shaking stoole under me. Whenas either the saile, or the gliding course of the water does equaly carry us away, or that we are but towed, that gently gliding and even agitation does no whit distemper or hurt me. It is an interrupted and broken motion that offends me, and more when it is languishing. I am not able to display its form. Phisitions have taught me to bind and gird my self with a napkin or swath round about the lower part of my belly as a remedy for this accident, which as yet I have not tride, beeing accustomed to wrestle and withstand such defects as are in me, and tame them by my self. Were my memory sufficiently informed of them, I would not think my time lost here to set down the infinite variety which histories present unto us of the use of coaches in the service of war; diverse according to the nations, and different according to the ages, to my seeming of great effect and necessity. So that it is wondrously strange how we have lost all true knowledge of them; I will only aleadge this, that even lately in our fathers time, the Hungarians did very availefully bring them into fashion, and profitably set them a work against the Turks; every one of them containing a Targattier and a Muskettier, with a certain number of harquebuses or calivers, ready charged, and so ranged that they might make good use of them, and all over covered with a pavesado after the manner of a Galliotte. They made the front of their battaile with three thousand such coaches, and after the Cannon had playd, caused them to discharge and shoote off a volie of small shott upon their enemies before they should know or feel what the rest of the forces could do, which was no small advancement; or if not this, they mainely drove those coaches amidde the thickest of their enemies squadrons, with purpose to breake, disroute, and make waie through them. Besides the benefit and helpe they might make of them in any suspicious or dangerous place, to flanke their troupes marching from place to place; or in hast to encompasse, to embarricado , to cover or fortifie any lodgement or quarter. In my time, a gentleman of quality in one of our frontiers, unwealdie and so burly of body that he could find no horse able to bear his waight, and having a quarrell or deadly fude in hand, was wont to travaile up and down in a coach made after this fashion, and found much ease and good in it. But leave we these warlike coaches, as if their nullity were not sufficiently known by better tokens; The last Kings of our first race were wont to travell in chariots drawne by foure oxen. Mark Antoni was the first that caused himself, accompanied with a minsterell harlot, to be drawne by Lyons fitted to a coach. So did Heliogabalus after him, naming himself Cibele, the mother of the Gods; and also by Tigers, counterfeiting God Bacchus; who sometimes would also be drawne in a coach by two Stagges, and another time by foure mastive dogs; and by foure naked wenches, causing himself to be drawne by them in pompe and state, he being all naked. The emperour Firmus made his coach to be drawne by Estriges of exceeding greatness, so that he rather seemed to flye then to roule on wheeles. The strangenesse of these inventions does bring this other thing unto my fantasie, That it is a kind of pusilanimity in Monarkes, and a testimony that they do not sufficiently know what they are when they labor to show their worth, and endeavour to appeare unto the world by excessive and intolerable expences. A thing which in a strange country might somewhat be excused, but among his native subjects where he swayeth all in all, he draweth from his dignity the extreamest degree of honor that he may possibly attaine unto. As for a gentleman in his own private house to apparrel himself richly and curiously, I deem it a matter vain and superfluous; his house, his houshold, his traine and his kitchin do sufficiently answere for him. The counsell which Isocrates gives to his King (in my conceite) seems to carry some reason, when he wills him to be richly-stored and stately adorned with mooveables and household- stuffe, forasmuch as it is an expence of continuance, and which descendeth even to his posterity or heirs; And to avoyde all magnificences which presently vanish both from custom and memory. I loved when I was a yonger brother to set my self foorth and be gaye in cloathes, though I wanted other necessaries, and it became me well: There are some on whose backes their rich Robes weepe, or as we say their rich cloathes are lyned with heavy debts. We have diverse strange tales of our auncient Kings frugality about their own persons, and in their gifts: great and far renouned Kings both in credit, in valor, and in fortune. Demosthenes mainely combates the law of his City, who assigned their public money to be employed about the stately setting forth of their playes and feasts. He wills that their magnificence should be seen in the quantity of tall ships well manned and appointed, and armies well furnished. And they have reason to accuse Theophrastus, who in his book of riches established a contrary opinion, and upholdeth such a quality of expences to be the true fruit of wealth and plenty. They are pleasures (says Aristotle) that only touch the vulgar and basest communalty, which as soone as a man is satisfied with them, vanish out of mind; and whereof no man of sound judgement or gravity can make any esteeme. The employment of it, as more profitable, just and durable, would seem more royall, worthy and commendable, about ports, havens, fortifications and walles; in sumptuous buildings, in churches, hospitals, colledges, mending of heighwayes and streetes, and such like monuments; in which things Pope Gregory the thirteenth shall leave aye-lasting and commendable memory unto his name; and wherein our Queene Catherine should witnes unto succeeding ages her natural liberality and exceeding bounty, if her means were answerable to her affection. Fortune has much spighted me to hinder the structure and breake-off the finishing of our new bridge in our great City, and before my death to deprive me of all hope to see the great necessity of it set forward again. Moreover, it appeareth unto subjects, spectators of these triumphs, that they have a show made them of their own riches, and that they are feasted at their proper charges; For the people do easily presume of their kings as we do of our servants that they should take care plenteously to provide us of whatsoever we stand in neede of, but that on their behalfe they should no way lay hands on it. And therefore the Emperor Galba sitting at supper, having taken pleasure to hear a musitian play and sing before him, sent for his casket, out of which be took a handful of Crowns and put them into his hand, with these wordes: ’Take this, not as a gift of the public money but of my own private store.’ So is it, that it often commeth to pass, that the common people have reason to grudge, and that their eyes are fedde with that which should feede their belly. Liberality it self, in a sovereign hand, is not in her own luster: private men have more right, and may challenge more interest in her. For, taking the matter exactly as it is, a King has nothing that is properly his own; he oweth even himself to others. Authority is not given in favor of the authorising, but rather in favor of the authorised. A superiour is never created for his own profit, but rather for the benefit of the inferiour; and a Physition is instituted for the sicke, not for himself. All Magistracie, even as each arte, rejects her end out of herself. Nulla ars in se versatur: ’No arte is all in itself.’ Wherefore the governours and overseers of Princes’ childhood or minority, who so earnestly endeavor to imprint this virtue of bounty and liberality in them, and teach them not to refuse any thing, and esteeme nothing so well employed as what they shall give (an instruction which in my dayes I have seen in great credit) either they prefer and respect more their own profit than their masters, or they understand not aright to whom they speak. It is too easy a matter to imprint liberality in him that has wherewith plenteously to satisfie what be desires at other men’s charges. And his estimation being directed not according to the measure of the present, but according to the quality of his means that exerciseth the same, it commeth to prove vain in so puissant hands. They are found to be prodigall before they be liberall. Therefore it is but of small commendation, in respect of other royall vertues; and the only (as said the tyrant Dionysius) that agreed and squared well with tyrannie itself. I would rather teach him the verse of the ancient labourer, τη χειρι δει σπειρειν αλλα η ολω τω θυλακω. -- PLUT. de Athen. ERAS. Chil. iii. cent. i. ad. 32. Not whole sackes, but by the hand A man should sow his seed i’ the land. That whosoever will reape any commodity by it must sow with his hand, and not powre out of a sacke; that corne must be discreetly scattered, and not lavishly dispersed; and that being to give, or, to say better, to pay and restore to such a multitude of People, according as they have deserved, he ought to be a loyall, faithfull, and advised distributer thereof. If the liberality of a Prince be without heedy discretion and measure, I would rather have him covetous and sparing. Princely virtue seems to consist most in justice; and of all parts of justice that does best and most belong to Kings which accompanieth liberality; for they have it particularly reserved to their charge; whereas all other justice they happily exercise the same by the intermission of others. Immoderate bounty is a weake meane to acquire them good will: for it rejects more people than it obtaineth: Quo in plures usus sis, minus in multos uti possis. Quid autem est stultius, quam, quod libenter facias, curare ut id diutius facere non possis? (Cic. Off. 1.) ’The more you have used it to many, the less may you use it to many more; and what is more foolish than what you willingly would do, to provide you can no longer do it?’ And if it be emploied without respect of merit, it shameth him that receiveth the same, and is received without grace. Some Tyrants have been sacrificed to the peoples hatred by the very hands of those whom they had rashly preferred and wrongfully advanced: such kind of men, meaning to assure the possession of goods unlawfully and indirectly gotten, if they show to hold in contempt and hatred him from whom they held them, and in that combine themselves unto the vulgar judgement and common opinion. The subjects of a Prince rashly excessive in his gifts become impudently excessive in begging: they adhere, not unto reason, but unto example. Verily we have often, just cause to blush for our impudency. We are overpaid according to justice, when the recompence equaleth our service; for do we not owe a kind of natural duty to our Princes? If he bear our charge, he does overmuch; it sufficeth if he assist it: the over- plus is called a benefit which cannot be exacted; for the very name of liberality implyeth liberty. After our fashion we have never done; what is received is no more reckoned of: only future liberality is loved: Wherefore the more a Prince does exhaust himself in giving, the more friends he impoverisheth. How should he satisfie intemperate desires which increase according as they are replenished? Whoso has his mind on taking, has it no more on what he has taken. Covetousnesse has nothing so proper as to be ungrateful. The example of Cyrus shal not ill fit this place, for the behoofe of our kings of these days, as a touch-stone, to know whether their gifts be well or ill employed: and make them perceive how much more happily that Emperor did wound and oppresse them than they do. Whereby they are afterward forced to exact and borrow of their unknown subjects, and rather of such as they have wronged and aggrieved than of those they have enriched and done good unto; and receive no aids, where any thing is gratitude, except the name. Croesus upbraided him with his lavish bounty, and calculated what his treasure would amount unto if he were more sparing and close-handed. A desire surprised him to justify his liberality, and dispatching letters over all parts of his dominions to such great men of his estate whom he had particularly advanced, entreated every one to assist him with as much money as they could for an urgent necessitie of his, and presently to send it him by declaration; when all these count- bookes or notes were brought him, each of his friends supposing that it sufficed not to offer him no more than they had received of his bounteous liberality, but adding much of their own unto it, it was found that the said summe amounted unto much more than the niggardly sparing of Croesus. Whereupon Cyrus said: ’I am no less greedy of riches than other Princes, but I am rather a better husband of them. You see with what small venture I have purchased the unvaluable treasure of so many friends, and how much more faithfull treasurers they are to me than mercenary men would be, without obligation and without affection; and my exchequer or treasury better placed than in paltery coafers; by which I draw upon me the hate, the envy and the contempt of other Princes.’ The ancient Emperours were wont to draw som excuse, for the superfluity of their sports and public shewes, for so much as their authority did in some sort depend (at least in apparance) from the will of the Roman people; which from all ages are accustomed to be flattered by such kind of spectacles and excesses. But they were particular ones who had bred this custom to gratifie their con- citizens and fellowes; especially by their purse, by such profusion and magnificence. It was cleane altered when the masters and chief rulers came once to imitate the same. Pecuniarum translatio a justis dominis ad alienos non debet liberalis videri: (Cic. Off. 1.) ’The passing of money from right owners to strangers should not seem liberality.’ Philip, because his son indeavoured by gifts to purchase the good will of the Macedonians, by a letter seemed to be displeased, and chid him in this manner: ’What, would you have your subjects to account you for their purse-bearer, and not repute you for their King? Wilt you frequent and practise them? Then do it with the benefits of your virtue, not with those of your cofers.’ Yet was it a goodly thing to cause a great quantity of great trees, all branchie and greene, to be far brought and planted in plots yielding nothing but dry gravell, representing a wild shady forrest, divided in due seemely proportion; And the first day to put into the same a thousand Estriges, a thousand Stagges, a thousand wild Boares, and a thousand Buckes, yielding them over to be hunted and killed by the common people: the next morrow in the presence of all the assembly to cause a hundred great Lions, a hundred Leopards, and three hundred huge Beares to be baited and tugged in pieces: and for the third day, in bloody manner and good earnest, to make three hundred couple or Gladiators or Fencers to combate and murder one another, as did the Emperor Probus. It was also a goodly show to see those huge Amphitheaters all enchased with rich marble, on the outside curiously wrought with curious statues, and all the inner side glittering with precious and rare embellishments: Balteus en gemmis, en illita porticus auro. A belt beset with gemmes behold, Behold a walke bedawb’d with gold. All the sides round about that great void, replenished and invironed from the ground unto the very top with three or foure score rankes of steps and seates, likewise all of marble covered with fair cushions ----- exeat, inquit, Si pudor est, et de pulvino surgat equestri, Cujus res legi non sufficit. -- Juven. Sat. iii. 153. If shame there be, let him be gone, he cries, And from his knightly cushion let him rise, Whose substance to the law does not suffice. Where might conveniently be placed an hundred thousand men, and all sit at ease. And the plaine-ground-work of it, where sports were to be acted, first by Art to cause the same to open and chap in sunder with gaps and cranishes representing hollow cavernes, which vomited out the beasts appointed for the spectacle; that ended, immediately to overflow it all with a main deepe sea, fraught with store of sea- monsters and other strange fishes , all over-laid with goodly tall ships, ready rigd and appointed to represent a Sea-fight; and thirdly, suddenly to make it smooth and drie again for the combate of Gladiators; and fourthly, being forthwith cleansed, to strewe it over with Vermilion and Storax, insteade of graven, for the erecting of a solemn banket for all that infinite number of people: the last act of one only day. ----- quoties nos descendentis arenæ Vidimus in partes, ruptaque voraqine terræ Emersisse feras, et ijsdem sæpe latebris Aurea cum croceo creuerunt arbuta libro. Nec solum nobis silvestria cernere monstra Contigit equoreos; ego cum certantibus ursis Spectavi vitulos, et equorum nomine dignum, Sed deforme pecus. How oft have we beheld wild beasts appeare From broken gulfes of earth, upon some parte Of sande that did not sinke? how often there And thence did golden boughs ore saf fron’d starte? Nor only saw we monsters of the wood, But I have seen Sea-calves whom Beares withstood And such a kind of beast as might be named A horse, but in most foul proportion framed. They have sometimes caused an high steepy mountaine to arise in the midst of the sayd Amphitheaters, all over-spred with fruitfull and flourishing trees of all sortes, on the top whereof gushed out streames of water as from out the source of a purling spring. Other times they have produced therein a great tall Ship floating up and down, which of itself opened and split asunder, and after it had disgorged from out its bulke foure or five hundred wild beasts to be baited, it closed and vanished away of it self, without any visible helpe. Sometimes from out the bottome of it they caused streakes and purlings of sweet water to spoute up, bubling to the highest top of the frame, and gently watring, sprinkling and refreshing that infinite multitude. To keep and cover themselves from the violence of the wether, they caused that huge compasse to be all over-spred, sometimes with purple sailes, all curiously wrought with the needle, sometimes of silke and of some other colour in the twinkling of an eye, as they pleased they displaid and spred, or drewe and pulled them in again. Quamvis non modico caleant spectacula sole Vela reducuntur cum venit Hermogenes. -- Mart. xii. Epig. 29, 15. Though fervent Sunne make’t hotte to see a play, When linnen thieves come, sailes are kept away. The nets likewise, which they used to put before the people to save them from harm and violence of the baited beasts, were woven with golde. ----- auro quoque torta refulgent Retia. Nets with gold enterlaced, Their shewes with glittring graced. If any thing be excusable in such lavish excesses it is where the invention and strangenesse breedeth admiration, and not the costlie charge. Even in those vanities, we may plainely perceive how fertile and happy those former ages were of other manner of wittes then ours are. It happens of this kind of fertilitie as of all other productions of nature. We may not say what nature employed then the utmost of her power. We go not, but rather creepe and stagger here and there: we go our pace. I imagine our knowledge to be weake in all senses: we neither discerne far- forward, nor see much backward. It embraceth little and liveth not long: It is short both in extension of time and in amplenesse of matter or invention. Vixere fortes ante Agamemnona Multi, sed omnes illachrymabiles Urgentur, ignotique longa Nocte. -- HOR. Car. 1. iv. Od. ix. 25. Before great Agamemnon and the rest Many liv’d valiant, yet are all supprest, Unmoan’d, unknown, in darke oblivious nest. Et supera bellum Troianum et funera Troiæ, Multi alias alii quoque res cecinere poetæ. -- LUCR. 1. v. 326. Beside the Trojan war, Troyes funerall night, Of other things did other poets write. And Solons narration concerning what he had learned of the Egyptian Priests of their states, long-life and manner how to learne and preserve strange or forraine histories, in mine opinion is not a testimony to be refused in this consideration. Si interminatant in omnes partes magnitudinem regionum videremus, et temporum in quam se iniiciens animus et intendens, ita late longeque peregrinatur, ut nullam oram ultimi videat in qua possit insistere: In hæc immensitate infinita vis innumerabilium appareret formarum: (CIC. Nat. Deo. i. ) ’If we behold an unlimited greatness on all sides both of regions and times, whereupon the mind casting itself and intentive does travell far and neare, so as it sees ----- 1 2 3 no bounds of what is last, whereon it may insist; in this infinite immensity there would appeare a multitude of innumerable formes.’ If whatsoever has come unto us by report of what is past where true and known of any body, it would be less then nothing, in respect of that which is unknown. And even of this image of the world, which while we live therein, glideth and passeth away, how wretched, weake and how short is the knowledge of the most curious? Not only of the particular events which fortune often maketh exemplar and of consequence; but of the state of mighty commonwealths, large Monarkies and renowned nations, there escapeth our knowledge a hundred times more then commeth unto our notice. We keep a coile and wonder at the miraculous invention of our artilerie, and amazed at the rare devise of Printing; when as unknown to us, other men, and an other end of the world named China, knew and had perfect use of both a thousand years before. If we sawe as much of this vaste world as we see but a least part of it, it is very likely we should perceive a perpetuall multiplicity and over-rouling vicissitude of formes. Therein is nothing singular and nothing rare, if regard be had unto nature, or to say better, if relation be had unto our knowledge; which is a weake foundation of our rules, and which does commonly present us a right-false Image of things. How vainely do we now-adayes conclude the declination and decrepitude of the world, by the foolish arguments we drawe from our own weaknesse, drooping and declination: Jamque adeo afecta est ætas, affetaque tellus: -- LUCR. ii. 1159. And now both age and land So sicke affected stand. And as vainly did another conclude its birth and youth by the vigor he perceiveth in the wits of his time, abounding in novelties and invention of diverse Arts: Verum ut opinor, habet novitatem summa, recensque Natura est mundi, neque pridem exordia cepit; Quare etiant quædam nunc artes expoliuntur, Nunc etiam augescunt, nunc addita navigiis sunt Multa. -- Ibid. v. 330. But all this world is new, as I suppose, Worlds nature fresh, nor lately it arose Whereby some arts refined are in fashion, And many things now to our navigation Are added, daily grown to augmentation. Our world has of late discovered another (and who can warrant us whether it be the last of his brethren, since both the Damons, the Sibylles, and all we have hitherto been ignorant of this? no less- large, fully-peopled, all-things- yielding, and mighty in strength than ours; nevertheless so new and infantine, that he is yet to learne his A. B. C. It is not yet full fifty yeeres that he knew neither letters, nor waight, nor measures, nor apparell, nor corne, nor vines; But was all naked, simply-pure, in Natures lappe, and lived but with such means and food as his mother-nurce affoorded him. If we conclude aright of our end, and the foresaid Poet of the infancie of his age, this late-world shall but come to light when ours shall fall into darknesse. The whole Universe shall fall into a palsey or convulsion of sinnowes: one member shall be maimed or shrunken, another nimble and in good plight. I fear that by our contagion we shall directly have furthered his declination and hastened his ruine and that we shall too dearely have sold him our opinions, our new-fangles and our Arts. It was an unpolluted, harmelesse, infant world; yet have we not whipped and submitted the same unto our discipline, or schooled him by the advantage of our valor or natural forces; nor have we instructed him by our justice and integrity, nor subdued by our magnanimity. Most of their answers, and a number of the negotiations we have had with them, witness that they were nothing short of us, not beholding to us for any excellency of natural wit or perspicuitie concerning pertinency. The wonderful, or as I may call it, amazement- breeding magnificence of the never-like seen cities of Cusco and Mexico, and amongst infinite such like things, the admirable Garden of that King, where all the Trees, the fruits, the Hearbes and Plants, according to the order and greatness they have in a Garden, were most artificially framed in gold; as also in his Cabinet; all the living creatures that his Countrey or his Seas produced, were cast in gold; and the exquisite beauty of their workes, in precious Stones, in Feathers, in Cotton and in Painting, show that they yielded as little unto us in cunning and industrie. But concerning unfained devotion, awefull observance of laws, unspotted integrity, bounteous liberality, due loyalty and free liberty, it has greatly availed us that we had not so much as they: By which advantage they have lost, castaway, sold, undone and betraied themselves. Touching hardinesse and undaunted courage, and as for matchlesse constancy, unmooved assurednesse, and undismaied resolution against pain, smarting, famine and death itself, I will not fear to oppose the examples which I may easily find amongst them, to the most famous ancient examples we may with all our industrie discover in all the Annales and memories of our knowen old World. For as for those which have subdued them, let them lay aside the wiles, the policies and stratagems which they have emploied to cozen, to cunny-catch, and to circumvent them; and the just astonisbment which those nations might justly conceive, by seeing so unexpected an arrivall of bearded men, diverse in language, in habite, in religion, in behaviour, in form, in countenance, and from a part of the world so distant, and where they never heard any habitation was: mounted upon great and unknowen monsters, against those who had had never so much as seen any horse, and less any beast whatsoever apt to bear, or taught to carry either man or burden; covered with a shining and harde skinne, and armed with slicing-keene weapons and glittering armour: against them, who for the wonder of the glistring of a looking-glasse or of a plaine knife would have changed or given inestimable riches in Gold, Precious Stones and Pearles; and who had neither the skill nor the matter wherewith at any leisure they could have pierced our steele: to which you may adde the flashing-fire and thundring roare of shotte and Harguebuses; able to quell and daunt even Cæsar himself, had he been so sodainely surprised and as little experienced as they were; and thus to come unto and assault silly-naked people, saving where the invention of weaving of Cotton cloath was known and used; for the most altogether unarmed, except some bowes, stones, staves and woodden bucklers; unsuspecting poore people, surprised under colour of amity and well-meaning faith overtaken by the curiosity to see strange and unknown things: I say, take this disparity from the conquerors, and you deprive them of all the occasions and cause of so many unexpected victories. When I consider that stern-untamed obstinacy and undanted vehemence wherewith so many thousands of men, of women and children, do so infinite times present themselves unto inevitable dangers, for the defense of their Gods and liberty: This generous obstinacy to endure all extremities, all difficulties and death, more easily and willingly, then basely to yielde unto their domination, of whom they have so abhominably been abused: some of them choosing rather to starve with hunger and fasting, being taken, then to accept food at their enemies handes, so basely victorious: I perceive, that whoseever had undertaken them man to man, without ods of arms, of experience or of number, should have had as dangerous a war, or perhaps more, as any we see amongst us. Why did not so glorious a conquest happen under Alexander, or during the time of the ancient Greekes and Romanes? or why befell not so great a change and alteration of Empires and people under such hands as would gently have polished, reformed and incivilized what in them they deemed to be barbarous and rude: or would have nourished and fostered those good seedes which nature had there brought foorth: adding not only to the manuring of their grounds and ornaments of their cities such artes as we had, and that no further then had been necessary for them, but there-withall joyning unto the originall vertues of the country those of the ancient Greeks and Romanes? What reputation and what reformation would all that far spredding world have found, if the examples, demeanors and pollicies wherewith we first presented them had called and allured those uncorrupted nations to the admiration and imitation of virtue, and had established betweene them and us a brotherly society and mutual correspondency? How easy a matter had it been profitably to reforme and christianly to instruct minds yet so pure and new, so willing to be taught, being for the most part endowed with so docile, so apt and so yielding natural beginnings? Whereas, contrarywise, we have made use of their ignorance and inexperience, to drawe them more easily unto treason, fraude, luxurie, avarice and all manner of inhumanity and cruelty, by the example of our life and patterne of our customs. Who ever raised the service of marchandize and benefit of traffick to so high a rate? So many goodly citties ransacked and raged; so many nations destroyed and made desolate; so infinite millions of harmelesse people of all sexes, states and ages, massacred, ravaged and put to the sword; and the richest, the fairest and the best part of the world topsiturvied, ruined and defaced for the traffick of Pearles and Pepper. Oh mechanicall victories, oh base conquest. Never did greedy revenge, publik wrongs or general enmities, so moodily enrage and so passionately incense men against men, unto so horrible hostilities, bloody dissipation, and miserable calamities. Certain Spaniardes, coasting alongst the Sea in search of mines, fortuned to land in a very fertile, pleasant and well peopled country, unto the inhabitants whereof they declared their intent and showed their accustomed persuasions; saying, That they were quiet and well-meaning men, coming from far-countries, being sent from the King of Castile, the greatest King of the habitable earth, unto whom the Pope, representing God on earth, had given the principality of all the Indies. That if they would become tributaries to him, they should be most kindly used and courteously entreated: They required of them victualles for their nourishment, and some gold for the behoofe of certain Physicall experiments. Moreover, they declared unto them the beleeving in one only God and the trueth of our religion, which they persuaded them to embrace, adding thereto some minatorie threates. Whose answer was this: That happily they might be quiet and well meaning, but their countenance showed them to be otherwise: As concerning their King, since he seemed to beg, he showed to be poore and needy; And for the Pope, who had made that distribution, he expressed himself a man loving dissention, in going about to give unto a third man a thing which was not his own, so to make it questionable and litigious amongst the ancient possessors of it. As for victualles, they should have part of their store; And for gold, they had but little, and that it was a thing they made very small accoumpt of, as meerely unprofitable for the service of their life; whereas all their care was but how to pass it happily and pleasantly, and therefore, what quantity soever they should find, that only excepted which was employed about the service of their Gods, they might bouldly take it. As touching one only God, the discourse of him had very well pleased them; but they would by no means change their religion under which they had for so long time lived so happily; and that they were not accustomed to take any counsell, but of their friends and acquaintance. As concerning their menaces, it was a signe of want of judgement to threaten those whose nature, condition, power and means was to them unknown. And therefore they should with all speed hasten to avoid their dominions (forasmuch as they were not wont to admit or take in good part the kindnesses and remonstrances of armed people, namely, of strangers) otherwise they would deale with them as they had done with such others, shewing them the heads of certain men sticking upon stakes about their City, which had lately been executed. See here an example of the stammering of this infancy. But so it is, neither in this nor in infinite other places, where the Spaniards found not the merchandise they sought for, neither made stay or attempted any violence whatsoever other commodity the place yielded: witness my Canibales. Of two the most mighty and glorious Monarkes of that world, and perhaps of all our Westerne parts, Kings over so many Kings, the last they deposed and overcame; He of Peru, having by them been taken in a battle, and set at so excessive a ransome that it exceedeth all beliefe, and that truely paide: and by his conversation having given them apparant signes of a free, liberall, undanted, and constant courage, and declared to be of a pure, noble, and well composed understanding; a humor possessed the conquerors, after they had most insolently exacted from him a Million three hundred five and twenty thousand, and five hundred waights of golde, besides the silver and other precious things, which amounted to no less a summe (so that their horses were all shood of massive gold), to discover (what disloyalty or treachery soever it might cost them) what the remainder of this Kings treasure might be, and without controlment enjoy whatever he might have hidden or concealed from them. Which to compasse, they forged a false accusation and proofe against him, that he practised to raise his provinces, and intended to induce his subjects to some insurrection, so to procure his liberty. Whereupon, by the very judgement of those who had complotted this forgery and treason against him, he was condemned to be publikely hanged and strangled; having first made him to redeeme the torment of being burned alive by the baptisme which at the instant of his execution in charity they bestowed upon him; a horrible and the like never heard of accident, which nevertheless he undismaiedly endured with an unmoved manner and truly-royall gravity, without ever contradicting himself either in countenance or speech. And then, somewhat to mitigate and circumvent those silly unsuspecting people, amazed and astonished at so strange a spectacle, they counterfeited a great mourning and lamentation for his death, and appointed his funeralls to be solemnely and sumptuously celebrated. The other King of Mexico, having a long time manfully defended his besieged city, and in the tedious siege showed whatever pinching- sufferance and resolute-perseverance can effect, if ever any courageous Prince or war-like people showed the same; and his disastrous success having delivered him alive into his enemies hands, upon conditions to be used as beseemed a King: who during the time of his imprisonment did never make the least show of any thing unworthy that glorious title. After which victory, the Spaniards, not finding that quantitie of gold they had promised themselves, when they had ransacked and ranged all corners, they by means of the cruellest tortures and horriblest torments they could possibly devise, beganne to wrest and draw some more from such prisoners as they had in keeping. But unable to profit any thing that way, finding stronger hearts than their torments, they in the end fell to such moody outrages, that, contrary to all law of nations and against their solemn vows and promises, they condemned the King himself and one of the chiefest Princes of his Court, to the Racke, one in presence of another: the Prince, environed round with hot burning coales, being overcome with the exceeding torment, at last in most pitious sort turning his dreary eyes toward his Master, as if he asked mercy of him for that he could endure it no longer; The king, fixing rigorously and fierce his looks upon him, seeming to upbraid him with his remisnesse and pusilanimity, with a stern and setled voice uttered these few words unto him: ’What, supposest then I am in a cold bath? am I at more ease than you are?’ Whereat the silly wretch immediately fainted under the torture, and yielded up the ghost. The king, half rosted, was carried away: Not so much for pity (for what ruth could ever enter so barbarous mindes, who upon the furnished information of some odde piece or vessell of golde they intended to get, would broyle a man before their eyes, and not a man only, but a king, so great in fortune and so renowned in desert?), but for as much as his unmatched constancy did more and more make their inhumane cruelty ashamed, they afterwards hanged him, because he had courageously attempted by arms to deliver himself out of so long captivity and miserable subjection; where he ended his wretched life, worthy an high minded and never danted Prince. At another time, in one same fire, they caused to be burned all alive foure hundred common men and threescore principal Lords of a Province, whom by the fortune of war they had taken prisoners. These narrations we have out of their own bookes, for they do not only avouch, but vauntingly publish them. May it be they do it for a testimony of their justice or zeale toward their religion? Verily they are ways over-different and enemies to so sacred an ende. Had they proposed unto themselves to enlarge and propagate our religion, they would have considered that it is not amplified by possession of lands, but of men; and would have been satisfied with such slaughters as the necessity of war bringeth, without indifferently adding thereunto so bloody a butchery as upon savage beasts, and so universall as fire or sword could ever attaine unto having purposely preserved no more than so many miserable bond- slaves, as they deemed might suffice for the digging, working and service of their mines: So that diverse of their chieftains have been executed to death, even in the places they had conquered, by the appointment of the Kings of Castile, justly offended at the seld-seen horror of their barbarous demeanours, and well nigh all disesteemed, contemned and hated. God has meritoriously permitted that many of their great pillages and ill-gotten goods have either been swallowed up by the revenging Seas in transporting them, or consumed by the intestine wars and civill broiles wherewith themselves have devoured one another; and the greatest part of them have been overwhelmed and buried in the bowels of the earth, in the very places they found them, without any fruit of their victory. Touching the objection which some make, that the receipt, namely in the hands of so thrifty, wary and wise a Prince, does so little answer the foreconceived hope which was given unto his predecessors, and the said former aboundance of riches, they met withall at the first discovery of this new-found world (for although they bring home great quantity of gold and silver, we perceive the same to be nothing, in respect of what might be expected thence), it may be answered, that the use of money was there altogether unknown; and consequently that all their gold was gathered together, serving to no other purpose than for show, state and ornament, as a moovable reserved from father to son by many puissant Kings, who exhausted all their mines to collect so huge a heape of vessels or statues for the ornament of their Temples, and embellishing of their Pallaces; whereas all our gold is employed in commerce and trafficke betweene man and man. We mince and alter it into a thousand formes; we spend, we scatter and disperse the same to severall uses. Suppose our King should thus gather and heape up all the gold they might for many ages hoard up together, and keep it close and untouched. Those of the kingdome of Mexico were somewhat more encivilized, and better artists, than other nations of that world. And as we do, so judged they, that this Universe was neare his end, and took the desolation we brought amongst them as an infallible signe of it. They beleeved the state of the world to be divided into five ages, as in the life of five succeeding Sunnes, whereof foure had already ended their course or time; and the same which now shined upon them was the fifth and last. The first perished together with all other creatures, by an universall inundation of waters. The second by the fall of the heavens upon us, which stifled and overwhelmed every living thing: in which age they affirme the Giants to have been, and showed the Spaniards certain bones of them, according to whose proportion the stature of men came to be, of the height of twenty handfuls. The third was consumed by a violent fire, which burned and destroyed all. The fourth by a whirling emotion of the air and winds, which with the violent fury of itself remooved and overthrew diverse high mountaines: saying that men dyed not of it, but were transformed into Munkeis. (Oh what impressions does not the weakenesse of mans beliefe admit?) After the consummation of this fourth Sunne, the world continued five and twenty years in perpetuall darkenesse, in the fifteenth of which one man and one woman were created, who renewed the race of man-kind. Ten years after, upon a certain day, the Sunne appeared as newly created, from which day beginneth ever since the calculation of their years. On the third day of whose creation, died their ancient Gods, their new ones have day by day been borne since. In what manner this last Sunne shall perish, my aucthor could not learne of them. But their number of this fourth change does jumpe and meete with that great conjunction of the Starres which eight hundred and odde years since, according to the Astrologians supposition, produced diverse great alterations and strange novelties in the world. Concerning the proud pompe and glorious magnificence by occasion of which I am fallen into this discourse, nor Grece, nor Rome, nor Ægipt, can (be it in profit, or difficultie or nobility) equall or compare sundrie and diverse of their workes. The cawcy or high-way which is yet to be seen in Peru, erected by the Kings of that countrie, stretching from the city of Quito unto that of Cusco (containing three hundred leagues in length), straight, even, and fine, and twentie paces in breadth curiously paved, raysed on both sides with goodly high masonrie-walles, all along which, on the inner side, there are two continuall running streames, pleasantly beset with beauteous trees, which they call Moly. In framing of which, where they mette any mountaines or rockes, they have cut, raised and levelled them, and filled all below places with lime and stone. At the ende of every dayes journey as stations, there are built stately great pallaces, plenteously stored with all manner of victuals, apparrell and arms, as well for dayelie wayfaring men as for such armies that might happen to pass that way. In the estimation of which work I have especially considered the difficulty, which in that place is particularly to be remembred. For they built with no stones that were less then ten foote square: they had no other means to cary or transport them then by meere strength of arms to draw and dragge the carriage they needed: they had not so much as the arte to make scaffolds, nor knew other devise then to raise so much earth or rubbish against their building according as the work riseth, and afterward to take it away again. But return we to our coaches. In steade of them and of all other carrying beastes, they caused themselves to be carryed by men, and upon their shoulders. This last King of Peru, the same day he was taken, was thus carried upon rafters or beames of massive Golde, sitting in a fair chaire of state, likewise all of golde, in the middle of his battaile. Looke how many of his porters as were slain to make him fall (for all their endeavor was to take him alive) so many others, and as it were avye, took and underwent presently the place of the dead: so that they could never be brought down or made to falle, what slaughter soever was made of those kind of people, until such time as a horseman furiously ranne to take him by some part of his body, and so pulled him to the ground. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER VII: OF THE INCOMMODITIE OF GREATNESSE CHAPTER VII: OF THE INCOMMODITIE OF GREATNESSE INCE WE cannot attaine unto it, let us revenge ourselves with railing against it: yet is it not absolute railing to find fault with any thing: There are defects found in all things, how fair soever in show and desirable they be. It has generally this evident advantage, that whenever it pleaseth it will decline, and has well-nigh the choise of one and other condition. For a man does not fall from all heights; diverse there are whence a man may descend without falling. Verily, me seems that we value it at too high a rate, and prize over-dear the resolution of those whom we have either seen or heard to have contemned, or of their own motion rejected the same. Her essence is not so evidently commodious but a man may refuse it without wonder. Indeed I find the labor very hard in suffering of evils; but in the contentment of a meane measure of fortune and shunning of greatness, therein I see no great difficillty. In my conceit it is a virtue whereunto my self, who am but a simple ninny, might easily attaine, and without great contention. What shall they do who would also bring into consideration the glory which accompanieth this refusall, wherein may fall more ambition then even in the desire and absolute enjoying of greatness? Forasmuch as ambition is never better directed according to itself then by a straying and unfrequented path. I sharpen my courage toward patience, and weaken the same against desire. I have as much to wish for as another, and leave my wishes as much liberty and indiscretion; but yet it never came into my mind to wish for Empire, for Royalty, or eminency of high and commanding fortunes. I aime not that way: I love my self too well. When I think to grow, It is but meanly, with a forced and coward advancement, fit for me; indeed in resolution, in wisdom, in health, in beauty, and also in riches. But this credite, this aspiring reputation, this overswaying authority, suppresseth my imagination. And cleane opposite to some other, I should perhaps love my self better to be the second or third man in Perigot then the first in Paris; At least, without faining, I had rather be the third man in Paris then the first in charge. I will neither contend with an Usher of a doore, as a silly unknowen man; nor with gaping and adoration make a Lane through the throng as I pass. I am enured to a meane calling; mediocrity best fitteth me, as well by my fortune as by my own humor. And I have showed by the conduct of my life and course of my enterprises, that I have rather sought to avoid then otherwise to embrace beyond the degree of fortune that at my birth it pleased God to call me unto. Each natural constitution is equally just and easy. My mind is so dull and slowe that I measure not good fortune according to her height, but rather according to her facility. And if my hart be not great enough, it is ratably free and open, and who biddeth me bouldly to publish my weaknesse. Should any will me, on the one part, to conferre and consider the life of L. Thurius Balbus, a worthy gallant man, wise, fair, goodly, healthy, of good understanding, richly plenteous in all manner of commodities and pleasures, leading a quiet easefull life, altogether his own, with a mind armed and well prepared against death, superstition, griefes, cares and other encombrances of humane necessity; dying in his old age in an honorable battle, with his weapons in his hand, for the defense of his countrie; and on the other side the life of M. Regulus, so high and great, as all men know, together with his admirable and glorious end: the one unmentioned and without dignity, the other exemplare and wonderful renouned: truly I would say what Cicero says of it, had I the gift of well- speaking as he had. But if I were to sute them unto mine, I would also say that the former is as much agreeing to my quality, and to the desire I endeavor to conforme my quaiity unto, as the second is far beyond it. That to this I cannot attaine but by veneration; and to the other I would willingly attaine by custom. But return we to our temporall greatness, whence we have digressed. I am distasted of all mastry, both active and passive. Otanes, one of the seaven that by right might chalenge the crowne or pretend the Kingdome of Persia, resolved upon such a resolution as I should easily have done the like, which was, that he utterly renounced all manner of claime he might in any sort pretend unto that crowne to his fellow competitores, were it either by election or chance: alwayes provided that both himself and all his might live in that Empire free from all subjections and exempted from all manner of commandement, except that of the ancient laws, and might both challenge all liberty and enjoy all immunities that should not prejudice them: being as impacient to command as to be commanded. The sharpest and most dificile profession of the world is (in mine opinion) worthily to act and play the king. I excuse more of their faults then commonly other men do; and that in consideration of the down- bearing waight of their immense charge, which much astonisheth me, It is a very hard task to keep a due measure in so unmeasurable a power. Yet is it, that even with those that are of a less excellent nature it is a singular incitation to virtue to be seated in such a place where you shall do no manner of good that is not registred and recorded, and where the least well-dooing extendeth to so many persons, and where your sufficiency (as that of Preachers) is principally directed to the people; a weake and partiall judge, easily to be beguiled, and easy to be pleased. There are but few things of which we may give a sincere judgement; for there be very few wherein in some sort or other we are not particularly interessed. Superiority and inferiority, maistry and subjection, are joyntly tied unto a natural kind of envy and contestation; they must perpetually enter-spoile one another. I believe neither the one nor the other concerning her companions rights: let us suffer reason to speak of it) which is inflexible and impassible, when or how we shall make an end. I was not long since reading of two Scottish bookes striving upon this subject. The popular makes the King to be of worse condition then a Carter; and he that extolleth, Monarchy placeth him both in power and soveraignty many steps above the Gods. Now the incommodity if greatness, which here I have undertaken to note and to speak of (upon some occasion lately befalne me), is this: There is perhaps nothing more pleasing to the commerce of men then the Essayes which we through jealousie of honor or valor make one against another, be it in the exercise of the body or mind wherein sovereign greatness has no true or essentiall part. Verily, it has often seemed unto me, that through over-much respect Princes are therein used disdainefully and treated injuriously; For the thing whereat (in my youth) I was infinitely offended was, that those which were trained and schooled with me, should forbeare to do it in good earnest, because they found me unworthy to be withstood or to resist their endevours. It is that we dayly see to happen unto them; every man finding himself unworthy to force himself against them. If one perceive them never so little affected to have the victory, there is none but will strive to yield it them, and that will not rather wrong his glory then offend theirs: no man employeth more diligence then needs he must to serve their honor. What share have Princes in the throng, where all are for them? Mee thinks I see those Paladines of former ages presenting themselves in joustes, tiltings and combates, with bodies and arms enchanted. Brisson running against Alexander, counterfeited his course; Alexander chid him for it; but he should have caused him to be whipt. For this consideration was Carneades wont to say, that ’Princes children learn’t nothing aright but to mannage and ride horses; forasmuch as in all other exercises every man yieldeth and gives them the victory; but a horse who is neyther a flatterer nor a Courtier, will as soone throw the child of a King as the son of a base porter.’ Homer has been forced to consent that Venus (so sweet a saint and delicate a Goddesse) should be hurt at the siege of Troy, thereby to ascribe courage and hardinesse unto her, qualities never seen in those that are exempted from danger. The Gods themselves are feigned to be angry, to fear, to be jealous, to grieve, to show passion, and be subject to mortal sense, thereby to honor them with the vertues which the Poets and Philosophers invent amongst us: Nay, they are supposed to run away, and to have a feeling of all our imperfections. Who does not participate both hazard and difficulties, cannot justly pretend interest in the honor, or challenge share in the pleasure that followeth dangerous actions or hazardous attempts. it is pity a man should be so powerfull, that all things must yield and give place unto him. Such as are in so high eminency of greatness, their fortune rejects society and conversation too far from them: she placeth them in over remote and uncouth places. This easefull life and plausible facility to bring all under, and subject mens mindes, is an enemy to all manner of Pleasure. It is a kind of sliding, and not a going: It is to sleepe and not to live. Conceive man accompanied with omnipotency, you overwhelme him: he must in begging manner crave some empeachment and resistance of you. His being and his food is in want and indigence. Their good qualities are dead and lost, for they are not heard but by comparison, and they are excluded: they have little knowledge of true praise, being beaten with so continuall and uniform an approbation. Have they to do with the simplest of their subjects? They have no meane to take advantage of him if he but say, It is because he is my King, he supposeth to have sufficiently expressed, and you must understand that in so saying he has lent a helping hand to overthrow himself. This quality suppresseth and consumeth all other true and essentiall qualities: they are even drowned in the Royaltie; which gives them no leave to make the offices of their charge to prevaile, except in such actions as directly concerne and stead the same. To be a King is a matter of that consequence, that only by it he is so. That strange glimmering and eye- dazeling light which round about environeth, overcasteth and hideth from us: or weake sight is thereby bleared and dissipated, as beeing filled and obscured by that greater and further-spredding brightnesse. The Senate allotted the honor and prize of eloquence unto Tiberius; he refused it, supposing that if it had been true, he could not revenge himself of so limited and partiall judgement. As we yield Princes all advantages of bonor, so we aucthorize their defects and sooth-up their vices; not only by approbation, but also by imitation. All Alexanders followers bare their heads sideling, as he did. And such as flattered Dionysius in his own presence did run and jostle one another, and either stumbled at or over-threw what ever stood before their feete, to inferre that they were as short-sighted or spur-blinde as he was. Naturall imperfections have sometimes served for commendation and favor. Nay, I have seen deafnesse affected. And because the maister hated his wife, Plutarch has seen courtiers to sue a divorce of tbeirs, whom they loved very well. And which is more, paillardise and all manner of dissolution has thereby been held in credit; as also disloyalty, blasphemy, cruelty, heresie, superstition, irreligion, wantonnesse, and worse, if worse may be. Yea, by an example more dangerous then that of Mithridates his flatterers, who for so much as their master pretended to have skill in phisick and aspired to the honor of a good Physition, came to him to have their members incized and cauterized. For these others suffer to have their soules cauterized; a much more precious and nobler part then the body. But to end where I began: Adrian the Emperor, debating with Favorinus the Philosopher about the interpretation of some word, Favorinus did soone yield the victory unto him, his friends finding fault with him for it: ’you but jest, my masters’ (quoth he); ’would you not have him to be much wiser than I, who has the absolute command over thirty legions?’ Augustus wrote some verses against Asinius Pollio, which Pollio hearing, he said, ’I will hold my peace; for it is no wisdom to contend in writing with him who may proscribe.’ And they had reason; for Dionysius, because he could not equall Philoxenus in poesie, nor match Plato in discourse, condemned the one to the stone-quarries, and sent the other to be sold as a slave in the Ile of Aegina. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER VIII: OF THE ART OF CONFERRING CHAPTER VIII: OF THE ART OF CONFERRING T IS a custom of our law to condemne some for the warning of others. To condemne them because they have misdone were folly, as says Plato. For what is once done can never be undone: but they are condemned to the end that they should not offend a gain, or that other, may avoide the example of their offence. ’He who is hanged is not corrected, but others by him.’ Even so do I. My errors are sometimes natural, incorrigible, and remedilesse. But whereas honest men profit the Common wealth in causing themselves to be imitated, I shall happily benefit the same in making my self to be evitated. Nonne vides Albi ut male vivat filius, utque Barrus inops magnum documentum, ne patriam rem Perdere quis velit. -- HOR. Ser. i. sect. iv. 109. Doe you not see how that mans son lives badly, That man’s a beggar by his spending madly? A lesson great, that none take joy: His patrimony to destroy. By publishing and accusing my imperfections, some man may perhaps learne to fear them. The parts I most esteeme in my self, reape more honor by accusing then by commending my self. And that’s the cause I more often fall into them again and rest upon them. But when all the cards be told, a man never speaks of himself without loss. A mans own condemnations are ever increased: praises ever decreased. There may be some of my complexion, who am better instructed by contrariety then by similitude; and more by escaping then by following. Cato senior had a speciall regard to this kind of discipline when he said that wisemen have more to learne of fooles then fooles of wisemen. And that ancient player on the Lyra, whom Pausanias reporteth to have been accustomed to compell his schollers sometimes to go hear a bad Player, who dwelt right over-against him, where they might learne to hate his discords and false measures. The horror of cruelty draws me nearer unto clemency then any patterne of clemency can possibly win me. A cunning rider or skilfull horseman does not so properly teach me to sit well on horsebacke, as does one of our Lawyers, or a Venetian by seeing him ride. And an ill manner of speech does better reforme mine then any well polished form of speaking. The sottish countenance of another does daily advertise and forewarn me; that which pricketh, toucheth, and rouzeth better, then that which delighteth. These times are fit to reforme us backward, more by dissenting then by consenting more by difference then by accord. Being but little instructed by good examples, I make use of bad; the lesson of which is ordinary. I have endeavoured, nay I have laboured, to yield my self as pleasing and affable as I saw others peevish and froward; as constant, as I saw others variable; as gentle and mild, as I perceived others intractable and wild; and as good and honest, as I discerned others wicked and dishonest. But I proposed certain invincible measures unto my self. The most fruitfull and natural exercise of our spirit is, in my self-pleasing conceit, conference. The use whereof I find to be more delightsome then any other action of our life: And that’s the reason why, if I were now forced to choose (being in the mind I now am in), I would rather yield to lose my sight then forgoe my bearing or my speech. The Athenians and also the Romans did ever hold this exercise in high honor and reputation, namely, in their Academies. And at this day the Italians do yet keep a kind of form and trace of it, to their great profit, as may apparently be discerned by comparing their wits unto ours. The study and plodding on bookes is a languishing and weake kind of motion, and which heateth or earnesteth nothing; whereas conference does both learne, teach and exercise at once. If I conferre with a stubborne wit and encounter a sturdy wrestler, he toucheth me to the quick, hits me on the flanks, and pricks me both on the left and right side; his imaginations vanquish and confound mine. Jelousie, glory and contention drive, cast and raise me above my self. And an unison or consent is a quality altogether tedious and wearisome in conference. But as our mind is fortified by the communication of regular and vigorous spirits, it cannot well be expressed how much it loses and is bastardized by the continuall commerce and frequentation we have with base, weake and dull spirits. No contagion spreds itself further then that. I know by long experience what an ell of it is worth. I love to contest and discourse, but not with many, and only for my self. For to serve as a spectacle unto great men, and by way of contention for one to make a glorious show of his ready wit and running tongue. I deem it a profession far unfitting a man of honor. Sottishnes is an ill quality, but not to be able to endure it, and to fret and vex at it, as it happens to me, is another kind of imperfection which in opportunity is not much behind sottishnes; and that’s it I will now accuse in my self. I do with great liberty and facility enter into conference and disputation; forasmuch as opinion findes but a hard soile to enter and take any deepe roote in me. No propositions amaze me, no conceit woundeth me, what contrariety soever they have to mine. There is no fantazie so frivolous or humor so extravagant, that in mine opinion is not sortable to the production of humane wit. We others, who debarre our judgement of the right to make conclusions, regard but negligently the diverse opinions: and if we lend it not our judgement, we easily affoord it our ears. Where one scale of the balance is altogether empty, I let the other waver too and fro, under an old wives dreames. And me seems I may well be excused if I rather except an odde number than an even: Thursday in respect of Friday, if I had rather make a twelfth or fourteenth at a table, then a thirteenth; if when I am travelling I would rather see a Hare coasting then crossing my way; and rather reach my left then my right foote to be shod. All such foolish conceits, now in credit abo ut us, deserve at least to be listned unto. As for me, they only bear away inanity, and surely they do so. Vulgar and casual opinions are yet of some waight, which in nature are something els then nothing. And who wadeth not so far into them to avoid the vice of superstition, falleth happily into the blame of wilfulnesse. The contradictions then of judgements do neither offend nor move, but awaken and exercise me. We commonly shunne correction, whereas we should rather seek and present ourselves unto it, chiefly when it commeth by the way of conference, and not of regency. At every opposition we consider not whether it be just, but be it right or wrong, how we may avoide it; In stead of reaching our arms, we stretch forth our clawes unto it. I should endure to be rudely handled and checked by my friends, though they should call me foole, coxecombe, or say I raved. I love a man that does stoutly express himself amongst honest and worthy men, and whose words answere his thoughts. We should fortifie and harden our hearing against the tenderness of the ceremonious sound of words. I love a friendly society and a virile and constant familiarity; An amitie which in the earnestnesse and vigor of its commerce flattereth itself: as love in bitings and bloody scratchings. It is not sufficiently generous or vigorous, except it be contentious and quarrelous; if she be civilised and a skilfull artist; if it fear a shocke or free encounter, and have her starting holes or forced by-ways. Neque enim disputari sine reprehensione potest: ’Disputation cannot be held without reprehension.’ When I am impugned or contraried, then is mine attention and not mine anger stirred up. I advance my self toward him that does gainesay and instruct me. The cause of truth ought to be the common cause both to one and other. What can he answer? The passion of choller has already wounded his judgement: before reason has seized upon it. It were both profitable and necessary that the determining of our disputations might be decided by way of wagers, and that there were a materiall marke of our losses; that we might better remember and make more accompt of it; and that my boy might say unto me: Sir, if you call to mind your contestation, your ignorance, and your self- wilfulnesse, at severall times, cost you a hundred crownes the last yeare: I feast, I cherish and I embrace truth, where and in whom soever I find it, and willingly and merily yield my self unto her, as soone as I see but her approach, though it be a far-off, I lay down my weapon and yield my self vanquished. And alwayes provided one persist not or proceede therein, with an over-imperious stiffnesse or commanding surlinesse, I am well pleased to be reprooved. And I often accommodate my self unto my accusers more by reason of civility then by occasion of amendment: loving by the facility of yielding to gratifie and foster their liberty, to teach or advertise me. It is notwithstanding no easy matter to draw men of my times unto it. They have not the courage to correct, because they want the heart to endure correction; and ever speak with dissimulation in presence one of another. I take so great a pleasure to be judged and known, that it is indifferent to me in whether of the two formes I be so. Mine own imagination does so often contradict and condemne itself, that if another do it, all is one unto me; especially seeing I give his reprehension no other authority then I list. But I shall breake a straw or fall at ods with him, that keepes himself so aloft; as I know some that will fret and chafe if their opinions be not believed, and who take it as an injury, indeed fall out with their best friends, if they will not follow it. And that Socrates, ever smiling, made a collection of such contradictions as were opposed to his discourse, one might say his force was cause of it, and that the advantage being assuredly to fall on his side, he took them as a subject of a new victory; nevertheless we see on the contrary that nothing does so nicely yield our sense unto it as the opinion of preheminence and disdaine of the adversary. And that by reason it rather befits the weakest to accept of opposition in good part, which restore and repair him. Verily I seek more the conversation of such as curbe me, then of those that fear me. It is an unsavory and hurtful pleasure to have to do with men who admire and give us place. Antisthenes commanded his children never to be beholding unto or thanke any that should commend them. I feel my self more lusty and cranke for the victory I gain over my self, when in the heate or fury of the combate I perceive to bend and fall under the power of my adversaries reason, then I am pleased with the victory I obtain of him by his weakenesse. To conclude, I receive all blowes and allow all attaints given directly, how weake soever; but am very impatient at such as are strucken at randan and without order. I care but little for the matter, and with me opinions are all one, and the victory of the subject in a manner indifferent: I shall quietly contest a whole day, if the conduct of the controversie be followed with order and decorum. It is not force nor subtilty that I so much require, as form and order. The form and order dayly seen in the altercations of shepheards, or contentions of shop-prentise boyes; but never amongst us. If they part or give one another over, it is with incivilitie; and so do we. But their wrangling, their brawling and impatience, cannot make them to forgoe or forget their theame. Their discourse holds on his course. If they prevent one another, if they stay not for, at least they understand one another. A man does ever answere sufficiently well for me if he answere what I say. But when the disputation is confounded and orderlesse, I quit the matter and betake me to the form, with spight and indiscretion; and embrace a kind of debating, teasty, headlong, malicious and imperious, whereat I afterward blush. It is impossible to treate quietly and dispute orderly with a foole. My judgement is not only corrupted under the hand of so imperious a maister, but my conscience also. Our disputations ought to be forbidden and punished, as other verball crimes. What vice raise they not, and heape up together, being ever swayed and commanded by choller? First we enter into enmity with the reasons, and then with the men. We learne not to dispute, except it be to contradict; and every man contradicting and being contradicted, it commonly followeth that the fruit of disputing is to loose and to disanull the trueth. So Plato in his common wealth forbiddeth foolish, unapt and base-minded spirits to undertake that exercise. To what purpose go you about to quest or enquire that which is with him who has neither good pace nor proceeding of woorth? No man wrongs the subject when he quits the same for want of means to treat or mannage it. I meane not a scholasticall and artist meane, but intend a natural meane, and of a sound understanding. What will the end be? one goeth Eastward and another Westward: They loose the principal, and stray it in the throng of incidents. At the end of an hours wrangling they wot not what they seek for: one is high, another low, and another wide. Some take hold of a word, some of a similitude. Some forget what was objected against them, so much are they engaged in the pursuite, and think to follow themselves, and not you. Some finding themselves weake-backt, fear all, refuse all, and at the very entrance mingle the subject and confound the purpose; or in the heate of the disputation mutiny to hold their peace altogether: through a spightfull ignorance, affecting a proud kind of contempt, or a foolish modesty avoyding of contention. Provided that one strike and hit, he c areth not how open he lie. Another compteth his words, and wayeth them for reasons; Another employeth nothing but the advantage of his voice and winde. Here one concludeth against himself; here another wearyeth you with idle prefaces and frivolous digressions. Another armeth himself afore hand with injuries, and seekes after a Dutch quarrell, to rid himself of the society and shake off the conference of a spirit that presseth and overbeareth his. This last has no insight at all in reason, but still beleagreth you with the dialecticall or logicall close of his clause, and ties you to the rule of his arte or form of his skill. Now who does not enter into distrust of sciences, and is not in doubt, whether in any necessity of life he may reape solid fruit of them, if he consider the use we have of them? Nihil sanantibus literis: Since learning does not cure. Who has learnt any wit or understanding in Logique? Where are her fair promises? Nec ad melius vivendum, nec ad commodius disserendum: Neither to live better or to dispute fitter. Shall a man bear more brabling or confusion in the tittle-tattle of fish wives or scoulding sluts, then in the public disputations of men of this profession? I had rather my child should learne to speak in a Taverne then in the schooles of well-speaking Art. Take you a maister of arts, and conferre with him, why does he not make us perceive his artificiall excellency, and by the admiration of his reasons-constancy, or with the beauty of his quaint order and grace of his method, ravish silly women, and bleare ignorant men as we are? Why does he not sway, winde and persuade us as he list? Why should one so advantageous in matter and conduct entermixe injuries, indiscretion and chollericke rage with his fence? Let him pull of his two-faced hoode, his gowne and his latine, let him not fill our ears with meerely beleeved Aristotle, you will discover and take him for one of us, and worse if may be. Me thinks this implication and entangling of speech, wherewith they do so much importune us, may fitly be compared unto juglers play of fast and loose; their nimblenesse combats and forceth our sences, but it nothing shaketh our beliefe: Take away their jugling, what they do is but base, common and slight. Though they be more witty and nimble spirited, they are not tthe less foolish, simple and unapt. I love wit and honor wi sedome as much as them that have it. And beeing rightly used, it is the noblest, the most forcible, indeed richest purchase men can make. But in such (of which kind the number is infinit) that upon it establish their fundamentall sufficiency and worth: that from their wit refer themselves to their memory, sub aliena umbra latentes: reposing them under another mans protection, and can do nothing but by the book (if I may be bold to say so) I hate the same a little more then sottishnes. In my country and in my dayes learning and bookishnes does much mend purses, but minds nothing at all. If it chance to find them empty, light and dry, it filleth, it overburthens and swelleth them: a raw and indigested masse; if thinne, it does easily purifie, clarifie, extenuate and subtilize them even unto exinanition or evacuation. It is a thing of a quality very neare indifferent: a most profitable accessory or ornament unto a well-borne mind, but pernicious and hurtfully damageable unto any other or rather a thing of most precious use, that will not basely be gotten nor vily possessed. In some hands a royall scepter, in other some a rude mattocke. But let us proceed. What greater or more glorious victory can you expect, then teach your enemy that he cannot withstand you? When you gain the advantage of your proposition, it is Truth that winneth; when you get the advantage of the order and conduct, it is you that winne. I am of opinion that both in Plato and in Xenophon, Socrates disputeth more in favor of the disputers then in grace of the disputation; and more to instruct Euthydemus and Protagoras with the knowledge of the impertinency of their art. He takes hold of the first matter, as who has a more profitable end, then to clear it; that is, to clear the spirits he undertaketh to manage and to exercise. Agitation, stirring and hunting, is properly belonging to our subject or drift; we are not excusable to conduct the same ill and impertinently, but to misse the game and faile in taking, that’s another matter. For we are borne to quest and seek after trueth; to possesse it belongs to a greater power. It is not (as Democritus said) hidden in the deepes of abisse; but rather elevated in infinite height of divine knowledge. The world is but a School of inquisition. The matter is not who shall put in, but who shall run the fairest courses. As well may he play the foole that speaks truely as he that speaks falsely; for we are upon the manner and not upon the matter of speaking. My humor is, to have as great a regard to the form as to the substance; as much respect to the Advocat as to the cause; as Alcibiades appointed we should do. And I dayly ammuse my self to read in authors, without care of their learning; therein seeking their manner, not their subject. Even as I pursue the communication of some famous wit, not that he should teach me, but that I may know him; and knowing him (if he deserve it) I may immitate him. Every one may speak truely, but to speak orderly, methodically, wisely and sufficiemtly, few can do it. So falsehood proceeding from from ignorance does not offend me; ineptnesse and trifling does. I have broken off diverse bargaines, that would have been very commodious unto me, by the impertinency of their contestation, with whom I did bargaine. I am not mooved once a yeare, with the faults or oversights of those over whom I have power: but touching the point of the sottishnesse and foolishnes of their allegations, excuses, and defences, rude and brutish, we are every day ready to go by the ears. They neither understand what is said nor why, and even so they answer; a thing able to make one despaire. I feel not my head to shocke hard but by being hit with another. And I rather enter into composition with my peoples vices, then with their rashnesse, importunity and foolishnesse. Let them do less, provided they be capable to do. You live in hope to enflame their will. But of a blocke there is nothing to be hoped for, nor any thing of worth to be enjoyed. Now, what if I take things otherwise then they are? So it may be; and therefore I accuse my impatience. And first Ihould that it is equally vicious in him who is in the right as in him that is in the wrong; For it is ever a kind of tyrannical sharpenesse not to be able to endure a form different from his; and verily, since there is not a greater fondnesse, a more constant gullishnesse, or more heteroclite insipidity then for one to move or vex himself at the fondnesse, at the gullishnesse, or insipidity of the world: For it principally formalizeth and moveth us against ourselves; and that Philosopher of former ages should never have wanted occasion to weepe so long as he had considered himself. Miso, one of the seaven sages (a man of a Timonian disposition and Democraticall humor) being demanded where-at he laughed alone, be answered, because I laugh alone; how many follies do I speak and answer every day, according to my self; and then how much more frequent according to others? And if I bite my own lips at them, what ought others to do? In fine, we must live with the quick, and let the water run under the bridge, without any care, or at least without alteration to us. In good sooth, why meet we sometimes with crooked, deformed, and in body mishapen men, without falling into rage and discontent, and cannot endure to light-upon a froward, skittish, and ill-ranged spirit, without falling into anger and vexation? This vicious austerity is rather in the Judge then in the fault. Let us ever have that saying of Plato in our mouthes: What I find unwholsome, is it not to be unhealthy my self? Am not I in fault my self? May not mine own advertisement be retorted against my self? Oh wise and divine restraint, that curbeth the most universall and common error of men. Not only the reproches we do one to another, but our reasons, our arguments and matter controversed, are ordinarily retortable unto us; and we pinch ourselves up in our own arms. Whereof antiquity has left me diverse grave examples. It was ingeniously spoken and fit to the purpose by him that first devised the same: Stercus cuique suum bene olet. -- ERAS. Chil. iii. cent. iv. ad. 2. Ev’ry mans ordure well, To his own sense does smell. Our eyes see nothing backward. A hundred times a day we mocke ourselves upon our neigbbours subject, and detest some defects in others that are much more apparent in us; indeed, and admire them with a strange impudency and unheedinesse. Even yesterday I chanced to see a man of reasonable understanding, who no less pleasantly then justly flouted at anothers foolish fashion, and yet upon every silly occasion does nothing but molest all men with the impertinent bedrowle and register of his pedigrees, genealogies and alliances, more then halfe false and wrested in (for it is the manner of such people commonly to undertake such foolish discourses, whose qualities are more doubtfull and less sure); who if be had impartially considered and looked upon himself, should doubtlesse have found himself no less intemperate, indiscreet, and tedious, in publishing and extolling the prerogative of his wives pedigree and descent. Oh importunate presumption, wherewith the wife seeth herself armed by the hands of her own husband. If he understand Latin, a man should say to him, Age, si hæc non insanit satis sua sponte, instiga. -- TER. And. act. iv. sc. 2. Goe too, if of her own accord before, She were not mad enough, provoke her more. I say not that none should accuse except he be spotlesse in himself; For then none might accuse: no not spotlesse in the same kind of fault. But my meaning is, that our judgement charging and blaming another, of whom there is then question, spareth us nothing of an inward and severe jurisdiction. It is an office of charity, that he who cannot remove a vice from himself, should nevertheless endeavor to remove it from others, where it may have a less hurtful and froward seed. Nor do I deem it a fit answer for him that warneth me of my fault, to say the same is likewise in him. But what of that? Well meaning warning is alwayes true and profitable. Had we a good and sound nose, our own ordure should be more unsavory unto ourselves, forasmuch as it is our own. And Socrates is of opinion that he who should find himself, and his son, and a stranger guilty of any violence or injury, ought first begin by himself, and present himself to the sentence and condemnation of the law, and for his own discharge and acquital implore the assistance of the executioners hand: secondly, for his son, and lastly, for the stranger. If this precept take his tune somewhat too high, it should at lest be first presented to the punishment of one’s own conscience. Our senses are our proper and first judges, who distinguish not things, but by externall accidents; and no marvell, if in all parts of the service belonging to our society there is so perpetuall and universall commixture of ceremonies and superficiall apparances; so that the best and most effectuall part of policies consists in that. It is man with whom we have alwayes to do, whose condition is marvellously corporall. Let those who in these latter dayes have so earnestly laboured to frame and establish unto us an exercise of Religion and Service of God, so contemplative and immateriall, ponder nothing at all if some be found who think it would have escaped and moultred away betweene their fingers, if it had not held and continued amongst us, as a marke, a title, and instrument of division and faction, more then by itself. As in conference, The gravity, the gowne, and the fortune of him that speaks, does often adde and winne credit unto vain, trifling, and absurd discourses. It is not to be presumed that one of these gowne-Clarkes or quoifed Serjants, so followed and so redoubled, have not some sufficiency within him more then popular: and that a man so sullen, so grim, and so disdainfull, to whom so many commissions, charges, and authorities are given, be not more sufficient and worthy then another who saluteth and vaileth to him so far-off, and whom no man employeth. Not only the words, but the powtings of such people are considered and registred, every one applying himself to give them some notable and solid interpretation. If they stoop to common conference, and that a man affoord or show them other then reverence and approbation, they overthrow you with the autority of their experience: they have read, they have heard, seen, and done goodly things, you are cleane overwhelmed with examples. I would faine tell them that the fruit of a Chirurgion’s experience is not the story of his practises, or the remembrance that he has cured foure who had the Plague, and healed as many that had the Goute, except he know and have the wit, from his use and experience, to draw a methode how to frame his judgements, and by his skill and practise make us perceave he is become wiser in his art. As in a consort of instruments, one heares not severally a Lute, a Vyol, a Flute, or a pair of Virginalles, but a perfect-full harmony: the assembly and fruit of all those instruments in one. If their travels and charges have amended them, it is in the production of their understanding to make it appeare. It sufficeth not to number the experiments; they ought to be well poised and orderly sorted: and to extract the reasons and conclusions they containe, they should be well disgested and thorowly distilled. There were never so many Historians. It is ever good and profitable to hear them; for out of the magazin of their memory they store us with diverse good instructions and commendable documents. Verily a chief part, for the assistance of our life. But now a dayes we seek not after that, but rather whether the Collectors and reporters of them be praise worthy and directing themselves. I hate al manner of tyranny both verball and effectuall. I willingly band and oppose my self against these vain and frivolous circumstances, which by the sences delude our judgement; and holding my self aloofe of from these extraordinary greatnesses, have found that for the most part they are but men as others be: Rarus enim ferme sensus communis in illa Fortuna -- JUV. Sat. viii. 73 For common sense is seldom found In fortunes that so much abound. They are, perhaps, esteemed and discerned less then they be, forasmuch as they undertake more, and so show themselves; they answer not the charge they have taken. There must necessarily be more vigor and strength in the bearer then in the burden. He who is not grown to his full strength, leaves you to ghesse whether he have any left him beyond that, or have been tried to the utmost of his power. He who fainteth under his burden bewrayeth his measure and the weaknesse of his shoulders. Thats the reason why amongst the wiser sort there are so many foolish and unapt minds seen, and more then of others. They might happily have been made good husbandmen, thriving merchants, and plodding artificers. Their natural vigor was cut out to this proportion. Learning is a matter of great consequence: they faint under it. To enstall and distribute so rich and so powerfall a matter, and availefully to employ the same, their wit has neither sufficient vigor, nor conduct enough to manage it. It has no prevailing virtue but in a strong nature, and they are very rare; and such as are weake (says Socrates) corrupt and spoilingly deface the dignity of Philosophy in handling the same . She seems faulty and unprofitable, being ill placed and unorderly disposed. See here how they spoile and entangle themselves. Humani qualis simulator simius oris, Quem puer arridens, pretioso stamine serum Velavit, nudasque nates ac terga reliquit, Ludibrium mensis. -- CLAUD. Eutrop. 1. i. 803. Such counterfeits as Apes are of mans face, Whom children sporting at, featly incase In costly coates, but leave his backeside bare For men to laugh at, when they feasting are. To those likewise who sway and command us, and have the world in their own bands, ’tis not sufficient to have a common understanding, and to be able to do what we can effect. They are far beneath us, if they be not much above us. As they promise more, so owe they more. And therefore silence is in them, not only a countenance of respect and gravitie, but often of thrift and profit. Megabysus going to visite Apelles in his work- house, stood still a good while without speaking one word, and then began to discourse of his workes. Of whom he received this rude and nipping cheke: So long as you holdest your peace, by reason of your garish clothes, goodly chaines and stately pompe, you seemedst to be some worthy gallant; but now you hast spoken, there is not the simplest boy of my shop but scorneth and contemns you.’ That great state of his, those rich habiliments and goodly traine did not permit him to be ignorant with a popular ignorance, and to speak impertinently of painting. He should have kept mute and concealed his externall and presuming sufficiency. Unto how many foolish and shallow minds has in my dayes a sullen, cold, and silent countenance served as a title of wisdom and capacity? Dignities, charges and places are necessarily given more by fortune then by merit; and they are often to blame, that for it lay the blame on Kings. Contrariwise it is a wonder that, being so untoward, they should therein have so good lucke: Principis est virtue maxima nosse suos: ’Chiefe virtue it is known, In Kings to know their own.’ For Nature has not given them so perfect a sight that it might extend itself and overlooke so many people, to discerne their pre-excellency; and enter their breasts where lodgeth the knowledge of our will and better worth. It is by conjectures, and as it were groping they must try us; by our race, alliances, dependences, riches, learning, and the peoples voice: all over-weake arguments. He that could devise a meane how men might be judged by law, chosen by reason and advanced by desert, should establish a perfect form of a commonwealth. Yea but he has brought that great business unto a good pass. It is to say something, but not to say sufficiently. For this sentence is justly received, That counsels ought not to be judged by the events. The Carthaginians were wont to punish the ill counsels of their Captains, although corrected by some fortunate successes And the Roman people has often refused triumphes to famous, successfull and most profitable victories, forasmuch as the Generals conduct answeared not his good fortune. It is commonly perceived by the worlds actions that fortune, to teach us how far her power extendeth unto all things, and who taketh pleasure to abate our presumption, having not bin able to make silly men wise, she has made them fortunate in envy of virtue; and commonly gives herself to favor executions, when as their complot and devise is meerly hirs. Whence we dayly see that the simplest amongst us compass diverse great and important affairs, both public and private. And as Sirannez, the Persian Prince, answered those who seemed to wonder how his negotiations succeeded so ill, his discourses being so wise, that he was only maister of his discourses, but fortune mistris of his affairs successes. These may answer the like; but with a contrary bias. Most things of the world are made by themselves. Fata viam inveniunt. -- VIRG. Æn. iii. 356. Fates find and know which way to go. The issue does often aucthorize a simple conduct. Our interposition is in a manner nothing els but an experience, and more commonly a consideration of use and example then of reason. And as one amazed at the greatness of some businesses I have sometimes understood by those who had atchieved them, both their motives and addresses: wherein I have found but vulgar advises: and the most vulgar and used are perhaps the surest and most commodious for the practice, if not for the show. And what if the plainest reasons, are the best seated, the meanest, basest and most beaten, are best applied unto affairs? To maintaine the authority of our Kings counsell it is not requisite that prophane persons should be partakers of it, and looke further into it then from the first barre. To uphold its reputation, it should be reverenced upon credit, and at full. My consultation does somewhat roughly hew the matter, and by its first show, lightly consider the same: the main and chief point of the work I am wont to resigne to heaven. Permitte, divis cætera. -- HOR. i. Od. ix. 9. How all the rew shall go, Give leave to Gods to know. Good and bad fortune are in my conceit two sovereign powers. ’Tis folly to think that humane wisdom may act the full part of fortune. And vain is his enterprise that presumeth to embrace both causes and consequences, and lead the progresse of his fact by the hand. And above all, vainest in military deliberations. There was never more circumspection and military wisdom then is sometimes seen amongst us: may it be that man feareth to lose himself by the way, reserving himself to the catastrophe of that play? I say, moreover, that even our wisdom and consultation for the most part followeth the conduct of hazard. My will and my discourse is sometimes mooved by one air and sometimes by another; and there be many of these motions that are governed without me. My reason has dayly impulsions and casual agitations: Vertuntur species animorum, et pectora motus Nunc alios, alios dum nubila ventus agebat, Concipiunt. -- VIRG. Geo. iv. 20. The showes of mindes are chang’d, and brests conceave At one time motions which anon they leave, And others take again, As winds drive clouds amaine. Let but a man looke who are the mightiest in Cities and who thrive best in their business: he shall commonly find they are the siliest and poorest in wit. It has hapned to simple women, to weake children, and to mad men to command great states, as well as the most sufficient Princes. And the gullish or shallow-pated (says Thucidides) do more ordinarily come unto them then the wisest and subtilest. We ascribe their good fortunes effects unto their prudence. ------ ut quisque fortuna utitur, Ita præcellit: atque exinde sapere illum omnes dicimus. -- PLAU. Pse. act v. sc. 4. As men their fortune use, so they excel, And so we say, they are wise and do well. Wherefore I say well that however events are but weake testimonies of our worth and capacity. I was now upon this point that we need but looke upon a man advanced to dignity; had we but three days before known him to be of little or no worth at all: an image of greatness and an Idea of sufficiency does insensibly glide and creepe into our opinions; and we persuade ourselves that increasing in state and credit and followers, he is also increased in merit. We judge of him, not according to his worth, but after the manner of casting-counters, according to the prerogative of his rank. But let fortune turn her wheele, let him again decline and come down amongst the vulgar multitude; every one with admiration enquireth of the cause and how he was raised so high. Good Lord, is that he? will some say. What, knew he no more? had he no other skill when he was so aloft? Are Princes pleased with so little? Now in good sooth we were in very good hands, will others say. It is a thing my self have often seen in my dayes. Yea the very maske of greatness or habit of Majesty represented in Tragedies does in some sort touch and beguile us. The thing I adore in Kings is the throng of their adorators. All inclination and submission is due unto them, except the mindes. My reason is not framed to bend or stoop: my knees are. Melanthius, being demanded what be thought of Dionysius his tragedy answered, I have not seen it, so much was it over-clouded with language. So should those say that judge of great mens discourses: I have not understood his discourse, so was it overdarkned with gravity, with greatness and with Majesty. Antisthenes one day persuaded the Athenians to command that their asses should as well be employed about the manuring of grounds as were their horses who answered him that the asse was not borne for such service: That’s all one (quoth he), there needs but your allowance for it: for the most ignorant and incapable men you employ about the directing of your wars leave not to be come out of hand most worthy only because you employ them. Whereupon depends the custom of so many men, who canonize the King, whom they have made amongst them, and are not contented to honor him, unless they also adore him. Those of Mexico, after the ceremonies of his consecration are finished, dare no more looke him in the face; but as if by his Royalty they had deified him, they afterward deem him to be a God: amongst the oathes, they make him sweare to maintaine their Religion, to keep their Lawes, to defend their liberties, to be valiant, just and debonaire; he is also sworne to make the Sun march in his accustomed light; in time of need to cause the clouds showre down their waters; to enforce rivers to run in their right wonted chanels; and compell the earth to produce all necessary things for his people. I differ from this common fashion, and more distrust sufficiency, when I see it accompanied with the greatnes of fortune, and lauded by popular commendation. We should speedfully marke of what consequence it is for a man to speak in due time, to choose fit opportunity, to breake or change his discourse with a magistrate authority; to defend himself from others oppositions, by a nod or moving of the head, by a smile, a shrug, or a silence, before an assembly trembling with reverence and respect. A man of monstrous fortune, chancing to shoote his boult, and give his opinion upon a frivolous subject, which but jestingly was tossed too and fro at his table, began ever thus: he cannot choose but be a lyer, or an ignorant asse, that will say otherwise then, &c. Follow this Philosophicall point, out commeth a dagger, and there is some mischief. See here another advertisement, from whence I reape good use; which is, that in disputations and conferences all good seeming words ought not presently to be allowed and accepted. Most men are rich of a strange sufficiency. Some may chance to speak a notable saying, to give a good answere, to use a witty sentence, and to propound it, without knowing the force of it. That a man holdeth not all he borroweth, may perhaps be verified in my self. A man should not alwayes yield, what truth or goodnes soever it seems to containe. A man must either combat the same in good earnest, or draw back, under colour of not understanding the matter: to try on all parts, how it is placed in it’s author. It may fortune that we shut ourselves up and further the stroake, beyond its caring. I have sometimes in necessity and throng of the combat employed some reviradoes or turnings, which beyond my intent have prooved false offers. I but gave them by tale, and they were received by waight. Even as when I contend with a vigourous man, I please my self to anticipate his conclusions; I ease him the labor to interpret himself; endeavor to prevent his imperfect and yet budding imagination; the order and pertinency of his understanding forwarneth and menaceth a far off. Of these others I do cleane contrary; a man must understand or presuppose nothing but by them. If they judge in general termes: This is is good, that’s naught: and that they jump right, see whether it be fortune that jumpeth for them. Let them a little circumscribe and restraine their sentence why it is, and which way it is. These universall judgements I see so ordinarily say nothing at all. They are men that salute a whole multitude in throng and troupe. Such as have true knowledge of the same, salute and marks it by name and particularly. But it is a hazardous enterprise. Whence I have oftner and daily seen to happen that wits weakly grounded, intending to show themselves ingenious by observing in the reading of some work the point of beauty, stay their admiration with so bad a choise, that in lieu of teaching us the authors excellency, they show us their own ignorance. This manner of exclamation is safe: See this is very excellent: Surely this is very good; having heard a whole page of Virgil. And that’s the shift whereby the subtill save themselves. But to undertake to follow him by shrugs and crinches, and with an express selected judgement to go about to marke which way a good author surmounteth himself; pondring his words, his phrases, his inventions, and his severall vertues one after another: Away, go by: It is not for you. Videndum est non modo, quid quisque loquatur, sed etiam quid quisque sen tiat, atque etiam qua de causa quisque sentiat: ’Man must take heed not only what he speaks, but what he thinkes, and also why he thinkes.’ I dayly hear fooles utter unfoolish words. Speake they any good thing; let us understand whence they know it, how far they understand and whereby they hold it. We helpe them to employ this fine word and this goodly reason, which they possesse not, and have but in keeping; they have happily produced the same by chance and at random, ourselves bring it in credit and esteeme with them. You lend them your hand what to do? to konne you no thankes, and thereby become more simple and more foolish. Doe not second them: let them go-on: they will handle this matter as men affraid to bewray themselves, they dare neither change her seats or light, nor enter into it. Shake it never so little, it escapeth them; quit the same how strong and goodly soever it be. They are handsome weapons, but ill hafted. How often have I seen the experience of it! Now if you come to expound and confirme them, they take hold of you, and presently steale the advantage of your interpretation from you. It was that which I was about to say: It was just my conceit; If I have not so exprest it, it is but for want of speech. Handy-dandy, what is this? Malice itself must be employed to correct this fierce rudenesse. Hegesias his position, that a man must neither hate nor accuse, but instruct, has some reason else where. But here it is injustice to assist, and inhumanity to raise him up again, that has nothing to do with it, and is thereby of lesser worth. I love to have them entangle and bemire themselves more then they are, and if it be possible to wade so deepe into the gulphe of error, that in the end they may recall and advise themselves. Sottishnesse and distraction of the senses is no disease curable by a tricke of advertisment. And we may fitly say of this reparation, as Cyrus answered one who urged him to exhort his army in the nicke when the battle should begin: ’That men are not made warlike and courageous in the field by an excellent oration, no more then one becomes a ready cunning Musition by hearing a good song.’ They are prentisages that must be learned a forehands by long and constant institution. This care we owe to ours, and this assiduity of correction and instruction; but to preach to him that first passeth by, or sway the ignorance or fondnesse of him we meete next, is a custom l cannot well away with. I seldom use it, even in such discourses as are made to me; and I rather quit all, then come to these far-fetcht and magistrate instructions. My humor is no more proper to speak then to write, namely for beginners. But in things commonly spoken, or amongst others, how false and absurd soever I judge them, I never crosse or gibe them, neither by word nor signe. Further, nothing does more spight me in sottishnesse then that it pleaseth itself more then any reason may justly be satisfied. It is ill lucke that wisdom forbids you to please and trust your self, and sends you alwayes way discontented and fearefull; whereas wilfulnesse and rashnesse fill their guests with gratulation and assurance. It is for the simplest and least able to looke at other men over their shoulders, ever returning from the combat full of glory and gladnesse. And most often also, this outrecuidance of speech and cheerefulnesse of countenance gives them the victory over the bystanders, who are commonly weake, and incapable to judge a right and discerne true advantage. Obstinacy and earnestnesse in opinion is the surest tryall of folly and self conceit. Is there any thing so assured, so resolute, so disdainfull, so contemplative, so serious and so grave, as the Asse? May we not commixe with the title of conference and communication the sharpe and interrupted discourses which mirth and familiarity introduceth amongst friends, pleasantly dallying and wittily jesting one with another? An exercise to which my natural blithnesse makes me very apt. And if it be not so wire-drawne and serious as this other exercise I now speak of, yet is it no less sharpe or ingenious, no less profitable, as it seemed to Lycurgus. For my regard I bring more liberty then wit unto it, and have therin more lucke then invention; but I am perfect in sufferance; for I endure the revenge, not only sharpe but also indiscreete, without any alteration. And to any assault given me, if I have not presently or stoutly wherewith to work my own amends, I ammuse not my self to follow that ward or point, with a tedious and self-wil’d contestation, enclining to pertinacy: I let it pass, and hanging down mine ears, remit my self to a better hour to right my self. He is not a marchant that ever gaineth. Most men change both voice and countenance, where might faileth them: And by an importunate rage, instead of avenging themselves, they accuse their weaknesse and therewith bewray their impacience. In this jollity we now and then harpe upon some secret strings of our imperfections, which setled or considerate we cannot touch without offence, and we profitably enter-advertize ourselves of our defects. There are other handy-sports indiscreete, foolish and sharpe, just after the French manner, which I hate mortally; I have a tender and sensible skinne: I have in my days seen two Princes of our Royall blood brought to their graves for it. It is an ill seeming thing for men in jest to hitte, or in sport to strike one another. In other matters, when I shall judge of any body, I demaund of him how far or how much he is contented with himself; how far his speach or his work pleaseth him. I will avoyd these goodly excuses, I did it but in jest: Ablatum mediis opus est incudibus istud. -- OVID. Trist. 1. i. Eleg. vi. 29. This work away was brought, Halfe hamm ered, halfe wrought. I was not an hour there: I have not seen him since. Now I say, let us then leave these partes; give me one that may represent you whole and entire, by which it may please you to be measured by another. And then, what find you fairest in your own work? Is it that or this part? The grace or the matter, the invention, the judgement, or the learning? For I ordinarily perceive that a man misseth as much in judging of his own work as of anothers. Not only by the affection he therein employeth, but because be has not sufficiencie to know, nor skill to distinguish it. The work of its own power and fortune may second the workeman, and transport him beyond his invention and knowledge. As for me, I judge not the worth of anothers work more obscurely then of my own; and place my Essayes sometime lowe, sometimes high, very unconstantly and doubtfully. There are diverse bookes profitable by reason of their subjects, of which the author reapeth no commendations at all; And good bookes, as also good workes, which make the workeman ashamed. I shall write the manner of our bankets and the fashion of our garments, and I shall write it with an ill grace: I shall publish the Edicts of my time, and the letters of Princes that publikely pass from hand to hand: I shall make an abridgement of a good book (and every abridgement of a good book is a foole abridged), which book shall come to be lost, and such like things. Posterity shall reape singular profit by such compositions; but I, what honor except by my good fortune? Many famous bookes are of this condition. When I read Philip de Commines (now diverse years since), a right excellent author, I noted this speech in him as a saying not vulgar: That a man should carefully take heed how be do his master so great or much service, that he thereby be hindred from finding his due recompence for it. I should have commended the invention, but not him. After that I found it in Tacitus: Beneficia eo usque lata sunt dum videntur exolvi posse, ubi multum antevenere pro gratia odium redditur: (CORN. TACIT. Annal. iv.) ’Benefits are so long well-come, as we think they may be requited, but when they much exceed all power of recompence, hate is returned for thankes and good will.’ Seneca very stoutly: Nam qui putat esse turpe non reddere, non vult esse cui reddat: (SEN. Epist. lxxxi.) ’For he that thinkes it a shame not to requite, could wish he were not whom he should requite.’ Q.Cicero with a looser byas: Qui se non putat satisfacere, amicus esse nullo modo potest: ’He that thinkes he does not satisfie, can by no means be a friend.’ The subject according as it is may make a man be judged learned, wise, and memorious; but to judge in him the parts most his own and best worthy, together with the force and beautie of his mind, ’tis very requisite we know first what is his own, and what not; and in what is not his own, what we are beholding to him for, in consideration of his choise, disposition, ornament, and language he has thereunto furnished. What if he have borrowed the matter and empaired the form? as many times it commeth to pass. We others that have little practise with bookes are troubled with this, that when we meet with any rare or quaint invention in a new Poet, or forcible argument in a Preacher, we dare not yet commend them until we have taken instruction of some wise man, whether that art be their own or another bodies, And until then I ever stand upon my own guard. I come lately from reading over (and that without any intermission) the story of Tacitus (a matter not usual with me; it is now twenty years, I never spent one whole hour together upon a book), and I have now done it at the instant request of a gentleman whom France holdeth in high esteeme, as well for his own worth and valor as for a constant form of sufficiencie and goodnes apparently seen in diverse brethren of his. I know no author that in a public register entermixeth so many considerations of manners and particular inclinations. And I deem cleane contrary to what he thinketh; who being especially to follow the lives of the Emperours of his time, so diverse and extreme in all manner of form, so many notable and great actions, which namely their cruelty produced in their subjects, he had a more powerfull and attractive matter to discourse and relate, then if he had been to speak or treat of battles and universall agitations. So that I often find him barren, sleightlie running-over those glorious deaths, as if he feared to attediate and molest us with their multitude and continuance. This form of historie is much more profitable: Publike innovations depend more on the conduct of fortune; private on ours. It is rather a judgement then a deduction of an history: therein are more precepts then narrations. It is not a book to read, but a volume to study and to learne; it is so fraught with sentences, that right or wrong they are hudled up. It is a seminary of morall and a magazine of pollitique discourses, for the provision and ornament of those that possesse some place in the managing of the world. He ever pleadeth with solid and forcible reasons, after a sharpe and witty fashion; following the affected and laboured stile of his age. They so much loved to raise and puffe themselves up, that where they found neither sharpnesse not subiility in things, they would borrow it of wordes. He draweth somewhat neare to Seneca’s writing. I deem Tacitus more sinnowy, Seneca more sharpe. His service is more proper to a crazed troubled state, as is ours at this present; you would often say, he portrayeth and toucheth us to the quick. Such as doubt of his faith do manyfestly accuse themselves to hate him for somewhat else. His opinions be sound, and enclining to the better side of the Roman affairs. I am nevertheless something greeved that he has more bitterly judged of Pompey then honest men’s opinions, who lived and conversed with him, do well allow of: to have esteemed him altogether equall to Marius and Silla, saving that he was more close and secret. His intention and canvasing for the government of affairs has not been exempted from ambition nor cleared from revenge; and his own friends have feared that had he gotten the victory, it would have transported him beyond the limits of reason, but not unto an unbridled and raging measure. There is nothing in his life that has threatned us with so manifest a cruelty and express tyranny. Yet must not the suspition be counterpoised to the evidence: So do not I believe him. That his narrations are natural and right might happily be argued by this, that they do not alwaies exactly apply themselves to the conclusions of his judgement, which he pursueth according to the course he has taken, often beyond the matter he showeth us, which be has dained to stoop unto with glance. He needeth no excuse to have approoved the religion of his times according to the laws which commanded him, and been ignorant of the true and perfect worship of God, That’s his ill fortune, not his defect. I have principally considered his judgement, whereof I am not everywhere throughly resolved. As namely these words contayned in the letter, which Tiberius, being sicke and aged, sent to the Senate: ’What shall I write to you my masters, or how shall I write to you, or what shall I not write to you in these times? May the gods and goddesses loose me worse then I dayly feel myself to perish, if I can tell.’ I cannot perceive why he should so certainly apply them onto a stinging remorse, tormenting the conscience of Tiberius; At least when my self was in the same plight, I saw it not. That has likewise seemed somwhat demiss and base unto me, that having said how he exercised a certain honorable magistracy in Rome, he goeth about to excuse himself that it is not for ostentation he spake it. This one tricke, namely in a mind of his quality, seems but base and course unto me; For not to dare speak roundly of himself, accuses some want of courage. A constant, resolute, and high judgement, and which judgeth soundly and surely, every hand while useth his own examples, as well as of any strange thing, and witnesseth as freely of himself as of a third person: a man must overgoe these populare reasons of civility in favor of truth and liberty. I dare not only speak of my self, but speak alone of my self. I stragle when I write of any other matter, and digresse from my subject. I do not so indiscreetly love my self, and am so tied and commixt to my self as that I can not distinguish and consider my self a part, as a neighbour, as a tree; it is an equall error either not to see how far a mans worth stretcheth, or to say more of it then one seeth good cause. We owe more love to God then to ourselves, and know him less, and yet we talk our fill of him. If his writings relate any thing of his conditions, he was a notable man, upright and courageous, not with a superstitious virtue, but Philosophicall and generous: He may be found over- hardy in his testimonies. As where he holdeth that a souldier carrying a burden of wood, his hands were so stifly benumbed with cold that they stucke to his wood, and remained so fast unto it, that as dead flesh they were divided from his arms. In such cases I am wont to yield unto the authority of so great testimonies. Where he also says that Vespasian, by the favor of the God Serapis, healed in the citie of Alexandria a blinde woman with the rubbing and anointing her eyes with fasting spettle, and some other miracles, which I remember not well now, he does it by the example and devoire of all good historians. They keep a register of important events; among public accidents are allso popular reports and opinions. It is their part to relate common conceits, but not to sway them. This part belongeth to Divines and Philosophers, directors of consciences. Therefore, that companion of his, and as great a man as he, said most wisely: Equidem plura transcribo quam credo: Nam nec affirmare sustineo de quibus dubito nec sub ducere quæ accepi: ’I write out more then I believe: for neither can I bide to affirm what I doubt of, nor to withdrawe what I have heard.’ And that other: Hæc neque affirmare neque refellere operæ precium est: famæ rerum standum est: ’It is not worth the talk, or to avouch, or to refute these things we must stand to report.’ And writing in an age wherein the beliefe of prodigies began to decline, he says he would notwithstanding not omit to insert in his Annals and give footing to a thing received and allowed of so many honest men, and with so great reverence by antiquity. It is very well said: That they yielde us the history, more according as they receave then according as they esteeme it. I, who am king of the matter I treat of, and am not to give accompt of it to any creature living, do nevertheless not altogether believe my self for it: I often hazard upon certain outslips of my mind for which I distrust my self; and certain verball wilie-beguilies, whereat I shake mine ears; but I let them run at hab or nab, I see some honor them selves with such like things: ’Tis not for me alone to judge of them. I present my self standing and lying before and behinde, on the right and left side, and in all by natural motions. Spirits likewise in force are not ever likewise in application and taste. See here what my memory does in grose, and yet very uncertainely present unto me of it. In breefe, all judgments are weake, demiss and imperfect. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER IX: OF VANITIE CHAPTER IX: OF VANITIE HERE IS perhaps no vanity more manyfest then so vainely to write of it. What Divinity has so divinely expressed thereof unto us, ought of all men of understanding to be diligently and continually meditated upon. Who seeth not that I have entered so large a field, and undertaken so high a pitch, wherein so long as there is either Inke or Paper in the world, I may uncessantly wander and fly without encombrance? I can keep no register of my life by my actions: fortune placeth them to lowe: I hould them of my fantasies. Yet have I seen a gentleman who never communicated his life but by the operations of his belly; you might have seen in his house, set out for a show, a row of basins for seaven or eight dayes. It was all his study, it was all his talk: All other discourses were unsavory to him. These are somewhat more civile, the excrements of an ould spirit, sometimes hard, sometimes laxative; but ever indigested. And when shall I come unto an end of representing a continuall agitation or incessant alteration of my thoughts, what subject soever they happen; since Diomedes filled six thousand bookes only with the subject of Grammar? What is idle babling like to produce, since faltring and liberty of the tongue has stuft the world with so horrible a multitude of volumes? So many words only for words. Oh Pythagoras, why didst not you conjure this tempest? One Galba, of former ages, being accused for living idlie, answered that ’all men ought to give an account of their actions, but not of their abiding.’ He was deceived; for justice has also knowledge and animadversion over such as gather stubble (as the common saying is) or looke about for gape-seed. But there should be some correction appointed by the laws against foolish and unprofitable writers, as there is against vagabonds and loiterers; so should both my self and a hundred others of our people be banished. It is no mockerie: Scribling seems to be a Symthome or passion of an irregular and licentious age. When wrote we ever so much as we have done since our intestine troubles, or when filled the Romans so many volumes as in the times of their ruine? Besides that, the refining of wits in a common wealth does seldom make them the wiser; this idle working proceedeth of this, that all men do over slowly give themselves to the office of their function, and are easily withdrawne from it. The corruption of the times we live in is wrought by the particular contribution of every one of us: some conferre treason unto it, some injustice, other some irreligion, tyranny, avarice and cruelty, according as they are more or less powerfull; the weaker sort, whereof I am one, imparte foolishnesse, vanity and idlenesse unto it. It seems to be the season of vain things when the domageable press us. In a time where to do evil is common, to do nothing profitable is in a manner commendable. One thing comforts me, that I shall be of the last that shall be attached; whilst they shall provide for the worser sort and the most hurtful, I shall have leisure to amend my self; for me thinkes it would be against reason busily to insist and pursue petty inconveniences, when great ones infect us. And the Physition Philotimus, to one that offred his finger to dresse, by whose face, looke and breath he apparently perceaved that he had an impostume in his loonges: ’My friend (quoth he), it is now no fit time to busie your self about your nayles.’ Yet concerning this purpose, I saw not many years since a friend of mine, whose name and memory (for diverse respects) I hould in singular account, who in the midst of our troublous mischiefes, when no more then at this time neither lawe, nor justice, nor magistrate was executed or did his office, published certain silly reformations concerning the excess of aparell, gluttony and dyet, and abuses committed among pettyfogging lawiers. They be ammusings wherewith a people in a desperate taking is fed, that so men may say they are not cleane forgotten. Even so do these others who mainely apply themselves to forbid certain manners of speach, dances and vain sports, unto a people wholy given over to all licenciousnesse and execrable vices. It is then no convenient time for a man to wash and netifie himself when he is assailed by a violent fever. It only belongs to Spartans to tricke, to combe and wash themselves at what time they are ready to cast themselves into some extreme hazard of life. As for me, I am subject to this ill custom, that if but a pump fit not handsomly upon my foot, I shall also neglect my shirt and my cloake; for I disdaine to correct my self by halfes when I am in bad estate, I flesh my self on evil and abandon my self through despaire, and run to downefall, and (as the saying is) cast the haft after the hatchet. I grow obstinate in empairing; and esteeme my self no more worthy of my care, either all well or all evil. It is a favor to me that the desolation of our state does sutably meet with the desolation of my age: I rather endure that my evills should thereby be surcharged then if my goods had thereby been troubled. The words I utter against misfortune are words of spite. My courage, insteed of yielding, does grow more obstinate; and contrary to others, I find my self more given to devotion in prosperous then adverse fortune; according to Xenophons rule, if not according to his reason. And I rather looke on heaven with a chearefull eye, to thanke it, then to begge any thing. I am more careful to encrease my health when it smiles upon me, then to recover it when I have lost it. Prosperities are to me as discipline and instruction, as adversities and crosses are to others. As if good fortune were incompatible with a good conscience, men never become honest but by adverse and crosse chances. Good fortune is to me a singular motive unto moderation and forcible spurre unto modesty. Prayers winne me, menaces reject me, favors relent me, fear imperverseth me. Amongst humane conditions this one is very common, that we are rather pleased with strange things then with our own; we love changes, affect alterations, and like innovations. Ipsa dies ideo nos grato perluit haustu, Quod permutatis hora recurrit equis. Times therefore us refresh with welcome air, Because their hours on chang’d horse do repayre. And my share is therein. Such as follow the other extremity, only to be well pleased with and in themselves, and self-conceitedly to over-esteeme what they possesse above others, and acknowledge no form fayrer then that they see, if they be not more advised then we, they are indeed more happy. I envie not their wisdom, but grudge their good fortune. This greedy humor of new and unquenchable desire of unknown things dooth much increase and nourish in me a desireto travell; but diverse other circumstances conferre unto it. I am well pleased to neglect and shake of the government of my own household. It is some pleasure to command, were it but a mole-hill, and a delight to be obaied. But it is a pleasure over-uniform and languishing. Besides that it is ever necessarily intermixed with troublous cares and hart-wearing thoughts. Sometimes the indigence and oppression of your own people, sometimes the contentions and quarels of your neighbors, and othertimes their insulting and usurpation over you, does vexe, does trouble and afflict you: Aut verberatæ grandine vineæ, Fundusque mendax, arbore nunc aquas Culpante nunc torrentia agros Sydera, nunc hyemes iniquas. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. i. 29. Or Vinevards beate and wet with haile and raine, Or grounds defrauding hope, while trees complain, Sometime of waters, sometime of those starres That scorch the fields, sometime of winters wars. And that God will hardly once in halfe a yeare send you a season that shall throughly please your Bayly and content your Receaver; and that if it be good for your vines, it be not hurtful for your meddowes. Aut nimiis torret fervoribus ætherius Sol, Aut subiti perimunt imbres, gelidæque pruinæ Flabraque ventorum violento turbine vexent. -- Lucr. v. 215. Or with excessive heate heavens Sunne does toast, Or sodaine stormes do kill, and chilling frost, Or violent whirle-wind blasts do vexe the coast. As that new and well-shapen shoe of that man of former ages, which hurts and wrings your foote and that a stranger knowes not what it costes you and what you contribute to maintaine the show of that order which is seen in your housholde, and which perhaps you purchase at too high a rate. It was very late before I betooke my self to husbandrie. Those whom nature caused to be borne before me have long time ridde me of that careful burden: I had already taken another habite more suitable to my complexion. Nevertheless by that I have observed therein, I find it to be rather a troublesome then a hard occupation. Whosoever is capable of any other thing may easily discharge that. If I would seek to grow rich, that way would seem over-long and tedious to me: I would then have served our kings, a trade more beneficiall then all others, since I pretend but to get the reputation that as I have gotten nothing, so have I not wasted any thing; suitable to the rest of my life; as unfit to affect any good, as improper to work any evil of consequence; and that I only seek to weare out my life, I may (God be thanked) do it without any great attention: if the worst come to pass, before poverty assaile you, seek by prevention to cut of your charges, and by husbanding your expences keep aforehand with it; that is it I trust unto, and hope to reforme my self before it come neare or enforce me to it. As for other matters, I have forestalled many degrees and established sundry ways in my mind, to live and rubbe out with less then I have. I say to live with contentment. Non estimatione census, verum victu atque cultu, terminatur pecuniæ modus: (Cic. Parad.) ’The measure of money is lymited not by the estimate of wealth or place, but by the manner of living and other furniture.’ My very neede does not so precisely possesse my whole estate, but that without touching to the quick or empairing the main, fortune shall find something to play upon or take hold of. My very presence, as ignorant and grim as it is, affordeth much helpe to my houshould affairs: I apply my self thereunto but somewhat dispightfully, considering the manner of my house, which is, that severally to burne my candle at one end, the other is thereby nothing spared. Travelsdo not much hurt me, were it not for the charges, which are exceeding great and beyond my ability, having ever been accustomed to journey not only with necessary, but also decent equipage; and that’s the reason I make but short journeis and travel not to often; wherein I employ but the scumme and what I can well spare, temporising and differing according as it commeth more or less. I will not have the pleasure of my wandring to corrupt the delight of my retiring. Contrary-wise, my intent is that they nourish and favor one another. Fortune has steaded me in this, that since my chiefest profession in this life was to live delicately and quietly, and rather negligently then seriously, it has deprived me of need to hoard up riches to provide for the multitude of my heirs. For one, if that be not sufficient for him, wherewith I have lived so plenteously, at his own perill be it. His indiscretion shall not deserve that I wish him more. And every man (according to the example of Phocion) provideth sufficiently for his children, that provideth they be not unlike to him. I should by no means be of Crates his mind, or commend his proceedings. He left his money with a banquier upon this condition, That if his children were fooles be should deliver it them; but prooving wise and able to shift for themselves, he should distribute the same amongst the greatest fooles. As if fooles, being least capable to make a shift with out it, were more capable to use riches. So it is that the hurt proceeding from my absence does not (in mine opinion) deserve, so long as I shall have means to bear it, I should refuse to accept the occasions that offer themselves to distract me from this toylesome assistance. There is ever some peece out of square. Sometimes the business of one house, and other times the affairs of another, do hurry you. You pry too neare into all things; herein, as well as elsewhere, your perspicuity does harme you. I steale from such occasions as may move me to anger, and remoove from the knowledge of things that thrive not; yet can I not so use the matter, but still I stumble (being at home) upon some inconvenience which displeaseth me. And slight knaveries that are most hidden from me are those I am best acquainted with. Some there are which to avoyd a further mischief a man must helpe to conceal himself: vain prickings (vain sometimes), but yet ever prickings. The least and sleightest hindrances are the sharpest. And as the smallest letters hurt our eyes most, so the least affairs grieve us most: A multitude of slender evils offendeth more then the violence of one alone, how great soever. Even as ordinary thornes, being small and sharpe, pricke us more sharpely and sans threatning, if on a sudden we bit upon them. I am no Philosopher: Evils oppresse me according as they waigh, and waigh according to their form, as well as according to the matter, and often more. I have more insight in them then the vulgar sort; and so have I more patience. To conclude, if they hurt me not, they lie heavy upon me. Life is a tender thing and easy to be distempered. Since I began to grow towards peevish age, and by consequence toward frowardnes, nemo enim resistit ubi cum ceperit impelli: (SEN. Epist. i. 13 f.) ’For no man stayes himself when he is set on going.’ What ever foolish cause has brought me to it, I provoke the humor that way, which afterward by his own motion is fostred and exasperated, attracting and heaping up one matter upon another, to feede it self withall. Stillicidii casus lapidem cavat. By often falling on, Even water breakes a stone. These ordinary distilling drops consume and ulcerate me. Ordinary inconveniences are never light. They are continuall and irreparable if they continually and inseperatly aryse from the members of husbandry. When I consider my affairs a far off and in grosse, I find, be it because I have no exact memory of them, that hitherto they have thrived beyond my reasons and expectation. Me thinks I draw more from them then there is in them: their good success betraieth me. But am I waded into the business? See I all these parcels march? Tum vero in curas animum deducimus omnes. -- Virg. Æn. v. 720. Then we our mind divide, To cares on every side. A thousand things therein give me cause to desire and fear. Wholy to forsake them is very easy unto me; without toyling, and vexation altogether to apply my self unto them is most hard. It is a pittyfull thing to be in a place where whatsoever you see doeth set on a work and concerne you; And me thinkes enjoy more blithly and taste more choisely the pleasures of a stranger house then of my own, and both my mind and taste run more freely and purely on them. Diogenes answered according to my humor, when being demanded what kind of Wine he liked best, ’Another mans,’ said he. My father delighted to build at Montaigne, where he was borne; and in al this policy of domestick affairs, I love to make use of his examples and rules, unto which I will as much as possibly I can tie my successors. Could I do better for him, I would performe it. I glory his will is at this day practised by me, and does yet work in me. God forbid I should ever suffer any image of life to perish under my hands, that I may yield unto so good and so kind a father. If I have undertaken to finish any old peece of wall, or repare any building either imperfect or decaied, it has certainly been because I had rather a respect to his intention then a regard to my contentment. And I blame my negligence or lithernesse that I have not continued to perfect the foundations he had laid, or beginnings he had left in his house; by so much the more because I am in great likelihood to be the last possessor of it, namely of my race, and set the last hand unto it. For concerning my particular Application, neither the pleasure of building, which is said to be so bewitching, nor hunting, nor hawking, nor gardens, nor such other delights of a retired life, can much embusie or greatly ammuse me. It is a thing for which I hate my self, as of all other opinions that are incommodious to me. I care not so much to have them vigorous and learned as I labor to have them easy and commodious unto life. They are indeed sufficiently true and sound, if they be profitable and pleasing. Those who hearing me relate my own insufficiencie in matters pertaining to husbandry or thrift, are still whispering in mine ears that it is but a kind of disdaine, and that I neglect to know the implements or tooles belonging to husbandry or tillage, their seasons and orders; how my wines are made, how they graft, and understand or know the names and formes of hearbes, of simples, of fruits, and what belongs to the dressing of meats wherewith I live and whereon I feede; the names and prices of such stuffes I cloath my selfewithall, only because I do more seriously take to heart some higher knowledge; bring me in a manner to deaths doore. This is meere sottishnesse, and rather brutishnesse then glory: I would rather be a cunning horseman then a good Logician. Quin tu aliquid saltem potius quorum indiget usus, Viminibus Monique paras detexere junco? -- Virg. Buc. Ecl. ii. 71. Why rather with soft wings make you not speed, To work-up something whereof there is need? We hinder our thoughts from the general and main point, and from the causes and universall conducts, which are very well directed without us, and omit our own business, and Michæl, who concernes us nearer then man. Now I most commonly stay at home, but I would please my self better there then any where else. Sit mea sedes utinam senectæ, Sit modus lasso maris, et viarum, . . . Militiæque. -- Hor. Car. ii. Od. vi. 6. Some repair and rest to mine old age I crave Journying, failing, with a weary warring, O let an end have. I wot not whether I shall come to an end of it. I would that in lieu of some other part of his succession, my father had resigned that passionate love and dear affection which in his aged yeeres he bare unto his houshold husbandry. He was very fortunate in conforming his desires unto his fortune, and knew how to be pleased with what he had. Politike Philosophy may how it list accuse the basenesse and blame the sterilitie of my occupation, if, as he did, I may but once find the taste of it. I am of this opinion, that the honorablest vocation is to serve the Commonwealth, and be profitable to many. Fructus enim ingenii et virtutis, omnisque præstantiæ, tum maximus accipitur, quum in proximum quemque confertur: (Cic. Amer.) ’For then is most fruit reaped, both of our wit and virtue and all other excellencie, when it is bestowed upon our neighbors.’ As for me, I depart from it, partly for conscience sake (for whence I discern the waight concerning such vacations, I also discover the slender means I have to supply them withall; And Plato, a master workeman in all politike government, omitted not to abstaine from them), partl y for lithernesse. I am well pleased to enjoy the world without troubling or pressing my self with it; to live a life only excusable, and which may neither be burthensome to me nor to any other. Never did man go more plainly and carelesly to work in the care and government of a third man, then I would, had I a ground to work upon. One of my wishes at this instant should be to find a son in law that could handsomely allure and discreetly beguile my old yeeres, and lull them asleepe; into whose hands I might despose and in all soveraignity resigne the conduct and managing of my goods, that he might dispose of them as I do, and gain upon them what I gain; alwaies provided he would but carry a truely thankfull and friendly mind. But what? we live in a world where the loyalty of our own children is not knowen. Whosoever has the charge of my purse when I travell has it freely and without controll; as well might he deceive me in keeping of reckonings. And if he be not a Divell, I bind him to deale well and honestly by my carelesse confidence. Multifallere docuerunt, dum timent falli, et aliis jus peccandi suspicando fecerunt: ’Many have taught others to deceive while themselves fear to be deceived, and have given them just cause to offend by suspecting them unjustly.’ The most ordinary assurance I take of my people is a kind of disacknowledge or neglect; I never presume vices but after I have seen them; and trust more yoong men such as I imagine to be the least debaushed and corrupted by ill examples. I had rather hear at two months end that I have spent foure hundred crownes, then every night when I should go to my quiet bed have mine ears tired and my mind vexed with three, five, or seven. Yet in this kind of stealing have I had as little stolne from me as any other; True it is, I lend a helping hand to ignorance. I wittingly entertaine a kind of troubled and uncertaine knowledge of my money; until it come to a certain measure I am content to doubt of it. It is not amisse if you allow your boy or servant some small scope for his disloyalty and indiscretion. If in grosse we have sufficiently left to bring our matters to pass, this excess of fortunes- liberalitie, let us somewhat more suffer it to stand to her mercy, It is the gleaners fee. After all, I esteeme not so much my peoples fidelity as I disesteeme their injuries. Oh base and absurd study, for a man to study his money, and please himself with handling and counting the same; for that’s the way whereby covetousnesse maketh her approches. Since eighteene yeeres that I have had the full disposing of my goods in my own hands, I could never yet be brought to overlooke neither titles nor bookes, no not so much as the principal affairs that should necessarily pass through my knowledge and care. It is no Philosophicall contempt to neglect worldly and transitorie things: my taste is not so exquisitely nice, for I value them according to their worth at least: but truly it is all inexcusable slothfulnesse and childish negligence. What would I not rather do then read a contract? And more willingly, as a slave to my businesses with carke to overlooke and care to survay a company of old-dusty bookes, and plod upon musty writings? and which is worse, other mens, as so many do daily for money? I have nothing so dear as care and pain; and I only endeavour to become carelesse and retchlesse. I had, in mine opinion, been fitter (if it might be) to live by others fortune, without bounden duty or bondage. And yet I wot not (the matter being thorowly sifted) whether, according to my humor and fortune, what I must endure with my affairs, and pocket up at my servants and familiars hands, has not more abjection, importunitie and sharpenesse, then the following of another man should have better borne then my self, and who should [guide] me somewhat at mine ease. Servitus obedientia est fracti animi et abjecti, arbitrio carentis suo: (Cic. Parad. v.) ’Service is an obedience of an abject, broken heart, that cannot dispose of itself.’ Crates did worse who voluntarily cast himself into liberties of povertie, only to ridd himself of the inconveniences, indignities and cares of his house; which I would not do. I hate povertie as much as grief; yet could I find in my heart to change this manner of life with another less glorious and not so troublesome. Being absent, I discharge my self of all such careful thoughts, and should less feel the ruinous down-fall of a Town, then, being present, the fall of a Tile: Alone my mind is easily freed, but in company it indureth as much as a Plough-mans. My horse uncurb’d, his reines misplaced, or a stirrup or a strap hitting against my legge, will keep me in a checke a whole day long. I rouze my courage sufficiently against inconvenience; mine eyes I cannot, Sensus o superi sensus! At home I am ever answerable for whatsoever is amisse. Few masters (I speak of meane condition, as mine is; whereof if any be, they are the more happy) can so fully rely upon a second, but still a good part of the burden shall lie upon them. That does perhaps take something from my fashion, in entertaining of guests or new commers; and happily I have been able to stay some, more by my kitchin then by my behaviour or grace, as do the peevish and fantastic; and I greatly diminish the pleasure I should take in my house by the visitations and meetings of my friends. No countenance is so foolish or so ill beseeming a gentleman in his own house, as to see him vexed or troubled about his houshold or domesticke affairs; to see him whisper one of his servants in the eare, and threaten another with his looke. It should insensibly glide on, and represent an ordinary course. And I utterly dislike that a man should entertains his guest with either excusing or boasting of the entertainment he affoordeth them. I love order and cleanlinesse - ------ et cantharus et lanx, Ostendunt mihi me. -- Hor. i. Ep. v. 23. My dish, my drinking kanne, Shew me what kind of man - well nigh as much as plentie: In my own house I exactly looke unto necessities, little unto state, and less unto ornament. If your neighbors servant be fighting with his companion, if a dish be overthrowen, you but laugh at it, you sleepe quietly whilst Sir such a one is busie casting up of accounts, and over-seeing his stocke with his steward, and all about your provision for tomorrow. I speak according to mine opinion, omitting not in general to think how pleasing an ammusement it is to certain natures to see a quiet and prosperous houshold directed by a formall and guided by a regular order. But not intending to fasten my own errours and inconveniences to the matter: Nor to gainesay Plato, who deemeth that the happiest occupation any man can follow, is, to apply himself to his own private business without injustice. When I journey, I have nothing to care for but my self, and how my money is laid out, which is disposed with one only precept. Over-many parts are required in hoarding and gathering of goods: I have no skill in it. In spending I have some knowledge, and how to give my expences [play]: which indeed is its principal use. But I attend it over ambitiously, which makes it both unequall and deformed; and besides that immoderate in one and other usage. If it appeare and make a good show, if it serve the turn, I indiscreetly go after it; and as indiscreetly restraine my self, if it shine or smile not upon me. Whatsoever it be, either Art or nature, that imprints this condition of life into us, by relation to others, it does us much more hurt then good. In going about to frame apparances according to the common opinion, we defraud ourselves of our own profits. We care not so much what our state or how our being is in us, and in effect, as we do how and what it is, in the public knowledge of others. Even the goods of the mind, and wisdom itself, seem fruitlesse unto us, if only enjoyed by us; except it be set forth to the open view and approbation of strangers. There are some whose gold runnes by streames in places under ground, and that imperceptible; others extend the same in plates and leaves. So that to some pence are worth crownes, to others the contrary; the world judging the employment and value according to the outward show. All over-nice care and curious heed about riches has a touch or a taste of avarice. Even their dispending and over regular and artificiall liberalities are not worth a warie heed taking, and countervaile not a painefull diligence. Who so will make his expence even and just, makes it strict and forced; either close-keeping or employing of money are in themselves things indifferent, and admit no colour of good or evil but according to the application of our will. The other cause that draws me to these Journeyes or Vagaries is the dissent or disparitie in the present manners of our state. I could easily comfort my self with this corruption in regard of the public interest; -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 28. Times worse then times of Iron, for whose bad frame And wickednesse even nature findes no name, Nor has from any metall set the same. But not for my own: I am in particular over-pressed by it. For round about where I dwell we are, by the over-long licentiousnesse of our intestine civill wars, almost growen old, in so licentious and riotous a form of state, Quippe ubi fas versum atque nefas. -- Virg. Georg. i. 505. As where of good and bad, There is no difference had. That in good truth it were a wonder if it should continue and maintaine itself. Armati terram exercent, semperque recentes Convectare juvat prædas, et vivere rapto. -- Virg. Æn. ix. 612. They armed plow the land, and joy to drive, And draw new booties, and on rapine live. To conclude, I see by our example that the societie of men does hold and is sewed together, at what rate soever it be; where ever they be placed, in mooving and closing, they are ranged and stowed together, as uneven and rugged bodies, that orderlesse are hudled in some close place, of themselves find the way to be united and joined together one with another; and many times better then Art could have disposed them. King Philip assembled a rabble of the most leaud, reprobate and incorrigible men be could find out, all whch he placed in a City which of purpose he had caused to be built for them, of whom it bare the name. I imagine that even of their vices they erected a politike contexture amongst themselves, and a commodious and just societie. I see not one action, or three, or a hundred, but even diverse manners, admitted and commonly used; so extravagant (namely, in disloyalty) and so barbarous in inhumanities which in my conceit are the worst and most execrable kind of vices, that I have not the heart so much as to conceive them without horrour: All which I in a manner admire as much as I detest. The exercise of these egregious villanies beareth a brand of vigor and hardinesse of mind as much as of error and irregular confusion. Necessitie composeth and assembleth men together. This casual combining is afterward framed into laws. For there have been some as barbarously-savage as humane opinion could possibly produce, which notwithstanding have kept their bodies in as good health and state, in long life, as those of Plato or Aristotle could do. And to say true, all these descriptions of policy, feigned by Art and supposition, are found ridiculous and foolish to be put in practise. These great and long continuing altercations about the best form of societie and most commodious rules to unite us together, are altercations only proper for the exercise of our wit: As in arts diverse subjects are found that have no essence but in agitation and disputing, without which they have no life at all. Such an Idea of policy, or picture of government, were to be established in a new world; but we take a world already made and formed to certain customs; we engender not the same as Pyrrha, nor beget it as Cadmus. By what means soever we have the privilege to re-erect and range the same anew, we can very hardly wrest it from the accustomed habit and fold it has taken, except we breake all. Solon being demanded whether he had established the best laws he could for the Athenians: answered, indeed of those they would have received: with such a shift does Varro excuse himself, saying, that if he were newly to beginne to write of religion, he would plainly tell what his beleefe were of it: But being alreadie received, he will speak more of it according to custom then to nature. Not to speak by opinion, but consonant to truth, the most excellent and best policy for any nation to observe, is that under which it has maintained itself. Its form and essentiall commoditie does much depend of custom. We are easily displeased with the present condition; yet do I hold that to wish the government of few in a popular estate, or in a Monarchie another kind of policy, it is a manifest vice and meere folly. Ayme l’estat tel que tu le vois estre, S’il est royall, ayme la royaute, S’il est de peu, ou bien Communaute, Ayme l’aussi, car Dieu a faict naistre. -- Pibrac. Love you the state as you seest it to be: If it be Regall, love the royall race, If of a few or Common-weale, embrace It as it is, borne there God pointed you. So was the good Lord of Pibrac wont to speak of it, whom we have lately lost, a man of so quaint and rare wit, of so sound judgement, and of so mild and affable behaviour. The untimely loss of whom, with that of the Lord of Foix, both fatally happning to us at one time, are surely losses of great consequence unto our crowne. I wot not well, whether France, amongst all the men it has left, is able to affoord us two such other Gentlemen as may, either in sincerity and woorth, or in sufficiencie and judgement for the counsell of our Kings match these two Gascoynes. They were two mindes diversly fair, and verily, if we respect the corrupted age wherein we live, both rare and gloriously-shining, every one in her form. But alas! what destiny had placed them on the Theater of his age, so dissonant and different in proportion from our deplorable corruption, and so far from agreeing with our tumultuous stormes? Nothing does so neerely touch and so much overlay an estate as innovation: Only change does give form to injustice and scope to tyranny. If some one peece be out of square, it may be underpropt: one may oppose himself against that which the alteration incident and corruption natural to all things does not too much elonge and draw us from our beginnings and grounded principles. But to undertake to re-erect and found again so huge a masse, and change or remoove the foundations of so vast a frame, belongeth only to them who, instead of purging deface, and in liew of cleansing scrape out; that will amend particular faults by an universall confusion and cure diseases by death: Non tam commutandarum quam evertendarum rerum cupidi: ’Not so desirous to have things altered as overthrowen.’ The world is fondly unapt to cure itself: So impatient with that which vexeth or grieveth it, that it only aimeth to ridd itself of it, never regarding at what rate. We see by a thousand examples that it does ordinarily cure itself at its own charges: To be freed from a present evil is no perfect cure, except there be a general amendment of condition. The end of a skilfull Chirurgion is not to mortifie the bad flesh, it is but the beginning and addressing of his cure: he aimeth further, that is, to make the natural to grow again, and reduce the partie to his due being and quality. Who ever proposeth only to remoove what gnaweth him shall be to seek: for good doeth not necessarily succeed evil: another, indeed a worse evil may succeed it. As it hapned unto Cesars murderers, who brought the commonwealth to so distresfull a plunge that they repented themselves they ever medled with the same. The like has since fortuned to diverse, indeed in our days. The French that live in my times know very well what to speak of such matters. All violent changes and great alterations, disorder, distemper and shake a state very much. He that should rightly respect a sound recovery or absolute cure, and before all other things thorowly consult about it, might happily grow slacke in the business, and beware how he set his hand unto it. Pacuvius Calavius corrected the vice of this manner of proceeding by a notable example. His fellow Citizens had mutinied against their magistrates; He being a man of eminent authority in the cittie of Capua, found one day the means to shut up the Senate in the Guildhall or Palace; then calling the people together in the market place, told them that the day was now come wherein with full and unresisted liberty they might take vengeance of the tyrants that had so long and so many ways oppressed them, all which he had now at his mercy, and unarmed. His opinion was, that orderly by lots they should be drawne out one after another; which done they might particularly dispose of every one, and whatsoever should be decreed of them, shold immediately be executed upon the place; provided they should therewithall presently advise and resolve to nominate and establish some honest and undetected man to supply the roome of the condemned, lest their cittie should remaine void of due officers. To which they granted, and heard no sooner the name of a Senatour read, but a loud exclamation of a general discontent was raised against him; which Pacuvius perceiving, he requested silence, and thus bespake them. ’My countrymen, I see very well that man must be cut off, he is a pernicious and wicked member but let us have another sound good man in his place and whom would you name for that purpose?’ This unexpected speech bred a distracted silence, each one finding himself to seek and much confounded in the choise. Yet one, who was the boldest impudent amongst them, nominated one whom he thought fittest; who was no sooner heard but a general consent of voices, louder than the first, followed, all refusing him, as one taxed with a hundred imperfections, lawfull causes, and just objections, utterly to reject him. These contradicting humors growing more violent and hot, every one following his private grudge or affection, there ensued a far greater confusion and hurly-burly in drawing of the second and third Senatour, and in naming and choosing their successours, about which they could never agree. As much disorder and more confusion about the election, as mutual consent and agreement about the demission and displacing. About which tumultuous trouble when they had long and to no end laboured and wearied themselves, they began some here, some there, to scatter and steale away from the assemblies every one with this resolution in his mind, that the oldest and best knowen evil is ever more tolerable then a fresh and unexperienced mischiefs. By seeing ourselves piteously tossed in continuall agitation: for what have we not done? Eheu cicatricum et sceleris pudet, Fratrumque: quid nos dura refugimus Ætas? quid intactum nefasti Liquimus? unde manus juventus Metu Deorum continuit? quibus Pepercit aris? -- Hor. Car. i. Od. xcv. 33. Alas for shame of wickenuesse, and scarres, Of brother-country-men in civill wars. We of this hardned world, what do we shunne? What have we execrable left undone? To set their hand whereto has youth not dared For fear of Gods? what altars has it spared? I am not very sudden in resolving or concluding. ----ipsa si velit salus, Servare prorsus non potest hanc familiam: -- Ter. Adel. act. iv. sc. 7. This familie if safetie would Keepe safe, I do not think it could. Yet are we not perhaps come unto our last period. The preservation of states is a thing in all likelihood exceeding our understanding. A civill policy (as Plato says) is a mighty and puisant matter, and of very hard and difficult dissolution; it often endureth against mortal and intestine diseases, indeed, against the injury of unjust laws, against tyrannie, against the ignorance and debordement of Magistrates, and against the licentiousnesse and sedition of the people. In all our fortunes we compare ourselves to that which is above us, and looke toward those that are better. Let us measure ourselves by that which is beneath us; there is no creature so miserably wretched but findes a thousand examples to comfort himself withall. It is our fault that we more unwillingly behold what is above us then willingly what is beneath us. And Solon said, that should a man heape up in one masse all evils together, there is none that would not rather chuse to carry back with him such evils as he alreadie has, then come to a lawfull division with other men of that chaos of evils, and take his allotted share of them. Our Common-wealth is much crazed and out of tune. Yet have diverse others been more dangyerously sicke, and have not died. The gods play at hand-ball with us, and tosse us up and down on all hands. Enim vero dii nos homines quasi pitas habent: (Plaut. Capt. Prol.) ’The gods perdie do reckon and racket us men as their tennis-balles.’ The destinies have fatally ordained the State of Rome for an exemplar patterne of what they can do in this kind. It containeth in itself all formes and fortunes that concerne a state, whatsoever order, trouble, good or bad fortune may in any sort effect in it. What man may justly despaire of his condition, seeing the agitation, troubles, alterations, turmoiles, and motions wherewith it was tossed to and fro, and which it endured? If the extention of rule and far-spreading domination be the perfect health of a state, of which opinion I am not in any wise (and Isocrates does greatly please me, who instructeth Nicocles not to envie those Princes who have large dominations, but such as can well maintaine and orderly preserve those that have been hereditarily escheated unto them) that of Rome was never so sound as when it was most sicke and distempered. The worst of its form was to it the most fortunate. A man can hardly distinguish or know the image of any policy under the first Emperors; it was the most horrible and turbulent confusion that could be conceaved, which notwithstanding it endured and therein continued, preserving, not a Monarchie bounded in her limits, but so many nations, so different, so distant, so evil affected, so confusedly commanded, and so unjustly conquered. -----nec gentibus ullis Commodat in populum terræ pelagique potentem, Invidiam fortuna suam. -- Lucr. i. 82. Fortune does to no other nation lend Envie, against that people force to bend, Which both by land and sea their force extend. All that shaketh does not fall: The contexture of so vast a frame holds by more then one naile. It holds by its antiquity, as olde buildings which age has robbed of foundation, without loame or morter, and nevertheless live and subsist by their own waight. ------ nec jam validis radicibus hærens Pondere tuta suo est. -- Ibid. 138. Though now to no strong roote it sticke so fast Yet is it safe by self-waight, and will last. Moreover, he goes not cunningly to work, that only survayes the flankes and dykes; to judge well of the strength of a place, he must heedily marke how and view which way it may be approached, and in what state the assailant stand. Few vessels sinke with their own waight, and without some extraordinary violence. Cast we our eyes about us and in a general survay consider all the world; all is tottring, all is out of frame. Take a perfect view of all great states by in Christendome and where ever else we have knowledge of, and in all places you shall find a most evident threating of change and ruine: Et sua sunt illis incommoda, pargue per omnes Tempestas. Their discommodities they know: One storme likewise oer all does grow. Astrologers may sport themselves with warning us, as they do, of imminent alterations and succeeding revolutions; their divinations are present and palpable; we need not prie into the heavens to find them out. We are not only to draw comfort from this universall aggregation of evil and threats, but also some hope for the continuance of our state; forasmuch as naturally nothing falleth where all things fall; a general disease is a particular health: Conformitie is a quality enemy to dissolution. As for me, I nothing despaire of it, and me thinks I already perceive some starting holes to save us by: Deus hæc fortasse benigna Reducet in sedem vice. -- Hor. Epod. xiii. 10. It may be, God with gracious entercourse Will reestablish these things in their course. Who knowes whether God has determined it shall happen of them as of bodies that are purged, and by long grievous sicknesses brought to a beter and sounder state; which thorowly purged diseases do afterward yield them a more entire and purely-perfect health then that they took from them? That which grieveth me most is, that, counting the symptomes or affects of our evil, I see as many meerely proceeding of nature, and such as the heavens send us, and which may properly be termed theirs, as of those that our own surfet, or excess, or misse-diet, or humane indiscretion confer upon us. The very Planets seem orderly to declareunto us that we have continued long enough, indeed beyond our ordinary limits. This also grieves me, that the neerest evil threatning us is not a distemper or alteration in the whole and solid masse, but a dissipation and divulsion of it - the extreamest of our feares. And even in these fantastic humors or dotings of mine, I fear the treason of my memory, least unmanly it have made me to register somethings twise. I hate to correct and agnize my self, and can never endure but grudgingly to review and repolish what once has escaped my pen. I here set down nothing that is new or lately found out. They are vulgar imaginations, and which perhaps having been conceived a hundred times, I fear to have already enrolled them. Repetition is ever tedious, were it in Homer: But irkesome in things that have but one superficiall and transitorie show. I am nothing pleased with inculcation or wresting-in of matters, be it in profitable things, as in Seneca. And the manner of his Stoike schoole displeaseth me, which is, about every matter, to repeat at large, and from the beginning to the end such principles and presuppositions as serve in general: and every hand-while to re-allege anew the common arguments and universall reasons. My memory does daily grow worse and worse, and is of late much empaired: Pocula lethæos ut si ducentia somnos, . . . Arente fauce traxerim.-- Hor. Epod. xiv. 3. As though with drie lips I had drunke that up, Which draws oblivious sleepe in drowsie cup. I shall henceforward be faine (for hitherto, thankes be to God, no capital fault has hapned), whereas others seek time and occasion to premeditate what they have to say, that I avoid to prepare my self, for fear I should tie my self to some strict bond, on which I must depend. To be bound and tied does somewhat distract me: namely, when I am wholly to rely and depend on so weake an instrument as is in my memory. I never read this story, but I feel a certain proper and natural offence. Lyncestes being accused of a conspiracie against Alexander, the very same day that, according to custom, he was led forth in presence of all the army to be heard in his own defense, had in his mind a premeditated oration, which he had studiously learnt by rote, whereof, stammering and faltring, having uttered some words: And wrestling with his memory, and striving to run-it over again, he was sodainly charged by the soldiers that were about him, and slain with pikes, as they who held him to be convicted. His amazement and silence served them as a confession; for they supposed that having had so long leisure in prison to prepare himself, it was not (as they thought) his memory failed him, but his guilty conscience bridled so his tongue and deprived him of his wonted faculties. It was truly well spoken. The very place, the company and expectation astonishes a man when he most aimeth at an ambition of well-speaking. What can a man do when a meere oration shall bring his life into consequence? As for me, if I be tide unto a prescript kind of speaking, what bindes me to it dooth also loose me from it, when I have committed and wholly assigned my self unto my memory, I so strongly depend on the same that I overwhelme it: she faints under her own burden. So much as I refer my self unto her, so much am I divided from self, until I make tryall of in countenance. And I have some times been in pain in concealing the bondage whereunto I was engaged: whereas my dessigne, in speaking, to represent a main carelesnesse of accent and countenance, suddaine and unpremeditated, or casual motions as rising of present occasions; rather loving to say nothing of any worth, then make show I came provided to speak well: a thing above all unseemely to men of my profession, and of over strict an obligation to one that cannot hold much. Preparation gives more to hope then it brings with it.A man does often strip himself into his doblet, to leape shorter then he did in his gowne. Nihil est his, qui placere volunt, tam adversauum, quam expectatio: ’There is none so great an enemy to them that would please as expectation.’ It is written of Curio the Orator, that when he proposed the distribution of the parts of his oration into three or foure, or the number of his arguments and reasons, it was his ordinary custom either to forget some one, or adde one or two more unto it. I have ever shunned to fall into such an inconvenience, as one hating these self-promises and prescriptions: Not only for the distrust of my memory, but also because this form draws over neare unto an artiste. Simpliciora militates decent: ’Plaine wordes and manners become Martialists.’ Sufficeth, I have now made a vow unto my self, no more to undertake the charge to speak in any place of respect: For to speak in reading what one has written, besides that it is most foolish and absurde, it is a matter of great disadvantage to such as by nature were interressed or might do any thing in the action. And wholy to rely or cast my self to the mercy of my present invention, much less: I have it by nature so dulle and troubled, that it cannot in any wise supply me in sudaine and stead me in important necessities. May it please the gentle reader to suffer this one part of Essay to run on, and this third strain or addition of the rest of my pictures peeces. I adde, but I correct not; First, because he who has hypothekised or engaged his labor to the world, I find apparance that he has no longer right in the same; let him, if he be able, speak better els where, and not corrupt the work he has already made sale off; Of such people a man should buy nothing but after they are dead: let them throughly think on it before they produce the same. Who hastens them? My book is alwaies one, except that according as the Printer goes about to renew it, that the buyers depart not altogether empty-handed, I give my self law to adde thereto (as it is but uncoherent checky, or ill joined in laid work) some supernumerall embleme. They are but over-waights, which disgrace not the first form, but give some particular price unto every one of the succeeding, by an ambitious pety subtility. Whence, notwithstanding, it may easily happen that some transposition of chronology is thereto commixt: my reports taking place according to their opportunity, and not ever according to their age. Secondly, forasmuch as in regard of my self I fear to loose by the exchange: My understanding does not alwaies go forward, it sometimes goes also backeward: I in a manner distrust my own fantasies as much, though second or third, as I do when they are the first, or present as past. We many times correct ourselves as foolishly as we taxe others unadvisedly. I am grown aged by a number of years since my first publications, which were in a thousand five hundred and foure score. But I doubt whether I be encreased one inch in wisdom. My self now and my self anon are indeede two; but when better, in good sooth I cannot tell. It were a goodly thing to be old if we did only march towards amendment. It is the motion of a drunkard, stumbling, reeling, giddie-brain’d, formeles, or of reedes, which the air dooth casually wave to and fro what way it bloweth. Antiochus, in his youth, had stoutly and vehemently wrote ten in favor of the Academy, but being olde be changed copy, and wrote as violently against it: which of the two I should follow, should I not ever follow Antiochus? Having once established a doubt, to attempt to confirme the certainty of humane opinions, were it not an establishing of a doubt, and not of the certainty? and promise that had he had another age given him, with assurance to live, he should ever have been in termes of new agitations , not so much better as other and different? Publike favor has given me some more boldnes then I hoped for; but the thing I fear most is to breed a glutting saciety: I would rather spur then be weary, as a wiseman of my time has done. Commendation is ever pleasing, from whom, from whence, or where-fore soever it come; yet ought a man to be informed of the cause, if he will justly please and applaud himself therewith. Imperfections themselves have their means to be recommended. Vulgar and common estimation is little happy if it come to encounter: And I am deceived, if in my dayes the worst composition,; and absurdest bookes have not gained the credit of popular breath. Verily I am much beholding to diverse honest men, and I thanke them that vouchsafe to take my endeavors in good parte. There is no place where the defects of the fashion do so much appeare, as in a matter that in itself has nothing to recommend it. Good reader, blame not me, for those that pass here, either by the fantazie or unwarinesse of others; for every hand, each workeman brings his own unto them. I neither meddle with orthography (and would only have them follow the ancient) nor with curious painting: I have small experience in either. Where they altogether breake the sence, I little trouble my self therewith; for at least they discharge me. But where they will wrest-in and substitute a false sence (as often they do) and wyre-draw me to their conceits, then they spoyle me. Nevertheless, when the sentence is not strong or sinnowy according to my meaning, an honest man may reject it to be mine. He that shall know how little laborious I am and how framed after my own fashion, will easily believe I would rather endite anew as many more other Essayes, then subject my self to trace these over again, for this childish correction. I was saving, erewhile that being plunged in the deepest mine of this new kind of mettall, I am not only deprived of great familiarity with men of different custom from mine, and other opinions, by which they holde together by a knot, commanding all other knots; but am not also without some hazard, amongst those with whom all things are equally lawfull, most of which cannot now adayes empaire their market towarde our justice, whence the extreme degree of licenciousnesse proceedeth. Casting over all the particular circumstances that concerne me, I find no one man of ours to whome the inhibition of our laws costeth any thing, either in gain ceasing, or in loss appearing (as Lawyers say), more then onto my self. And some there be that in chollericke heate and humorous fury will cracke and vaunt much, that will performe a great deale less then my self, if once we come to an equall balance. As a house at all times freely open, much frequented, of great haunt and officious in entertaining all sorts of people (for I could never be induced to make an implement of war thereof; which I perceive much more willingly to be sought-out and flocked unto where it is furthest from my neighbors) my house has merited much popular affection: And it were a hard matter to gourmandize my self upon my own dung-hill: And I repute it a wonderful and exemplar strangenesse, that having undergone so many stormy- wrackes, so diverse changes and tumultuous-neighbour agitations, it does yet this day continue free, and (as I may say) an undefiled virgin from shedding of blood, spoile, or sacking. For, to say true, it was possible for a man of my disposition to escape from a constant and continuall form, whatsoever it was. But the contrary invasions, hostile incursions, alterations and vicissitudes of fortune round about me, have hitherto more exasperated then mollified the humor of the country, and recharge me with dangers and invincible difficulties. I have escaped. But it grieveth me that it is rather by fortune, indeed and by my discretion, then by justice: And it vexeth me to be without the protection of the laws and under any other safegard then theirs. As things now stand I live more then halfe by the favor of others, which is a severe obligation. I would not be endebted for my safety neither to the goodnesse nor to the good will of our great men, which applaude themselves with my liberty and legalitie; nor to the facilitie of my predecessours or mine own manners: for what if I were other then I am? If my demeanour, the liberty of my conversation, or happilie alliance, binde my neighbors; It is a cruelty that they should acquit themselves of it in suffering me to live, and that they may say, we give him a free and undisturbed continuation of divine service in the chaple of his house, whilst all other Churches round about are by us prophaned and deserted; and we freely allow and pardon him the fruition of his goods and use of his life, as he maintaineth our wives, and in time of need keepeth our cattle. It is long sin ce that in my house we have a share in Lycurgus the Athenians praise, who was the general storier, depositary and guardian of his fellow- citizens goods and purses. I am now of opinion that a man must live by law and authorities and not by recompence or grace. How many gallant men have rather made choise to lose their life then be indebted for the same? I shunne to submit my self to any manner of obligation. But above all to which bindes me by duty of bonds of honor. I find nothing so dear as what is given me, and that because my will remaines engaged by a title of ingratitude: And I more willingly receive such offices as are to be sold: A thing easy to be beleeved, for these I give nothing but money, but for those I give my self. The bond that holdes me by the law of honestie seems to me much more urgent and forcible then that of civill compulsion. I am more gently tyed by a Notarie then by my self. Is it not reason that my conscience be much more engaged to that wherein she has simply and only been trusted? Els my faith oweth nothing, for she has nothing lent her. Let one helpe himself with the confidence or assurance he has taken from me. I would much rather breake the prison of a wall or of the laws, then the bond of my word. I am nicely scrupulous in keeping of my promises, nay almost superstitious, and in all subjects I commonly pass them uncertaine and conditionall. To such as are of no weighty consequence I adde force with the jealousie of my rule: she rackes and chargeth me with her own interest. Yea, in such enterprises as are altogether my own and free, if I speak the word or name the point, me thinkes I prescribe the same unto me; and that to give it to anothers knowledge, it is to preordaine it unto himself. Me seems I absolutely promise when I speak. Thus I make but small bragge of my propositions. The condemnation I make of my self is more mooving, forcible and severe, then that of the judges, who only take me by the countenance of common obligation; the constraint of my conscience is more rigorous and more strictly severe; I faintly follow those duties to which I should be hauled if I did not go to them. Hoc ipsum ita justum est quod recte fit, si voluntarium: (Cic. Off. i.) ’This is so just, as it is well done, if it be voluntary.’ If the action have no glimps of liberty, it has neither grace nor honor. Quid mejus cogit, vix voluntate impetrent. -- Ter. Ad. act. iii. sc. 4. What law enforceth me to do, By will they can scarce winne me to. Where necessitie draws me, I love to relent my will. Qua quicquid imperio cogitur, exigenti magis, quam præstanti acceptum refertur. ’For whatsoever is enforced by command is more imputed to him that exacteth then in him that performeth.’ I know some that follow this aire even unto injustice. They will rather give then restore; sooner lend then pay; and more sparingly do good to him to whom they are bound to do it. I bend not that way, but am mainely against it. I love so much to disoblige and discharge my self, that I have sometimes esteemed as profit the ingratitudes, the offences, and indignities I had received of those to whom, either by nature or accidents, I was by way of friendship somewhat beholding; taking the occasion of their fault for a quittance and discharge of my debt. Although I continue to pay them the apparent offices with common reason, I notwithstanding find some sparing in doing that by justice which I did by affection; and somewhat to ease my self with the attention and diligence of my inward will. Est prudentis sustinere ut cursum, sic impetum benevolentiæ: (Cic. De Amic.)’It is a wisemans part to keep a hand as on the course, so on the career of his goodwill.’ Which where ever I apply my self, is in me too urgent and over pressing, at least for a man that by no means would be enthronged. Which husbandrie stands me in stead of some comfort, about the imperfections of those that touch me. Indeed I am much displeased they should thereby be of less worth; but so it is that I also save something of my engagement and application towards them. I allow of him that loves his child so much the less by how much more he is either deformedly crooked or scald-headed. And not only when he is knavish or shrewd, but also being unlucky or ill borne (for God himself has in that abated of his worth and natural estimation) alwaies provided, that in such a cold and sleight affection he bear himself with moderation and exact justice. In me proximitie of blood does nothing diminish, but rather aggravate defects. After all, according to the skill I have in the knowledge of benefits and thankfulnesse, which is a knowledge very subtill and of great use, I see no man more free and less indebted then hitherto I am my self. What ever I owe, the same I owe simply to common and natural obligations. There is no man more absolutely quit and clear else whence. ----nec sunt mihi nota potentum Munera. With gifts I am not much acquainted, Of mighty men, and much less tainted. Princes give me sufficiently if they take nothing from me, and do me much good if they do me no hurt; it is all I require of them. Oh how much am I beholding to God, forasmuch as it has pleased him that whatsoever I enjoy I have immediately received the same from his grace; that he has particularly reserved all my debt unto himself. I most instantly beseech his sacred mercy that I may never owe any man so much as one essentiall God amercie. Oh thrise fortunate liberty, that has brought me so farr. May it end successefully. I endeavour to have no manner of need of any man. In me omnis spes egt mihi: ’All my hope for all my helpes is my self.’ It is a thing that every man may effect in himself; but they more easily whom God has protected and sheltred from natural and urgent necessities. Indeed it is both lamentable and dangerous to depend of others. Our selves, which is the safest and most lawfull refuge, are not very sure under ourselves. I have nothing that is my own but my self; yet is the possession thereof partly defective and borrowed. I manure my self, both in courage (which is the stronger) and also in fortune, that if all things else shou ld forsake me, I might find something wherewith to please and satisfie my self. EleusHippias did not only store himself with learning, that in time of need he might joyfully withdraw himself amongst the Muses, and be sequestred from all other company; nor only with the knowledge of Philosophie to teach his mind to be contented with her, and when his chance should so dispose of him, manfully to pass over such incommodities as exteriorlie might come unto him; but, moreover, he was so curious in learning to dresse his meat, to notte his hair, to make his cloathes, breeches and shoes, that as much as could possibly be he might wholly rely and trust to himself, and be freed from all forraine helpe. A man does more freely and more blithely enjoy borrowed goods when it is not a bounden jovissance and constrained through neede, and that a man has in his will the power and in his fortune the means to live without them. I know my self well. But it is very hard for me to imagine any liberalitie of another body so pure towards me, or suppose any hospitalitie so free, so hartie and genuine, as would not seem affected, tyrannical, disgraced and attended-on by reproach, if so were that necessitie had forced and tied me unto it. As to give is an ambitious quality, and of prerogative, so is taking a quality of submission. Witnes the injurious and pick-thanke refusall that Bajazeth made of the presents which Themir had sent him. And those which in the behalfe of Soliman the Emperor were sent to the Emperor of Calicut, did so vex him at the heart that he did not only utterly reject and scornfully refuse them, saying that neither himself nor his predecessors before him were accustomed to take any thing, and that their office was rather to give; but beside he caused the Ambassadors, to that end sent unto him, to be cast into a deepe dungeon. When Thetis (says Aristotle) flattereth Jupiter, when the Lacedemonians flatter the Athenians, they do not thereby intend to put them in mind of the good they have done them, which is ever hateful, but of the benefits they have received of them. Those I see familiarly to employ and make use of all men, to begge and borrow of all men, and engage themselves to all men, would doubtlesse never do it, knew they as I do, or tasted they as I have done, the sweet content of a pure and undepending liberty, and if therewithall (as a wiseman ought) they did duly ponder what it is for a man to engage himself into such an obligation, or liberty depriving bond. It may happily be paid sometimes, but it can never be utterly dissolved. It is a cruel bondage to him that loves throughly and by all means to have the free scope of his liberty. Such as are best and most acquainted with me know whether ever they saw any man living less soliciting, less craving, less importuning or less begging then I am, or that less employeth or chargeth others, which if I be, and that beyond all modern example, it is no great wonder, sithence so many parts of my humors or manners contribute thereunto. As a natural kind of stubbornnesse, an impatience to be denied, a contraction of my desires and desseignes, and an insufficiencie or unto- wardlinesse in all manner of affairs; but above all, my most favoured qualities, lethall sloathfulnesse, and a genuine liberty, by all which means I have framed all habite mortally to hate, to be beholding to any creature els, or to depend of other then unto and of my self. True it is, that before I employ the beneficence or liberality of an other, in any light or waighty occasion, small or urgent neede soever, I do to the utmost power employ all that ever I am able to avoid and forbeare it. My friends do strangelie importune and molest me, when they solicite and urge me to entreate a third man. And I deem it a matter of no less charge and imputation to disengage him that is endebted unto me, by making use of him, then to engage my self unto him that oweth me nothing. Both which conditions being removed, let them not looke for any cumbersome, negotious and careful matter at my hands (for I have denounced open war unto all manner of carke and care); I am commodiously easy and ready in times of any bodies necessities and I have also more avoyded to receive, then sought to give, which (as Aristotle says) is also more facile. My fortune has afforded me small means to benefit others, and that little she has bestowed on me, the same has she also meanely and indifferently placed. Had she made me to be so borne that I might have kept some rank amongst men, I would then have been ambitious in procuring to be beloved, but never to be feared or admired. Shall I express it more insolentlie? I would have had as much regard unto pleasing as unto profiting. Cyrus does most wiselie, and by the mouth of an excellent Captain and also a better Philosopher, esteeme his bountie and praise his good deedes far beyond his valor and above his warlike-conquests. And Scipio the elder, wherever he seeketh to prevaile and set forth himself, rateth his debonairitie and valueth his humanitie above his courage and beyond his victories, and has ever this glorious saying in his mouth: ’That he has left his enemies as much cause to love him as his friends.’ I will therefore say that if a man thus owe any thing, it ought to be under a more lawfull title then that whereof I speak, to which the law of this miserable war does engage me, and not of so great a debt, as that of my totall preservation and whole estate, which does unreparablie overwhelme me. I have a thousand times gone to bed in mine house, imagining I should the very same night either have been betrayed or slain in my bed; compounding and conditioning with fortune that it might be without apprehension of feareful astonishment and languishment; And after my praiers have cried out, Impius hæc tam culta novalia miles habebit? -- Virg. Eclog. i. 11. Shall these our grounds so deekt and drest, By godles soldiers be possest? What remedie? It is the place where my self and most of my ancestors were borne: therein have they placed their affection and their name. We harden ourselves unto whatsoever we accustome ourselves. And to a wretched condition, as ours is, custom has been a most favourable present, given us by nature, which enureth and lulleft our sense asleepe to the suffring of diverse evils. Civill wars have this one thing worse then other wars, to cause every one of us to make a watch-tower of his own house. Quam miserum, porta vitam muroque tueri, Vixque suæ tutum viribus esse domus! -- Ovid. Trist. iv. El. i. 69. How hard with gate and wall our life to gard, And scarce be safe in our own houses bard! It is an irkesome extremity for one to be troubled and pressed even in his own houshold and domesticall rest. The place wherein I dwell is ever both the first and last to the battery of our troubles, and where peace is ever [never?] absolutely discerned. Tum quoque cum pax est, trepidant formidine belli -- Lucan. i. 256. Ev’n when in peace they are, They quake for fear of war. -----quoties pacem fortuna lacessit, Hac iter est bellis, melius fortuna, dedisses Orbe sub Eoo sedem, gelidaque sub Arcto, Errantesque domos. -- Ibid. 252. As oft as fortune troubleth peace, their race, Warres makes this way: fortune with better grace, In the Easterne world you shouldst have giv’n them place, Or wandring tents for war, under the cold North-starre. I sometimes draw the means to strengthen my self against these considerations, from carelesnesse and idlenesse, which also in some sort bring us unto resolution. It often befalleth me, with some pleasure, to imagine what mortal dangers are, and to expect them. I do even hood-winkt, with my head in my bosome and with stupidities, plunge my self into death, without considering or knowing it, as into a deep, hollow and bottomlesse abysse, which at one leape does swallow me up, and at an instant does cast me into an eternall slumber, full of insipiditie and indolencie. And in these short, sudden or violent deaths, the consequence I fore-see of them affords me more comfort then the effect of fear. They say, that even as life is not the best because it is long, so death is the best because it is short. I estrange not my self so much by being dead, as I enter into confidence with dying. I enwrap and shrowd my self in that storme which shall blinde and furiously wrap me with a ready and insensible charge. Yet if it hapned (as some gardners say) that those Roses and Violets are ever the sweeter and more odoriferous that grow near unto Garlike and Onions, forasmuch as they sucke and draw all the ill savours of the ground unto them, so that these depraved natures would draw and sucke’all the venome of mine aire and infection of my climate, and by their neerenesse unto me make me so much the better and purer, that I might not lose all. That is not, but of this, something may be, forasmuch as goodnesse is the fairer and more attracting when it is rare, and that contrarietie stifneth and diversitie encloseth well doing in itself, and by the jealousie of opposition and glory it does enflame it. Theeves and stealers (godamercie their kindness) have in particular nothing to say to me: no more have I to them. I should then have to do with over-many sorts of men. Alike consciences lurke under diverse kinds of garments, Alike crueltie, disloialtie and stealing. And so much the worse, by how much it is more base, more safe and more secret under the colour of laws. I hate less an open- professed injurie then a deceiving traiterous wrong, an hostile and war-like then a peacefull and lawfull. Our feaver has seased upon a body which it has not much empaired. The fire was in it, but now the flame has taken hold of it. The report is greater, the hurt but little. I ordinarily answere such as demand reasons for my voiages: That I know what I shunne, but wot not what I seek. If one tell me there may be as little sound health amongst strangers, and that their manners are neither better nor purer then ours, I answere first, that it is very hard: Tam multæ scelerum facies. -- Virg. Georg. i. 506. The formes so manifold Of wickednesse we hold. Secondly, that it is ever a gain to change a bad estate for an uncertaine. And that others evils should not touch us so neare as ours. I will not forget this, that I can never mutiny so much against France but I must needs looke on Paris with a favourable eye: It has my hart from my infancy, whereof it has befalne me as of excellent things: the more other fair and stately cities I have seen since, the more her beauty has power and does still usurpingly gain upon my affection. I love that City for her own sake, and more in her only subsisting and own being then when it is full fraught and embellished with forraine pompe and borrowed garish ornaments: I love her so tenderly that even her spotts, her blemishes and her warts are desire unto me. I am no perfect Frenchman, but by this great- matchlesse City, great in people, great in the felicitie of her situation; but above al, great and incomparable in varietie and diversitie of commodities. The glory of France, and one of the noblest and chief ornaments of the world. God of his mercy free her, and chase away all our divisions from her: Being entirely united to herself, I find her defended from all other violence. I forewarn her, that of all factions, that shall be the worst which shall breed discord and sedition in her. And for her sake, I only fear herself. And surely I am in as great fear for her as for any other part of our state. So long as she shall continue, so long shall I never want a home or retreat to retire and shrowd my self at all times a thing able to make me forget the regret of all other retreates. Not because Socrates has said it, but because such is in truth my humor, and perhaps not without some excuse, to esteeme all men as my countrymen; and as I kindly. embrace a Polonian as a Frenchman, postponing this natural bond to universall and common. I am not greatly strucken with the pleasantnesse of natural aire. Acquaintances altogether new and wholly mine do in my conceit countervaile the worth of all other vulgar and casual acquaintances of our neighbors. Friendships meerely acquired by ourselves do ordinarily exceed those to w hich we are joined either by communication of climate or affinity of blood. Nature has plac’t us in the world free and unbound, we emprison our selves into certain straights: As the Kings of Persia, who bound themselves never to drinke other water then of the river Choaspez, foolishly renouncing all lawfull right of use in all other waters, and for their regard dried up all the rest of the world. What Socrates did in his latter dayes, to deem a sentence of banishment worse then a doom of death against himself, being of the mind I am now, I shall never be neither so base minded nor so strictly habituated in my country that I would follow him. The celestiall lives have diverse images which I embrace more by estimation then by affection. And some too extraordinary, and so highly elevated, which because I am not able to conceive, I cannot embrace by estimation. This humor was very tenderly apprehended by him who deemed all the world to be his city. True it is he disdained peregrinations, and had not much set his foote beyond the territory of Athens. What if he bewailed the mony his friend offred to lay out, to disengage his life, and refused to come out of prison, by the intercession of others, because he would not disobey the laws in a time wherein they were otherwise so corrupted? These examples are of the first kind for me. Of the second there are others, which I could find in the very same man. Many of these rare examples exceed the power of my action; but some exceed also the force of my judgement.Besides these reasons, I deem travell to be a profitable exercise. The mind has therein a continuall excitation, to marke things unknown, and note new objects. And as I have often said: ’I know no better schoole to fashion a man’s life then uncessantly to propose unto him the diversitie of so many other mens lives, customs, humors, and fantasies; and make him taste or apprehend one so perpetuall variety of our natures, shapes, or formes. Therein the body is neither absolutely idle nor wholly troubled, and that moderate agitation does put him into breath.’ My self, as crazed with the collicke as I am, can sit eight, indeed sometimes ten hours on horse-backe, without wearinesse or tyring. Vires ultra sortemque senectæ. -- Virg. Æn. vi. 114. Beyond strength ordinary, Which old yeeres use to carry. No weather is to me so contrary as the scorching heat of the parching Sunne. For, these Umbrels or riding canapies, which since the ancient Romans, the Italians use, do more weary the arms then ease the head. I would faine-faine know what industry it was in the Persians, so anciently, and even in the infancy of luxuriousnesse (as Xenophon reporteth) to fanne themselves, and at their pleasures to make cold shades. I love rainy and durty weather as duckes do. The change either of aire or climate does nothing distemper me. All heavens are likewise to me, I am never vexed or beaten, but with internall alterations, such as I produce my self, which surprise and possesse me least in times of Wayfaring. It is a hard matter to make me resolve of any journey; but if I be once on the way, I hold out as long and as far as another. I strive as much in small as I labor in great enterprises; and to prepare my self for a short journey or to visite a friend, as to undertake a far set voiage. I have learnt to frame my journeyes after the Spanish fashion, all at once and out- right, great and reasonable. And in extreme heats I travell by night, from Sunne-set to Sunne rising. The other fashion, confusedly and in haste to bait by the way and dine, especially in Winter, when the days are so short, is both troublesome for man and incommodious for horse. My Jades are the better, and hold out longer. No horse did ever faile me that held out the first days journey with me. I water them in all waters, and only take care of their last watering, that before I come to mine Inne they have way enough to heat their water. My slothfulnesse to rise in the morning alloweth such as follow me sufficient leisure to dine before we take horse. As for me, I never feed over-late: I commonly get an appetite in eating, and no otherwise: I am never hungry but at the table. Some complain that being maried, and well strucken in years, I have enured my self, and been pleased to continue this exercise. They do me wrong. The best time for a man to leave his house is when he has so ordered and settled the same that it may continue without him; and when he has so disposed his affairs, that they may answere the ancient course and wonted form. It is much more indiscretion, and an argument of want of judgement, to go from home and leave no trusty guard in his house, and which for lacke of care may be slow or forgetfull in providing for such necessities as in your absence it may stand in need of. The most profitable knowledge and honourablest occupation for a matron or mother of a familie is the occupation and knowledge of huswiferie. I see diverse covetous, but few huswifes. It is the mistresse-quality that all men should seek after, and above all other endeavour to find, as the only dowry; that serveth either to ruine and overthrow, or to save and enrich our houses. Let no man speak to me of it; according as experience has taught me, I require in a maried woman the Oeconomicall virtue above all others. Wherein I would have her absolutely skilfull, since by my absence I commit the charge and bequeath the full government of my houshold to her. I see (and that to my grief) in diverse houses the master or goodman come home at noone all weary, durty and dusty, with drudging and toiling about his business; when the mistresse or good-wife is either scarce up, or if she be, she is yet in her closet, dressing, decking, smugging, or trimming of herself. It is a thing only fitting Queenes or Princes; whereof some doubt might be made. It is ridiculous that the idlenesse and unjust that the lithernesse of our wives should be fostered with our sweat and maintained by our travell. No man (as near as I can) shall fortune to have a more free and more absolute use, or a more quiet and more liquid fruition of his goods then I have. If the husband bring matter, nature herself would have women to bring form. Concerning duties of wedlocke-friendship, which some happily imagine to be interessed or prejudiced by the husbands absence, I believe it not. Contrariwise, it is a kind of intelligence that easily growes cold by an over- continuall assistance, and decaieth by assiduitie; for to stand still at racke and manger breedeth a satietie. Every strange woman seems to us an honest woman: And all feel by experience that a continuall seeing one another cannot possibly represent the pleasure men take by parting and meeting again. These interruptions fill me with a new kind of affection toward my own people, and yield me the use of my house more pleasing: vicissitude does now and then en-earnest my mind toward one, and then toward another. I am not ignorant how true amitie has arms long enough to embrace, to claspe and holde from one corner of the world unto another; namely in this, where is a continuall communication of offices that cause the obligation and reviv e the remembrance thereof. The stoickes say that there is so great an affinitie and mutual relation betweene wise men that he who dineth in France feedeth his companion in Egypt; and if one of them do but hould up his finger, where ever it be, all the wise men dispersed upon the habitable land feel a kind of aid thereby. Jovissance and possession appertaine chiefly unto imagination. It embraceth more earnestly and uncessantly what she goeth to fetch, then what we touch. Summon and count all your daily ammusements, and you shall find you are then furthest and most absent from your friend when he is present with you. His assistance releaseth your attention, and gives your thoughts liberty at all times and upon every occasion to absent themselves. If I be at Rome, or any where else, I hold, I survay, and governe my house and the commodities which I have left about and in it. I even see my walles, my trees, my grasse, and my rents to stand, to grow, to decay, and to diminish, within an inch or two of that I should do when I am at home. Ante oculos errat domus, errat forma locorum. My house is still before mine eyes, There still the form of places lies. If we but only enjoy what we touch, farewell our crownes when they are in our coffers, and adiew to our children when they are abroad or a hunting; we would have them nearer. In the garden is it far off? within halfe a days journey ? What, within ten leagues, is it far or near? If it be near, what is eleven, twelve, or thirteene? and so step by step. Verely that woman who can prescribe unto her husband how many steps end that which is near, and which step in number begins the distance she counts far, I am of opinion that she stay him betweene both. ------ excludat jurgia finis.-- Hor. ii. Epist. i. 38. Let the conclusion, Exclude confusion. Utor permiso, caudæque pilos ut equinæ. Paulatim vello: et demo unum, demo etiant unum Dum cadat elusus ratione ruentis acervi. -- Ibid. 45 . I use the grant, and plucke by one and one The horse-tail haires, till when the bush is gone I leave the Jade a curtall tail or none. And let them boldly call for Philosophy to helpe them. To whom some might reproach, since she neither discerneth the one nor other end of the joint, betweene the overmuch and the little, the long and the short, the light and the heavy, the neare and the far, since she neither knowes the beginning nor ending thereof, that she does very uncertainly judge of the middle. Rerum natura nullam nobis dedit cognitionem finium: ’Nature has affoorded us no knowledge of her ends.’ Are they not yet wives and friendes of the deceased that are not at the end of this, but in the other world? we embrace both those that have been, and those which are not yet, not only the absent. We did not condition when we were maried, continually to keep ourselves close hugging one another as some, I wot not what little creatures do we see daily; or as those bewitched people of Karenti, in a kind of dogged manner. And a woman should not have her eyes so greedily or so dotingly fixed on her husband’s fore-part, that if neede shall require she may not view his hinderpartes. But might not the saying of that cunning painter, who could so excellently set foorth their humors and portray their conditions, fitly be placed here, lively to represent the cause of their complaints? Uxor, si cesses, aut te amare cogitat, Aut tete amare, aut potare, aut animo obsequi, Et tibi bene esse soli, cum subi sit male. -- Ter. Adelph. act. i. sc. 1. If you be slow, your wife thinkes that in love you are, Or are belov’d, or drinke, or all for pleasure care, And that you only fare-well when she ill does fare. Or might it be that opposition and contradiction do naturally entertaine, and of themselves nourish them; and that they are sufficiently accommodated, provided they disturbe and incommode you? In truly perfect friendship wherein I presume to have well- grounded experience, I give my self more unto my friend than I draw him unto me. I do not only rather love to do him good, then he should do any to me, but also that he should rather do good unto himself then unto me: For then does he me most good when he does it to himself. And if absence be either pleasing or beneficiall unto him, it is to me much more pleasing then his presence; and that may not properly be termed absence where means and waies may be found to enter-advertise one another. I have heeretofore made good use and reaped commoditie by our absence and distance. We better replenished the benefit and extended further the possession of life by being divided and far-asunder: he lived, he rejoiced, and he saw for me and I for him, as fully as if he had been present: Being together, one partie was idle: We confounded one another. The separation of the place made the conjunction of our mindes and wills the richer. This insatiate and greedy desire of corporall presence does somewhat accuse the weakenesse in the jovissance of soules. Concerning age, which some allege against me, it is cleane contrary. It is for youth to subject and bondage itself to common opinions, and by force to constraine itself for others. It may fit the turn of both the people and itself: We have but overmuch to do with ourselves alone. According as natural commodities faile us, let us sustain ourselves by artificiall means. It is injustice to excuse youth in following her pIeasnres, and forbid age to devise and seek them. When I was yong I concealed my wanton and covered my youthfull passions with wit; and now being aged, I endeavour to pass the sadde and incident to yeeres with sport and debauches. Yet do Platoes laws forbid men to travell abroad before they are forty or fifty years of age, that so their travell may sort more profitable and proove more instructive. I should more willingly consent to this other second article of the said laws, which forbiddeth men to wander abroad after they are once threescore. Of which age few that travell far journies return home again. What care I for that? I undertake it not either to return or to perfect the same. I only undertake it to be in motion: So long as the motion pleaseth me, and I walke that I may walke. Those run not that run after a Benefice or after a hare.But they run that run at barriers and to exercise their running. My design is every where divisible, it is not grounded on great hopes: each day makes an end of it. Even so is my lifes voiage directed. Yet have I seen diverse far countries where I would have been glad to have been staied. Why not? If Chrysippus, Diogenes, Cleanthes, Antipater, and Zeno, with so many other wise men of that roughly-severe and severely-strict Sect, forsooke their Countries (without just cause to be offended with them), only to enjoy another aire? Truly the greatest grief of my peregrinations is, that I cannot have a firme resolution to establish my abiding where I would. And that I must ever resolve with my self to return for to accommodate my self onto common humors, If I should fear to die in any other place then where I was borne, if I thought I should die less at my ease far from my own people, I would hardly go out of France; nay, I should scarcely go out of my own parish without feeling some dismay. I feel death ever pinching me by the throat or pulling me by the backe: But I am of another moulde; to me it is ever one, and at all times the same. Nevertheles, if I were to chuse, I think it should rather be on horsebacke than in a bed, from my home and far from my friends. There is more harts- sorrow than comfort in taking ones last farewell of his friends. I do easily forget or neglect these duties or complements of our common or civill courtesy. For, of Offices appertaining to unaffected amitie, the same is the most displeasing and offensive: And I should as willingly forget to give a body that great adiew or eternall farewell. If a body reape any commoditie by this assistance, he also findes infinite inconveniences in it. I have seen diverse die most piteously, compassed and beset round with their friends and servants: Such multitudes and thronging of people does stifle them. It is against reason and a testimony of smal affection, and little care they have that you should die at rest. One offendeth your eyes, another molesteth your ears, the third vexeth your mouth: You have neither sense nor limme, or parte of your body, but is tormented and grieved. Your hart is ready to burst for pittie to hear your friends moanes and complaints, and to rive asunder with spite to hear perhaps some of their wailings and moanes that are but feigned and counterfet. If a man have ever had a mild or tender nature, being weake and readie to die, he must then necessarily have it more tender and relenting. It is most requisite that in so urgent a necessitie one have a gentle hand, and fitly applied to his senses, to scratch him where he itcheth, or else he ought not be clawed at all. If we must needs have the helpe of a Midwife to bring us into this world, there is reason we should also have the aiding-hand of a wise man to deliver us out of the same. Such a one, and therewithall a true friend, should a man before-hand purchase very dear, only for the service of such an occasion. I am not yet come to that disdainfull vigor which so fortifieth itself that at such times nothing aideth nor nothing troubleth; I flie a lower pitch. I seek to squat my self and steale from that passage, not by fear, but by Art. My intent is not in such an action to make either trial or show of my constancy. Wherefore? Because then shall the right and interest I have in reputation cease. I am content with a death united in itself, quiet and solitarie, wholly mine, convenient to my retired and private life. Cleane contrary to the Roman superstition, where he was judged unhappy that died without speaking, and had not his nearest friends to close his eyes. I have much adoe to comfort my self, without being troubled to comfort others; cares and vexations enow in my mind without needing circumstances to bring me new; and sufficient matter to entertaine my self without borrowing any. This share belongs not to the part of societie: It is the act of one man alone. Let us live, laugh and be merry amongst our friends, but die and yield up the ghost amongst strangers and such as we know not. He who has money in his purse shall ever find some ready to turn his head, make his bedde, rubbe his feet, attend him, and that will trouble and importune him no longer than he list, and will ever show him an indifferent and well-composed countenance, and without grumbling or grudging give a man leave to do what he please, and complain as he list. I dayly endeavor by discourse to shake off this childish humor and inhumane conceit, which causeth that by our griefes and paines we ever desire to moove our friends to compassion and sorrow for us, and with a kind of sympathy to condole our miseries and passions. We endeare our inconveniences beyond measure to exact tears from them: And the constancy we so much commend in all others, undauntedly to endure all evil fortune, we accuse and upbraid to our neerest allies when they molest us; we are not contented they should have a sensible feeling of our calamities if they do not also afflict themselves for them. A man should, as much as he can, set foorth and extend his joy, but to the utmost of his power suppresse and abridge his sorrow. He that will causelessly be moaned and sans reason, deserveth not to be pitied when he shall have cause and reason for it. To be ever complaining and alwaies moaning is the way never to be moaned and seldom to be pitied; and so often to seem over passionately pitifull is the meane to make no man feelingly ruthful towards others. He that makes himself dead, being alive, is subject to be counted alive when he is dying. I have seen some take pepper in the nose, forasmuch as they were told that they had a cheerful countenance, that they looked well, that they had a temperate pulse; to force laughter because some betraied their recovery, and hate their health because it was not regreetable. And which is more, they were no women. I for the most represent my infirmities such as they are: And shunne such words as are of evil presage, and avoid composed exclamations. If not glee and mirth, at least an orderly setled countenance of the bystanders and assistants is sufficiently-convenient to a wise and discreet sicke-man, who, though he see himself in a contrary state, he will not picke a quarrel with health. He is pleased to be told the same sound and strong in others, and at least for company-sake to enjoy his part of it. Though he feel and find himself to faint and sinke down, he does not altogether reject the conceits and imaginations of life, nor does he avoid common entertainments. I will studie sicknesse when I am in health, when it comes it will really enough make her impression without the helpe of my imagination. We deliberately prepare ourselves beforehand for any voiage we undertake, and therein, are resolved; the hour is set when he wil take horse, and we give it to our company in whose favor we extend it. I find this unexpected profit by the publication of my maners, that in some sort it serveth me for a rule. I am sometimes surprised with this consideration not to betray the history of my life. This public declaration bindes me to keep my self within my course, and not to contradict the image of my conditions, commonly less disfigured and gain-said then the malignity and infirmitie of modern judgements does bear. The uniformitie and singlenesse of my manners produces a visage of easy interpretation; but because the fashion of them is somewhat new and strange, and out of use, it gives detraction to fair play. Yet is it true, that to him who will go about loyally to injure me, me thinkes I do sufficiently affoord him matter whereby he may detract and snarle at my avowed and knowen imperfections, and wherewith he may be satisfied, without vain contending and idle skirmishing. If my self by preoccupating his discovery and accusation he thinkes I barre him of his snarling, it is good reason he take his right towards amplification and extension: Offence has her rights beyond justice: And that the vices whereof I strew him the rootes in me, he should amplifie them to trees. Let him not only employ thereunto those that possesse me, but those which but threaten me. Injurious vices, both in quality and in number. Let him beate me that way. I should willingly embrace the example of Dion the Philosopher. Antigonus going about to scoffe and quip at him touching his birth and offspring, he interrupted him and took the worde out of his mouth: I am’ (said he ) ’the son of a bond slave, a butcher, branded for a rogue, and of a whoore, whom my father by reason of his base fortune took to wife. Both were punished for some misdeede. Being a child, an orator bought me as a slave, liking me for my beautie and comelinesse; and dying, left me all his goods; which having transported into this citie of Athens, I have applied my self unto Philosophy. Let not Historians busie themselves in seeking news of me; I will at large blazon my self, and plainely tell them the whole discourse.’ A generous and free-minded confession does disable a reproch and disarme an injurie. So it is, that when all cards be told, me seems that I am as oft commended as dispraised beyond reason. As also me thinks, that even from my infancie, both in rank and degree of honor, I have had place given me, rather above and more than less and beneath that which appertained to me. I should better like to be in a countrie where these orders might either be reformed or contemned. Among men, after that striving or altercation for the prerogative or upper hand in going or sitting exceedeth three replies, it becomes incivill. I neither fear to yield and give place, nor to follow and proceed unjustly, so I may avoid such irkesome and importunate contestations. And never did man desire precedencie or place before me, but I quitted the same without grudging. Besides the profit I reape by writing of my self, I have hoped for this other, that if ever it might happen my humors should please or sympathize with some honest man, he would before my death seek to be acquainted with me, or to overtake me. I have given him much ground: For whatsoever a long acquaintance or continuall familiarity might have gained him in many wearisome years, the same has he in three dayes fully seen in this Register, and that more safely and more exactly. A pleasant fantazie is this of mine, many things I would be loath to tell a particular man, I utter to the whole world. And concerning my most secret thoughts and inward knowledge, I send my dearest friends to a Stationers shop. Excutienda damus præcordia. -- Pers. Sat. v. 22. Our very entrailes we Lay forth for you to see. If by so good markes and tokens I had ever knowen or heard of any one man that in this humor had been answerable to me, I would assuredly have wandred very far to find him out: For, the exceeding joy of a sortable, and in one consent agreeing company, cannot (in mine opinion) be sufficiently endeared or purchased at too high a rate. Oh God! who can express the value or conceive the true worth of a friend? How true is that ancient golden saying, that the use of a friend is more necessary and pleasing, then of the elements, water and fire. But to return to my former discourse. There is, then, no greater inconvenience in dying far from home and abroad. We esteeme it a part of duty and decencie to withdraw ourselves for natural actions less hideous and less disgracefull then this. But also those that come unto that in languishing manner to draw a long space of life should not happily wish with their misery to trouble a whole family? Therefore did the Indians of a certain countrie deem it just and lawfull to kill him that should fall into such necessitie. And in another of their Provinces they thought it meet to forsake him, and as well as he could, leave him alone to seek to save himself. To whom at last proove they not themselves tedious and intolerable? Common offices proceed not so far. Perforce you teach cruelty unto your best friends, obdurating by long use both wife and children, not to feel, nor to conceive, nor to moan your evils any longer. The groanes and outcries of my chollicke cause no more ruth and wailing in any body. And should we conceive pleasure by their conversation (which seldom happens, by reason of the disparitie of conditions, which easily produces either contempt or envy towards what man soever) is it not too-too much therwith to abuse a whole age? The more I should see them with a good heart to strain themselves for me, the more should I bewaile their pain. The law of curtesie alloweth us to leane upon others, but not so unmanerly to lie upon them and underpropt ourselves in their ruine. As he who caused little infants to be slain, that with their innocent blood he might be cured of a malady he had. Or another, who was continually stored with young tendrels or lasses to keep his old frozen limbs warme a nights, and entermix the sweetness of their breath with his old-stinking and offensive vapours. Decrepitude is a solitary quality. I am sociable even unto excess, yet do I think it reasonable at last to subtract my opportunity from the sight of the world, and hatch it in my self. Let me shrowd and shrugge my self into my shell as a tortoise, and learne to see men without taking hold of them. I should outrage them in so steepe a passage. It is now high time to turn from the company. But here will some say that in these far journies you may peraventure fall into some miserable dog-hole or poore cottage, where you shall want all needfull things. To whom I answere, that for things most necessary in such cases I ever carry most of them with me: And that where-ever we are we cannot possibly avoid fortune if she once take upon her to persecute us. When I am sicke I want nothing that is extraordinary; what nature cannot work in me I will not have a Bolus or a glister to effect. At the very beginning of my agues or sicknesses that cast me down, whilst I am yet whole in my senses and near unto health, I reconcile my self to God by the last duties of a Christian, whereby I find my self free and discharged, and think I have so much more reason and authority over my sicknesse. I find less want of notaries and counsell then of Physitians. What I have not disposed of my affairs or setled of my state when I was in perfect health, let none expect I should do it being sicke. Whatever I will do for the service of death is alwayes ready done. I dare not delay it one only day. And if nothing be done it is as much to say that either some doubt has delaide the choise: For sometimes it is a good choice not to chose at all: Or that absolutely I never intended to do any thing. I write my book to few men and to few years. Had it been a matter of lasting continuance, it should have been compiled in a better and more polished language: According to the continuall variation that hitherto has followed our French tongue, who may hope that its present form shall be in use fifty years hence? It dayly changeth and slips our hands; and since I could speak the same it is much altred and wellnigh halfe varied. We say it is now come to a full perfection. There is no age but says as much of hirs. It lies not in my power, so long as it glideth and differeth and altereth as it does, to keep it at a stay. It is for excellent and profitable compositions to fasten it unto them, whose credit shall either diminish or encrease according to the fortune of our state. For all that I fear not to insert therein diverse private articles, whose use is consumed amongst men living now adayes, and which concerne the particular knowledge of some that shall further see into it, then with a common understanding. When al is done, I would not (as I often see the memory of the deceased tossed too and fro) that men should descant and argue, Thus and thus he judged, thus he lived, thus he ment; had he spoken when his life left him, he would have given I wot what: There is no man knew him better than my self. Now, as much as modesty and decorum does permit me, I here give a taste of any inclinations and an essay of my affection, which I do more freely and more willingly by word of mouth to any that shall desire to be throughly informed of them. But so it is, that if any man shall looke into these memorialls, he shall find that either I have said all or desseigned all. What I cannot express, the same I point at with my finger. Verum animo satis hæc vestigia parva sagaci Sunt, per quæ possis cognoscere cætera tute. -- Lucr. i. 419. But this small footing to a quick-sent mind May serve whereby safely the rest to find. I leave nothing to be desired or divined of me. If one must entertaine himself with them, I would have it to be truly and justly. I would willingly come from the other world to give him the lie that should frame me other then I had been; were it he meant to honor me. I see that of the living, men never speak according to truth, and they are ever made to be what they are not. And if with might and main I had not upheld a friend of mine whom I have lately lost, he had surely been mangled and torn in a thousand contrary shapes. But to make an end of my weake humors: I confesse that in travelling I seldom alight in any place or come to any Inne, but first of all I cast in my mind whether I may conveniently lie there, if I should chaunce to fall sicke, or dying, die at my ease and take my death quietly. I will as nere as I can be lodged in some convenient part of the house, and in particular from all noise or stinking savours; in no close, filthy, or smoaky chamber. I seek to flatter death by these frivolous circumstances: Or, as I may rather say, to discharge my self from all other trouble or encombrance, that so I may wholly apply and attend her, who without that shall happily lie very heavily upon me. I will have her take a full share of my lives cases and commodities; it is a great part of it and of much consequence, and I hope it shall not belie what is past. Death has some formes more easy then others, and assumeth diverse qualities according to all mens fantazies. Among the natural ones, that proceeding of weakenesse and heavy dulnesse, to me seems gentle and pleasant. Among the violent I imagine a precipice more hardly then a ruine that overwhelmes me, and a cutting blow with a sword then a shot of an harquebuse; and I would rather have chosen to drinke the potion of Socrates, then wound my self as Cato did. And though it be all one, yet does my imagination perceive a difference, as much as is betweene death and life to cast my self into a burning fornace or in the channell of a shallow river. So foolishly does our fear respect more the meane then the effect. It is but one instant, but of such moment that to pass the same according to my desire, I would willingly renounce many of my lives dayes. Since all mens fantazies find either excess or diminution in her sharpnesse, since every man has some choise betweene the formes of dying, let us trie a little further whether we can find out some one free from all sorrow and grief. Might not one also make it seem voluptuous, as did those who died with Anthonie and Cleopatra? I omit to speak of the sharpe and exemplar efforts that Philosophy and religion produce. But amongst men of no great fame some have been found (as one Petronius and one Tigillinus at Rome) engaged to make themselves away who by the tenderness of their preparations have in a manner lulled the same asleepe. They have made it pass and glide away even in the midst of the security of their accustomed pastimes and wanton recreations. Amongst harlots and good felowes no speech of comfort, no mention of will or testament, no ambitious affectation of constancy, no discourse of their future condition, no compunction of sinnes committed, no apprehension of their soules-health, ever trouling them, amid sports, playes, banketting, surfetting, chambering, jesting, music, and singing of amorous verses, and all such popular and common entertainements. Might not we imitate this manner of resolution in more honest affairs and more commendable attempts? And since there are deaths good unto wise men and good unto fooles, let us find some one that may be good unto such as are betweene both. My imagination presents me some easy and mild countenance thereof, and (since we must all die) to be desired. The tyrants of Rome have thought they gave that criminall offender his life to whom they gave the free choise of death. But Theophrastus, a Philosopher so delicate, so modest, and so wise, was he not forced by reason to dare to utter this verse, latinized by Cicero: Vitam regit fortuna non sapientia. -- Cic. Tusc. Qu. v. Theoph. Calisth. Fortune our life does rule, Not wisdom of the schoole. Fortune gives the facilitie of my lives-condition some aide, having placed it in such a time wherein it is neither needfull nor combersome unto my people. It is a condition I would have accepted in all the seasons of my age, but in this occasion to trusse my bag and baggage and take up my bed and walke. I am particularly pleased that when I shall die, I shall neither breede pleasure nor cause sorrow in them. Shee has caused (which is the recompence of an artist) that such as by my death may pretend any materiall benefit, receive thereby elswhere jointly a materiall loss and hinderance. Death lies sometimes heavy upon us, in that it is burthensome to others; and interesseth us with their interest almost as much as with ours, and sometimes more; indeed altogether. In this inconveniency of lodging that I seek, I neither entermix pompe nor amplitude; For I rather hate it. But a certain simple and humble proprietie, which is commonly found in places where less Arte is, and that nature honoureth with some grace peculiar unto herself. Non ampliter sed munditer convivium. Plus sales quam sumptus.(Plautin.) ’Not a great, but a neat feast. More conceit then cost.’ And then it is for those who by their urgent affairs are compelled to travell in the midst of deepe Winter, and amongst the Grisons, to be surprised by such extreamities in their journies. But I who for the most part never travell but for pleasure, will neither be so ill advised nor so simply guided. If the way be foul on my right hand, I take the left. If I find my self ill at ease or unfit to ride, I stay at home. Which doing, and observing this course, in very truth I see no place and come no where that is not as pleasant, as convenient, and as commodious as my own house. True it is that I ever find superfluitie superfluous, and observe a kind of troublesomenesse in delicatenesse and plenty. Have I omitted or left any thing behind me that was worth the seeing? I return backe; It is ever my way, I am never out of it. I trace no certain line, neither right nor crooked. Comming to any strange place, find I not what was told me? As it often fortuneth that others judgements agree not with mine, and have most times found them false, I grieve not at my labor; I have learned that what was reported to be there is not. I have my bodies complexion as free and my taste as common as any man in the world. The diversity of fashions betweene one and other Nations concerneth me nothing , but by the varieties-pleasure. Each custom has his reason. Bee the trenchers or dishes of wood, of pewter, or of earth; be my meate boiled, rosted, or baked; butter or oyle, and that of Olives or of Wallnuts, hot or colde, I make no difference, all is one to me. And as one that is growing old, I accuse the generous faculties and had need that delicatenesse and choise should stay the indiscretion of my appetite, and sometime ease and solace my stomacke. When I have been out of France, and that to do me curtesie some have asked me Whether I would be served after the French manner, I have jested at them, and have ever thrust-in amongst the thickest tables and fullest of strangers. I am ashamed to see our men besotted with this foolish humor, to fret and chafe when they see any fashions contrary to theirs. They think themselves out of their element when they are out of their Village. Where ever they come they keep their own country and hate, indeed abhorre all strange manners. Meet they a countriman of theirs in Hungary, they feast that good fortune. And what do they? Marry close and join together, to blame, to condemne, and to scorne so many barbarous fashions as they see. And why not Barbarous since not French? Nay, happily they are the better sort of men that have noted and so much exclaimed against them. Most take going out but for coming home. They travell close and covered, with a silent and incommunicable wit, defending themselves from the contagion of some unknown air. What I speak of such puts me in mind in the like matter of that I have heretofore perceived in some of your young Courtiers. They only converse with men of their coate, and with disdains or pity looke upon us as if we were men of another world. Take away their new fangled, mysterious, and affected courtly complements, and they are out of their byase. As far to seek and short of us as we of them. That saying is true; That An honest man is a man compounded. Cleane contrary, I travell fully glutted with our fashions: Not to seek Gaskoines in Sicilie, I have left over many at home. I rather seek for Græcians and Persians. Those I accost, Them I consider, and with such I endeavor to be acquainted; to that I prepare and therein I employ my self. And which is more, me seems I have not met with many maners that are not worth ours. Indeed I have not wandred far, scarsly have I lost the sight of our Chimnies. Moreover, most of the casual companies you meete withall by the way have more incommodity than pleasure, a matter I do not greatly take hold of, and less now that age does particularize and in some sort sequester me from common formes. You suffer for other or others endure for you. The one inconvenience is yrkesome, the other troublesome, but yet the last is (in my conceipt) more rude. It is a rare chaunce and seld-seen fortune, but of exceeding solace and inestimable worth, to have an honest man of singular experience, of a sound judgement, of a resolute understanding and constant resolution, and of manners conformable to yours, to accompany or follow you with a good will. I have found great want of such a one in all my voyages. Which company a man must seek with discretion and with great heed obtaine before he wander from home. With me no pleasure is fully delightsome without communication, and no delight absolute except imparted. I do not so much as apprehend one rare conceipt, or conceive one excellent good thought in my mind, but me thinks I am much grieved and grievously perplexed to have produced the same alone and that I have no sympathizing companion to impart it unto. Si cum hac exceptione detur sapientia, ut illam inclusam teneam, nec enunciem, rejiciam: ’If wisdom should be offered with this exception, that I should keep it concealed and not utter it, I would refuse it.’ The other strain’d it one note higher. Si contigerit ea vita sapienii, ut omnium rerum afluentibus copiis, quamvis omnia, quæ cognitione digna sunt, summo otio secum ipse consideret et contempletur; tamen si solitudo tanta sit, ut hominem videre non possit, excedat e vita: (Cic. Offic. ii.) ’If a wiseman might lead such a life, as in abundance of all things he may in full quiet contemplate and consider all things worthy of knowledge, yet if he must be so solitary as he may see no man, he should rather leave such a life.’ Architas his opinion is suitable to mine, which was that it would be a thing unpleasing to the very heavens, and distastefull to man, to survay and walke within those immense and divine and coelestiall bodies, without the assistance of a friend or companion; Yet is it better to be alone than in tedious and foolish company. Aristippus loved to live as an alien or stranger every where: Me si fata meis patereutur ducere vitam Auspiciis. -- Virg. Æn. iv. 339. If fates would me permit To live as I think fit, I should chose to weare out my life with my bum in the saddle, ever riding. ------ visere gestiens, Qua parte debacchentur ignes, Qua nebulæ pluviique rores. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. iii. 54. Delighting much to go and see Where firy heats rage furiously, Where clouds and rainy dews most be. Have you not more easy pastimes? What is it you want? Is not your house well seated, and in a good and wholesome air? Sufficiently furnished and more then sufficiently capable? His Royall Majesty has in great state been in the same, and more then once taken his repast there. Does not your family in rule and government leave many more inferior to her than above her eminency? Is there any locall thought or care that as extrordinary does ulcerate, or as indigestible does molest you? Quæ te nunc coquat et vexet sub pectore fixa. -- Enni, Cic. Senect. p. Which now boyles in your brest, And lets you take no rest. Where do you imagine you may be without empeachment or disturbance? Nunquam simpliciter fortuna indulger: ’Fortune never favors fully without exception.’ You see then there is none but you that trouble and busie your self: and every where you shall follow your self, and in all places you shall complain. For, Here below there is no satisfaction or content, except for brutal or divine mindes. He who in so just an occasion has no content, where does he imagine to find it? Unto how many thousands of men does such a condition as yours bound and stay the limits of their wishes? Reforme but your self, by that you may do all: Whereas towards fortune you have no right or interest but patience. Nulla placida quies est, nisi quam ratio composuit: (Sen. Ep. lvi. m.) There is no pleasing setled rest, but such as reason has made up.’ I see the reason of this advertisement, indeed I perceive it well. But one should sooner have done, and more pertinently, in one bare word to say onto me: Be wise. This resolution is beyond wisdom. It is her Worke and her production. So does the Physition that is ever crying to a languishing, heart-broken sicke- man, that he be merry and pull up a good heart; he should less foolishly persuade him if he did but bid him be healthy; as for me, I am but a man of the common stamp. It is a certain sound and of easy understanding precept: Be content with your own, that is to say, with reason, the execution wherof not-withstanding is no more in the wiser sort than in my self: It is a popular word, but it has a terrible far-reaching extension. What comprehends it not? All things fall within the compasse of discretion and modification. Wel I wot that being taken according to the bare letter, the pleasure of travell brings a testimony of unquietnesse and irresolution. Which to say truth, are our mistrisse and predominant qualities. Yea, I confesse it: I see nothing, be it but a dreame or by wishing whereon I may take hold. Only varietie and the possession of diversitie does satisfie me, if at least any thing satisfie me. In travell this does nourish me, that without interest I may stay my self; and that I have means commodiously to divert my self from it. I love a private life because it is by my own choice that I love it, not by a diffidence or dis- agreeing from a public life, which perhaps is as much according to my complexion: I thereby serve my Prince more joyfully and genuinely because it is by the free election of my judgement and by my reason, without any particular obligation. And that I am not cast or forced thereunto, because I am unfit to be received of any other, or am not beloved, so of the rest. I hate those morsels that necessitie does carve me. Every commoditie of which alone I were to depend, should ever hold me by the throat: Alter remus aquas, alter mihi radat arenas. -- Propert. iii. El. ii. 23. Let me cut waters with one oar, With th’other shave the sandie shoare. One string alone can never sufficiently hold me. You will say there is vanity in this ammusement. But where not? And these goodly precepts are vanity, and Meere vanity is all worldly wisdom. Dominus novit cogitationes sapientum, quoniam vanæ sunt: (Psal. xciii. 11.) ’The Lord knowes the thoughts of the wise that they are vain.’ Such exquisite subtilities are only fit for sermons. They are discourses that will send us into the other world on horsebacke. Life is a materiall and corporall motion, an action imperfect and disordered by its own essence; I employ or apply my self to serve it according to it self. Quisque suos patimur manes. -- Virg. Æn. vi. 743. All of us for our merit, Have Some attending spirit. Sic est faciendum, ne contra naturam universam nihil contendamus, ea tamen conservata, propriam sequamur: (Cic. Offic. i.) ’We must so work as we endeavor nothing against nature in general, yet so observe it as we follow our own in speciall.’ To what purpose are these heaven-looking and nice points of Philosophie, on which no humane being can establish and ground itself? And to what end serve these rules that exceed our use and excel our strength? I often see that there are certain Ideæs or formes of life proposed unto us, which neither the proposer nor the Auditors have any hope at all to follow, or and which is worse, no desire to attaine. Of the same paper whereon a Judge wrote but even now the condemnation against an adulterer, he will teare a scantlin thereon to write some love-lines to his fellow-judges wife. The same woman from whom you came lately, and with whom you have committed that unlawfull-pleasing sport, will soone after, even in your presence, rail and scold more bitterly against the same fault in her neighbour than ever Portia or Lucrece could. And some condemne men to die for crimes that themselves esteeme no faults. I have in my youth seen a notable man with one hand to present the people most excellent and well-written verses, both for invention and extreme licentiousnesse, and with the other hand, at the same instant, the most sharpe- railing reformation, according to Divinitie, that happily the World has seen these many- many years. Thus goes the world, and so go men. We let laws and precepts follow their way, but we keep another course; Not only by disorder of manners, but often by opinion and contarary judgment. Hear but a discourse of Philosophy read, the invention, the pertinencie, does presently tickle your spirit and move you. There is nothing tickleth or pricketh your conscience; it is not to her that men speak. Is it not true? Ariston said that Neither Bath nor Lecture are of any worth, except the one wash cleane and the other cleanse all filth away. One may busie himself about the barke when once the pith is gotten out: As when we have drunke off the Wine we consider the graving and workmanship of the cuppe. In all the parts of ancient Philosophie this one thing may be noted, that one same work-man publisheth some rules of temperance and therewithall some compositions of love and licentiousnesse. And Xenophon in Cliniæs bosome wrote against the Aristippian virtue. It is not a miraculous conversion that so does wave and hull them to and fro. But it is, that Solon does sometimes represent himself in his own colours, and sometimes in form of a Law-giver; now he speaks for the multitude and now for himself, And takes the free and natural rules to himself; warranting himself with a constant and perfect sounduesse. Curentur dubii medicis majoribus ægri. -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 124. Let patients in great doubt, Seeke great Physitians out. Antisthenes alloweth a wise man to love and do what he list, without respect of laws, especially in things he deemeth needfull and fit: Forasmuch as he has a better understanding than they, and more knowledge of virtue. His Disciple Diogenes said: To perturbations we should oppose reason, to fortune, confidence, and to laws nature; to dainty and tender stomacks constrained and artificiall ordinances. Good stomackes are simply served with the prescriptions of their natural appetite. So do our Phisitions, who, whilst they tie their patients to a strik’t diet of a panada or a sirope, feed themselves upon a melone, dainty fruits, much good meate, and drinke all manner of good Wine. I wot not what Bookes are, nor what they meane by wisdom and philosophy (quoth the Curtizan Lais), but sure I am those kinds of people knocke as often at my gates as any other men. Be cause our licenciousnesse transports us commonly beyond what is lawfull and allowed, our lives-precepts and laws have often been wrested or restrained beyond universall reason. Nemo satis credit tantum delinquere, quantum, Permittas. -- Juven. Sat. xiv. 233. No man thinkes it enough so far t’offend As you give lawfull leave (and there to end). It were to be wished there were a greater proportion betweene commandement and obedience; And unjust seems that ayme or goale whereto one cannot possibly attaine. No man is so exquisitely honest or upright in living but brings all his actions and thoughts within compasse and danger of the laws, and that ten times in his life might not lawfully be hanged. Yea happily such a man as it were pity and dangerously-hurtful to loose and most unjust to punish him. -----Olle, quid ad te, De cute quid faciat ille, vel illa sua? -- Mart. vii. Epig. ix. 1. Foole, what hast you to do, what he or she With their own skinnes or themselves doing be? And some might never offend the laws, that notwithstanding should not deserve the commendations of vertuous men, and whom philosophy might meritoriously and justly cause to be whipped; so troubled, dimme-sighted and partiall in this relation. We are far enough from being honest according to God, for we cannot be such according to ourselves. Humane wisdom could never reach the duties or attaine the devoires it had prescribed unto itself. And had it at any time attained them, then would it doubtlesse prescribe some others beyond them, to which it might ever aspire and pretend. So great an enemy is our condition unto consistence. Man does necessarily ordaine unto himself to be in fault. He is not very crafty to measure his duty by the reason of another being than his own. To whom prescribes he that which he expects no man will performe? Is he unjust in not dooing that which be cannot possibly atchieve? The laws which condemne us not to be able, condemne us for that we cannot performe. If the worst happen, this deformed liberty for one to present him-self in two places, and the actions after one fashion, the discourses after an other, is lawfull in them which report things. But it cannot be in them that acknowledge themselves as I do. I must walke with my penne as I go with my feete. The common high way must have conference with other ways. Catoes virtue was vigorous beyond the reason of the age he lived in, and for a man that entermedled with governing other men destinated for the common service, it might be said to have been a justice; if not unjust, at least vain and out of season. Mine own manners, which scarse disagree one inch from those now current, make me notwithstanding in some sort strange, uncouth and unsociable to my age. I wot not, whether it be without reason, I am so distasted and out of liking with the world wherein I live and frequent; but well I know I should have small reason to complain, the world were distasted and out of liking with me, since I am so with it. The virtue assigned to the worlds affairs, it is a virtue with sundry byases, turnings, bendings and elbowes, to apply and join itself to humane imbecilities mixed and artificiall; neither right, pure or constant, nor meerely innocent. Our Annales even to this day blame some one of our Kings to have over- simply suffered himself to be led or misled by the conscientious persuasions of his Confessor. Matters of state have more bold precepts. ----- exeat aula, Qui vult esse pius. -- Lucan. Bell. Civ. i. 493. He that will godly be, From Court let him be free. I have heretofore assayed to employ my opinions and rules of life as new, as rude, as impolished, or as unpolluted as they we re naturally born with me, or as I have attained them by my institution: and wherewith, if not so commodiously, at least safely in particular, I serve my own turn unto the service of public affairs and benefit of my Common-wealth. A scholasticall and novice virtue, but I have found them very unapt and dangerous for that purpose. He that goeth in a press or throng of people must sometimes step aside, hold in his elbowes, crosse the way, advance himself, start backe, and forsake the right way according as it falls out: Live he not so much as he wouldhimselfe, but as others will, not according to that he proposeth to himself, but to that which is proposed to him: according to times, to men and to affairs, and as the skilfull Mariner saile with the winde. Plato says, that who escapes untainted and cleane-handed from the managing of the world, escapeth by some wonder. He sayes also that when he instituteth his Philosopher as chief over a Common-wealth, he means not a corrupted or law broken common-wealth as that of Athens, and much less as ours, with which wisdom herself would be brought to a nonplus or put to her shifts. And a good hearb, transplanted into a soile very diverse from her nature, does much sooner conforme itself to the soile then it reformeth the same to itself. I feelingly perceive that if I were wholly to enure my self to such occupations I should require much change and great repairing. Which could I effect in me (and why not with time and diligence?) I would not. Of that little which in this vocation I have made trial of, I have much distasted my self: I sometimes find certain temptations arise in my mind towards ambition, but I start aside, bandie and opinionate my self to the contrary: At tu Catulle obstinatus obdura. -- Catul. Lyr. Epig. viii. 19. Be you at any rate, Obdurate, obstinate. I am not greatly called, and I invite my self as little unto it. Libertie and idlenesse, my chief qualities, are qualities diameterly contrary to that mysterie. We know not how to distinguish mens faculties. They have certain divisions and limits uneasie and over nice to be chosen. To conclude by the sufficiency of a private life, any sufficiency for public use it is ill concluded; Some one directs himself well that cannot so well direct others, and composeth Essayes that could not work effects. Some man can dispose and order a siege that could but ill command and marshall a battle; and discourseth well in private that to a multitude or a Prince would make but a bad Oration. Yea, perhaps, tis rather a testimony to him that can do one that he cannot do the other, but otherwise. I find that high spirits are not much less apt for base things then base spirits are for high matters. Could it be imagined that Socrates would have given the Athenians cause to laugh at his own charges, because he could never justly compt the suffrages of his tribe and make report thereof unto the counsell? Truely the reverence I bear and respect I owe unto that mans perfections deserveth that his fortune bring to the excuse of my principal imperfections one so notable example. Our sufficiencie is retailed into small parcells. Mine has no latitude, and is in number very miserable. Saturninus answered those who had conferred all authority upon him, saying, ’Oh you, my fellow-soldiers, you have lost a good Captain by creating him a bad General of an Armie.’ Who in time of infection vanteth himself for the worlds-service to employ a genuine or sincere virtue, either knowes it not (opinions being corrupted with manners; in good sooth hear but them paint it forth, marke how most of them magnifie themselves for their demeanours, and how they form their rules; in liew of portraying a virtue they only set forth meere injustice and vice, and thus false and adulterate they present the same to the institution of Princes), or if he know it he wrongfully boasteth himself; and whatever he says he does many things whereof his own conscience accuses him. I should easily believe Seneca of the experience he made of it in such an occasion, upon condition he would freely speak his mind of it unto me. The honourablest badge of goodnesse in such a necessitie is [ingenuously] for a man to acknowledge both his own and others faults; to stay and with his might hinder the inclination towards evil, and avie to follow this course to hope and wish better. In these dismembrings or havocks of France and divisions whereinto we are miserably falne, I perceive every man travell and busie himself to defend his own cause, and the better sort with much dissembling and falsehood. He that should plainely and roundly write of it should write rashly and viciously. Take the best and justest part, what is it else but the member of crased, worme-eaten and corrupted body? But of such a body the member least sicke is called sound; and good reason why, because our qualities have no title but in comparison. Civill innocency is measured according to places and seasons. I would be glad to see such a commendation of Agesilaus in Xenophon, who, being entreated of a neighbour Prince, with whom he had sometimes made warr, to suffer him to pass through his countrie, was therewith well pleased; granting him free passage through Peloponnese, and having him at his mercy did not only not emprison nor empoison him, but, according to the tenour of his promise, without show or offence, or unkindenesse, entertained him with all courtesy and humanitie. To such humors it were a matter of no moment: At other times and elsewhere the liberty and magnanimity of such an action shall be highly esteemed. Our gullish Gaberdines would have mockt at it, so little affinity is there betweene the Spartan and the French innocencie. We have, notwithstanding, some honest men amongst us; but it is after our fashion. He whose manners are in regularity established above the age he liveth in, let him either wrest or muffle his rules; or (which I would rather persuade him) let him withdraw himself apart and not medle with us. What shall he gains thereby? Egregium sanctumque virum si cerno, bimembri Hoc monstrum puero, et miranti jam sub aratro Piscibus inventis et foetæ comparo mulæ. -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 64. See I a man of holinesse and vertues rare, To births bimembred, under wonderful Plowshare Fish found, or moiles with fole, this monster I compare. One may bewaile the better times, but not avoide the present; one may desire other magistrates, but notwithstanding he must obey those he has; And happily it is more commendable to obey the wicked than the good. So long as the image of the received, allowed, and ancient laws of this Monarchie shall be extant and shine in any corner thereof, there will I be, there will I abide. And if by any disaster they shall chaunce to have contradiction or empeachment amongst themselves, and produce two factions, or doubtfull or hard choise; my election shall be to avoide, And, if I can, escape this storme. In the meane while, either nature or the hazard of war shall lend me that helping hand. I should freely have declared my self betweene Cæsar and Pompey. But betweene those three theeves which came after, where either one must have hid himself or followed the winde: which I deem lawfull, when reason swayeth no longer. Quod diversus abis? -- Virg. Æn. v. 166. Whither have you recourse, So far out of your course? This mingle-mangle is somewhat beside my text. I stragle out of the path; yet it is rather by licence then by unadvisednesse: my fantasies follow one another, but sometimes a far off, and looke one at another, but with an oblique looke. I have heretofore cast mine eyes upon some of Platoes Dialogues, bemolted with a fantastic variety; the first part treateth of love, all the latter of Rhetorick. They fear not those variances, and have a wonderful grace in suffering themselves to be transported by the wind, or to seem so. The titles of my chapters embrace not allwayes the matter; they often but glance at it by some marke: as these others, Andria, Eunuchus; or these, Sylla, Cicero, Torquatus. I love a Poeticall kind of march, by friskes, skips, and jumps. It is an arte (says Plato) light, nimble, fleeting, and light braind. There are some treatises in Plutarke where he forgets his theame, where the drift of his argument is not found but by incidencie and chaunce, all stuffed with strange matter. Marke but the vagaries in his Dæmon of Socrates. Oh God! what grace has the variation, and what beautie these startings and nimble escapes! And then most, when they seem to employ carelesnesse and casualtie. It is the unheedie and negligent reader that loses my subject, and not my life. Some word or other shall ever be found in a corner that has relation to it, though closely couched. I am indiscreetly and tumultuously at a fault; my stile and wit are still gadding likewise. A little folly is tolerable in him, that will not be more sottish, say our masters precepts, and more their examples. A thousand Poets labor and languish after the prose-manner, but the best ancient prose, which I indifferently scatter here and there for verse, shineth every where, with a poettical vigor and boldness, and representeth some aire or touch of its fury: Verily she ought to have the maistry and preheminence given her in matters of speech. A Poet (says Plato) seated on the Muses footestoole does in a fury powre out whatsoever commeth in his mouth, as the pipe or cocke of a fountain, without considering or ruminating the same: and many things escape him, diverse in colour, contrary in substance, and broken in course. Antient Divinitie is altogether Poesie (say the learned) and the first Philosophie. It is the original language of the Gods. I understand that the matter distinguisheth itself. It sufficiently declareth where it changeth, where it concludeth, where it beginneth, and where it rejoyneth; without enterlacings of words, joyning ligaments and binding seames wrested-in for service of weake and unattentive ears, and without glossing or expounding my self. What is he that would not rather not be read at all, then read in a drowsie and cursorie manner: Nihil est tam utile, quod in transitu prosit: ’There is nothing so profitable, that being lightly past over, will do good.’ If to take bookes in hand were to learne them, and if to see were to view them, and if to run them over were to seize upon them, I should be too blame, to make my self altogether so ignorant as I say. Since I cannot stay the reader’s attention by the weight, Manco male, if I happen to stay him by my intricate confusion; indeed, but he will afterward repent that ever he amused himself about it. You say true, but he shall have amused himself upon it. And there be humors to whom understanding causeth disdaine, who because they shall not know what I meane will esteeme me the better, and will conclude the mystery and depth of my sense by the obscuritie, Which, to speak in good earnest, I hate as death, and would shunne it if I could avoid my self. Aristotle vaunteth in some place to affect the same. A vicious affectation. Forasmuch as the often breaking of my chapters, I so much used in the beginning of my book, seemed to interrupt attention before it be conceived, Disdaining for so little a while to collect and there seat itself; I have betaken my self to frame them longer, as requiring proposition and assigned leisure. In such an occupation he to whom you will not grant one hour, you will allow him nothing; And you do nought for him for whom you do, but in doing some other thing. Sithence perhaps I am particularly tied and precisely vowed to speak by halves, to speak confusedly, to speak discrepantly; I therefore hate this trouble-feast reason, and these extravagant projects, which so much molest man’s life, and these so subtle opinions, if they have any truth; I deem it over-dear, and find it too incommodious. On the other side, I labor to set forth vanity and make sottishnesse to prevaile, if it bring me any pleasure; And without so nicely controlling them, I follow my own natural inclinations. I have elsewhere seen some houses ruined, statues overthrowne, both of heaven and of earth; But men be alwaies one. All that is true; and yet I can not so often survay the vast toombe of that City, so great, so populous, and so puissant, but I as often admire and reverence the same. The care and remembrance of evills is recommended unto us. Now have I from my infancie been bred and brought up with these; I have had knowledge of the affairs of Rome, long time before I had notice of those of my house. I knewthe Capitoll and its platforme, before I knew Louvre, the pallace of our Kings in Paris; and the River Tiber before Seyne. I have more remembred and thought upon the fortunes and conditions of Lucullus, Metellus and Scipio, then of any of our country-men. They are deceased, and so is my father as fully as they; and is as distant from me and life in eighteene yeeres as they were in sixteene hundred; Whose memory, amitie, and societie I notwithstanding omit not to continue, to embrace and converse withall, with a perfect and most lively union. Yea, of my own inclination I am more officious toward the deceased. They can no longer helpe them- selves, but (as me seemetlh they require so much the more my ayde, There is Gratitude, and there appeareth she in her perfect lustre. A benefit is less richly assigned where retrogradation and reflexion is. Arcesilaus, going to visit Ctesibius that was sicke, and finding him in very poore plight, fair and softly thrust some money under his boulster, which he gave him; And concealing it from him, left and gave him also a quittance for ever being beholding to him. Such have at any time deserved friendship or love thanks at my hands, never lost in the same by being no longer with me. I have better paid and more careful rewarded them, being absent and when they least thought of it. I speak more kindely and affectionately of my friends when there is least means that ever it shall come to their ears. I have heretofore undergone a hundred quarrels for the defense of Pompey and Brutus his cause. This acquaintance continueth to this day betweene us. Even of present things we have no other holde but by our fantazie. Perceiving my self unfit and unprofitable for this age, I cast my self to that other, and am so besotted with it that the state of the said ancient, free, just and florishing Rome (for I neither love the birth nor like the old age of the same), does interest, concerne and passionate me. And therefore can I not so often looke into the situation of their streets and houses, and those wondrous strange ruines, that may be said to reach down to the Antipodes, but so often must I ammuse my self on them. Is it nature or by the error of fantasie, that the seeing of places we know to have been frequented or inhabited by men, whose memory is esteemed or mentioned in stories, does in some sort move and stir us up as much or more than the hearing of their noble deeds, or reading of their compositions? Tanta vis admonitionis inest in locis: Et id quidem in hoc urbe infinitum; quacunque enim ingredimur, in aliquam historiam vestigium ponimus: (Cic. s. De Fin.) ’So great a power of admonition is in the very place. And that in this City is most infinite, for which way soever we walke, we set our foote upon some History.’ I am much delighted with the consideration of their countenance, port and abilliments. I ruminate those glorious names betweene my teeth, and make mine ears to ring with the sound of them. Ego illos veneror, et tantis nominibus semper assurgo. ’I do reverence them, and at their names I do rise and make curtesie.’ Of things but in some sort great, strange and admirable, I admire their common parts. I could wish to see them walk and suppe together, and hear their discourses. It were ingratitude to despise and impiety to neglect the reliques or images of so many excellent, honest good men, and therewithall so valiant, which I have seen live and die; And who by their examples, had we the wit or grace to follow them, affoord us so many notable instructions. And Rome as it stands now deserveth to be loved, Confederated so long since and sharing titles with our Crowne of France, Being the only common and universall City: The Soveraigne Magistrate therein commanding is likewise known abroad in diverse other places. It is the chief Metropolitan City of all Christian nations; both French and Spaniards, and all men else, are there at home. To be a Prince of that state, a man needs but be of Christendome, where ever it be seated. There’s no place here on earth that the Heavens have embraced with such influence of favors and grace, and with such constancy; Even her ruine is glorious with renown, and swolne with glory. Laudandis preciosior ruinis. Ev’n made more honorable, By ruines memorable. Low-levelled as she lieth, and even in the tombe of her glory, she yet reserveth the lively image and regardfull markes of Empire. Ut palam sit uno in loco gaudentis opus esse naturæ: ’So as it is clear, in one place is set-forth the work of nature in her jollity.’ Some one would blame himself, indeed mutiny, to feel himself tickled with so vain a pleasure. Our humors are not overvaine that be pleasant. Whatsoever they be that constantly content a man capable of common understanding, I could not find in my heart to moan or pity him. I am much beholding to fortune, inasmuch as until this day she has committed nothing outrageously against me, or imposed any thing upon me that is beyond my strength, or that I could not well bear. Is it not perhaps her custom to suffer such as are not importunate or over busie with her to live in peace? Quanto quisque sibi plura negaverit, A Diis plura feret, nil cupientium Nudus castra peto, multa petentibus Desunt multa. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. xvi. 21, 42. The more that men shall to themselves denie, The more the gods will give them: threadbare I Follow the campe of them that nought desire, They still want much that still do much require. If she continue so, I shall depart very well content and satisfied. -----nihil supra, Deos lacesso. -- Ibid. Car. ii. Od. xviii.11. More than will serve, to have Of Gods I do not crave. But beware the shocke; Thousands miscary in the haven, and are cast away, being neerest home. I am easily comforted with what shall happen here when I am gone. Things present trouble me sufficiently, and set me thorowly a work. Fortunæ cætera mando. -- Ovid. Metam. ii. 140. The rest I do commit To Fortune (as is fit). Besides, I am not tied with that strong bond which some say bindes men to future times, by the children bearing their names, and succeeding them in honors; And being so much to be desired, it may be I shall wish for them so much the less. I am by myself but overmuch tied unto the world and fastned unto life; I am pleased to be in Fortunes hold by the circumstances properly necessary to my state, without enlarging her Jurisdiction upon me by other ways; And I never thought that to be without children were a defect, able to make mans life less compleat and less contented. A barren state or sterill vacation have also their peculiar commodities. Children are in the number of things that need not greatly be desired; especially in corrupted days, wherein it would be so hard a matter to make them good. Bona jam nec nasci licet ita corrupta sunt semina: ’We cannot now have good things so much as grow, the seeds are so corrupt.’ Yet have they just cause to moan them, that, having once gotten, lose them untimely. He who left me my house in charge, considering my humor, which was to stay at home so little, fore-saw I should be the overthrow of it. He was deceived; I am now as I came unto it, if not somewhat better; and that without any Office or Churchliving, which are no small helps. As for other matters, if Fortune have offred me no violent or extraordinary offence, so has she not showed me any great favor or extraordinary grace. Whatsoever I have belonging to it that may properly be termed her gifts, was there before I came unto it; indeed, and a hundred yeeres before. I particularly enjoy no essentiall good, or possesse no solid benefit, that I owe unto her liberalitie. Indeed she has bestowed some wind-pufft favors upon me, which may rather be termed titular and honorable in show, then in substance or materiall; and which, in good truth, she has not granted, but offered me, God he knowes, to me, who am altogether materiall; not satisfied but with realitie, which must also be massie and substantiall; And who, if I durst confesse it, would not think avarice much less excusable then ambition, nor grief less evitable then shame, nor health less desirable then learning, or riches less to be wished then nobility. Amongst her vain favors I have none does so much please my foolish self-pleasing conceit as an authentic Bull, charter or patent of denizonship or borgeouship of Rome, which at my last being there, was granted me by the whole Senate of that City--garish and trimly adorned with goodly Seales, and written in fair golden letters--bestowed upon me with all gracious and free liberalitie. And forasmuch as they are commonly conferred in diverse stiles more or lease favourable, and that before I had ever seen any I would have been glad to have had but a paterne or formular of one, I will for the satisfaction of any, if be fortune to be possessed with such a curiosity as mine, here set down the true copy or transcript of it, and thus it is:-- Quod Horatius Maximus, Martius Cecius, Alexander Mutus, almæ urbis conservatores de illustrissimo viro Michæle Montano, Equite sancti Michælis, et a Cubiculo Regis Christianissimi, Romana civitate donando, ad Senatum retulerunt, S. P. Q. R. de ea re ita fieri censuit. Cum veteri more et instituto cupide illi semper studioseque suscepti sint, qui virtute ac nobilitate præstantes, magno Reipublicæ nostræ usui atque ornamento fuissent, vel esse aliquando possent: Nos majorum nostrorum exemplo atque auctoritate permoti, preclarum hanc Consuetudinem nobis imitandam ac servandam fore censemus. Quamobrem cum Illustrissimus Michæl Montanus Eques sancti Michælis, et cubiculo Regis Christianissimi; Romani nominis studio sissimus, et familiæ laude atque splendore et propriis virtutum meritis dignissimus sit, qui summo Senatus Populique Romani judicio ac studio in Romanam Civitatem adsciscatur, placere Senatui P. Q. R. Illustrissimum Michælem Montanum rebus omnibus ornatissimum, atque huic inclyto Populo charissimum, ipsum posterosque in Rom. civitatem adscribi, ornarique omnibus et premiis et honoribus, quibus illi fruuntur, qui Cives patritiique Romani nati aout jure optimo facti sunt. In quo censere Senatum P. Q. R. se non tam illi Jus Civitatis largiri quam debitum tribuere, neque magis beneficium dare quam ab ipso accipere, qui hoc Civitatis munere accipiendo, singular Civitatem ipsam ornamento atque honore affecerit. Quam quidem S.C. auctoritatem iidem Conservatores per Senatus P. Q. R. scribas in acta referri atque in Capitolii curia servari, privilegiumque hujusmodi fieri, solitoque urbis sigillo communiri, curarunt. Anno ab urbe condito CX C CCXXXI. post Christum natum M.D.LxxxI.III. Idus Martii. Horatius Fuscus sacri S. P. Q. R. scriba, Vincent. Martholus sacri S.P. Q. R. scriba. At the motion of Horatius Maximus, Martius Cecius, Alexander Mutus, who are Conservators of this beautifull Cittie concerning the endenizing and making cittizen of Rome the noble Gentleman Michæl de Montaigne, Knight of the Order of Saint Michæll, and one of the Chamber of the most Christian King, the Senate and people of Rome thought good thereof thus to exact. Whereas by the ancient custom and good order, they have ever and with good will been entertained, who excelling in virtue and nobility have been, or at any time might be, of any great use or ornament unto our common-weale: We, mooved by example and authority Of our Auncesters, decree, That this notable custom by us should be ensued and observed. Wherefore, sithence the right Noble Michæl de Montaigne, Knight of Saint Michæls Order, and one of the Chamber of the most Christian King, both is most affectionate unto the Roman name, and by the commendations and splendor of his pedegree, as also by the merits of his proper vertues, most worthe to be adopted and inserted into the Roman Cittie with a speciall judgement and good will of the Senate and people of Rome. It pleaseth the Senate and people of Rome that the right noble Michæl de Montaigne, adorned in all complements and wellbeloved of this famous Communaltie, both himself and his successours should be ascribed and enfranchised into this Roman Cittie, and be graced with al rewards and honors which they enjoy who either have been borne or elected either Citizen or Noblemen of Rome. Wherein the Senate and people do decree that they do not so much vouchsafe him the right of their City, as give him that is due unto him, nor do they rather give him a benefite then receive it of him, who by accepting this gift of the Cittie does countenance the Cittie with a singular ornament and honor. Which Act and authority of the Senates Decree the said Conservators caused by the Clearks of the Senate and people to be registred and laid-up in the Capitoll Court, and this Priviledge to be made and signed with the Cities usual Seale. In the yeare since the building of the City CX C CCXXXI. after the birth of Christ a thousand five hundred eighty and one: the Ides of March. Horatius Fuscus, and Vincent Martholus, Clarks of the Sacred Senate and people of Rome. Being neither Burgeois nor Denizen of any City, I am well pleased to be so of the noblest and greatest that ever was heretofore, or ever shall be hereafter. If others did so attentively consider and survay themselves as I do, they shall, as I do, find themselves full of inanitie, fondnesse, or vanity. I can not be rid of it, except I rid and quit my self. We are all possessed and overwhelmed therewith, as well one as the other. But such as have a feeling of it have somewhat the better bargaine; and yet I am not sure of it. This common opinion and vulgar custom, to looke and marke elsewhere then on ourselves, has well provided for our affairs. It is an object full-fraught with discontent, wherein we see nothing, but misery and vanity. To the end we should not wholly be discomforted, Nature has very fitly cast the action of our sight outward; We go forward according to the streamer but to turn our course backe to ourselves is a painefull motion; the sea likewise is troubled, raging and disquieted when t’is turned and driven into itself. Observe (says every one) the motions and bransles of the heavens: take a survay of all - the quarrell of this man, the pulse of that man, and anothers last testament: to conclude, behold and marke ever, high or low, right or oblique, before or behind you. It was a paradoxall commandement which the God of Delphos laid heeretofore upon us; saying, ’View yourselves within, know yourselves and keep you to yourselves.’ Your mind and your will, which elsewhere is consumed, bring it unto itself again: you scatter, you stragle, you stray, and you distract yourselves; call yourselves home again; rowze and uphold yourselves; you are betrayed, you are spoiled and dissipated; yourselves are stolen and taken from yourselves. Seest you not how all this universe holdeth all his sights compelled inward, and his eyes open to contemplate itself? Both inward and outward it is ever vanity for you; but so much less vanity by how much less it is extended. Except your self, Oh man (said that God) every thing does first seek and study itself, and according to it’s neede has limits to her travells and bounds to her desires. There’s not one so shallow, so empty, and so needy as you are who embracest the whole world. Thou art the Scrutator without knowledge the magistrate without jurisdiction, and when all is done, the vice of the play. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER X: HOW ONE OUGHT TO GOVERNE HIS WILL. CHAPTER X: HOW ONE OUGHT TO GOVERNE HIS WILL. N REGARD of the common sort of men, few things touch me, or (to speak properly) sway me; for it is reason they touch, so they possesse- us not. I have great neede, both by study and discourse, to encrease this priviledge of insensibility, which is naturally crept far into me. I am not wedded unto many things, and by consequence not passionate of them. I have my sight clear, but tied to few objects; My senses delicate and gentle, but my apprehension and application hard and dull. I engage my self with difficulty. As much as I can I employ my self wholly to my self. And in this very subject I would willingly bridle and uphold my affection, lest it be too far plunged therein; Seeing it is a Subject I possesse at the mercy of others, and over which fortune has more interest then my self. So as even in my health, which I so much esteeme, it were requisite not to desire, nor so carefully to seek it, as thereby I might light upon intollerable diseases. We must moderate ourselves betwixt the hate of pain and the love of pleasure. Plato sets down a meane course of life betweene both. But to affections that distract me from my self, and divert me elsewhere, surely to such I oppose my self with all my force. Mine opinion is, that one should lend himself to others, and not give himself but to himself. Were my wil easy to engage or apply itself, I could not continue: I am over tender both by nature and custom, Fugax rerum, securaque in otia natus. -- OVID. Trist. 1 iii. Eleg. ii. 9. Avoiding active business, And borne to secure idlenesse. Contested and obstinate debates, which in the end would give mine adversarie advantage, the issue which would make my earnest pursuit ashamed, would perchance torment me cruelly. If I vexed as other men, my soul should never have strength to bear the alaroms and emotions that follow such as embrace much. She would presently be displaced by this intestine agitation. If at any time I have been urged to the managing of strange affairs, I have promised to undertake them with my hand, but not with my lungs and liver; to charge, and not to incorporate them into me, to have a care, but nothing at all to be overpassionate of them: I looke to them, but I hatch them not. I work enough to dispose and direct the domesticall troubles within my own entrailes and veines, without harbouring, or importune my self with any forraine employments; and am sufficiently interessed with my proper, natural and essentiall affairs, without seeking others businesses. Such as know how much they owe to themselves, and how many offices of their own they are bound to performe, shall find that nature has given them this commission fully ample and nothing idle. Thou hast business enough within your self, therefore stray not abroad; Men give themselves to hire. Their faculties are not their own, but theirs to whom they subject themselves; their inmates, and not themselves, are within them. This common humor does not please me. We should thriftily husband our mindes liberty, and never engage it but upon just occasions, which if we judge impartially, are very few in number. Looke on such as suffer themselves to be transported and swayed, they do it every where; in little as well as in great matters, to that which concerneth as easy as to that which toucheth them not. They thrust themselves indifferently into all actions, and are without life if without tumultuary agitation. In negotiis sunt negotii causa: ’They are busie that they may not be idle, or else in action for actions sake.’ They seek work but to be working. It is not so much because they will go, as for that they cannot stand still - much like to a rowling stone, which never stayes until it come to a lying place. To some men employment is a marke of sufficiencie and a badge of dignity. Their spirits seek rest in action, as infants repose in the cradle. They may be said to be as serviceable to their friends as importunate to themselves, No man distributes his mony to others, but every one his life and time. We are not so prodigall of any thing as of those whereof to be covetous would be both commendable and profitable for us. I follow a cleane contrary course; I am of another complexion; I stay at home and looke to my self. What I wish for I commonly desire the same but mildely, and desire but little; so likewise I seldom employ and quietly embusie my self. Whatever they intend and act they do it with all their will and vehemency. There are so many dangerous steps, that for the more security we must somewhat slightly and superficially slide through the world, and not force it. Pleasure itself is painefull in its height. ------ incedis per ignes, Sub positos cineri deloso. -- HOR. Car. 1. ii. Od. i. 7. You pass through fire (though unfraid) Under deceitfull ashes laid. The town counsell of Bourdeaux chose me Maior of their City, being far from France, but further from any such thought. I excused my self, and would have avoided it; but they told me I was to blame, the more because the Kings commandement was also employed therein. It is a charge should seem so much the more goodly because it has neither fee nor reward other than the honor in the execution. It lasteth two years, but may continue longer by a second election, which seldom happens. To me it was, and never had been but twice before: some years past the Lord of Lansac, and lately to the Lord of Biron, Marshall of France, in whose place I succeeded, and left mine to the Lord of Matigon, likewise Marshall of France, glorious by so noble an assistance. Uterque bonus pacis bellique minister. Both, both in peace and war, Right serviceable are. Fortune would have a share in my promotion by this particular circumstance which she of her own added thereunto, not altogether vain; for Alexander disdained the Corinthian Ambassadors who offred him the freedome and Burgeoise of their City, but when they told him that Bacchus and Hercules were likewise in their registers he kindly thanked them and accepted their offer. At my first arrivall I faithfully deciphered and conscientiously displaied my self such as I am indeede, without memory, without diligence, without experience and without sufficiencie; so likewise without hatred, without ambition, covetousnesse and without violence; that so they might be duly instructed what service they might or hope or expect at my hands. And forasmuch as the knowledge they had of my deceased father, and the honor they bare unto his memory, had mooved them to chuse me to that dignitie, I told them plainly I should be very sorie that any man should work such an opinion in my will as their affairs and City had done in my fathers, while he held the said government, whereunto they had called me. I remembred to have seen him, being an infant and he an old man, his mind cruelly turmoiled with the public toile, forgetting the sweet aire of his own house, whereunto the weakenes of his age had long before tied him, neglecting the care of his health and family, in a manner despising his life, which as one engaged for them, he much endangered, riding long and painefull journies for them. Such a one was he, which humor proceeded from the bountie and goodnesse of his nature. Never was mind more charitable or more popular. This course, which I commend in others, I love not to follow. Neither am I without excuse. He had heard that a man must forget himself for his neighbour; that in respect of the general, the particular was not to be regarded. Most of the worlds-rules and precepts hold this traine, to drive us out of ourselves into the wide world, to the use of public societie. They presumed to work a goodly effect in distracting and withdrawing us from ourselves, supposing we were by a natural Instinct too-too much tied unto it: and to this end have not spared to say any thing. For to the wise it is no novelty to reach things as they serve, and not as they are. Truth has her lets, discommodities and incomparabilities with us. We must not often deceive others, lest we beguile ourselves; and seele our eyes, and dull our understanding, thereby to repair and amend them. Imperiti enim judicant, et qui frequenter in hoc ipsum fallendi sunt, ne errent: ’For unskilfull men judge, who must often even therefore be deceived, lest they erre and be deceived.’ When they prescribe us, to love three, foure, indeed fifty degrees of things before ourselves, they present us with the Arte of shooters, who to come near the marke take their aime far above the same. To make a crooked sticke straight, we bend it the contrary way. I suppose that in the [temple] of Pallas, as we see in all other religions, they had some apparant mysteries, of which they made show to all the people, and others more high and secret, to be imparted only to such as were professed. It is likely that the true point of friendship, which every man oweth to himself, is to be found in these. Not a false amitie, which makes us embrace glory, knowledge, riches, and such like, with a principal and immoderate affection, as members of our being; nor an effeminate and indiscreet friendship, Wherein happens as to the Ivie, which corrupts and ruines the wals it claspeth; But a sound and regular amity, equally profitable and Pleasant. Who so understandeth all her duties and exerciseth them, he is rightly endenized in the Muses cabinet; He has attained the type of humane Wisedome and the perfection of our happinesse. This man, knowing exactly what he oweth to himself, findeth that he ought to employ the use of other men and of the world unto himself; which to performe, he must contribute the duties and offices that concerne him unto public societie. He that lives not somewhat to others, liveth little to himself. Qui sibi amicus est, scito hune amicum omnibus esse: (Sen. Epist. vi. f.) ’He that is friend to himself, know, he is friend to all.’ The principal charge we have is every man his particular conduct. And for this only we live here. As he that should forget to live well and religiously; and by instructing and directing others should think himself acquitted of his duty, would be deemed a foole; Even so, who forsaketh to live healthy and merrily himself, therwith to serve another, in mine opinion taketh a bad and unnaturall course. I will not that in any charge one shall take in hand he refuse or think much of his attention, of his labor, of his steps, of his speech, of his sweat, and if need be of his blood. -----non ipse pro charis amicis, Aut patria timidus perire. -- Hor. Car. iv. Od. ix. 51. Not fearing life to end For Country or dear friend. But it is only borrowed and accidentally, the mind remaining ever quiet and in health, not without action, but without vexation or passion; simply to moove or be dooing costs it so little that even sleeping it is mooving and dooing; but it must have its motion with discretion, for the body receiveth the charges imposed on him, justly as they are; But the spirit extendeth them, and often to his hinderance makes them heavy, giving them what measure it pleaseth. Like things are effected by diverse efforts and different contentions of will; the one may go without the other, for how many men do dayly hazard themselves in war which they regard not, and press into the danger of the battells, the loss whereof shall no whit breake their next sleepe? Whereas some man in his own house, free from this danger, which he durst not so much as have looked towards it, is for the wars issue more passionate, and therewith has his mind more perplexed than the souldier that therin employeth his blood and life. I know how to deal in public charges without departing from my self. This sharpnesse and violence of desires hindreth more then steade the conduct of what we undertake, filling us with impatience to the events, either contrary or slow, and with bitternesse and jealousie toward those with whom we negotiate. We never governe that thing well wherewith we are possessed and directed. ------Male cuncta ministrat Impetus. Fury and haste do lay all waste, Misplacing all, disgracing all. He who therein employeth but his judgement and direction, proceeds more cheerfully, he faines, he yields, he deferres at his pleasure according to the occasions of necessity; he failes of his attempt without torment or affliction, ready and prepared for a new enterprise. He marcheth alwaies with the reines in his hand. He that is besotted with this violent and tyrannical intention does necessarily declare much indiscretion and injustice. The violence of his desire transports him. They are rash motions, and if fortune helpe not much, of little fruit. Philosophie wills us to banish choller in the punishment of offences; not to the end revenge should be more moderate but contrary, more weighty and surely set on; wherunto this violence seems to be a let. Choller does not only trouble, but wearieth the executioners arms. This passionate heat dulleth and consumes their force. As in too much speede, festinatio tarda est: ’Hastinesse is slow.’ Haste makes waste, and hinders and stayes itself: ipsa se velocitas implicat: ’Swiftnesse entangles itself.’ As for example, according as by ordinary custom I perceive, covetousnesse has no greater let then itself. The more violent and extended it is, the less effectuall and fruitfull. Commonly it gathers wealth more speedily, being masked with a show of liberality. A very honest Gentleman and my good friend was likely to have endangered the health of his body by an over passionate attention and earnest affection to the affairs of a Prince, who was his Maister. Which Maister has thus described himself unto me: That as another, he discerneth and has a feeling of the burden of accidents; but such as have no remedie, he presently resolveth to suffer with patience. For the rest, after he has appointed necessary provisions, which by the vivacitie and nimblenesse of his with he speedily effects, he then attends the event with quietnesse. Verily, I have seen in him at one instant a great carelesnesse and liberty, both in his actions and countenance, even in important and difficult affairs. I find him more magnanimous and capable in bad then in good fortune. His losses are to him more glorious than his victories, and his mourning than his triumphs. Consider how in meere vain and frivolous actions, as at chesse, tennis and such like sports, this earnest and violent engaging with an ambicious desire to winne, does presently call both mind and limbs into disorder and indiscretion. Wherein a man does both dazle his sight and distemper his whole body. He who demeaneth himself with most moderation both in winning and loosing is ever neerest unto himself, and has his wits best about him. The less he is moved or passionate in play, the more safely does be governe the same, and to his greater advantage. We hinder the minds seazure and holdfast by giving her so many things to seize upon. Some we should only present unto her, others fasten upon her, and others incorporate into her. Shee may see and feel all things, but must only feede on herself: And be instructed in that which properly concerneth her, and which meerely belongeth to her essence and substance. The laws of nature teach us what is just and fit for us. After the wise-men have told us, that according to nature no man is indigent or wanteth, and that each one is poore but in his own opinion, they also distinguish subtilly the desires proceeding from nature, from such as grow from the disorders of our fantasie. Those whose end may be discerned are meerely hirs; and such as flie before us, and whose end we cannot attaine, are properly ours. Want of goods may easily be cured, but the poverty of the mind is incurable. Nam si, quod satis est homini, id satis esse potesset, Hoc sat erat, nunc, quum hoc non est, qui credimus porro Divitias ullas animum mi explere potesse? If it might be enough, that is enough for man, This were enough, since it is not, how think we can Now any riches fill My mind and greedy will? Socrates seeing great store of riches, jewells, and pretious stuffe, carried in pompe through the City: Oh how many things (quoth he) do not I desire! Metrodorus lived daily with the weight of twelve ounces of foode; Epicurus with less; Metrocles in winter lay with sheepe, and in summer in the Cloisters of Churches. Sufficit ad id natura, quod poscit: (Sen. Epist. xc.) ’Nature is sufficient for that which it requires.’Cleanthes lived by his hands, and boasted that if Cleanthes would, he could nourish another Cleanthes. If that which nature does exactly and originally require at our handes for the preservation of our being, is over little (as in truth what it is, and how good cheape our life may be maintained, cannot better be known or expressed than by consideration that it is so little, and for the smalnesse thereof, it is out of Fortunes reach, and she can take no hold of it) let us dispense something els unto ourselves and call the custom and condition of every-one of us by the name of Nature. Let us taxe and stint and feede ourselves according to that measure; let us extend both our appurtenances and reckonings thereunto. For so far, me seems, we have some excuse. Custome is a second Nature, and no less powerfull. What is wanting to custom, I hold it a defect; and I had well nigh as leefe one should deprive me of my life, as refraine or much abridge me of my state wherein I have lived so long. I am no more upon termes of any great alteration nor to thrust my self into a new and unusuall course, no not toward augmentation; it is no longer time to become other or be transformed; and as I should complain if any great adventure should now befall me, and grieve it came not in time that I might have enjoyed the same. Quo mihi fortuna, si non conceditur uti? -- HOR. i. Epist. v. 12. Whereto should I have much, If I to use it grutch? I should likewise be grieved at any inward purchase. I were better in a manner never, than so late, to become an honest man, and well practised to live when one has no longer life. I who am ready to depart this World could easily be induced to resigne the share of wisdom I have learn’t concerning the World’s commerce, to any other man new-come into the world. It is even as good as Mustard after dinner. What neede have I of that good which I cannot enjoy? Whereto serveth knowledge if one have no head? It is an injury and disgrace of Fortune to offer us those presents, which forasmuch as they faile us when we should most neede them, fill us with a just spite. Guide me no more; I can go no longer. Of so many dismembrings that Sufficiency has, patience sufficeth us. Give the capacity of an excellent treble to a Singer that has his lungs rotten, and of eloquence to a hermit confined into the Deserts of Arabia. There needs no Arte to further a fall. The end findes it self in the finishing of every work. My world is at an end, my form is expired. I am wholly of the time past, and am bound to authorize the same, and thereto conforme my issue. I will say this by way of example, that the eclipsing or abridging of tenne dayes, which the Pope has lately caused, has taken me so low that I can hardly recover my self. I follow the years wherein we were wont to compt otherwise; so long and ancient a custom does challenge and recall me to it again, I am thereby enforced to be somewhat an hereticke, Incapable of innovation though corrective. My imagination mauger my teeth runnes still tenne dayes before or tenne behinde, and whispers in mine ears: This rule toucheth those which are to come. If health itself, so sweetly pleasing, comes to me but by fittes, it is rather to give me cause of grief then possession of itself; I have no where left me to retire it. Time forsakes me, without which nothing is enjoyed. How small accompt should I make of these great elective dignities I see in the world, and which are only given to men ready to leave the world, wherein they regard not so much how duely they shall discharge them, as how little they shall exercise them, from the beginning they looke to the end. To conclude, I am ready to finish this man, not to make another. By long custom this form is changed into substance and Fortune into Nature. I say, therefore, that amongst us feeble creatures, each one is excusable to compt that his own, which is comprehended under measure. And yet all beyond these limits is nothing but confusion. It is the largest extension we can grant our rights. The more we amplifie our neede and possession, the more we engage ourselves to the crosses of fortune and adversities. The cariere of our desires must be circumscribed, and tied to strict bounds of neerest and contiguous commodities. Moreover, their course should be managed, not in a straight line having another end, but round, whose two points hold together, and end in ourselves with a short compasse. The actions governed without this reflection, I meane a near and essentiall reflection, as those of the covetous, of the ambitious, and so many others, that run directly point-blancke, the course of which carrieth them away before them, are erroneous and crazed actions. Most of our vacations are like Playes. Mundus universus exercet histrioniam: ’All the world does practise stage-playing.’ We must play our parts duly, but as the part of a borrowed personage. Of a visard and apparance we should not make a reall essence, nor proper of that which is another. We cannot distinguish the skinne from the shirt; it is sufficient to disguise the face without deforming the breast. I see some transforme and transubstantiate themselves into as many new formes and strange beings as they undertake charges; and who emprelate themselves even to the heart and entrailes; and entraine their offices, even sitting on their close stoole. I cannot teach them to distinguish the salutations and cappings of such as regard them, from those that respect either their office, their traine, or their mule. Tantum se fortunæ permittunt, etiam ut naturam dediscant: ’They give themselves so much over to Fortune, as they forget Nature.’ They swell in mind and puffe up their natural discourse according to the dignity of their office. The Maior of Bourdeaux, and Michæl, Lord of Montaigne, have ever been two, by an evident separation. To be an advocate or a Treasurer one should not be ignorant of the craft incident to such callings. An honest man is not comptable for the vice and folly of his trade, and therefore ought not to refuse the exercise of it. It is the custom of his country, and there is profit in it. We must live by the World, and such as we find it, so make use of it. But the judgement of an Emperor should be above his Empire, and to see and consider the same as a strange accident. He should know how to enjoy himself apart, and communicate himself as James and Peter, at least to himself, I cannot so absolutely or so deepely engage my self. When my wil gives me to any party, it is not with so violent a bond that my understanding is thereby infected. In the present intestine trouble of our State my interest has not made me forget neither the commendable qualities of our adversaries, nor the reproachfull of those I have followed. They partiall extoll whatever is on their side; I do not so much as excuse the greater number of my friends actions. A good Oratour loses not his grace by pleading against me. The intricatenesse of our debate remooved, I have maintained my self in equanimity and pure indifferency. Neque extra necessitates belli, præcipuum odium gero: ’Nor bear I capital hatred when I am out of the necessitie of war.’ Wherein I glory, for that commonly I see men erre in the contrary. Such as extend their choller and hatred beyond their affairs (as most men do) show that it proceedes elsewhence, and from some private cause; even as one being cured of an ulcer, and his fever remaineth still, declareth it had another more hidden beginning. It is the reason they bear none unto the cause in general, and forasmuch as it concerneth the interest of all and of the state; But they are vexed at it, only for this, that it toucheth them in private. And therefore are they distempered with a particular passion, both beyond justice and public reason. Non tam omnia universi, quam ea, quæ ad quemque pertinent, singuli carpebant: ’All did not so much find fault with all, as every one with those that appertained to every one.’ I will have the advantage to be for us, which though it be not I enrage not, I stand firmely to the sounder parts. But I affect not to be noted a private enemy to others, and beyond general reason I greatly accuse this vicious form of obstinate contesting. He is of the League because he admireth the grace of the Duke of Guise; or he is a Hugonote, forasmuch as the King of Navarres activitie amazeth him. He finds fault in the Kings behaviours, therefore he is sedicious in his heart. I would not give the magistrate my voice that he had reason to condemne a book, because an hereticke was therein named and extolled to be one of the best Poets of this age. Dare we not say that a theefe has a good leg if behave so indeed? If she be a strumpet, must she needs have a stinking breath? In wiser ages revoked they the proud title of Capitolinus they had formerly given to Marcus Manlius as the preserver of religion and public liberty? Suppressed they the memory of his liberalitie, his deeds of arms and military rewards granted to his vertues, because to the prejudice of his countries laws he afterwards affected a Royalty? If they once conceive an hatred against an Orator or an advocate, the next day he becomes barbarous and uneloquent. I have elsewhere discoursed of zeale which has driven good men into like errours. For my self I can say, that he does wickedly, and this vertuously. Likewise, in prognostickes or sinister events of affairs, they will have every man blinde or dull in his own cause, and that our persuasion and judgement serve not the truth but the project of our desires. I should rather erre in the other extremity? So much I fear my desire might corrupt me. Considering I somewhat tenderly distrust my self in things I most desire. I have in my dayes seen wonders in the indiscreet and prodigious facilitie of people, suffering their hopes and beliefes to be led and governed as it has pleased and best fitted their leaders, above a hundred discontents, one in the necke of another, and beyond their fantasies and dreames. I wonder no more at those whom the apish toyes of Apollonius and Mahomet have seduced and blinded. Their sense and understanding is wholly smothered in their passion. Their discretion has no other choise but what pleaseth them and furthereth their cause. Which I had especially observed in the beginning of our distempered factions and factious troubles. This other which is grown since by imitation surmounteth the same. Whereby I observe that it is an inseparable quality of popular errours. The first beeing gone, opinions entershocke one another, following the winde as waves do. They are no members of the body, if they may renounce it, if they folow not the common course. But truely they wrong the just parts when they seek to helpe them with fraude or deceipts. I have alwaies contracted the same. This meane is but for sicke braines; the healthy have surer and honester ways to maintaine their resolutions and excuse all contrary accidents. The Heavens never saw so weighty a discord and so harmefull a hatred as that betweene Cæsar and Pompey, nor ever shall hereafter. Mee seems, notwithstanding I see in those noble and Heroicall mindes an exemplar and great moderation of the one toward the other. It was a jelousie of honor and emulation of command which transported them, not to a furious and indiscreete hatred, without malice or detraction. In their sharpest exploites I discover some reliques of respect and cinders of well-meaning affection. And I imagine that had it been possible either of them desired rather to effect his purpose without overthrowing his competitour than by working his utter ruine. Note how contrary the proceeding was betweene Sylla and Marius. We must not run headlong after our affections and private interests. As in my youth I ever opposed my self to the motions of love, which I felt to usurpe upon me, and laboured to diminish its delights, lest in the end it might vanquish and captivate me to his mercy; So do I now in all other occasions which my will apprehendeth with an over great appetite. I bend to the contrary of my disposition as I see the same plunged and drunke with its own Wine. I shunne so far foorth to nourish her pleasure as I may not revoke it without a bloody loss. Those mindes which through stupidity see things but by halves enjoy this happinesse, that such as be hurtful offend them least. It is a spirituall leprosie that has some show of health, and such a health as Philosophy does not altogether contemne. But yet it may not lawfully be termed wisdom, as we often do. And after this manner did in former times some body mocke Diogenes, who, in the dead of Winter, went all naked, embracing an image of Snow to try his patience, who, meeting him in this order, said thus unto him: ’Art you now very colde?’ ’Nothing, at all,’ answered Diogenes. ’What thinkest you to do then that is either hard or exemplar by standing in the colde?’ replied the other. ’To measure constancy we must necessarily know sufferance.’ But such minds as must behold crosse events and fortunes injuries in their height and sharpnesse, which must weigh and taste them according to their natural bitternesse and charge, let them employ their skil and keep themselves from embracing the causes and divert their approaches. What did King Cotys? He payed liberally for that godly and rich Vessell which one had presented unto him, but forasmuch as it was exceeding brittle he presently broke it himself, that so betimes he might remoove so easy an occasion of choller against his servants. I have in like sort shunned confusion in my affairs, and sought not to have my goods contiguous to my neighbors, and to such as I am to be linked in strict friendshippe, Whence commonly ensue causes of alienation and unkindnesse. I have heretofore loved the hazardous play of Cardes and Dice. I have long since left it; only for this, that notwithstanding any fair semblance I made in my losses I was inwardly disquieted. Let a man of honor, who is to take a lie or endure an outrageous wrong, and cannot admit a bad excuse for paiment or satisfaction, avoid the progresse of contentious altercations. I shunne melancholike complexions and froward men, as infected. And in matters I cannot talk of without interest and emotion, I meddle not with them, except duty constraine me thereunto. Melius non incipient quam desinent: ’They shall better not beginne than leave off.’ The surest way is then to prepare ourselves before occasion. I know that some wisemen have taken another course, and have not feared to engage and vehemently to insinuate themselves into diverse objects. Those assure themselves of their own strength, under which they shrowd themselves against all manner of contrary events, making mischiefes to wrestle one against another by vigor and virtue of patience: Velut rupes vastum quæ prodit in æquor, Obvia ventorum furiis, expostaque ponto. Vim cunct am atque minas perfert cælique marisque, . . . ipsa immota manens. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. x. 693. Much like a rocke, which buts into the Maine, Meeting with winds-rage, to the Sea laid plaine, It does the force of skies and Seas sustain, Endure their threats, yet does uumoov’d remaine. Let us not imitate these examples; we shall not attaine them. They opinionate themselves resolutely to behold, and without perturbation to be spectatours of their Countries ruine, which whilome possessed and commaunded their full will. As for our vulgar mindes, therein is too much effort and roughnesse. Cato quit thereby the noblest life that ever was. We seely ones must seek to escape the storme further off: We ought to provide for apprehension and not for patience, and avoid the blowes we cannot withstand. Zeno seeing Chremonides, a young man whom he loved, approach to sit near him, rose up sodainly. Cleanthes asking him the reason? I understand (says he) that physicians above all things prescribe rest, and forbid emotion in all humors. Socrates says not: Yeeld not to the allurements of beauty; maintaine it, enforce ourselves to the contrary. Shunne her (says he), run out of her sight and company, as from a violent poison that infecteth and stingeth far-off. And his good Disciple, faining or reciting, but in mine opinion rather reciting then faining, the matchles perfections of the great Cyrus, describeth him distrusting his forces to withstand the blandishments or allurings of the divine beautie of that famous Panthea his Captive, committing the visitation and guarde of her to an other, that had less liberty then himself. And likewise the Holy-Ghost says, ne nos inducas in tentationem: (Matth. vi. 13.) ’and lead us not into temptation.’ We pray not that our reason be not encountered, and vanquished by concupiscence, but that it be not so much as assayed therewith; That we be not reduced to an estate, where we should but suffer the approaches, sollicitations and temptations of sinne: and we entreat our Lord to keep our conscience quiet, fully perfectly free from all commerce of evil. Such as say they have reason for their revenging passion, or any other mind-troubling perturbation, say often truth, as things are, but not as they were. They speak to us when the causes of their error are by themselves fostred and advanced. But retire further backeward, recall their causes to their beginning: there you surprise and put them to a non-plus. Would they have their fault be less because it is more ancient; and that of an unjust beginning, the progresse be just? He that (as I do) shall wish his countries well-fare, without fretting or pining himself, shall be grieved, but not swoune, to see it threatning, either his own downefall, or a continuance no less ruinous. Oh seely-weake barke, whom both waves, winds and Pilot, hull and tosse to so contrary desseignes: -----in tam diversa, magister, Ventus et unda trahunt. Maister the wave and winds So diverse ways do binde. Who gapes not after the favor of Princes, as after a thing without which he cannot live, nor is much disquieted at the coldnes of their entertainment or frowning countenance, nor regardeth the inconstancy of their will. Who hatcheth not his children or huggeth not honors, with a slavish propension, nor leaves to live commodiously having once lost them. Who does good namely for his own satisfaction, nor is much vexed to see men censure of his actions against his merit. A quarter of an ownce of patience provideth for such inconveniences. I find ease in this receit: redeeming my self in the beginning as good cheape as I can, by which means I perceive my self to have escaped much trouble and manifold difficulties. With very little force I stay these first motions of my perturbations, And I abandon the subject which beginnes to molest me, and before it transport me. He that stops not the loose, shall hardly stay the course. He that cannot shut the doore against them shall never expell them being entered. He that cannot attaine an end in the beginning, shall not come to an end of the conclusion; nor shall he endure the fall that could not endure the starts of it. Etenim ipsæ se impellunt , ubi semel a ratione discessum est, ipsague ibi imbecillitas indulget, in altumque provehitur imprudens: nec resent locuni consistendi: (CIC. Tusc. Qu. iv.) ’For they drive themselves headlong, when once they are parted and past reason, and weaknesse soothes itself, and unawares is carried into the deepe, nor can it find a place to tarry in.’ I feel betimes the low winds which are forerunners of the storme, buzze in mine ears and sound and trie me within: -----ceu flamina prima Cum deprensa fremunt sylvis, et cæca volutant Murmura, venturos nautis prodentia ventos. -- VIRG. Æn. 1. x. 97. At first blasts in the woods perceiv’d to go, Whistle, and darkely speak in murmurs low, Foretelling Marriners what winds will grow. How often have I done myself an apparent injustice to avoid the the danger I should fall into by receiving the same, happily worse, from a world of troubles, and of foul and vile practises, more enemies to my natural disposition t hen fire and torment? Convenit a litibus quantum licet, et nescio an paulo plus etiam quam licet, abhorrentem esse; Est enim non modo liberale, paululum nonnunquam de suo jure decedere, sed interdum etiam fructuosum: (CIC. Off. i.) ’As much as we may, and it may be more then we may, we should abborre brabling and lawing; for it is not only an ingenious part, but sometimes profitable also at sometimes to yield a little of our right.’ If we were wise indeede, we should rejoice and glory, as I heard once a yong-gentleman, borne of a very great house, very wittily and unfainedly rejoice with all men that his mother had lost her sute; as if it had been a cough, an ague, or any other yrksome burden. The favors which fortune might have given me, as aliances and acquaintances with such as have Soveraigne authority in those things, I have in my conscience done much instantly to evoide employing them to others prejudice, and not over-value my rights above their worth. To conclude, I have so much prevailed by my endeavors (in a good hour I may speak it) that I am yet a virgin for any sutes in law which have notwithstanding not omitted gently to offer me their service, and under pretence of lawfull titles insinuate themselves into my allowance, would I but have given care unto them. And as a pure maiden from quarrels, I have without important offence, either passive or active, lingred out a long life, and never heard worse than my own name: A rare grace of heaven. Our greatest agitations have strange springs and ridiculous causes. What ruine did our last Duke of Burgundy run into for the quarrell of a cart-load of sheepes-skinnes? And was not the graving of a scale the chief cause of the most horrible breach and topsie-turvey that ever this worlds-frame endured? For Pompey and Cæsar are but the new buddings and continuation of two others. And I have seen in my time the wisest heads of this realm assembled with great ceremony and public charge about treaties and agreements, the true-deciding whereof depended in the meane while absolutely and soveraignely of the will and consultations held in some Ladies pate or cabinet, and of the inclination of some silly woman. Poets have most judiciously looked into this, who but for an apple have set all Greece and Asia on fire and sword. See why that man does hazard both his honor and life on the fortune of his rapier and dagger; let him tell you whence the cause of that contention arises; he can not without blushing, so vain and so frivolous is the occasion. To embarke him, there needs but little advisement, but being once-in, all parts do work. There are greater provisions required, more difficult and important. How far more easy is it not to enter than to get forth? We must proceed contrary to the brier, which produces a long and straight stalke at the first springing; but after, as tired and out of breath, it makes many and thicke knots, as if they were pawses, shewing to have no more that vigor and constancy. We should rather begin gentle and leasurely, and keep our strength and breath for the perfection of the work. We direct affairs in the beginning, and hold them at our mercy, but being once undertaken, they guide and transport us, and we must follow them. Yet may it not be said that this counsell has freed me from all difficulties, and that I have not been often troubled to controle and bridle my passions, which are not alwayes governed according to the measure of occasions, whose entrances are often sharpe and violent. So is it that thence may be reaped good fruit and profit, except for those who in well doing are not satisfied with any benefit, if their reputation be in question. For in truth such an effect is not compted of but by every one to himself. You are thereby better satisfied, but not more esteemed, having reformed your self before you come into action or the matter was in sight; yet not in this only, but in all other duties of life, their course which aime at honor is diverse from that which they propound unto themselves that follow order and reason. I find some that inconsiderately and furiously thrust themselves into the lists, and grow slacke in the course. As Plutarke says, that ’Such as by the vice of bashfullnesse are soft and tractable to grant whatsoever is demanded, are afterward as proxie and facile to recant and breake their word.’ In like manner, he that enters lightly into a quarrel is subject to leave it as lightly. The same difficulty which keepes me from embracing the same should incite me, being once mooved and therein engaged, to continue resolute. It is an ill custom. Being once embarked, one must either go on or sinke. ’Attempt coldly’ (sayed Byas), ’but pursue hotly.’ For want of judgement our hearts faile us, Which is also less tolerable. Most agreements of our modern quarrels are shamefull and false; We only seek to save apparances and therewhilst betray and disavow our true intentions. We salve the deede; We know how we spake it, and in what sence the by- standers know it; indeed our friends to whom we would have our advantages known. It is to the prejudice of our liberty and interest of our resolutions honor that we dis-avow our thoughts and seek for starting holes in falshood to make our a greements. We bely ourselves to salve a lie we have given to another. We must not looke whether your action or word may admit another interpretation, but it is your own true and sincere construction that you must now maintaine, whatsoever it cost you. It is to your virtue and to your conscience that men speak; parts that ought not to be disguised. Leave we these base courses, wrangling shifts and verball means, to pettyfogging Lawyers. The excuses and reparations, or satisfactions, which dayly I see made, promised and given to purge indiscretion, seem to me more foul than indiscretion itself; Better were it for one to offend his adversary again, than in giving him such satisfaction to wrong himself so much. You have braved him mooved by choller, and now you seek to pacify and flatter him in your cold and better sense; Thus you abase yourselfe more than you were before exalted. I find no speech so vicious in a Gentleman as I deem any recantation he shall make, dishonorable, especially if it be wrested from him by authority; Forasmuch as obstinacy is in him more excusable than cowardice. Passions are to me as easy to be avoyded as they are difficult to be moderated. Excinduntur facilius animo, quam temperantur: ’They are more easily rooted out of the mind than brought to good temper.’ He that cannot attaine to this noble Stoicall impassibility let him shrowd himself in the bosome of this my popular stupidity. What they did by virtue I inure my self to do by Nature. The middle region harboureth stormes; the two extreames containe Philosophers and rurall men, they concurre in tranquility and good hap. Felix qui potuit rerum coqnoscere causas, Atque metus omnes et inexorabile fatum. Subjecit pedibus, strepitumque Acherontis avari. Fortunatus et ille, Deos qui novit agrestes, Pandaque, Silvantimque senem, Nymphasque sorores. Virg. Georg. ii. 490. Happy is he that could of things the causes find, And subject to his feete all fearefulnesse of mind, Inexorable fate, and noyse of greedy Hell. And happy he, with Country Gods acquainted well, Pan and old Sylvan knowes, And all the sister shrowes. The beginnings of all things are weake and tender. We must therefore be clear-sighted in beginnings; For, as in their budding we discerne not the danger, so in their full growth we perceive not the remedy. I should have encountered a thousand crosses, daily more hard to be digested in the course of ambition, than it has bin uneasie for me to stay the natural inclination that led me onto them. ----- jure perhorrui, Late conspicuum tollere verticem. -- Hor. Car. iii. 16, 18. I have been much afraid for causes right, To raise my foretop far abroad to sight. All public actions are subject to uncertaine and diverse interpretations: For, too many heads judge of them. Some say of this my City-employment (whereof I am content to speak a word, not that it deserves it, but to make a show of my manners in such things) I have demeaned my self like one that is too slowely moved and with a languishing affection; And they are not altogether void of reason. I strive to keep my mind and thoughts quiet. Cum semper Natura, tum etiam ætate jam quietus: ’Both ever quiet by Nature, and now because of yeeres.’ And if at any time they are debauched to some rude and piercing impression it is in truth without my consent, from which natural slacknesse one must not therefore inferre any proofe of disability; For, Want of care and lacke of judgement are two things; And less unkindnesse and ingratitude toward those Citizens who to gratifie me, employed the utmost of all the means they could possibly, both before they knew me and since; And who did much more for me in appointing me my charge the second time, then in choosing me the first. I love them with all my heart, and wish them all the good that may be; And truly if occasion had been offered I wold have spared nothing to have done them service. I have stirred and laboured for them as I do for my self. They are good people, warlike and generous, yet capable of obedience and discipline and fit for good employment, if they be well guided. They say likewise that I passed over this charge of mine without any deede of note or great show. It is true. Moreover, they accuse my cessation, when as all the world was convicted of too much doing; I have a most nimble motion where my will does carry me. But this point is an enemy unto perseverance. Whosoever will make use of me according to my self, let him employ me in affairs that require vigor and liberty; that have a short, a straight, and therewithall a hazardous course I may perhaps somewhat prevaile therein. Whereas if it be tedious, crafty, laborious, artificiall and intricate, they shall do better to address themselves to some other man. All charges of importance are not difficult. I was prepared to labor somewhat more earnestly if there had been great neede. For it lyes in my power to do something more than I make show of, and than I love to do. To my knowledge I have not omitted any motion that duty required earnestly at my hands. I have easily forgotten those which ambition blendeth with duty and cloketh with her title. It is they which most commonly fill the eyes and ears and satisfie men. Not the thing itself, but,; the apparance payeth them. If they hear no noise they imagine we sleepe. My humors are contrary to turbulent humors; I could pacify an inconvenience or trouble without troubling my self, and chastise a disorder without alteration. Have I neede of choller and inflammation, I borrow it and therewith maske my self; My maners are musty, rather wallowish then sharpe; I accuse not a Magistrate that sleepeth so they that are under it sleepe also. So sleepe the laws. For my part I commend a gliding, an obscure and reposed life. Neque submissam et abjectam, neque se efferentem: (Cic. Off. i.) ’Neyther too abject and submissive, nor vaunting itself too much.’ But my fortune will have it so; I am descended of a family that has lived without noise and tumult, and of long continuance particularly ambitious of integrity. Our men are so framed to agitation and ostentations that goodnesse, moderation, equity, constancy, and such quiet and meane qualities are no more heard of. Rough bodies are felt, smooth ones are handled imperceptibly. Sickenesse is felt, health little or not at all; nor things that annoint us, in regard of such as sting us. It is an action for ones reputation and private commodity, and not for the common good, to refer that to be done in the market place which a man may do in the counsel-chamber; and at noone day what might have been effected the night before; and to be jealous to do that himself which his fellow can performe as well. So did some Surgeons of Greece show the operations of their skill upon scaffolds in view of all passengers, thereby to get more practise and custom. They suppose that good orders cannot be understood but by the sound of a trumpet. Ambition is no vice for petty companions, and for such endevours as ours. One said to Alexander: ’Your father will leave you a great commaund, easy and peacefull;’ the boy was envious of his father’s victories and of the justice of his government. He would not have enjoyed the world’s Empire securely and quietly. Alcibiades in Plato loves rather to die yong, fair, rich, noble, learned, and all that in execellence, then to stay in the state of such a condition. This infirmity is happily excusable in so strong and full a mind. When these petty wretched soules are therewith enveagled, and think to publish their fame, because they have judged a cause rightly, or continued the order in guarding of a Cities gates; by how much more they hoped to raise their head, so much more do they show their simplicity. This petty well-doing has neither body nor life. It vanisheth in the first moneth, and walkes but from one corner of a street to another. Entertaine therewith your son and your servant, and spare not. As that ancient fellow, who having no other auditor of his praises and applauding of his sufficiency, boasted with his chambermaids, exclaiming: ’Oh Perette! what a gallant and sufficient man you hast to your maister!’ If the worst happen, entertaine yourselves in yourselves; As a Councellour of my acquaintance, having degorged a rable of paragraphes with an extreme contention and like foolishnesse, going out of the counsell chamber to a pissing place near unto it, was heard very conscienciously to utter these words to himself: Non nobis, Domine, non nobis, sed nomini tuo da gloriam (Psal. cvx. i.). ’Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us but unto your name give the glory.’ He that cannot otherwise, let him pay himself out of his own purse. Fame does not so basely prostitute itself, nor so cheape. Rare and exemplar actions, to which it duly belongeth, could not brooke the company of this innumerable multitude of vulgar petty actions. Well may a piece of marble raise your titles both as you list, because you have repaired a piece of an olde Wall, or cleansed a common ditch, but men of judgement will never do it. Report followeth not all goodnesse, except difficulty and rarietie be joined thereunto. Yea simple estimation, according to the Stoics, is not due to every action proceeding from virtue. Neither would they have him commended, who through temperance abstaineth from an old blear-ey’d woman. Such as have knowen the admirable qualities of Scipio the Affrican, renounce the glory which Panætius ascribeth unto him, to have abstained from gifts, as a glory, not his, alone, but peculiar to that age. We have pleasures sortable to our fortune; let us not usurpe those of greatness. Our own are more natural. They are the more solid and firme by how much the meaner. Since it is not for conscience, at least for ambition let us refuse ambition. Let us disdaine this insatiate thirst of honor and renown, base and beggerly, which makes us so suppliantly to crave it of all sorts of people: Quæ est ista laus quæ possite macello peti? (Cic. De Fin. ii.) ’What praise is this, which may be fetcht out of the Shambles?’ By abject means, and at what vile rate soever. To be thus honoured, is meerely a dishonour. Learne we to be no more greedy of glory then we are capable of it. To be proud of ever profitable and innocent action, is it fit for men to whom it is extraordinary and rare. They will value it for the price it cost them. According as a good effect is more resounding, I abate of its goodnesse; the jealousie I conceive, it is produced more because it is so resounding than because it is good. What is set out to show is halfe solde. Those actions have more grace which carelesly and under silence pass from the hands of a Workeman, and which some honest man afterward chuseth and redeemeth from darkenesse, to thrust them into the worlds light: Only for their worth. Mihi quidem laudabiliora videntur omnia, quæ sine venditatione, et sine populo teste fiunt: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. ii.)’All things in sooth seem to me more commendable that are performed with no ostentation, and without the people to witness,’ said the most glorious man of the world. I had no care but to preserve and continue, which are deafe and insensible effects. Innovation is of great lustre; But interdicted in times when we are most urged, and have to defend ourselves but from novelties; Abstinence from doing is often as generous as doing, but it is not so apparant. My small worth is in a manner all of this kind. To be short, the occasions in this my charge have seconded my complexion, for which I conne them harty thanks. Is there any man that desires to be sicke, to see his Physition set a work? And Should not that Physition be well whipped who to put his arte in practize, would wish the plague to infect us? I was never possessed with this impious and vulgar passion, to wish that the troubled and distempered state of this City might raise and honor my government. I have most willingly lent them my hand to further and shoulders to aid their ease and tranquility. He that will not thanke me for the good order and for the sweet and undisturbed rest which has accompanied my charge, cannot at least deprive me of that part which by the title of my good fortune belongeth unto me. This is my humor, that I love as much to be happy as wise, and attribute my successes as much to the meere gr ace of God as to the meane furtherance of my operation. I had sufficiently published to the World my sufficiency in managing of such public affairs; Nay, there is something in me worse than insufficiency, Which is, that I am not much displeased therewith, and that I endeavor not greatly to cure it, considering the course of life I have determined to my self. Nor have I satisfied my self in this employment, But have almost attainted what I had promised unto my self; Yet have I much exceeded what I had promised those with whom I was to negotiate, For I willingly promise somewhat less then I can performe or hope to accomplish. Of this I am assured, I have never left offence or hatred among them. To have left either regret or desire of me, This know I certainly, I have not much affected it. ------ Mene huic confidere monstro? Mene salis placidi vultum, fiuctdsque quietos Ignorare? -- VIRG. Æn. 1. v. 849. Should I this monster trust? Should I not know The calme Seas counterfeit dissembling show How quietly sometimes the flouds will go? Return to : Book III. CHAPTER XI: OF THE LAME OR CRIPPEL CHAPTER XI: OF THE LAME OR CRIPPEL WO OR three years are now past since the yeere has been shortned tenne dayes in France. Oh how many changes are like to ensue this reformation! It was a right remooving of Heaven and Earth together, yet nothing remooveth from it’s own place: My Neighbours find the season of their seede and Harvest time, the opportunity of their affairs, their lucky and unlucky dayes, to answer just those seasons to which they had from all ages assigned them. Neither was the error heretofore perceived, nor is the reformation now discerned in our use. So much uncertainty is there in all things; So grosse, so obscure and so dull [is] our understanding. Some are of opinion this reformation might have bin redressed after a less incommodious manner; substracting according to the example of Augustus, for some years, the bissextile or leape day, Which in some sort is but a day of hinderance and trouble, Until they might more exactly have satisfied the debt, Which by this late reformation is not done, For we are yet some dayes in arrerages; And if by such a meane we might provide for times to come, appoynting that after the revolution of such or such a number of years, that extraordinary day might for ever be eclipsed; so that our misreckoning should not henceforward exceed foure and twenty hours. We have no other computation of time, but years; The World has used them so many ages; and yet is it a measure we have not until this day perfectly established. And such as we daily doubt. what form other Nations have diversely given the same; and which was the true use of it. And if some day,that the Heavens in growing olde compresse themselves towards us, and cast into an uncertainty of hours and dayes? And as Plutarke says of moneths, that even in his dayes Astrology could not yet limit the motion of the moone? Are not we then well holp-up to keep a register of things past! I was even now plodding (as often I do) upon this, what free and gadding instrument humane reason is. I ordinarily see that men, in matters proposed them, do more willingly ammuze and busie themselves in seeking out the reasons than in searching out the trueth of them. They omit pre-suppositions, but curiously examine consequences. They leave things, and run to causes. Oh conceited [discoursers]! The knowledge of causes does only concerne him who has the conduct of things; Not us that have but the sufferance of them. And who according to our neede, without entering into their beginning and essence, have perfectly the full and absolute use of them. Nor is wine more pleasant unto him that knowes the first faculties of it. Contrariwise, both the body and the mind interrupt and alter the right which they have of the worlds use and of themselves, commixing therewith the opinion of learning. The effects concerne us, but the means nothing at all. To determine and distribute belongeth to superiority and regency as accepting, to subjection and apprentise-shippe. Let us re-assume our custom. They commonly beginne thus: How is such a thing done? Whereas, they should say: Is such a thing done? Our discourse is capable to frame an hundred other Worlds, and find the beginnings and contexture of them. It needeth neither matter nor ground. Let it but run on; It will as well build upon emptinesse as upon fulnesse, and with inanity as with matter. Dare pondus idonea fumo. -- Pers. Sat. v. 20. That things which vanish straight In smoke, should yet bear weight. I find that we should say most times: ’There is no such thing.’ And I would often employ this answer, but I dare not; for they cry: It is a defeature reduced by ignorance and weakenesse of spirit. And most commonly juggle for company sake, to treate of idle subjects and frivolous discourses, which I believe nothing at all. Since truely, it is a rude and quarrelous humor, flatly to deny a proposition. And few misse (especially in things hard to be persuaded) to affirme, that they have seen it; Or to alleadge such witnesses as their authority shall stay our contradiction. According to which use we know the foundation and means of a thousand things that never were. And the world is in a thousand questions discanted and bandied too and fro, the pro and contra of which is meerely false. Ita finitima sunt falsa veris ut in præcipitem locum non debeat se sapiens committere: (Cic. Acad. Que. iv.) ’Falsehood is so near Neighbour to trueth, that a wiseman should not put himself upon a slipperie downefall. Truth and falsehood have both likewise countenances; their port, their taste, and their proceedings semblable.’ We behold them with one same eyes. I observe that we are not only slow in defending our selves from deceipt, but that we seek and sue to embrace it. We love to meddle and entangle ourselves with vanity, as conformable unto our being. I have seen the birth of diverse miracles in my dayes. Although they be smoothered in the first growth, we omit not to foresee the course they would have taken had they lived their full age. The matter is to find the end of the clue; that found, one may winde-off what he list; And there is a further distance from nothing to the least thing in the World, than betweene that and the greatest. Now the first that are embrued with the beginning of strangenesse, coming to publish their history, find by the oppositions made against them, where the difficulty of persuasion lodgeth, and go about with some false patch to botch up those places. Besides that, Insita hominibus libidine alendi de industria rumores. ’Men having a natural desire to nourish reports.’ We naturally make it a matter of conscience to restore what has been lent us, without some usury and accession of our encrease. A particular error does first breed a public error; And when his turn commeth, a public error begetteth a particular error. So goeth all this vast frame, from hand to hand, confounding and composing itself, in such sort that the furthest-abiding testimony, is better instructed of it then the nearest, and the last informed better persuaded then the first. It is natural progresse; for whosoever beleeveth any thing, thinkes it a deede of charity to persuade it unto another; Which that he may the better effect, he feareth not to adde something of his own invention thereunto, so far as he seeth necessary in his discourse, to supply the resistance and defect, he imagineth to be in anothers conception. My self who make an especiall matter of conscience to lie, and care not greatly to add credit or authority to what I say, perceive, nevertheless by the discourses I have in hand, that being earnested, either by the resistance of another or by the earnestnesse of my naration, I swell and amplifie my subject by my voice, motions, vigor and force of wordes; as also by extension and amplification, not without some prejudice to the naked truth. But yet I do it upon condition that to the first that brings me home again, and enquireth for the bare and simple truth at my hands, I sodainly give over my hold, and without exaggeration, emphasis or amplification, I yield both my self and it unto him: A likely, earnest and ready speech as mine, is easy transported into hyperboles. There is nothing whereunto men are ordinarily more prone then to give way to their opinions. Where ever usual means faile us, we adde commandement, force, fire and sword. It is not without some ill fortune to come to that pass, that the multitude of believers in a throng where fooles do in number so far exceed the wise, should be the best touchstone of truth. Quasi vero quidquam sit tam valde, quam nil sapere vulgare. Sanitatis patrocinium est insanientium turba: (Cic. De Divin. ii.) ’As though any thing were so common as to have no wit. The multitude of them that are mad is a defense for them that are in their wit.’ It is a hard matter for a man to resolve his judgement against common opinions. The first persuasion taken from the very subject seizeth on the simple: whence under th’authority of the number and antiquity of testimonies it extends itself on the wiser sort. As for me, in a matter which I could not believe being reported by one, I should never credit the same though affirmed by a hundred. And I judge not opinions by years. It is not long since one of our Princes, in whom the gowt had spoiled a gentle disposition and blith composition, suffered himsefe so far to be persuaded or misled by the reports made unto him of the wondrous deedes of a Priest, who by way of charmes, spells and gestures cured all diseases, that he undertook a long-tedious journy to find him out; and by the virtue of his apprehension did so persuade, and for certain hours so lull his legs asleepe, that for a while he brought them to do him that service which for a long time they had forgotten. Had fortune heaped five or six like accidents one in the necke of another, they had doubtles been able to bring this miracle into nature. Whereas afterward there was so much simplicity and so little skill found in the architect of these works, that he was deemed unworthy of any punishment: As likewise should be done,with most such-like things, were they throughly knowen in their nature. Miramur ex intervallo fallentia: ’We wonder at those things that deceive us by distance.’ Our sight does in such sort, often represent us a far-off with strange images, which vanish in approaching nearer. Nunquam ad liquidum fama perducitur: ’Fame is never brought to be clear.’ It is a wonder to see how from many vain beginnings and frivolous causes, so famous impressions do ordinarily arise and ensue. Even that hindereth the information of them: For while a man endevoureth to find out causes, forcible and weighty ends, and worthy so great a name, he loses the true and essentiall. They are so little that they escape our sight. And verily a right wise, heedy and subtle inquisitor is required in such questings - impartiall and not preoccupated. All these miracles and strange events, are until this day hidden from me: I have seen no such monster or more express wonder in this world than my self. With time and custom a man does acquaint and enure himself to all strangenesse: But the more I frequent and know my self the more my deformitie astonishes me, and the less I understand my self. The chiefest priviledge to produce and advance such accidents is reserved unto fortune. Travelling yesterday through a village within two leagues of my house, I found the place yet warme of a miracle that was but newly failed and discovered, wherewith all the country thereabout had for many months been amused and abused, and diverse bordering Provinces began to listen unto it, and severall troupes of all qualities ceased not thicke and threefold to flocke thither. A yong man of that town undertook one night in his own house (never dreaming of any knavery) to counterfeit the voice of a spirit or ghost; but only for sport, to make himself merry for that present, which succeeding better than be had imagined, to make the jest extend further and himself the merrier, he made a country maiden acquainted with his devise; who because she was both seely and harmelesse, consented to be secret and to second him: In the end they got another, and were now three, all of one age and like sufficiency; and from private spirit-talking, they beganne with hideous voices to cry and roare aloud, and in and about churches biding themselves under the chief Altar, speaking but by night, forbidding any light to be set up; From speeches tending the worlds subversion, and threatning of the day of judgement (which are the subiects by whose authority and abusive reverence imposture and illusion is more easily lurked) they proceeded to certain visions and strange gestures, so foolish and ridiculous that there is scarce any thing more grosse and absurd used among Children in their childish sports. Suppose, I pray you, that fortune would have seconded this harmelesse devise or jugling tricke, Who knows how far it would have extended, and to what it would have growen? The poore seely three Divels are now in prison, and may happily e’re long pay dear for their common sottishnesse, and I wot not whether some cheverell judge or other will be avenged of them for his. It is manifestly seen in this, which now is discovered, as also in diverse other things of like quality, exceeding our knowledge; I am of opinion that we uphold our judgement as well to reject as to receive. Many abuses are engendered into the World, or, to speak more boldly, all the abuses of the World are engendered upon this, that we are taught to fear to make profession of our ignorance, and are bound to accept and allow all that we cannot refute. We speak of all things by precepts and resolution. The Stile of Rome did hear that even the same that a witnes deposed, because he had seen it with his own eyes, and that which a Judge ordained of his most assured knowledge, was conceived in this form of speech, ’It seems so unto me.’ I am drawen to hate likely things, when men go about to set them down as infallible. I love these words or phrases which mollifie and moderate the temerity of our propositions: ’It may be: Peradventure: In some sort: Some: It is aside: I think,’ and such like: And had I been to instruct children, I would so often have put this manner of answering in their mouth, enquiring and not resolving: ’What means it? I understand it not: It may well be: Is it true?’ that they should rather have kept the form of learners until three score yeeres of age, than present themselves Doctors at ten, as many do. Whosoever will be cured of ignorance must confesse the same. Iris is the daughter of Thaumantis; Admiration is the ground of all Philosophy; Inquisition the progresse; Ignorance the end. Yea but there is some kind of ignorance strong and generous, that for honor and courage is nothing beholding to knowledge. An ignorance which to conceive rightly there is required no less learning than to conceive true learning. Being yong, I saw a law-case which Corras, a Counsellor of Thoulouse, caused to be printed of a strange accident of two men, who presented themselves one for another. I remember (and I remember nothing else so well) that me thought, he proved his imposture, whom he condemned as guilty, so wondrous strange and so far exceeding both our knowledge and his own who was judge, that I found much boldnes in the sentence which had condemned him to be hanged. Let us receive some form of sentence that may say: ’The Court understands nothing of it; more freely and ingenuously than did the Areopagites, who finding themselves urged and entangled in a case they could not well clear or determine, appointed the parties to come again and appeare before them a hundred years after. The witches about my country are in hazard of their life upon the opinion of every new authour that may come to give their dreames a body. To apply such examples as the holy Word of God offreth us of such things (assured and irrefragable examples) and ioyne them to our modern events, since we neyther see the causes nor means of them, some other better wit than ours is thereunto required. Peradventure it appertaineth to that only most-mighty testimony to tell us, this here, and that there, and not this other are of them. God must be beleeved, and good reason he should be so. Yet is there not one amongst us that will be amazed at his own narration (and he ought necessarily to be astonished at it, if he be not out of his wits) whether he employ it about others matters or against himself. I am plaine and homely, and take hold on the main point, and on that which is most likely, avoiding ancient reproches. Majorem fidem homines adhibent iis quæ non intelligunt. Cupidine humani ingenii libentius obscura creduntur: ’Men give more credit to things they understand not; Things obscure are more willingly beleeved through a strange desire of mans wit.’ I see that men will be angry, and am forbid to doubt of it upon pain of execrable injuries, A new manner of perswading. Mercy for God’s sake. My beliefe is not carried away with blowes. Let them tyrannize over such as accuse their opinion of falsehood; I only accuse mine of difficulty and boldness. And equally to them I condemne the opposite affirmation, if not so imperiously. He that with bravery and by commandement will establish his discourse declareth his reason to be weake. For a verball and scholastical altercation that they have as much apparance as their contradictors. Videantur sane, non affirmentur modo: ’Indeede let them seem, so they be not avouched.’ But in effectuall consequence they draw from it, these have great ods. To kill men there is required a bright-shining and clear light. And our life is over-reall and essentiall to warrant their supernaturall and fantastic accidents. As for drugges and poisons, they are out of my element; they are homicides, and of the worst kind. In which, nevertheless, it is said that one must not alwayes rely upon the meere confession of those people: For they have sometimes been seen to accuse themselves to have made away men which were both sound and living. In these other extravagant accusations I should easily say that it sufficeth what commendations soever he has, a man be believed in such things as are humane, but of such as are beyond his conception and of a supernaturall effect, he ought then only be believed when a supernaturall approbation has authorized him. That priviledge if has pleased God to give some of our testimonies ought not to be vilified, or slightly communicated. Mine ears are full of a thousand such tales. Three saw him such a day in the east; three saw him the next day in the west, at such an hour, in such a place, and thus and thus attired; verily in such a case I could not believe my self. How much more natural and more likely do I find it, that two men should lie, then one in twelve hours pass with the winds from East to West? How much more natural that our understanding may by the volubility of our loose- capring mind be transported from his place? then that one of us should by a strange spirit, in flesh and bone, be carried upon a broome through the tunnell of a chimny? Let us, who are perpetually tossed too and fro with domesticall and our own illusions, not seek for forrane and unknowen illusions. I deem it a matter pardonable not to believe a wonder, so far foorth at least as one may divert and exlude the verification by no miraculous way. And I follow Saint Augustine’s opinion, that ’a man were better bend towards doubt than encline towards certaintie, in matters of difficult trial and dangerous beliefe.’ Some years are now past that I travelled through the country of a sovereign Prince, who in favor of me, and to abate my incredulity, did me the grace, in his own presence and in a particular place, to make me see tenne or twelve prisoners of that kind, and amongst others an olde beldam witch, a true and perfect sorceresse, both by her ugliness and deformity, and such a one as long before was most famous in that profession. I sawe both proofes, witnesses, voluntary confessions, and some other insensible markes about this miserable olde woman. I enquired and talked with her a long time, with the greatest heed and attention I could, yet am I not easily carried away by preoccupation. In the end, and in in conscience, I should rather have appointed them Helleborum than Hemlocke. Captisque res magis mentibus quam consceleratis similis visa. ’The matter seemed liker to mindes captivate than guiltie.’ Law has her own corrections for such diseases. Touching the oppositions and arguments that honest men have made unto me, both there and often elsewhere, I have found none that tie me, and that admit not alwaies a more likely solution than their conclusions. True it is that proofes and reasons grounded upon the fact and experience, I untie not, for indeede they have no end, but often cut them, as Alexander did his knot. When al is done it is an overvaluing of ones conjectures by them to cause a man to be burned alive. It is reported by diverse examples (and Prestantius says of his father) that being in a slumber much more deeply then in a full sound sleepe, he dreamed and verily thought himself to be a Mare, and served certain soldiers for a sumpter- horse, and was indeede what he imagined to be. If sorcerers dreame thus materially: If dreames may sometimes be thus incorporated into effects, I cannot possibly believe that our will should therefore be bound to the laws and justice; which I say, as one who am neither a Judge nor a Counsellor unto kings, and furthest from any such worthinesse; but rather a man of the common stamp, and both by my deedes and sayings borne and vowed to the obedience of public reason. He that should register my humors to the prejudice of the simplest law, or opinion, or custom of this village, should greatly wrong himself and injure me as much. For in what I say, I gape for no other certainly but that such was then my thought. A tumultuous and wavering thought. It is by way of discourse that I speak of all, and of nothing by way of advise. Nec me pudet, ut istos, fateri nescire quod resciam: ’Nor am I ashamed, as they are to confesse I know not that which I do not know.’ I would not be so hardy to speak if of duty I ought to be believed; and so I answered a great man who blamed the sharpnesse and contention of my exhortations. When I see you bent and prepared on one side, with all the endeavor I can I will propose the contrary unto you, to resolve and enlighten your judgement, not to subdue or binde the same. God has your hearts in his hands, and he will furnish you with choise. I am not so malapert as to desire that my opinions alone should give sway to a matter of such importance. My fortune has not raised them to so powerfull and deepe conclusions. Truely, I have not only a great number of complexions, but an infinite many of opinions, from which, had I a son of my own, I would disswade him, and willingly make him to distaste them. What? If the truest are not ever the most commodious for man, he being of so strange and untamed a composition: Whether it be to the purpose, or from the purpose, it is no great matter. It is a common Proverbe in Italie, that ’He knowes not the Perfect pleasure of Venus that has not laine with a limping woman.’ Either fortune or some particular accident have long since brought this by-saying in the peoples mouth; and it is as well spoken of men as of women, For the Queene of the Amazons answered the Scithian that wooed her to loves-embracements. αριστα χολ’ος οιει, ’The crooked man does it best.’ In that feminine common-wealth of theirs, to avoyde the domination of men, they were wont in their infancy to maime them, both their arms, and legs, and other limbs, that might any way advantage their strength over them, and make only that use of them that we in our World make of our Women. I would have said that the loose or disjoynted motion of a limping or crooke-backt Woman might adde some new kind of pleasure unto that business or sweet sinne, and some un-assaid sensuall sweetness to such as make trial of it; but I have lately learnt that even ancient Philosophy has decided the matter, Who says that the legs and thighs of the crooked-backt or halting-lame, by reason of their imperfection, not receiving the nourishment due unto them, it followeth that the Genitall parts that are above them are more full, better nourished and more vigorous. Or else, that such a defect hindring other exercise, such as are therewith possessed, do less waste their strength and consume their virtue and so much the stronger and fuller they come to Venus sports. Which is also the reason why the Græcians described their Women- Weavers to be more hotte and earnestly-luxurious than other Women; Because of their sitting-trade without any violent exercise of the body. What cannot we dispute of according to that rate? I might likewise say of these, that the same stirring which their labor so sitting does give them, does rouze and sollicite them, as the jogging and shaking of their Coache does our Ladies. Doe not these examples fit that whereof I spake in the beginning? That our reasons do often anticipate the effect, and have the extension of their jurisdiction so infinite, that they judge and exercise themselves in inanity, and to a not being? Besides the flexibilitie of our invention, to frame reasons unto all manner of dreames; our imagination is likewise found easy to receive impressions from falsehood by very frivolous apparances. For, by the only authoring of the ancient and public use of this word or phrase, I have heretofore persuaded my self to have received more pleasure of a Woman in that she was not straight, and have accompted her crookednesse in the number of her graces. Torquato Tasso, in the comparison he makes between Italy and France, reporteth to have noted that we commonly have more slender and spiny legs than the Italian Gentlemen; and, imputeth the cause unto our continuall riding and sitting on horse-backe. Which is the very same, from which Suetonius draweth another cleane contrary conclusion; For, he says, that Germanicus had by the frequent use of this exercise brought his to be very big. There is nothing so supple and wandering as our understanding. It is like to Theramenez shooe, fit for all feet. It is double and diverse, and so are matters diverse and double. Give me a Dragme of Silver, said a Cinicke Philosopher unto Antigonus. It is not the present of a King answered he; Give then a talent: It is not gift for a Cinicke, quoth he. Seu plures calor ille vias, et cæca relaxat Spiramenta, novas veniat qua succus in herbas: Seu durat magis, et venas astringit hiantes, Ne tenues pluviæ. rapidive potentia solis Acrior, aut Boreæ penetrabile frigus adurat. -- Virg. Georg. i. 89. Whether the heate layes open holes unseen, Whereby the sappe may pass to hearbs fresh-greene Or rather hardens and bindes gaping vaines, Lest sharpe power of hot sunne, or thinning raines Or piercing North-cold blaste, Should scortch, consume and waste. Ogni medaglia ha il suo riverscio: ’Each outside has his inside,’ says the Italian. See, why Clitomachus was wont to say that Carneades had surmounted the labours of Hercules, because be had exacted consent from men; that is to say, opinion and temerity to judge. This fantasia of Carneades, so vigorous (as I imagine) proceeded antiently from the impudency of those who make profession to know, and from their excessive self- overweening. Aesope was set to sale, together with two other slaves; a Chapman enquired of the first what he could do; he to endeare him self, answered, mountains and wonders, and what not? For he knew and could do all things. The second answered even so for himself, and more too; But when he came to Aesope, and demaunded of him what be could do, Nothing (said he), for these two have forestaled all, and know and can do all things, and have left nothing for me. So has it happened in the schoole of philosophy. The rashnes of those who ascribed the capacity of all things to mans wit, through spight and emulation produced this opinion in others, that humane wit was not capable of any thing. Some holde the same extremity in ignorance that others hold in knowledge. To the end none may deny that man is not immoderate in all and every where, and has no other sentence or arrest than that of necessity, and impuissance to proceede farther. Return to : Book III. CHAPTER XII: OF PHISIOGNOMY CHAPTER XII: OF PHISIOGNOMY LMOST all the opinions we have are taken by authority and upon credit: There is no hurt. We cannot chuse worse then by ourselves in so weake an age. This image of Socrates his discourse, which his friends have left us, we only approve it by the reverence of publicke approbation. It is not for our own knowledge: they are not according to our use. Might such a man be borne now adayes, there are but few would now esteeme him. We discerne not graces inly or aright; We only perceive them by a false light set out and puft up with arte; Such as pass under their natural purity and simplicity do easily escape so weake and dimnme a sight as ours is. Tbey have a secret, unperceived and delicate beauty; he had neede of a clear, far- seeing and true-discerning sight that should rightly discover this secret light. Is not ingenuity (according to us) cosin germaine unto sottishnesse, and a quality of reproach? Socrates maketh his soul to moove, with a natural and common motion. Thus says a plaine Country-man, and thus a seely Woman: He never has other people in his mouth than Coach-makers, Joyners, Coblers, and Masons. They are inductions and similitudes, drawen from the most vulgar and knowen actions of men: every one understands him. Under so base a form we should never have chosen the noble worthinesse and brightnesse of his admirable conceptions; We that esteeme all those but meane and vile that learning does not raise, and who have no perceiving of riches except set out in show and pompe. Our World is framed but unto ostentation. Men are puffed up with winde, and moved or handled by bounds, as Baloones. This man proposeth no vain fantasies unto himself. His end was to store us with things and furnish us with precepts, which really more substantially and joyntly serve our life: -----servare modum, finemque tenere, Naturamque sequi. -- LUCAN. Bel. Civ. ii. 380. To keep a meane, to hold the end, And natures conduct to attend. So was he ever all one a like: And raised himself to the highest pitch of vigor, not by fits, but by complexion. Or to say better, he raised nothing, but rather brought down and reduced all difficulties or sharpnesse to their originall and natural state, and thereunto subdued vigor. For in Cato it is manifestly seen to be an out-right proceeding, far above and beyond the common; By the brave exploits of his life, and in his death, he is ever perceived to be mounted upon his great horses. Whereas this man keepes on the ground, and with a gentle and ordinary pace treateth of the most profitable discourses, and addresseth himself both unto death and to the most thorny and crabbed crosses, that may happen unto the course of humane life. It has indeede fortuned, that the worthiest man to be known, and for a patterne to be presented to the world, he is the man of whom we have most certain knowledge. He has been declared and enlightned by the most clear- seeing men that ever were; the testimonies we have of him are in faithfulnesse and sufficiency most admirable. It is a great matter that ever he was able to give such order unto the pure imaginations of a child, that without altring or wresting them, he has thence produced the fairest effects of our mind. He neither represents it rich nor high raised, but sound and pure, and ever with a blithe and undefiled health. By these vulgar springs and natural wards, by these ordinary and common fantasies, sans mooving or without urging himself, he erected not only the most regular, but the highest and most vigorous opinions, actions, and customs that ever were. He it is that brought humane wisdom fro m heaven again, where for a long time it had been lost, to restore it unto man; where her most just and laborious work is. See or hear him pleade before his judges; marke with what reasons he rouzeth his courage to the hazards of war, what arguments fortifie his patience against detraction, calumniation, tyrranny, death, and against his wives peevish head; therein is nothing borrowed from art or from learning. The simplest may there know their means and might; it is impossible to go further backe or lower. He has done humane nature a great kindness to show what and how much she can do of herself. We are every one richer than we imagine, but we are taught to borrow and instructed to shift; and rather to make use of others goods and means then of our own. There is nothing whereon man can stay or fix himself in time of his need. Of voluptuousness, of riches, of pleasure, of power, he ever embraceth more than be can graspe or hold; His greedinesse is incapable of moderation. The very same I find to be in the curiosity of learning and knowledge; he cuts out more work than he can well make an end of, and much more then be neede. Extending the profit of learning as far as his matter. Ut omnium rerum, sic literarum quoque intemperantia laboramus: (SEN. Epist. cvi. f.) ’We are sicke of a surfet, as of all things, so of learning also.’ And Tacitus has reason to commend Agricolæs mother, to have brideled in her son an over-burning and earnest desire of learning. It is a good, being neerely looked unto, that containeth as other humane goods, much peculiar vanity and natural weakenesse, and is very chargeable; The acquisition and purchase whereof is much more hazardous then of all other viands and beverage. For whatsoever else we have bought, we carry home in some vessell or other, where we have law to examine its worth, how much and at what time we are to take it. But Sciences, we cannot sodainly put them into any other vessell than our mind: we swallow them in buying them, and go from the market either already infected or amended. There are some which insteade of nourishing do but hinder and surcharge us; and other some which under colour of curing empoison us. I have taken pleasure in some place to see men who for devotions sake have made a vow of ignorance, as of chastity, poverty and penitence. It is also a kind of guelding of our inordinate appetites to muzzle this greedinesse, which provoketh us to the study of bookes, and depriveth the mind of that voluptuous delight which, by the opinion of learning does so tickle us. And it is richly to accomplish the vow of poverty to join that of the mind unto it. We neede not much learning for to live at ease. And Socrates teacheth us that we have both it, and the way to find and make use of it, within us. All our sufficiency that is beyond the natural is well nigh vain and superfluous. It is much if it charge and trouble us no more then it steads us. Paucis opus est literis, ad mentem bonam: (Sen. ibid. ) ’We have neede of little learning to have a good mind.’ They are febricitant excesses of our spirit, a turbulent and unquiet instrument. Rowze up your self, and you shall find forcible arguments against death to be in your self; most true and very proper to serve and steade you in time of necessity. ’Tis they which induce a peasant swaine, indeed whole nations, to die as constantly as any Philosopher. Should I have died less merily before I read the Tusculanes? I think not. And when I find my self in my best wits I perceive that I have somewhat enriched my tongue, my courage but little. It is even as nature framed the same at first. And against any conflict it shields itself, but with a natural and common march. Bookes have not so much served me for instruction as exercitation. What if learning, assaying to arm us with new wards and fences against natural inconveniences, has more imprinted their greatness and weight in our fantasies then her reasons, quiddities, and subtilities, therewith to cover us? They are subtilities indeed, by which she often awaketh us very vainely. Observe how many sleight and idle arguments the wisest and closest authors frame and scatter about one good sound, which if you but consider neerely are but vain and incorporall. They are but verball wiles which beguile us. But forasmuch as it may be profitable I will not otherwise blanch them. Many of that condition are scattered here and there, in diverse places of this volume, either borrowed or imitated. Yet should a man somewhat heed be call not that force which is but quaintness or terme that which is but quipping sharpe, solid; or name that good which is but fair: Quæ magis gustata quam potata delectant: (CIC. Tusc. Qu. v.) ’Which more delight us being but tasted, then swild and swallowed down.’ All that which pleaseth feedeth not : Ubi non ingenii sed animi negocium agitur: ’Where it is no matter of wit, but of courage.’ To see the strugling endevors which Seneca gives himself to prepare himself against death; to see him sweate with panting; to see him bathe so long upon this pearch, thereby to strengthen and assure himself; I should have made question of his reputation had be not most undantedly maintained the same in his death. His so violent and frequent agitation sheweth that himself was fervent, and impetuous. Magnus animus remissius loquitur, et securius: Non est alius ingenio alius animo color: (SEN. Epist. cxv. Eleg. i. ) ’A great courage speaks softly but securely. Wit has not one colour and courage another.’ He must be convicted at his own charges, and sheweth in some sort that he was pressed by his adversary. Plutarkes manner by how much more disdainful and far- extending it is (in my opinion) so much more manlike and perswasive is it; I should easily believe that his soul had her motions more assured and more regu lar. The one more sharpe, pricketh and sodainely starts us, toucheth the spirit more. The other more solid, does constantly enforme, establish and comfort us; toucheth more the understanding. That ravisheth our judgement; this does gain it. I have likewise seen other compositions and more reverenced, which in portraying the combate they endure against the provocations of the flesh, represent them so violent, so powerfull and invincible, that ourselves, who are cast in the common mould of other men, have as much to admire the unknown strangenesse and unfelt vigor of their temptation, as their constant resistance. To what do we so arm and steele ourselves with these labouring-efforts of learning? Let us diligently survay the surface of the earth, and there consider so many seely-poore people as we see toyling, sweltring and drooping about their businesses which never heard of Aristotle nor of Plato, nor ever knew what exemples or precepts are. From those does nature dayly draw and afoord us effects of constancy and patternes of patience, more pure and forcible then are those we so curiously study-for in schooles. How many do I ordinarily see that misacknowledge poverty; how many that wish for death, or that pass it without any alarm or affliction? A fellow that dungeth my garden has happily this morning buried his father or his child. The very names whereby they call diseases do somewhat mylden and diminish the sharpnes of them. With them a Phthysique or consumption of the lungs is but an ordinary cough: A dysentery or bloody flux but a distemper of the stomacke; A pleurisie but a cold or murre; and as they gently name them so they easily endure them. Grievous are they indeed when they hinder their ordinary labor or breake their usual rest: They will not take their beds but when they shall dy. Simplex illa et aperta virtus in obscuram et solertem scienti am versa est: ’That plaine and clear virtue is turned into obscure and cunning knowledge.’ I was writing this about a time that a boistrous storme of our tumultuous broiles and bloody troubles did for many months space, with all its might and horrour, hang full over my head. On the one side I had the enemies at my gates; on the other the Picoreurs or freebooters, far worse foes. Non armis sed vitiis certatur: ’We contend not with armour, but with vices.’ And at one time felt and endured all manner of harme-bringing military injuries: Hostis adest dextra lævaque h parte timendus, Vicinoque malo terret utrumque latus. -- OVID. Pont. Eleg. iv. 55. A fearefull foe on left hand and on right Does with his neighbour harmes both sides afright. Oh monstrous Warre: Others work without, this inwardly and against herself, And with her own venome gnaweth and consumes herself. It is of so ruinous and maligne a Nature, that, together with all things els, she ruineth herself; and with spitefull rage does rent, deface and massacre itself. We do more often see it, by and through herself, to were, to desolate and dissolve herself, then by or through want of any necessary thing, or by enemies force. All manner of discipline does shunne and flie it. She commeth to cure sedition, and herself is throughly therewith infected; She goeth about to chastize dis- obedience, and sheweth the example of it; and being employed for the defense of Lawes entreth into actuall rebellion against her own ordinances. Aye me, where are we? Our Phisicke bringeth infection. Nostre mal s’empoisonne Du secours qu’on luy donne. Our evil is empoysond more By plaister they would lay to the sore. ----- exuperat magis ægrescitque medendo. -- VIRG. Æn. xii. It rises higher, quicker, And growes by curing sicker. Omnia fanda nefanda malo permista furore. Justificam nobis’mentem avertere Deorum. -- CATUL. Argon. v. 405. Lawfull unlawfull deeds with fury blended, Have turn’d from us the Gods just mind offended. In these popular diseases one may in the beginning distinguish the sound from the sicke; but if they chance to continue any time, as ours has done and does still, all the body, indeed head and heels, feel themselves the worse; no part is exempted from corruption; for there is no aire a man draws so greedily, or sucks so gluttonously, and that more spreds itself or penetrates more deepely, then does licentiousnesse. Our Armies have no other bond to tie them, or other eyment to fasten them, then what commeth from strangers. It is now a hard matter to frame a body of a more compleate, constant, well-ordered and coherent Army of Frenchmen. Oh, what shame is it? We have no other discipline then what borrowed or auxiliar Soldiers show us. As for us, we are led-on by our own discretion and not by the commanders; each man followeth his own humor, and has more to do within then without. It is the commandement should follow, court and yield unto, he only ought to obey; all the rest are free and loose. I am pleased to see what remisnesse and pusilanimity is in ambition, and by what steps of abjection and servitude it must arrive unto its end. But I am displeased to see some debonaire and well- meaning minds, indeed such as are capable of justice, dayly corrupted about the managing and commanding of this many-headed confusion. Long sufferance begets custom; custom, consent and imitation. We had too-too many infected and ill-borne minds without corrupting the good, the sound, and the generous; so that, if we continue any time, it will prove a difficult matter to find out a man unto whose skill and sufficiency the health or recovery of this state may be committed in trust, if fortune shall happily be pleased to restore it us again. Hunc saltem everso juvenem succurrere seclo, Ne prohibete. Forbid not yet this youth at least, To aide this age more then opprest. What is become of that ancient precept, That Soldiers ought more to fear their General than their enemy? And of that wonderful examplelesse example, That the Roman army, having upon occasion enclosed within her trenches, and round-beset an apple-orchard, so obedient was she to her Captains, that the next morning it rose and marched away without entring the same or touching one apple, although they were full-ripe and very delicious; So that when the owner came he found the full number of his apples! I should be glad that our Youths, in steade of the time they employ about less profitable peregrinations, and less honorable apprentiships, would bestow one moity in seeing and observing the wars that happen on the sea under some good Captain or excellent commander of Malta; the other moity in learning and surveying the discipline of the Turkish armies. For it has many differences and advantages over ours. This ensueth that here our Soldiers become more licentious in expeditions, that they prove more circumspect and fearfully wary. For small offences and petty larcenies, which in times of peace are in the common people punished with whipping and bastonadoes, in times of war are capital crimes. For an egge taken by a Turke without paying, he is by their law to have the full number of fifty stripes with a cudgell. For every other thing, how sleight soever, not necessary for mans feeding, even for very trifles, they are either thrust through with a sharpe stake, which they call Empaling, or presently beheaded. I have been amazed reading the story of Selim, the cruellest Conqueror that ever was, to see, at what time he subdued the country of Egypt, the beauteous gardens round about Damasco, all open and in a conquered country, his main army lying encamped about, those gardens were left untouched and unspoyled by the hands of his Soldiers, only because they were commanded to spoyle nothing, and had not the watch-word of pillage. But is there any malady in a Common-weale that deserveth to be combated by so mortal drug? No, said Favonius, not so much as the usurpation of the tyranicall possession of a Commonwealth. Plato likewise is not willing one should offer violence to the quiet repose of his Countrey, no not to reforme or cure the same; and alloweth not that reformation which disturbeth or hazardeth the whole estate; and which is purchased with the blood and ruine of the Citizens. Establishing the office of an honest man, in these causes, to leave all there: But only to pray God to lend his extraordinary assisting hand unto it; And seems to be offended with Dyon his great friend, to have therein proceeded somewhat otherwise. I was a Platonist on that side before ever I knew there had been a Plato in the world. And if such a man ought absolutely be banished our commerce and refused our society (he who for the sincerity of his conscience deserved by meane of divine favor, athwart the public darknesse, and through the general ignorance of the world wherein he lived, so far to enter and so deeply to penetrate into Christian light), I do not think that it befitteth us to be instructed by a Pagan. Oh what impiety is it to expect from God no succour simply his, and without our cooperation. I often doubt whether amongst so many men that meddle with such a matter, any has been found of so weake an understanding, that has earnestly been persuaded, he proceeded toward reformation by the utmost of deformations; that he drew toward his salvation by the most express causes, that we have of undoubted damnation; that overthrowing policy, disgracing magistrates, abusing laws, under whose tuition God has placed him; filling brotherly minds and loving hearts with malice, hatred and murther; calling the Divels and furies to his helpe; he may bring assistance to the most sacred mildness and justice of divine Law. Ambition, avarice, cruelty and revenge have not sufficient proppes and natural impetuousity; let us allure and serve them up by the glorious title of justice and devotion. There can no worse estate of things be imagined than where wickednesse commeth to be lawfull, And with the Magistrates leave to take the cloake of virtue: Nihil in speciem fallicius, quam prava religio, ubi deorum numen prætenditur sceleribus: ’There is nothing more deceiptfull to show than corrupt religion, when the power of Heaven is made a pretence and cloake for wickednesse.’ The extreme kind of injustice (according to Plato) is, that that which is unjust should be held for just. The common people suffered therein greatly then, not only present losses, -----undique totis. Usque adeo turbatur agris --- ----- Such revell and tumultuous rout In all the country round about. But also succeeding dammages. The living were faine to suffer, so did such as then were scarce borne. They were robbed and pilled, and by consequence so was I, even of hope; spoiling and depriving them of all they had to provide their living for many years to come. Quæ nequeunt secum ferre aut abduce re, perdunt, Et cremat insontes turba scelesta casas Muris nulla fides, squalent popularibus agri. They wretch-less spoyle and spill what draw or drive they may not, Guilty rogues to set fire on guilt-less houses stay not. In wals no trust, the field By spoyle growes waste and wild. Besides these mischiefes I endured some others. I incurred the inconveniences that moderation bringeth in such diseases. I was shaven on all hands. To the Ghibelin I was a Guelf, to Guelf a Ghibelin. Some one of my Poets expresseth as much, but I wot not where it is. The situation of my house, and the acquaintance of such as dwelt round about me, presented me with one visage; my life and actions with another. No formall accusations were made of it, for there was nothing to take hold of. I never opposed my self against the laws, and who had called me in question should have lost by the bargaine. They were mute suspicions that ranne under hand, which never want apparance in so confused a burly-burly, no more than lacke of envious or foolish wits. I commonly affoord ayde unto injurious presumption that fortune scattereth against me; by a fashion I never had, to avoid justifying, excusing, or interpreting my self; deeming it to be a putting of my conscience to compromise, to pleade for her: Perspicuitas enim, argumentatione elevatur: ’For the cleering of a cause is lessened by the arguing.’ And as if every man saw into me as clear as I do my self, in lieu of withdrawing, I advance my self to the accusation and rather endeare it by an erroneous and scoffing confession, except I flatly hold my peace as of a thing unworthy any answer. But such as take it for an over-proud confidence, do not much less disesteeme and hate me for it, then such as take it for weaknesse of an indefensible cause; Namely, the great, with whom want of submission, is the extreme fault. Rude to all justice, that is known or felt; not demiss, humble, or suppliant, I have often stumbled against that piller. So it is, that by the harmes which befell me, an ambitious man would have hanged himself; and so would a covetous churle. I have no care at all to acquire or get. Sit mihi quod nunc est, etiam minus, ut mihi vivam Quod superest ævi, si quid superesse volent dii. -- HOR.i. Epist. xviii. 107. Let me have that I have, or less, so I may live Unto my self the rest , if any rest God give. But losses that come unto me by others injury, be it larceny or violence, pinch me in a manner as one sicke and tortured with avarice. An offence causeth undoubtedly more grief and sharpnesse than a loss. A thousand severall kindes of mischiefes fell upon me one in the necke of another: I should more stoutly have endured them had they come all at once. I bethought my self amongst my friends, to whom I might commit a needy, a defective and unfortunate olde age; but after I had surveyed them all, and cast mine eyes every where, I found my self bare and far to seek. For one to sowse himself down headlong, and from so great a height, he should heedily fore-cast that it may be in the arms of a solid, stedfast, vigorous and fortunate affection. They are rare, if there be any. In the end I perceived the best and safest way was to trust both my self and my necessity unto my self. And if it should happen to be but meanly and faintly in Fortunes grace, I might more effectually recommend my self unto my own favor, more closely fasten and more neerely looke unto my self. In all things men rely upon strange props, to spare their own; only certain and only powerfull, know they but how to arm themselves with them. Every man runneth out and unto what is to come, because no man is yet come into himself. And I resolved that they were profitable inconveniences, forasmuch as when reason will not serve, we must first warne towards Scholars with the rod; as with fire and violence of wedges, we bring a crooked peece of wood to be straight. It is long since I call to keep my self unto my self, and live sequestered from alien and strange things, notwithstanding a daily start out and cast mine eyes aside. Inclination, a great man’s favorable word, a kind looke does tempt me. God he knows whether there be penury of them now-adayes, and what sense they bear. I likewise, without frowning, listen to the subornings, framed to draw me to some town of merchandise or city of trafficke; and so coldly defend my self that it seems I should rather endure to be overcome than not. Now to a spirit so indocile blowes are required; and this vessell, that of itself is so ready to warpe, to unhoope, to escape and fall in peeces, must be closed, hooped and strongly knockt with an adze. Secondly, that this accident served me as an exercitation to prepare my self for worse, if worse might happen, if I, who both by the benefit of fortune and condition of my maners, hoped to be of the last, should by this tempest be one of the first surprised; Instructing my self betimes to force my life, and frame it for a new state. True- perfect liberty is for one to be able to do and work all things upon himself. Potentissimus est qui se habet in potestate. (SEN. Epist. ix.) ’He is of most power that keepes himself in his own power.’ In ordinary and peacefull times a man prepares himself for common and moderate accidents; but in this confusion wherein we have been these thirty yeeres, every French man, be it in general or in particular, does hourely see himself upon the point of his fortunes overthrow and down-fall. By so much more ought each one have his courage stored and his mind fraughted, with more strong and vigorous provisions. Let us thanke Fortune, that has not made us live in an effeminate, idle, and languishing age; Some, whom other means could never bring unto it, shall make themselves famous by their misfortune. As I read not much in Histories, these confusions of other states, without regret, that I could not better them present; So does my curiosity make me somewhat please my self with mine eyes to see this notable spectacle of our public death; her symptomes and formes. And since I could not hinder the same, I am content to be appointed as an assistant unto it, and therby instruct my self. Yet seek we evidently to know in shadowes and understand by fabulous representations upon Theaters, to show of the tragicke revolutions of humane fortune. It is not without compassion of that we hear, but we please ourselves to rowze up our displeasure by the rarenesse of these pitifull events. Nothing tickles that pincheth not; and good Historians avoid calme narrations, as a dead water or mort-mere, to retreeve seditions and find out wars, whereto they know we cal them. I doubt whether I may lawfully avow at how base a rate of my lifes rest and tranquility I have past it more than half, in the ruine of my Country. In accidents that touch me not in my freehold I purchase patience very cheape; and to complain to my self I respect not so much what is taken from me, as what is left me both within and without. There is comfort in sometimes eschewing one and sometimes another of the evills, that one in the necke of another surprise us, and elsewhere strike us round about. As matters of public interrests, according as my affection is more universally scattered, she is thereby more enfeebled. Since it is halfe true: Tantum ex publicis malis sentimus, quantum ad privatas res pertinet. ’We feel so much of common harmes as appertaine to our private estate.’ And that the health whence we fell was such that herself solaceth the regret we should have for her. It was health, mary but in comparison of the contagion, which has followed the same. We are not falen very high. The corruption and the brigandage which now is in office and dignity seems to me the least tolerable. We are less injuriously robbed in the midst of a wood then a place of security. It was an universall coherency of members spoiled avie one another, and most of them, with old-rankled ulcers, which neither admitted nor demaunded recovery. Truely this shaking-fit did therefore more animate then deterre me, only by the aide of my conscience, which not only quietly but fiercely carried itself; and I found no cause to complain of my self. Likewise, as God never sends men either evils or goods absolutely pure, my health held out well for that time, indeed against her ordinary; and as without it I can do nothing, so with it, there are few things I cannot do. She gave me means to summon and rouze up all my provisions, and to bear my hand before my hurt, which happily would have gone further; And proved in my patience that yet I had some hold against fortune, and that to thrust me out of my saddle there was required a stronger counterbuffe. This I speak not to provoke her to give me a more vigorous charge. I am her servant, and yield my self unto her: For Gods sake let her be pleased. Demaund you whether I feel her assaults? I do indeede. As those whom sorrow possesseth and overwhelmeth do notwithstanding at one time or other suffer themselves by intermissions to be touched by some pleasure, and now and then smile. I have sufficient power over my self to make mine ordinary state quiet and free from all tedious and irkesome imaginations; but yet I sometimes suffer my self by starts to be surprised with the pinchings of these unpleasant conceits, which while I arm my self to expell or wrestle against them assaile and beate me. See here another huddle or tide of mischief, that on the necke of the former came rushing upon me. Both within and round about my house, I was overtaken, in respect of all other, with a most contagious pestilence. For, as soundest bodies are subject to grievous diseases, because they only can force them; so the aire about me being very healthy, wher in no mans memory infection (although very near) could ever take footing, coming now to be poisoned, brought forth strange effects. Mista senum et juvenum densantur funera nullum Sæva caput Proserpina fugit. -- HOR. Car. i. Od. xxviii. 19. Of old and young thicke funerals are shared By cruel Proserpine no head is spared. I was faine to endure this strange condition, that the sight of my house was irkesome unto me. Whatever was therein lay all at randon, no man looked thereunto, and was free for any that had a mind unto it. I who have so long been a good housekeeper, and used to hospitality was much troubled and put to my shifts, how to find out some retreate for my family, a dismaied and scattered family, making both herself and her friends afraide, and breeding horrour where it sought to retire for shelter, being now to shift and change her dwelling; so soone as any of the company beganne to feel his finger ake, all the rest were dismaied. Every sicknesse is then taken for the plague: none has leisure to consider them. And the mischief is, that according to rules of arte, what danger soever approcheth, a man must continue forty dayes in anxiety or fear of that evil; in which time your own imagination does perplex you as she list and infect your health. All which had much less touched me, had I not been forced to bear other mens burthens and partake all their grievances, and for six months space in miserable manner to be a woefull guide to so great- confused a Caravane. For I ever carry my preservatives above me which are resolution and sufferance. Apprehension does not greatly press me, which is particularly feared in this sicknesse. And if, being alone I should have taken it, it had been a stronger and further flight. It is a death, in my opinion, not of the worst: it is commonly short and speeding, voide of lingring pain, comforted by the public condition; without ceremony, without mourning, and without thronging. But for the people about us, the hundreth part of soules cannot be saved. ------ videas desertaque regna Pastorum, et longe saltus lati que vacantes. Kingdomes of Shepherds desolate, forlorn, Parkes far and near lie waste, a state all torn. In that place my best revenue is manuall: what a hundred men laboured for me lay fallow for a long time. What examples of resolution saw we not then in all this peoples simplicity? Each one generally renounced all care of life. The grapes (which are the countries chief commodities hung still and rotted upon the vines untouch’t; all indifferently preparing themselves, and expecting death either that night or the next morrow; with countenance and voice so little daunted, that they seemed to have compromitted to this necessitie, and that it was an universall and inevitable condemnation. It is ever such. But what slender hold has the resolution of dying? The difference and distance of some few hours; the only consideration of the company yields the apprehension diverse unto us. Behold these because they die in one same month, children, yong, old; they are no more astonied, they are no longer wept-for. I saw some that feared to stay behinde, as if they had been in some horrible solitude. And commonly I knew no other care amongst them but for graves; it much grieved them to see the dead carcasses scattered over the fields, at the mercy of wild beasts, which presently began to flocke thither. Oh how humane fantasies differ and are easily disjoined! The Neorites, a nation whilome subdued by Alexander the Great, cast out their dead mens bodies into the thickest of their woods, there to be devoured, the grave only esteemed happy among them. Some in good health digged already their graves, othersome yet living did go into them; And a day-labourer of mine, as he was dying, with his own hands and feet pulled earth upon him, and so covered himself. Was not this a lying down in the shade to sleepe at ease? An enterprise in some sort as highly noble as that of some Roman Soldiers, who, after the battle of Canna, were found with their heads in certain holes or pits, which themselves had made, and filled up with their hands, wherein they were smothered. To conclude, a whole nation was presently by use brought to a march, that in undantednesse yields not to any consulted and fore-meditated resolution. The greatest number of learnings instructions, to encourage us have more show then force, and more ornament then fruit. We have forsaken nature, and yet we will teach her her lesson; Shee, that lead us so happily, and directed us so safely. And in the means while, the traces of her instructions and that little which by the benefit of ignorance remaineth of her image, imprinted in the life of this rusticall troupe of unpolished men; learning is compelled to go daily a borrowing, thereby to make her disciples a patterne of constancy, of innocency, and of tranquilitie. It is a goodly matter to see how these men full of so great knowledge, must imitate this foolish simplicitie, indeed in the first and chief actions of virtue. And that our wisdom should learne of beasts the most profitable documents belonging to the chiefest and most necessary parts of our life. How we should live and die, husband our goods, love and bring up our children, and entertain justice. A singular testimony of mans infirmitie, and that this reason we so manage at our pleasure, ever finding some diversitie and noveltie, leaveth unto us no manner of apparant tracke of nature. Wherewith men have done as perfumers do with oyle, they have adulterated her with so many argumentations and sofisticated her with so diverse far-fetcht discourses, that she is become variable and peculiar to every man, and has lost her proper, constant, and universall visage; whereof we must seek for a testimony of beasts, not subject to favor or corruption, nor to diversity of opinions. For it is most true that themselves march not alwaies exactly in natures path, but if they chance to stray, it is so little that you may ever the perceive the tracke; Even as horses led by hand do sometimes bound and start out of the way, but no further then their halters length, and nevertheless follow ever his steps that leadeth them; And as a Hawke takes his flight but under the limits of her cranes or twyne. Exilia, tormenta, bella, morbos, naufragia, meditare, ut nullo sis malo tyro: ’Banishments, torments, wars, sicknesses, shipwracks, all these fore-cast and premeditate, that you mayest seem no novice, no freshwater souldier to any misadventure.’ What availeth this curiosity unto us, to preoccupate all humane natures inconveniences, and with so much labor and toyling against them to prepare ourselves, which perhaps shall nothing concern us? (Parem passis tristitiam facit, pati posse: ’It makes men as sad that they may suffer some mischiefs as if they had suffred it.’ Not only the blow, but the winde and cracke strikes us.) Or as the most febricitant, for surely it is a kind of fever, now to cause your self to be whipped because fortune may one day chance to make you endure it; and at Mid-Sommer to put-on your furr’d Gowne, because you shall neede it at Christmas? Cast yourselves into the experience of all the mischiefes that may befall you, namely of the extreamest; there try your self (say they), there assure your self. Contrariwise, the easiest and most natural were even to discharge his thought of them. They will not come soone enough, their true being does not last us long enough, our spirit must extend and lengthen them, and before-hand incorporate them into himself, and therewith entertaine himself, as if they lay not sufficiently heavy on our senses. They will weigh heavy enough when they shall be there (says one of the maisters, not of a tender, but of the hardest Sect); meane while favor your self; Beleeve what you lovest best. What availes it you to collect and prevent your ill fortune, and for fear of the future lose the present; and now to be miserable because in time you mayest be so? They are his own words. Learning does us willingly one good office, exactly to instruct us in the demensions of evils. Curis acuens mortalia corda. Mens cogitations whetting, With sharpe cares inly fretting. It were pity any part of their greatness should escape our feeling and understanding. It is certain that preparation unto death has caused more torment unto most than the very sufferance. It was whilome truely said of and by a most judicious Authour: Minus afficit sensus fatigatio, quam cogitatio: ’Wearinesse less troubleth our senses then pensivenesse does.’ The apprehension of present death does sometimes of itself animate us with a ready resolution no longer to avoide a thing altogether inevitable. Many Gladiators have in former ages been seen, having at first fought very cowardly, most courageously to embrace death; offering their throate to the enemies sword, indeed bidde them make haste. The sight distant from future death has neede of a slowe constancy, and by consequence hard to be found. If you know not how to die, take no care for it; Nature her self will fully and sufficiently teach you in the nicke, she will exactly discharge that work for you; trouble not your self with it. Incertam frustra, mortales, funeris horam Quæritis, et qua sit mors aditura via: Poena minor certam subito prefer ruinam; Quod timeas, gravius sutiniuisse diu. -- CATUL. Eleg. i. 29, 16. Of death the uncertaine hour you men in vain Enquire, and what way death shall you destraine: A certain sodaine ruine is less pain, More grievous long what you fear to sustain. We trouble death with the care of life, and life with the care of death. The one annoyeth, the other affrights us. It is not against death we prepare ourselves, it is a thing too momentary. A quarter of an hour of passion without consequence and without annoyance deserves not particular precepts. To say we prepare ourselves against the preparations of death. Philosophy teacheth us ever to have death before our eyes, to fore-see and consider it before it come; Then gives us rules and precautions so to provide, that such foresight and thought hurt us not. So do Phisitions, who cast up into diseases that they may employ their drugges and skill about them. If we have not known how to live, it is injustice to teach us how to die, and deforme the end from all the rest. Have we known how to live constantly and quietly, we shall know how to die resolutely and reposedly. They may bragge as much as they please. Tota Philosophorum vita commentatio mortis est: ’The whole life of a Philosopher is the meditation of his death.’ But me thinkes it is indeede the end, yet not the scope of life. It is her last, it is her extremity, not her object. Hir self must be unto herself, her aime, her drift, and her designe. Hir direct studie is to order, to direct, and to suffer herself. In the number of many other offices which the general and principal Chapter to know how to live containeth, is this speciall Article, ’To know how to die.’ And of the easiest, did not our own fear weigh it down. To judge them by their profit and by the naked truth, the lessons of simplicity yield not much to those which Doctrine preacheth to the contrary unto us. Men are different in feeling and diverse in force; they must be directed to their good according to themselves, and by diverse waies: Quo me cumque rapit tempestas, deferor hospes. -- HOR. i. Epist. i. 15. Where I am whirld by winde and wether, I guest-like straight am carried thether. I never saw meane paisant of my neighbors, enter into cogitation or care with what assurance or countenance he should pass this last hour. Nature teacheth him never to muze on death but when be dieth. And then has he a better grace in it than Aristotle, whom death perpelexed doubly both by herself and by so long a premeditiation. Therefore was it Cæsars opinion that ’The least premeditated death was the happiest and easiest.’ Plus dolet quam necesse est, qui ante dolet quam necesse est: ’He grieves more than be need, That grieves before he neede.’ The sharpenesse of this imagination proceeds from our curiosity. Thus we ever hinder ourselves, desiring to fore-run and sway natural prescriptions. It is but for Doctors being in health to fare the worse by it, and to frowne and startle at the Image of death. The vulgar sort have neither neede of remedy nor comfort, but when the shock or stroke commeth. And justly considers no more of it than he feeleth. And is it not as we say, that the vulgare stupidity and want of apprehension affoorde them this patience in private evils, and this deepe carelesnes of sinister future accidents? That their mind being more grosse, dull and blockish, is less penetrable and agitable? In Gods name, if it be so, let us henceforth keep a schoole of brutality. It is the utmost fruit that Sciences promise unto us, to which she so gently bringeth her disciples. We shall not want good teachers, interp reters of natural simplicity. Socrates shall be one; For, as neare as I remember, he speaks in this sense [to]the Judges that determine of his life: ’I fear me, my Maisters’ (says he), ’that if I entreate you not to make me die, I shall confirme the evidence of my accusers, which is, That I professe to have more understanding than others, as having some knowledge more secret and hid of things both above and beneath us. I know I have neither frequented nor known death, nor have I seen any body that has either felt or tried her qualities to instruct me in them. Those who fear her presuppose to know; As for me, I neither know who or what she is, nor what they do in the other world. Death may perhaps be a thing indifferent, happily a thing desirable. Yet it is to be beleeved that if it be a transmigration from one place to another, there is some amendment in going to live with so many worthy famous persons that are deceased, and be exempted from having any more to do with wicked and corrupted Judges. If it be a consummation of ones being, it is also an amendment and entrance into a long and quiet night. We find nothing so sweet in life as a quiet rest and gentle sleepe, and without dreames. The things I know to be wicked, as to wrong or offend ones neighbour, and to disobey his superiour, be he God or man, I carefully shunne them; Such as I know not whether they be good or bad, I cannot fear them. If I go to my death, and leave you alive, The Gods only see, whether you or I shall prosper best; and therefore, for my regarde, you shall dispose of it as it shall best please you. But acccording to my fashion, which is to counsell good and profitable things, this I say, that for your own conscience you shall do best to free and discharge me; except you see further into my own cause than my self. And judging according to my former actions, both public and private, according to my intentions; and to the profit, that so many of our Citizens, both young and olde, draw dayly from my conversation, and the fruit, all you reape by me, you cannot more justly or duely discharge yourselves toward my desertes than by appointing (my poverty considered) that I may live,and at the common charge be kept, in the Prytaneo, which for much less reasons I have often seen you freely graunt to others. Impute it not to obstinacy or disdaine in me, nor take it in ill part, that i, according to custom, precede not by way of i ntreatie, and moove you to commiseration. I have both friends and kinsfolk, being not (as Homer says) begotten of a blocke or stone, no more than other men, capable to present themselves humbly suing with tears and mourning; and I have three desolate, wailing children to move you to pittie. But I should make your City ashamed of the age I am in, and in that reputation of wisdom, as now I stand in prevention to yield unto so base an abject countenances. What would the world say of other Athenians? I have ever admonished such as have heard me speak, never to purchase or redeeme their life by any dishonest or unlawfull act. And in my countries wars, both at Amphipolis, at Potidea, at Delia, and others, in which I have been, I have shewen by effects how far I was from warranting my safety by my shame. Moreover, I should interest your duty, and prejudice your calling, and persuade you to foul unlawfull things; for, not my prayers, but the pure and solid reasons of justice should persuade you. You have sworne to the Gods so to maintaine yourselves. Not to believe there were any, might seem I would suspect, recriminate, or retorte the fault upon you. And my self should witness against my self, not to believe in them as I ought, distrusting their conduct, and not meerely remitting my affairs into their hands. I wholly trust and rely on them, and certainely holde that in this they will dispose as it shall be meetest for you and fittest for me. Honest men, that neither live nor are dead, have no cause at all to fear the Gods.’ Is not this a childish pleading of an unimaginable courage, and in what necessity employed? Verily it was reason he should prefer it before that which the great Orator Lysias had set down in writing for him, excellently fashioned in a judiciary Stile, but unworthy of so noble a criminall. Should a man have heard an humbly-suing voice out of Socrates his mouth? Would that proud virtue have failed in the best of her show? And would his rich and powerfull nature have committed her defense unto arte, and in her highest Essay renounced unto truth and sinceritie the ornaments of his speech, to adorn and decke himself with the embellishment of the figures and fictions of a fore-learn’t Oration? He did most wisely, and according to himself, not to corrupt the tenure of an incorruptible life, and so sacred an image of human form, to prolong his decrepitude for one yeere, and wrong the immortall memory of so glorious an end. He ought his life, not to himself, but to the worlds example. Had it not been a public loss if he had finished the same in some idle, base and obscure manner? Truely so carelesse and effeminate a consideration of his death deserved posterity should so much more consider the same for him; which it did. And nothing is so just in justice as that which fortune ordained for his commendation. For the Athenians did afterward so detest and abhorre those which had furthered and caused his death, that of all they were loathed and shunned as cursed and excommunicated men; what soever they had but touched was held to be polluted; No man would so much as wash with them in bathes or hot houses; no man affoord them a salutation, much less accost or have to do with them; so that, being in the end no longer able to endure this public hatred and general contempt, they all hanged themselves. If any man thinkes that amongst so many examples I might have chosen for the service of my purpose in Socrates his sayings, I have chosen or handled this but ill; and deemeth this discourse to be raised above common opinions, I have done it wittingly: for I judge otherwise, and hold it to be a discourse in rank and sincerity much shorter and lower then vulgar opinions. It representeth in an unartificiall boldness and infantine security, the pure impression and first ignorance of nature. Because it is credible that we naturally fear pain, but not death, by reason of her. It is a part of our being no less essentiall than life. To what end would Nature have else engendred the hate and horror of it, seeing it holdes therein, and with it a rank of most great profit, to foster the succession and nourish the vicissitude of her works? And that in this universall Common-weale it steadeth and serveth more for birth and augmentation, then for loss, decay, or ruine. Sic rerum summa novatur. -- LUCR. ii. 73. So does the summe of all, By courses rise and fall. Mille animas una necata dedit. We thousand soules shall pay For one soul made away. The decay of one life is the passage to a thousand other lives. Nature has imprinted in beasts the care of themselves and of their preservation. They proceede even to the fear of their empairing, to shocke or hurt themselves, and that we should not shackle or beate them, accidents subject to th eir sense and experience. But that we should kill them, they cannot fear it, nor have they the faculty to imagine or conclude their death. Yet it is reported that they are not seen only to embrace and endure the same joyfully (most Horses neigh in dying, and Swannes sing when it seiseth them), But, moreover, they seek it when they neede it, as by diverse examples may be prooved in the Elephants. Besides, the manner of arguing which Socrates useth here, is it not equally admirable both in simpli citie and in vehemence? Verily, It is much easier to speak as Aristotle and live as Cæsar, than speak and live as Socrates. Therein consists the extreme degree of difficulty and perfection; arte cannot attaine unto it. Our faculties are not now so addressed; We neither assay nor know them; we invest ourselves with others, and suffer our own to be idle. As by some might be said of me, that here I have but gathered a nosegay of strange floures, and have put nothing of mine unto it but the thred to binde them. Certes, I have given unto public opinion that these borrowed ornaments accompany me, but I meane not they should cover or hide me; it is contrary to mine intention, who would make show of nothing that is not my own, indeed my own by nature. And had I believed my self, at all adventure I had spoken alone. I dayly charge my self the more beyond my proposition and first form, upon the fantasie of time, and through idlenesse. If it mis-seem me, as I think it does, it is no great matter; it may be profitable for some other. Some alleadge Plato, some mention Homer, that never saw them; or, as they say in English, many a man speaks of Robin Hood that never shot in his bow; And I have taken diverse passages from others then in their spring. Without pain or sufficiency, having a thousand volumes of bookes about me where now I write, if I please I may presently borrow from a number of such botcherly-patchcotes (men that I plod not much upon) wherewith to enamell this treaty of Physiognomie. I need but the liminary epistle of a Germane to store me with allegations, and we go questing that way for a fading greedy glory to cousin and delude the foolish world. These rapsodies of common-places, wherewith so many stuffe their study, serve not greatly but for vulgar subjects, and serve but to show and not to direct us: A ridiculous-foolish fruite of learning that Socrates does so pleasantly enveigh and exagirate against Euthydemus. I have seen bookes made of things neither studied nor ever understood, the author coming to diverse of his learned and wise friends in the search of this and that matter, that so he might compile them into a book, contenting himself for his own part to have cast the plot and projected the design of it, and by his industry to have bound up the fagot of unknown provisions; at least is the inke and paper his own. This may be said to be a buying or borrowing and not a making or compiling of a book. It is to teach men, not that one can make a book, but to put them out of doubt that he cannot make it. A president of the law in a place where I was vanted himself to have hudled up together two hundred and od strange places in a presidential law-case of his: In publishing of which he defaced the glory which others gave him for it: A weake, childish and absurd boasting, in my opinion, for such a subject and for such a man. I do cleane contrary, and amongst so many borrowings am indeed glad to filch some one, disguising and altering the same to some new service. On hazard, to let men say that it is for lacke of understanding its natural use, I give it some particular addressing of my own hand, to the end it may be so much less meerely strange; Whereas these put their larcenies to pubIike view and garish show; so have they more credit in the laws then I. We other naturalists suppose th at there is a great and incomparable preference betweene the honor of invention and that of allegation; Would I have spoken according to learning, I had spoken sooner, I had written at such times as I was nearer to my studies, when I had more wit and more memory, and should more have trusted the vigor of that age then the imperfection of this had I been willing to professe writing of bookes. And what if this gratious favor, which fortune has not long since offered me by the intermission of this work, could have befalne me in such a season in liew of this, where it is equally desireable to possesse and ready to loose? Two of mine acquaintance (both notable men in this faculty) have, in my conceit, lost much because they refused to publish themselves at forty years of age, to stay until they were three score. Maturity has her defects as well as greenenesse, and worse. And as incommodious or unfit is old age unto this kind of work as to any other. Whosoever puts his decrepitude under the press committeth folly, if therby he hopes to wring out humors that shall not taste of dotage, of foppery, or of drousinesse. Our spirit becomes costive and thickens in growing old. Of ignorance I speak sumptuously and plenteously, and of learning meagerly and pitiously; This accessorily and accidentally, that expressely and principally; And purposely I treat of nothing but of nothing, nor of any one science but of unscience. I have chosen the time where the life I have to set forth is all before me, the rest holds more of death. And of my death only should I find it babling, as others do, I would willingly, in dislodging, give the World advise. Socrates has been a perfect patterne in all great qualities, I am vexed that ever he met with so unhandsome and crabbed a body as they say he had, and so dissonant from the beauty of his mind: Himselfe so amorous and so besotted on beauty. Nature did him wrong. There is no thing more truely-semblable as the conformity or relation betweene the body and the mind. Ipsi animi, magni refert, quali in corpore locati sint; multa enim e corpore existunt quæ acuant mentem, multa quæ obtundant: ’It is of great import in what body the mind is bestowed, for many things arise of the body to sharpen the mind, and many things to dull and rebate it.’ This man speaks of an unnaturall ill-favourdnesse and membrall deformity, but we call ill-favourdnesse a kind of unseemelinesse at the first sight, which chiefely lodgeth in the face, and by the colour worketh a dislike in us. A freckle, a blemmish, a rude countenance, a sower looke, proceeding often of some inexplicable cause, may be in well ordered, comely and compleate limbs. The foulenesse of face which invested a beauteous mind in my dear friend La Boitie was of this predicament. This superficiall ill-favourdnesse, which is notwithstanding to the most imperious, is of less prejudice unto the state of the mind, and has small certainty in mens opinion. The other, by a more proper name called a more substantiall deformity, beareth commonly a deeper inward stroke. Not every shooe of smoothshining leather, but every well-shapen and handsome-made shoe, sheweth the inward and right shape of the foote. As Socrates said of his, that it justly accused so much in his mind had he not corrected the same by institution; But in so saying I suppose, that according to his wonted use he did but jest, and so excellent mind did never frame itself; I cannot often enough repeat how much I esteeme beauty, so powerfull and advantageous a quality is she. He named it a short tyranny, and Plato the priviledge of Nature. We have none that exceeds it in credit; She possesseth the chief rank in the commerce of society of men: She presents itself forward, she seduceth and preoccupates our judgement with great authority and wonderful impression. Phryne had lost her plea, though in the hands of an excellent lawyer, if with opening her garments, by the sodaine flashing of her beauty she had not corrupted her judges; And I find that Cyrus, Alexander, and Cæsar, those three Masters of the World, have not forgotten or neglected the same in atchieving their great affairs; so has not the first Scipio. One same word in Greeke importeth fair and good; And even the Holy Ghost calleth often those good which he meaneth fair. I should willingly maintaine the rank of the goods as employed the song which Plato says to have been triviall, taken from some ancient Poet, Health, beauty and riches. Aristotle says that the right of commanding does of duty belong to such as are fair and if perhaps any be found whose beauty approached to that of the Gods images, that veneration is equally due unto them. To one that asked him why the fairest were both longer time and oftner frequented, ’This question,’ quoth he, ’ought not to be mooved but by a blinde man.’ Most and the greatest Philosophers paide for their schooling and attained unto Wisedome by the intermission of their beauty, and favor of their comlines. Not only in men that serve me, but in beasts also, I consider the same within two inches of goodnesse. Yet me thinkes that the same feature and manner of the face, and those lineaments by which some argue certain inward complexions and our future fortunes, is a thing that does not directly nor simply lodge under the Chapter of beauty and favourdnesse, no more than all good favors, or cleerenesse of aire do not alwayes promise health: nor all fogges and stinkes infection in times of the plague. Such as accuse Ladies to contradict the beauty by their manners, guesse not alwayes at the truth. For [an] ill favourd and ill composed face may sometimes harbour some aire of probity and trust. As on the contrary I have sometimes read between two fair eyes the threats of a maligne and dangerous ill-boding nature. There are some favourable Physiognomies, For in a throng of victorious enemies you shall presently ammiddest a multitude of unknown faces, make choise of one man more than of others to yield your self unto and trust your life, and not properly by the consideration of beauty. A mans looke or aire of his face is but a weake warrant, notwithstanding it is of some consideration; And were I to whipe them I would more rudely scourge such as maliciously belie and betray the promises which Nature had charactred in their front; And more severely would I punish malicious craft in a debonaire apparance and in a mild promising countenance. It seems there be some lucky and well boding faces, and other some unlucky and ill presaging; And I think there is some Art to distinguish gently-mild faces from nyæs and simple, the severe from the rude, the malicious from the froward, the disdainful from the melancholike and other neighbouring qualities. There are some beauties not only fierce-looking, but also sharpe working, some others pleasing-sweet and yet wallowishly tastlesse. To prognosticate future successes of them be matters I leave undecided. I have (as elsewhere I noted) taken for my regard this ancient precept, very rawly and simply : That We cannot erre in following Nature; and that the sovereign document is for a man to conforme himself to her. I have not (as Socrates), by the power and virtue of reason, corrected my natural complexions, nor by Art hindered mine inclination. Looke how I came into the World, so I go-on: I strive with nothing. My two Mistris parts live of their own kindness in peace and good agreement; but my nurses milke has (thankes be to God) been indifferently wholesome and temperate. Shall I say thus much by the way? That I see a certain image of bookish or scholastical preud’hommie only, which is in a manner in use amongst us, held and reputed in greater esteeme than it deserveth, and which is but a servant unto precepts, brought under by hope, and constrained by fear? I love it such as laws and religions make not, but over- make and authorize; that they may be perceived to have wherewith to uphold herself without other aide sprung up in us of her own proper roots, by and from the seed of universall reason, imprinted in every man that is not unnaturall. The same reason that reformeth Socrates from his vicious habite, yields him obedient both to Gods and men that rule and command his City; courageous in his death, not because his soul is immortall, but because he is mortal. A ruinous instruction to all common-weales, and much more harmefull than ingenious and subtile, is that which perswadeth men that only religious beliefe, and without manners, sufficeth to content and satisfie divine justice. Custome makes us see an enormous distinction betweene devotion and conscience. I have a favourable apparence, both in form and in interpretation. Quid dixi habere me? Imo habui, Chreme: Heu tantum attriti corporis ossa vides. -- TER. Heau. act i. sc. 1. I have; what did I say? I had what’s now away. Alas, you only now behold Bones of a body worne and old. And which makes a contrary show to that of Socrates. It has often betided me that by the simple credit of my presence and aspect, some that had no knowledge of me have greatly trusted unto it, were it about their own affairs or mine. And even in forraine countries, I have thereby reaped singular and rare favors. These two experiments are perhaps worthy to be particularly related. A quidam gallant determined upon a time to surprise both my house and my self. His plot was to come riding alone to my gate, and instantly to urge entrance. I knew him by name, and had some reason to trust him, being my neigbbour and somwhat alide unto me. I presently caused my gates to be opened, as I do to all men. He comes-in all afrighted, his horse out of breath; both much harassed. He entertaines me with this fable: that within halfe a league of my house he was sodainely set- upon by an enemy of his whom I knew well, and had heard of their quarrell; that his foe had wondrously put him to his spurres; that being surprised unarmed, and having fewer in his company than the other, he was glad to run away, and for safety had made haste to come to my house, as to his sanctuary; That he was much perplexed for his men, all which he supposed to be either taken or slain. I endevoured friendly to comfort and sincerely to warrant and refresh him. Within a while came galloping foure or five of his Soldiers, amazed, as if they had been out of their wits, hasting to be let in. Shortly after came others, and others, all proper men, well mounted, better armed, to the number of thirty or there abouts, all seeming distracted for fear, as if the enemy that pursued them had been at their heels. This mystery beganne to summon my suspicion. I was not ignorant of the age wherein I lived, nor how much my house might be envied; and had sundry examples of others of my acquaintance that had been spoiled, beset and surprised thus and thus. So it is, that perceiving with my self, there was nothing to be gotten though I had begun to use them kindly, if I continued not, and being unable to rid my self of them and clear my house without danger and spoiling all; as I ever do, I took the plainest and most natural well meaning way, and commanded they should be let-in and bid welcome. And to say truth, I am by nature little suspicious or mistrustfull. I am easily drawen to admit excuses and encline to mild interpretations. I take men according to common order, and suppose everyone to meane as I do, and believe these perverse and trecherous inclinations, except I be compelled by some authentic testimony, no more then monsters or miracles. Besides I am a man that willingly commit my self unto fortune, and carelesly cast my self unto her arms. Whereof hitherto I have more just cause to commend my self than to complain. And have found her more circumspect and friendly- careful of my affairs than I am my self. There are certain actions of my life, the conduct of which may justly be termed difficult, or if any be so disposed, prudent. And of those, suppose the third part of them to be my own, truely the other two are richly hirs. We are to blame, and in my conceit we erre, that we do not sufficiently and so much as we ought, trust the heavens with ourselves. And pretend more in our own conduct then of right appertaines unto us. Therefore do our desseignes so often miscarry, and our intents so seldom sort to wished effect. The heavens are angry, and I may say envious of the extension and large priviledge we ascribe unto the right of humane wisdom, to the prejudice of theirs: and abridge them so much the more unto us by how much more we endeavor to amplifie them. But to come to my former discourse. These gallants kept still on horsebacke in my court, and would not alight; their Captain with me in my hall, who would never have his horse set-up, still saying that be would not stay, but must necessarily withdraw himself so soon as he had news of his followers. He saw himself master of his enterprise, and nothing was wanting but the execution. He has since reported very often (for he was no whit scrupulous or afraid to tell this story) that my undaunted looks, my undismaide countenance, and my liberty of speech made him reject all manner of treasonable intents or trecherous desseignes. What shall I say more? He bids me farewell, calleth for his horse, gets up, and offreth to be gone, his people having continually their eyes fixed upon him, to observe his looks and see what signe be should make unto them; much amazed to see him begone, and wondring to see him omit and forsake such an advantage. An other time, trusting to a certain truce or cessation of arms that lately had been published through our campes in France, as one suspecting no harme, I undertook a journey from home, through a dangerous and very ticklish countrey. I had not rid far but I was discovered, and behold three or foure troupes of horsemen, all severall ways, made after me, with purpose to entrap me; One of which overtooke me the third day, where I was round beset and charged by fifteene or twenty Gentlemen, who had all vizards and cases, followed a loofe-off by a band of Argoletiers. I was charged; I yielded; I was taken and immediately drawne into the bosome of a thicke Wood that was not far-off; there puld from my horse, stripped with all speed, my truncks and clokebags rifled, my box taken, my horses, my equipage, and such things as I had, dispersed and shared amongst them. We continued a good while amongst those thorny bushes, contesting and striving about my ransome, which they racked so high that it appeared well I was not much known of them. They had long contestation among themselves for my life. And to say truth, there were many circumstances threatned me of the danger I was in. Tunc animis opus, Ænea, tuncpectore firmo. -- Virg. Æn. vi. Of courage then indeed, Then of stout brest is need. I ever stood upon the title and priviledge of the truce and proclamation made in the King’s name, but that availed not: I was content to quit them what ever they had taken from me, which was not to be despised, without promising other ransome. After we had debated the matter to and fro the space of two or three hours, and that no excuses could serve, they set me upon a lame jade, which they knew could never escape them, and committed the particular keeping of my person to fifteene or twenty harque-busiers, and dispersed my people to others of their crew, commanding we should diverse ways be carried prisoners, and my self being gone two or threescore paces from them, Jam prece Pollucis, jam Castoris implorata, -- Catul. El. iv. 65. Pollux and Castors aide, When I had humbly praide, behold a sodain and unexpected alteration took them. I saw their Captain coming towards me, with a cheerful countenance and much milder speeches than before, carefully trudging up and down through all the troops to find out my goods again, which as he found al scattred he forced every man to restore them unto me; and even my boxe came to my hands again. To conclude, the most precious jewell they presented me was in liberty; as for my other things, I cared not greatly at that time. What the true cause of so unlookt- for a change and so sodaine an alteration was, without any apparent impulsion, and of so wonderful repentance, at such a time, in such an opportunity and such an enterprise, fore- meditated, consulted and effected without controlement, and which through custom and the impiety of times was now become lawfull (for at the first brunt I plainely confessed and genuinly told them what side I was of, where my way lay, and whither I was riding), I verily know not yet, nor can I give any reason for it. The chiefest amongst them unmasked himself, told me his name, and repeated diverse times unto me that I should acknowledge my deliverance to my countenance, to my boldness and constancy of speech, and be beholding to them for it, insomuch as they made me unworthy of such a misfortune; and demanded assurance of me for the like curtesie. It may be that the inscrutable goodnesse of God would use this vain instrument for my preservation; For the next morrow it also shielded me from worse mischief or amboscadoes, whereof themselves gently forewarned me. The last is yet living, able to report the whole success himself; the other was slain not long since. If my countenance had not answered for me, if the ingenuity of mine inward intent might not plainely have been deciphered in mine eyes and voice, surely I could never have continued so long without quarrels or offences: with this indiscreete liberty, to speak freely (be it right or wrong) whatever commeth to my mind, and rashly to judge of things. This fashion may in some sort (and that with reason) seem uncivill and ill accommodated in our customa ry manners; but outrageous or malicious, I could never meete with any would so judge it, or that was ever distasted at my liberty if he received the same from my mouth. Words reported again have as another sound, so another sense. And to say true, I hate no body; And am so remisse to offend, or slow to wrong any, that for the service of reason itself I cannot do it. And if occasion have at any time urged me in criminall condemnations to do as others, I have rather been content to be amearced then to appeare. Ut magis peccari nolim, quam satis animi ad vindicanda peccata habeam: ’So as I had rather men should not offend, then that I should have courage enough to punish their offences.’ Some report that Aristotle, being up- braided by some of his friends that he had been over mercifull toward a wicked man, ’I have indeede (quoth he) been mercifull toward the man, but not toward his wickednesse.’ Ordinary judgements are exasperated unto punishment by the horror of the crime; And that enmildens me. The horror of the first murther makes me fear a second; And the uglinesse of one cruelty induceth me to detest all manner of imitation of it. To me, that am but a plaine fellow and see no higher than a steeple, may that concerne which was reported of Charillus, King of Sparta: ’He cannot be good, since he is not bad to the wicked.’ Or thus; for Plutarke presents it two ways, as he does a thousand other things diversly and contrary; ’He must needs be good, since he is so to the wicked.’ Even as in lawfull actions it grieves me to take any paines about them, when it is with such as are therewith displeased; So, to say truth, in unlawfull, I make no great conscience to employ my self or take paines about them, being with such as consent unto them. CHAPTER XIII: OF EXPERIENCE HERE IS no desire more natural then that of knowledge. We attempt all means that may bring us unto it. When reason failes us, we employ experience. Per varios usus artem experientia fecit, Exemplo monstrante viam. -- MANIL. i. Ast. 61. By diverse proofes experience art has bred, Whilst one by one the way examples led. Which is a meane by much more weake and vile. But truth is of so great consequence that we ought not disdaine any induction that may bring us unto it. Reason has so many shapes that we know not which to take hold of. Experience has as many. The consequence we seek to draw from the conference of events is unsure, because they are ever dissemblable. No quality is so universall in this surface of things as variety and diversity. The Greekes, the Latines, and we, use for the most express examples of similitude that of egges. Some have nevertheless been found, especially one in Delphos, that knew markes of difference betweene egges, and never took one for another; And having diverse hennes, could rightly judge which had laid the egge. Dissimilitude does of it self insinuate into our workes, no arte can come near unto similitude. Neither Perozet nor any other carde-maker can so industriously smoothe or whiten the backeside of his cards, but some cunning gamester will distinguish them only by seeing some other player handle or shuffle them. Resemblance does not so much make one as difference maketh another. Nature has bound herself to make nothing that may not be dissemblable. Yet does not the opinion of that man greatly please me, that supposed by the multitude of laws to curbe the authority of judges in cutting out their morsels. He perceived not that there is as much liberty and extension in the interpretation of laws as in their fashion. And those but mocke themselves who think to diminish our debates and stay them by calling us to the express word of sacred Bible. Because our spirit findes not the field less spacious to controule and checke the sense of others then to represent his own, and as if there were as litle courage and sharpnesse to glose as to invent. We see how far he was deceived. For we have in France more laws then all the world besides; indeed, more then were needefull to governe all the worlde imagined by Epicurus: Ut olim flagitiis, sic nunc legibus laboramus: ’As in times past we were sicke of offences, so now are we of laws.’ As we have given our judges so large a scope to moote, to opinionate, to suppose, and decide, that there was never so powerfull and so licentious a liberty. What have our lawmakers gained with chusing a hundred thousand kinds of particular cases, and adde as many laws unto them? That number has no proportion with the infinite diversity of humane accidents. The multiplying of our inventions shall never come to the variation of examples. Adde a hundred times as many unto them, yet shall it not follow that of events to come there be any one found that in all this infinite number of selected and enregistred events shall meete with one to which be may so exactly join and match it, but some circumstance and diversity will remaine that may require a diverse consideration of judgement. There is but little relation betweene our actions that are in perpetuall mutation and the fixed and unmoveable laws. The most to be desired are the rarest, the simplest, and most general. And yet I believe it were better to have none at all then so infinite a number as we have. Nature gives them ever more happy then those we give ourselves. Witness the image of the golden age that Poets faine, and the state wherein we see diverse nations to live, which have no other. Some there are who to decide any controversie that may rise amongst them, will chuse for judge the first man that by chance shall travell alongst their mountaines: Others, that upon a market day will name some one amongst themselves who in the place without more wrangling shall determine all their questions. What danger would ensue if the wisest should so decide ours according to occurences and at the first sight, without being tied to examples and consequences? Let every foote have his own shooe. Ferdinando, King of Spain, sending certain Colonies into the Indies, provided wisely that no lawyers or students of the laws should be carried thither, for fear lest controversies, sutes, or process should people that new found world. As a Science that of her own nature engendreth altercation and division, judging with Plato that Lawyers and Phisitions are an ill provision for any countrey.’ Wherefore is that our common language, so easy to be understood in all other matters, becomes so obscure, so harsh and so hard to be understood in law-cases, bils, contracts, indentures, citations, wils, and testaments? And that he who so plainely expresseth himself, what ever he spake or wrote of any other subject, in law matters findes no manner or way to declare himself his meaning that admits not some doubt or contradiction; Unless it be that the Princes of this art, applying themselves with a particular attention to lilve and chose strange, choise, and solemn words, and frame artificiall cunning clauses, have so plodded and poized every syllable, canvased and sifted so exquisitely every seame and quiddity, that they are now so entangled and so confounded in the infinity of figures and so several- small partitions, that they can no mor come within the compasse of any order, or prescription or certain understanding. Confusum est quidquid usque in pulverem sectum est: ’Whatsoever is sliced into very powder is confused.’ Whosoever has seen children labouring to reduce a masse of quick-silver to a certain number, the more they press and work the same and strive to force it to their will, so much more they provoke the liberty of that generous metall, which scorneth their arte, and scatteringly disperseth itself beyond all imagination. Even so of lawyers, who in subdividing their suttleties or quiddities, teach men to multiply doubts, and by extending and diversifying difficufties, they lengthen and amplifie, they scatter and disperse them. In sowing and retailing of questions they make the World to fructifie and abound in uncertainty, in quarrels, in sutes, and in controversies. As the ground the more it is crumbled, broken, and deeply removed or grupped up, becomes so much more fertile. Difficultatent fecit doctrine: ’Learning breeds difficulty.’ We found many doubts in Ulpian, we find more in Bartolus and Baldus. The trace of this innumerable diversity of opinions should never have been used to adorn posterity and have it put in her head, but rather have been utterly razed out. I know not what to say to it; but this is seen by experience, that so many interpretations dissipate and confound all truth. Aristotle has written to be understood: Which, if he could not, much less shall another not so learned as he was; and a third, than he who treateth his own imagination. We open the matter, and spill it in distempering it. Of one subject we make a thousand: And in multiplying and subdividing we fal again into the infinity of Epicurus his Atomes. It was never seen that two men judged likewise of one same thing: And it is impossible to see two opinions exactly semblable, not only in diverse men, but in any one same man at severall hours. I commonly find something to doubt of, where the commentary happily never deigned to touch, as deeming it so plaine. I stumble sometimes as much in an even smooth path, as some horses that I know who oftner trip in a fair plaine way than in a rough and stony. Who would not say that glosses increase doubts and ignorance, since no book is to be seen, whether divine or profane, commonly read of all men, whose interpretation dimmes or tarnisheth not the difficulty? The hundred commentary sends him to his succeeder more thorny and more crabbed than the first found him. When agreed we amongst ourselves to say, this book is perfect; there’s now nothing to be said against it? This is best seen in our French-pedling Law. Authority of Law is given to infinite Doctors, to infinite arrests, and to as many interpretations. Finde we for all that any end of need of interpreters? Is there any advancement or progresse towards tranquillity seen therein? Have we now less need of Advocates and Judges than when this huge masse of Law was yet in her first infancy? Cleane contrary: we obscure and bury understanding. We discover it no more but at the mercy of so many Courts, Barres, or Plea-benches. Men misacknowledge the natural infirmity of their mind. She does but quest and firret, and uncessantly goeth turning, winding, building, and entangling herself in her own work, as do our silke- wormes, and therein stifleth herself. Mus in pice: ’A mouse in pitch.’ He supposeth to note a far-off I wot not what apparance of cleerenesse and imaginary truth; but whilst he runneth unto it, so many lets and difficulties crosse his way, so many impeachments and new questings start up, that they stray loose and besot him. Not much otherwise than it fortuned to Aesops Dogs who far-off discovering some show of a dead body to flote upon the Sea, and being unable to approach the same, undertook to drinke up all the Water, that so they might drie up the passage, and were all stifeled. To which answereth that which Crates said of Heraclitus his compositions, that they needed a Reader who should be a cunning swimmer, lest the depth and weight of his learning should drowne and swallow him up. It is nothing but a particular weakenesse that makes us contend with that which others or we ourselves have found in this pursuite of knowledge. A more sufficient man will not be pleased therewith. There is a place for a follower, indeed for ourselves, and More ways to the Wood than one. There is no end in our inquisitions. Our end is in the other World. It is a signe his wits grow short when he is pleased, or a signe of wearinesse. No generous spirit stayes and relies upon himself: he ever pretendtfh and goeth beyond his strength. He has some vagaries beyond his effects. If he advance not himself, press, settle, shocke, turn, winde and front himself, he is but halfe alive; His pursuits are termelesse and formelesse. His nourishment is admiration, questing, and ambiguity: Which Apollo declared sufficiently, alwayes speaking ambiguously, obscurely, and obliquely unto us - not feeding, but busying and ammusing us. It is an irregular, uncertaine motion, perpetuall, patternelesse, and without end. His inventions enflame, follow, and enter-produce one another. Ainsi voit-on en un ruisseau coulant, Sans fin l’une eau, apres l’autre roulant, Et tout de rang, d’un eternal conduict, L’une suit l’autre, et l’une l’autre fuit. Par cette-cy, celle-la est Poussée, Et cette-cy, par I’autre est devancée: Tousjours l’leau va dans l’eau, et tousjours est ce Mesme ruisseau et tousjours eau diverse. As in a running river we behold How one wave after the other still is rold, And all along as it does endlesse rise, Th’ one the other followes, the one from the other flyes, By this Wave that is driv’n; and this again By the other is set forward all amaine: Water in Water still, one river still, Yet diverse Waters still that river fill. There’s more adoe to enterpret interpretations than to interpret things, and more bookes upon bookes then upon any other subject. We do but enter-glose ourselves. All swarmeth with commentaries; of Authors there is great penury. Is not the chiefest and most famous knowledge of our ages to know how to understand the wise? Is it not the common and last scope of our study? Our opinions are grafted one upon an other. The first serveth as a stocke to the second, the second to the third. Thus we ascend from steppe to steppe. Whence it followeth that the highest-mounted has often more honor than merit. For he is got-up but one inch above the shoulders of the last save one. How often, and perhaps foolishly, have I enlarged my Book to speak of himself? Foolishly, if it were but for this reason: That I should have remembred that what I speak of others they do the like of me. That those so frequent glances on their workes witnes their hart shivereth with the love they bear them, and that the disdainfull churlishnesse wherewith they beate them are but mignardizes and affectations of a motherly favor. Following Aristotle, in whom, both esteeming and dis-esteeming himself arise often of an equall aire of arrogancy. For mine excuse, That in this I ought to have more liberty than others, forasmuch as of purpose I write both of my self and of my writings as of my other actions, that my theame does turn into itself; I wot not whether every man will take it. I have seen in Germany that Luther has left as many divisions and altercations concerning the doubt of his opinions, indeed, and more, than himself moveth about the Holy Scriptures. Our contestation is verball. I demaund what Nature, voluptuousness, circle, and substitution is? The question is of words, and with words it is answered. A stone is a body: but he that should insist and urge: And what is a body? - A substance. And what is a substance? and so go-on, should at last bring the respondent to his Calepine or wits end. One word is changed for another word, and often more unknown. I know better what Homo is then I know what Animal is, either mortal or reasonable. To answere one doubt they give me three: It is Hidræs head. Socrates demanded of Memnon what virtue was. ’There is,’ answered Memnon, ’the virtue of a Man, of a Woman, of a Magistrate, of a private Man, of a Childe, of an old Man. What virtue meane you?’ ’Yea, marry. this is very well,’ quoth Socrates; ’we were in search of one virtue, and you bringest me a whole swarme.’ We propose one question, and we have a whole huddle of them made unto us again. As no event or form does wholly resemble another, so does it not altogether differ one from another. Oh, ingenious mixture of Nature! If our faces were not like, we could not discerne a man from a beast; If they were not unlike, we could not distinguish one man from another man. All things hold by some similitude; Every example limpeth. And the relation which is drawne from experience is ever defective and imperfect. Comparisons are, nevertheless, joined together by some end. So serve the Lawes, and so are they sorted and fitted to all our sutes or affairs by some wiredrawen, forced, and collateral interpretation. Since the morall Lawes, which respect the particular duty of every man in himself, are so hard to be taught and observed as we see they are: It is no wonder if those which governe so many particulars, are more hard. Consider the form of this Law by which we are ruled: It is a lively testimony of humane imbecility, so much contradiction and so many errours are therin contained. That which we think favor or rigour in Law (wherein is so much of either, that I wot not well whether we shall so often find indifferency in them), or crazed-infected parts and unjust members of the very body and essence of Law. Certain poore country-men came even now to tell me in a great haste, that but now in a forrest of mine they have left a man wounded to death, with a hundred hurts about him, yet breathing, and who for God’s sake has begged a little water and some helpe to raise himself at their hands; But that they durst not come near him, and ran all away, for fear some officers belonging to the Law should meete and catch them, and as they do with such as they find near unto a murthered body, so they should be compelled to give an account of this mischance, to their utter undooing, having neither friends nor mony to defend their innocency. What should I have said unto them? It is most certain that this Office of humanity had brought them to much trouble. How many innocent and guiltlesse men have we seen punished? I say without the Judge’s fault? and how many more that were never discovered? This has hapned in my time. Certain men are condemned to death for a murther committed; the sentence, if not pronounced, at least concluded and determined. This done, the Judges are advertised by the Officers of a subalternall Court, not far-off, that they have certain prisoners in hold that have directly confessed the foresaid murther, and thereof bring most evident markes and tokens. The question and consultation is now in the former Court, whether for all this they might interrupt or should deferre the execution of the sentence pronounced against the first. They consider the novelty of the example and consequence thereof, and how to reconcile the judgement. They conclude that the condemnation has passed according unto Law, and therefore the Judges are not subject to repentance. To be short, these miserable Wretches are consecrated to the prescriptions of the Law. Philip, or some other, provided for such an inconvenience in this manner: he had by an irrevocable sentence condemned one to pay another a round summe of money for a fine. A while after, the truth being discovered, it was found he had wrongfully condemned him. On one side was the right of the cause, on the other the right of judiciary formes. He is in some sort to satisfie both parties, suffering the sentence to stand in full power, and with his own purse recompenced the interest of the condemned. But he was to deale with a reparable accident; my poore slaves were hanged irreparably. How many condemnations have I seen more criminall than the crime itself? All this put me in mind of those ancient opinions: That He who will do right in grosse must needs do wrong by retaile; and injustly in small things, that will come to do justice in great matters. That humane justice is framed according to the modell of physicke, according to which, whatsoever is profitable is also just and honest; And of that the Stoices hold that Nature herself, in most of her workes, proceedeth against justice; And of that which the Cyreniaques hold, that there is nothing just of itself: That customs and laws frame justice. And the Theodorians, who in a wise man allow as just all manner of theft, sacriledge, and paillardise, so he think it profitable for him. There is no remedy: I am in that case as Alcibiades was, and if I can otherwise chuse, will never put my self unto a man that shall determine of my head, or consent that my honor or life shall depend on the industry or care of mine atturney more then mine innocency. I could willingly adventure my self and stand to that Law that should as well recompence me for a good deed as punish me for a mis-deede, and where I might have a just cause to hope, as reason to fear. Indemnitie is no sufficient coyne for him who does better than not to trespasse. Our Law presents us but one of her hands, and that is her left hand. Whosoever goes to Law, does in the end but lose by it. In China, the policy, arts and government of which kingdome, having neither knowledge or commerce with ours exceed our examples in diverse parts of excellency, and whose Histories teach me how much more ample and diverse the World is than either we or our forefathers could ever enter into. The Officers appointed by the Prince to visite the state of his Provinces, as they punish such as abuse their charge, so with great liberality they reward such as have uprightly and honestly behaved themselves in them, or have done any thing more then ordinary, and besides the necessity of their duty; There all present themselves, not only to warrant themselves, but also to get something. Not simply to be paid, but liberally to be rewarded. No judge has yet, God be thanked, spoken to me as a judge in any cause Whatsoever, either mine or another mans, criminal or civill. No prison did ever receive me, no not so much as for recreation to walke in. The very imagination of one maketh the sight of their outside seem irkesome and loathsome to me. I am so besotted unto liberty that should any man forbid me the accesse unto any one corner of the Indiæs I should in some sort live much discontented. And so long as I shall find land or open aire elsewhere, I shall never lurke in any place where I must bide my self. Oh God how hardly could I endure the miserable condition of so many men confined and immured in some corners of this kingdome, barred from entring the chiefest Cities, from accesse into Courts, from conversing with men, and interdicted the use of common ways, only because they have offended our laws. If those under which I live should but threaten my fingers end, I would presently go find out some others, wherever it were. All my small wisdom, in these civill and tumultuous wars wherein we now live, does wholly employ itself, that they may not interrupt my liberty to go and come where ever I list. Lawes are now maintained in credit, not because they are essentially just, but because they are laws. It is the mysticall foundation of their authority - they have none other - which availes them much: they are often made by fooles; more often by men who, in hatred of equality, have want of equity; But ever by men who are vain and irresolute Authours. There is nothing so grossely and largely offending, nor so ordinarily wronging as the Lawes. Whosoever obeyeth them because they are just, obeyes them not justly the way as he ought. Our French laws do in some sort, by their irregularity and deformity, lend a helping hand unto the disorder and corruption that is seen in their dispensation and execution. Their behest is so confused, and their command so inconstant, that it in some sort excuseth both the disobedience and the vice of the interpretation, of the administration, and of the observation. Whatsoever then the fruit is we may have of Experience, the same which we draw from forraine examples will hardly stead our institution much; if we reape so small profit from that we have of ourselves, which is most familiar unto us, and truely sufficient to instruct us of what we want. I study my self more than any other subiect. It is my supernaturall Metaphisik, it is my natural Philosophy. Qua Deus hanc mundi temperet arte domum, Qua venit exoriens, qua deficit unde coactis Cornibus in plenum menstrua luna redit: Unde salo superant venti, quid flamine captet Eurus, et in nubes unde perennis æqua. Sit ventura dies mundi quæ subruat arces. -- Propert. iii. El. iv. 26. This Worlds great house by what arte God does guide; From whence the monethly Moone does rising ride, How wane, how with clos’d horns returns to pride, How winds on seas bear sway, what the Easterne winde Would have, how still in clouds we water find; If this worlds Towers to rase a day be signde. Quærite, quos agitat mundi labor: All this do you enquire Whom this worlds travails tyre. In this universality I suffer my self ignorantly and negligently to be managed by the general law of the world. I shall sufficiently know it when I shall feel it. My learning cannot make her change her course; she will not diversifie herself for me; it were folly to hope it: And greater folly for a man to trouble him self about it; since it is necessarily semblable, publicke, and common. The governours capacity and goodnesse should throughly discharge us of the governments care. Philosophicall inquisitions and contemplations serve but as a nourishment unto our curiosity. With great reason do philosophers addresse us unto natures rules; but they have nought to do with so sublime a knowledge; They falsifie them, and present her to us with a painted face, too-high in colour and overmuch sophisticated; whence arise so many different pourtraits of so uniform a subject. As she has given us feete to go withall, so has she endowed us with wisdom to direct our life. A wisdom not so ingenious, sturdy, and pompous as that of their invention, but yet easy, quiet and salutairie. And that in him who has the hap to know how to employ it orderly and sincerely, effecteth very well what the other says, that is to say, naturally. For a man to commit himself most simply unto nature is to do it most wisely. Oh how soft, how gentle, and how sound a pillow is ignorance and incuriosity to rest a well composed head upon. I had rather understand my self well in my self then in Cicero. Out of the experience I have of my self I find sufficient ground to make my self wise were I but a good proficient scholler. Whosoever shall commit to memory the excess or inconvenience of his rage or anger past, and how far that fit transported him, may see the deformity of that passion better then in Arisiotle, and conceive a more just hatred against it. Whosoever calleth to mind the dangers he has escaped, those which have threatned him, and the light occasions that have remooved him from one to another state, does thereby the better prepare himself to future alterations and knowledge of his condition. Cæsar’s life has no more examples for us then our own; Both imperiall and popular, it is ever a life that all humane accidents regard. Let us but give care unto it, we recorde all that to us that we principally stand in neede of. He that shall call to mind how often and how severall times he has been deceived and mis- accompted his own judgement, is he not a simple gull if he do not for ever afterward distrust the same? When by others reason I find my self convicted of a false opinion, I learne not so much what new thing he has told me; and this particular ignorance, which were but a small purchase, as in general I learne my own imbecility and weakenesse, and the treason of my understanding, whence I draw the reformation of all the masse. The like I do in all my other errours, by which rule I apprehend and feel great profit for and unto my life. I regarde not the species or individuum as a stone whereon I have stumbled; I learne every where to fear my going, and endeavor to order the same. To learne that another has either spoken a foolish jest or committed a sottish act is a thing of nothing. A man must learne that he is but a foole: A much more ample and important instruction. The false steps my memory has so often put upon me at what time she stood most upon her self, have not idlely been lost: she may sweare and warrant me long enough, I shake mine ears at her: the first opposition made in witness of her makes me suspect. And I durst not trust her in a matter of consequence, nor warrant her touching others affairs. And were it not that what I do for want of memory, others more often do the same for lacke of faith, I would even in a matter of fact rather take the truth from anothers mouth then from my own. Would every man pry into the effects and circumstances of the passions that sway him as I have done of that whereunto I was allotted, he should see them coming, and would somewhat hinder their course and abate their impetuosity; They do not alwayes surprise and take hold of us at the first brunt there are certain forethreatnings and degrees as forerunners. Fluctus uti primo coepit cum albescere ponto, Paulatim sese tollit mare, et altius undas Erigit, inde imo consurgit ad æthera fundo. As when at sea, floods first in whiteness rise, Sea surgeth softly, and then higher plies In waves, then from the ground mounts up to skies. Judgement holds in me a presidential seate, at least he carefully endevours to hold it; He suffers my appetits to keep their course, both hatred and love, indeed that I bear unto my self, without feeling alteration or corruption. If he can not reforme other parts according to himself, at least he will not be deformed by them; he keepes his court apart. That warning-lesson given to all men, to know themselves, must necessarily be of important effect, since that God of wisdom, knowledge, and light, caused the same to be fixed on the fron tispiece of his temple, as containing whatsoever he was to counsell us. Plato says also that wisdom is nothing but the execution of that ordinance; And Socrates does distinctly verifle the same in Zenophon. Difficulties and obscurity are not perceived in every science, but by such as have entrance into them: For some degree of intelligence is required to be able to marke that one is ignorant, and we must knocke at a gate to know whether it be shutte. Whence ensueth this Platonicall subtilty, that neyther those which know have no further to enquire, forasmuch as they know already; nor they that know not, because to enquire it is necessary they know what they enquire after. Even so in this for a man to know himself, that every man is seen so resolute and satisfied and thinks himself sufficiently instructed or skilfull does plainely signifie that no man understands any thing, as Socrates teacheth Euthydemus. My self, who professe nothing else, find therein so bottomlesse a depth and infinite variety, that my apprentisage has no other fruit than to make me perceive how much more there remaineth form to learne. To my own weaknesse so often acknowledged I owe this inclination which I bear unto modesty, to the obedience of beliefes prescribed unto me, to a constant coldnesse and moderation of opinions, and hatred of this importunate and quarrellous arrogancy, wholly beleeving, and trusting itself, a capital enemy to discipline and verity. Doe but hear them sway and talk. The first fopperies they propose are in the stile, that Religions and Lawes are composeth in. Nihil est turpius quam cognitioni et præceptioni, assertionem approbationemque præcurrere: (Cic. Acad. Qu. i. f.) ’Nothing is more absurd than that avouching and allowance should run before knowledge and præcept.’Aristarchus said that in ancient times there were scarse seven wise men found in the world, and in his time hardly seven ignorant. Have not we more reason to say it in our dayes than he had? Affirmation and self-conceit are manifest signes of foolishnesse. Some one, who a hundred times a day has had the canvase and been made a stark coxcombe, shall notwithstanding be seen to stand upon his Ergoes, and as presumptuously-resolute as before. You would say he has since some now mind and vigor of understanding infused into him. And that it betides him as to that ancient child of the Earth, who by his falling to the ground and touching his Mother still gathered new strength and fresh courage. ------ cui cum tetigere parentem, Jam defecta vigent renovato robore membra. -- Antæus. Whose failing limbs with strength renew’d regrow, When they once touch his mother Earth below. Does not this indocile, blocke-headed asse think to reassume a new spirit by undertaking a new disputation? It is by my experience I accuse humane ignorance, which (in mine opinion) is the surest part of the Worlds schoole. Those that will not conclude it in themselves by so vain an example as mine or theirs, let them acknowledge it by Socrates, the Maister of Maisters. For the Philosopher Antisthenes was wont to say to his Disciples, ’Come on, my Maisters, let you and me go to hear Socrates; There shall I be a fellow Disciple with you.’ And upholding this Doctrine of the Stoices Sect, that only virtue sufficed to make a life absolutely-happy, and having no need of any thing but of Socrates his force and resolution, he added moreover: This long attention I employ in considering my self enableth me also to judge indifferently of others; And there are few things whereof I speak more happily and excusably. It often fortuneth me to see and distinguish more exactly the conditions of my friends than themselves do. I have astonied some by the pertinency of my own description, and have warned him of himself. Because I have from mine infancy enured my self to view my own life in others lives; I have thereby acquired a studious complexion therein. And when I think on it, I suffer few things to escape about me that may in any sort fit the same, whether countenances, humor, or discourses. I studiously consider all I am to eschew and all I ought to follow. So by my friends productions I discover their inward inclinations. Not to marshall or range this infinit variety of so diverse and so distracted actions to certain Genders or Chapters, and distinctly to distribute my parcels and divisions into formes and known regions. Sed neque quam multæ species, et nomina quæ sint, Est numerus. -- Virg. Georg. i. 103. But not how many kinds, nor what their names: There is a number of them (and their frames). The wiser sort speak and declare their fantasies more specially and distinctly: But I who have no further insight then I get from common use, without rule or methode generally present my own but gropingly. As in this, I pronounce my sentence by articles, loose and disjoynted; it is a thing cannot be spoken at once and at full. Relation and conformity are not easily found in such base and common minds as ours. Wisedome is a solid and compleate frame, every severall piece whereof keepeth his due place and beareth his marke. Sola sapientia in se tota conversa est: ’Only wisdom is wholy turned into itself.’ I leave it to Artists, and I wot not whether in a matter so confused, so severall and so casual, they shall come to an end, to range into sides this infinit diversity of visages; and settle our inconstancy and place it in order. I do not only find it difficult to combine our actions one unto another; but take every one apart, it is hard by any principal quality to design the same properly, so double, so ambiguous and party-coloured, are they to diverse lusters. Which in Perseus the Macedonian King was noted for a rare matter, that his spirit fastning itself to no kind of condition; went wandring through every kind of life, and representing so newfangled and gadding maners, that he was neyther known of himself nor of others what kind of man he was, me thinkes may well- nigh agree and sute with all the world. And above all, I have seen some other of his coate or humor, to whom (as I suppose) this conclusion might also more properly be applied. No state of mediocrity being ever transported from one extreme to another, by indivinable occasions, no manner of course without crosse and strange contrarieties; no faculty simple, so that the likeliest a man may one day conclude of him, shall be that he affected and laboured to make himself known by being not to be known. A man had neede of long-tough ears to hear himself freely judged. And because there be few that can endure to hear it without tingling, those which adventure to undertake it with us, show a singular effect of true friendship. For that is a truely perfect love which, to profit and do good, feareth not to hurt or offend. I deem it absurd to censure him in whom bad qualities exceed good conditions. Plato requireth three parts in him that will examine anothers mind: Learning, goodwill, and boldness. I was once demanded what I would have thought my self fit- for, had any been disposed to make use of me, when my years would have fitted service: Dum melior vires sanguis dabat, æmula nec dum Temporibus geminis canebat sparsa senectus. -- Virg. Æn. v. 415. While better blood gave strength, nor envious old years Ore-laid with wrinckled temples grew to hoary haires. I answered, for nothing. And I willingly excuse my self that I can do nothing which may enthrall me to others. But had my fortune made me a servant, I would have told my maister all truths ; and, had he so willd it, controled his maners: Not in grosse, by scholasticall lessons, which I cannot do: besides, I see no true reformation to ensue in such as know them but fair and softly, and with every opportunity observing them, and simply and naturally judging them distinctly by the eye. Making him to perceive how and in what degree he is in the common opinion; opposing himself against his flatterers and sycophants. There is none of us but would be worse then Kings if, as they are, we were continually corrupted with that rascally kind of people. But what? if Alexander, that mighty King and great Philosopher, could not beware of them? I should have had sufficient fidelity, judgement and liberty for that. It would be a namelesse office, otherwise it should lose both effect and grace; And is a part which cannot indifferently belong to all. For truth itself has not the priviledge to be employed at all times and in every kind; Be her use never so noble, it has his circumscriptions and limits. It often commeth to pass, the world standing as it does, that truth is whispered into Princes ears, not only without fruit, but hurtfully and therewithall unjustly. And no man shall make me believe but that an hallowed admonition may be viciously applied and abusively employed; and that the interest of the substance should not sometimes yield to the interest of the form. For such a purpose and mystery I would have an unrepining man and one contented with his own fortune, Quod sit, esse velit, nihilque malit: == Mart. x. Epig. xlvii.12. Willing to be as him you see, Or rather nothing else to be: and borne of meane degree; Forasmuch as on the one side he should not have cause to fear, lively and neerely to touch his maisters heart, thereby not to lose the cause of his preferment; And on the other side, being of a low condition, he should have more easy communication with all sorts of people. Which I would have in one man alone; for, to empart the priviledge of such liberty and familiarity unto many would beget an hurtful irreverence. Yea, and of that man I would above all things require trusty and assured silence. A King is not to be credited when for his glory he boasteth of his constancy in attending his enemies encounter, if for his good amendment and profit he cannot endure the liberty of his friends words, which have no other working power then to pinch his learning; the rest of their effect remaining in his own hands. Now, there is not any condition of men that has more neede of true, sincerely-free and open hearted advertisements then Princes. They undergoe a public life, and must applaude the opinion of so many spectators, that if they be once enured to have that concealed from them which diverteth them from their course, they at unawares and insensibly find themselves deepely engaged in the hatred and detestation of their subjects, many times for occasions, which had they been forewarned, and in time gently reformed, they might no doubt have eschewed to no interest or prejudice of their private delights. Favorits do commonly respect themselves more then their masters. And surely it toucheth their free-hold, forasmuch as in good truth the greatest part of true friendships-offices are towards their sovereign in a crabbed and dangerous Essay. So that there is not only required much affection and liberty, but also an undanted courage. To conclude, all this galiemafry which I huddle-up here is but a register of my lives-Essayes, which in regard of the internall health are sufficiently exemplary to take the instruction against the hair. But concerning bodily health, no man is able to bring more profitable experience then my self, who present the same pure, sincere, and in no sort corrupted or altred, either by art or self- will’d opinion. Experience in her own precinct may justly be compared to Physicke, unto which reason gives place. Tiberius was wont to say that whosoever had lived twenty years should be able to answer himself of all such things as were either wholesome or hurtful for him, and know how to live and order his body without Phisicke. Which he perhaps had learned of Socrates, who industriously advising his disciples (as a study of chief consequence) to study their health, told them, moreover, that it was very hard if a man of understanding, heedfully observing his exercises, his eating and drinking, should not better than any Phisition discerne and distinguish such things as were either good or bad or indifferent for him. Yet does Physicke make open profession alwayes to have experience for the touchstone of her operation. And Plato had reason to say that to be a good Pbysitian it were requisite that he who should undertake that profession had past through all such diseases as he will adventure to cure, and known or felt all the accidents and circumstances he is to judge of. It is reason themselves should first have the pox if they will know how to cure them in others. I should surely trust such a one better then any else. Others but guide us, as one who, sitting in his chaire paints seas, rockes, shelves and havens upon a board, and makes the modell of a tall ship to saile in all safety; But put him to it in earnest, he knowes not what to do nor where to begin. They make even such a description of our infirmities as does a town-crier, who crieth a lost horse, or dog, and describeth his hair, his stature, his ears, with other markes and tokens; but bring either unto him, he knowes him not. Oh God, that physicke would one day affoord me some good and perceptible helpe, how earnestly would I exclaime: Tandem efficaci do manus scientiæ, I yield, I yield at length, To knowledge of chief strength. The Arts that promise to keep our body and mind in good health promise much unto us, but therewith there is none performeth less what they promise. And in our dayes such as make profession of these Arts amongst us do less then all others show their effects. The most may be said of them is that they sell medicinable drugs; but that they are Physitians, no man can truly say it. I have lived long enough to yield an account of the usage that has brought me to this day. If any be disposed to taste of it, as his taster I have given him an assay. See here some articles, digested as memory shall store me with them. I have no fashion, but has varied according to accidents; I only register those I have most been acquainted with, and hitherto possesse me most. My form of life is ever likewise, both in sicknesse and in health: one same bed, the same hours, the same meate, the same drinke does serve me. I adde nothing to them but the moderation of more or less, according to my strength or appetite. My health is to keep my accustomed state free from care and trouble. I see that sicknesse does on the one side in some sort divert me from it, and if I believe Physitians, they on the other side will turn me from it; So that both by fortune and by art I am cleane out of my right bias. I believe nothing more certainly then this, that I cannot be offended by the use of things which I have so long accustomed. It is in the hands of custom to give our life what form it pleaseth, in that it can do all in all. It is drinke of Circes diversifieth our nature as she thinkes good. How many nations near bordering upon us imagine the fear of the sereine or night-calme to be but a jest, which so apparently does blast and hurt us? and whereof our Mariners, our watermen and our countrey men make but a laughing-stocke? You make a Germane sicke if you lay him upon a matteras, as you distemper an Italian upon a fetherbed, and a Frenchman to lay him in a bed without curtaines, or lodge him in a chamber without a fire. A Spaniard can not well brooke to feede after our fashion, nor we endure to drinke as the Swizzers. A Germane pleased me well at Augusta to rail against the commodity of our chimnies, using the same reasons or arguments that we ordinarily employ in condemning their stoves. For, to say truth, the same close-smoothered heate and the smell of that oft-heated matter whereof they are composed, fumeth in the heads of such as are not accustomed unto them; not so with me. But on the other side, that heate being equally dispersed, constant and universall, without flame or blazing, without smoake, and without that wind which the tonnels of our chimnies bring us, may many ways be compared unto ours. Why do we not imitate the Romanes architecture? It is reported that in ancient times they made no fire in their houses, but without and at the foote of them; Whence by tonnels, which were convaide through their thickest wals, and contrived near and about all such places as they would have warmed; so that the heat was convaied into every part of the house. Which I have seen manifestly described in some place of Seneca, though I can not well remember where. This Germane, hearing me commend the beauties and commodities of this City (which truely deserveth great commendation), beganne to pity me, because I was shortly to go from it. And the first inconvenience he urged me withall was the heaviness in the head which Chimnies in other places would cause me. He had heard some other body complain of it, and therefore alleadged the same against me, being wont by custom to perceive it in such as came to him. All heat coming from fire does weaken and dull me; Yet said Evenus, that fire was the best sauce of life. I rather allow and embrace any other manner or way to escape cold. We fear our Wines when they are low; whereas in Portugall the fum e of it is counted delicious, and is the drinke of Princes. To conclude, each severall Nation has diverse customs, fashions and usages, which to some others are not only onknowne and strange, but savage, barbarous, and wondrous. What shall we do unto that people that admit no witness except printed; that will not believe men if not printed in Bookes, nor credit truth unless it be of competent age? We dignifie our fopperies when we put them to the press. It is another manner of weight for him to say, I have seen it, then if you say I have heard it reported. But I, who misbelieve no more the mouth than the hand of men, and know that men write as indiscreetly as they speak unadvisedly, and esteeme of this present age as of another past, alleadge as willingly a friend of mine as Aulus Gellius or Macrobius, and what my self have seen as that they have written. And as they accompt virtue to be nothing greater by being longer, so deem I truth to be nothing wiser by being more aged. I often say it is meere folly that makes us run after strange and scholasticall examples. The fertility of them is now equall unto that of Homer and Platoes times. But is it not that we rather seek the Honour of allegations than the truth of discourses? As if it were more to borrow our proofes from out the shop of Vascosan or Plantin, then from that we dayly see in our village. Or verily that we have not the wit to blanch, sift out, or make that to prevaile which passeth before us, and forcibly judge of it to draw the same into example. For if we say that authority failes us to adde credit unto our testimony, we speak from the purpose. Forasmuch as in my conceit, could we but find out their true light, Natures greatest miracles and the most wonderful examples, namely, upon the subject of humane actions, may be drawne and formed from most ordinary, most common and most known things. Now concerning my subject, omiting the examples I know by bookes, And that which Aristotle speaks of Andron of Argos, that he would travell all over the scorching sands of Lybia without drinking: A Gentleman, who has worthily acquitted himself of many honorable charges, reported where I was, that in the parching heate of Summer he had travelled from Madrid to Lisbone without ever drinking. His age respected, he is in very good and healthy plight, and has nothing extraordinary in the course or custom of his life saving (as himself has told me) that he can very well continue two or three moneths, indeed a whole yeere, without any manner of beverage. He sometimes finds himself thirsty, but lets it pass, and holds that it is an appetit which will easily and of itself languish away; and if he drinke at any time it is more for a caprice or humor than for any need or pleasure. See here one of another key. It is not long since that I found, one of the wisest men of France (among those of so meane fortune) studying hard in the corner of a great Hall, which for that purpose was hung about with tapistry, and round about him a disordered rable of his servants, groomes and lackeis, pratling, playing and hoyting; who told me (as Seneca in a manner says of himself) that he learn’d and profited much by that burly-burly or tintimare, as if beaten with that confused noyse he did so much the better recall and close himself into himself for serious contemplation; and that the said tempestuous rumours did strike and repercusse his thoughts inward. Whilst he was a scholler in Padua his study was ever placed so near the jangling of bels, the ratling of coaches, and rumbling tumults of the market place, that for the service of his study he was faine not only to frame and enure himself to contemne, but to make good use of that turbulent noise. Socrates answered Alcibiades, who wondered how he could endure the continuall tittle-tattle and incessant scoulding of his Wife, even as those who are accustomed to hear the ordinary creaking of the squeaking wheeles of wells. My self am cleane contrary, for I have a tender braine, and easy to take snuffe in the nose or to be transported. If my mind be busie alone, the least stirring, indeed, the buzzing of a flie does trouble and distemper the same. Seneca in his youth, having earnestly undertaken to follow the example of Sextius, to feed on nothing that were taken dead, could with pleasure (as himself averreth) live so a whole yeere. And left it only because he would not be suspected to borrow this rule from some new religions that instituted the same. He therewithall followed some precepts of Attalus, not to lie upon any kind of carpets or bedding that would yield under one; and until he grew very aged he never used but such as were very hard and unyielding to the body. What the custom of his dayes makes him accompt rudenesse, ours makes us esteeme wantonnesse. Behold the difference betweene my varlets life and mine. The Indians have nothing further from my form and strength. Well I wot that I have heretofore taken boyes from begging, and that went roaguing up and down to serve me, hoping to do some good upon them, who have within a little while after left me, my fare and my livery, only that they might without controule or checke follow their former idle loytring life. One of which I found not long since gathering of muskles in a common sincke for his dinner, whom (do what I could) I was never able, neyther with entreaty to reclaime, nor by threatning to withdraw from the sweetness he found in want, and delight he felt in roaguing lazinesse. Even vagabondine roagues, as well as rich men, have their magnificences and voluptuousness, and (as some say) their dignities, preheminences and politike orders. They are effects of custom and use; and what is bred in the bone will never out of the flesh. Both which have power to enure and fashion us, not only to what form they please (therefore, say the wise, ought we to be addressed to the best, and it will immediately seem easy unto us), but also to change and variation. Which is the noblest and most profitable of their apprentisages? The best of my corporall complexions is that I am flexible and little opiniative. I have certain inclinations, more proper and ordinary, and more pleasing than others. But with small adoe and without compulsion, I can easily leave them and embrace the contrary. A yong man should trouble his rules to stir-up his vigor, and take heed he suffer not the same to grow faint, sluggish, or teasty; For there is no course of life so weake and sottish as that which is mannaged by Order, Methode, and Discipline. Ad primum lapidem vectari cum placet, hora Sumitur ex libro, si prurit frictus ocelli Angulus, inspecta genesi collyria quanerit. -- Juven. Sat. vi. 477. List he to ride in coach but to Mile-end, By th’Almanacke be does the hour attend: If his eye-corner itch, the remedy, He fets from calculation of nativity. If he believe me be shall often give himself unto all manner of excess; otherwise the least disorder wil utterly overthrow him, and so make him unfit and unwelcome in all conversations. The most contrary quality in an honest man is nice-delicatenesse, and to be tied to one certain particular fashion. It is particular, if it be not supple and pliable. It is a kind of reproch, through impuissance, not to do or not to dare what one seeth his other companions do or dare. Let such men keep their kitchin. It is undecent in all other men, but vitious and intolerable in one professing Armes, who (as Philopoemen said) should fashion himself to all manner of inequality and diversity of life. I have (as much as might be) been inured to liberty and fashioned to indifferency, yet in growing aged I have through carelesnesse relied more upon certain formes (my age is now exempted from institution, and has not any thing else to looke unto but to maintaine itself) which custom has already, without thinking on it, certain things so well imprinted her character in me, that I deem it a kind of excess to leave them. And without long practise I can neither sleepe by day, nor eate betweene meales, nor break my fast, nor go to bed without some entermission (as of three hours after supper), nor get children but before I fall asleepe, and that never standing, nor bear my own sweate, nor quench my thirst either with clear water or wine alone, nor continue long bare-headed, nor have mine hair cut after dinner. And I could as hardly spare my gloves as my shirt, or forbeare washing of my hands both in the mornng and rising from the table, or lie in a bed without a testerne and curtaines about it, as of most necessary things. I could dine without a tablecloth, but hardly without a cleane napkin, as Germans commonly do. I foul and sully them more then either they or the Italians, and I seldom use either spoone or forke. I am sory we follow not a custom which, according to the example of Kings, I have seen begunne by some, that upon every course or change of dish, as we have shift of cleane trenchers, so we might have change of cleane napkins. We read that that laborious souldier Marius, growing olde, grew more nicely delicate in his drinking, and would taste no drincke except in a peculiar cuppe of his. As for me, I observe a kind of like methode in glasses, and of one certain form, and drinke not willingly in a common-glasse, no more than of one ordinary hand. I mislike all manner of metall in regard of a bright transparent matter: let mine eyes also have taste of what I drinke according to their capacity. I am beholding to custom for many such nicenesses and singularities. Nature has also on the other side bestowed this upon me, that I can not well brooke two full meales in one day without surcharging my [stomacke]; nor the meere abstinence of one without filling my self with winde, drying my mouth, and dulling my appetite; And I do find great offence by a long sereine or night-calme. For some yeeres since, in the out-roades or night-services that happen in times of wars, which many times continue all night, five or sixe hours after my stomacke beginnes to qualme, my head feeleth a violent aking, so that I can hardly hold-out till morning without vomiting. When others go to breakefast, I go to sleepe, and within a while after I shall be as fresh and jolly as before. I ever thought that the serein never fell but in the shutting in of night, but having in these latter yeeres long time frequented very familiarly the conversation with a Gentleman possessed with this opinion, that it is more sharpe and dangerous about the declination of the Sunne, an hour or two before it set, which he carefully eschews and despiseth that which falls at night, he has gone about to persuade and imprint into me, not only his discourse, but also his conceit. What if the very doubt and inquisition woundeth our imagination and chanceth us? Such as altogether yielde to these bendings draw the whole ruine upon themselves. And I bewaile diverse Gentlemen, who being young and in perfect health, have by the ignorant foolishnes of their Physitians brought themselves into consumptions and other lingering diseases, and, as it were, in Physicks fetters. Were it not much better to be troubled with a rheume, than for ever through discustome, in an action of so great use and consequence, lose the commerce and conversation of common life? Oh, yrkesome learning! Oh, Science full of molestation, that wasteth us the sweetest hours of the day! Let us extend our possession unto the utmost means. A man shall at last, in opinionating himself, harden and enure himself for it, and so correct his complexion, as did Cæsars the falling sicknesse, with contemning and corrupting the same. A man should apply himself to the best rules, but not subject himself unto them: except to such (if any there be) that duty and thraldome unto them be profitable. Both Kings and Philosophers obey nature, and go to the stoole, and so do Ladies. Publike lives are due unto ceremony; mine, which is obscure and private, enjoyeth all natural dispensations. To be a Souldier and a Gascoyne are qualities somewhat subject to indiscretion. And I am both. Therefore will I say this much of this action, that it is requisite we should remit the same unto certain prescribed night-hours, and by custom (as I have done) force and subject ourselves unto it; But not (as I have done), growing in yeeres, strictly tie himself to the care of a particular convenient place, and of a commodious Ajax or easy close-stoole for that purpose, and make it troublesome with long sitting and nice observation. Nevertheless, in homeliest matters and fowlest offices, is it not in some sort excusable to require more care and cleanlinesse? Natura homo mundum et elegans animi est: (SEN. Epist. xcii.) ’By nature man is a cleanely and neate creature.’ Of all natural actions, there is none wherein I am more loath to be troubled or interrupted when I am at it. I have seen diverse great men and soldiers much troubled and vexed with their bellies untune and disorder, when at untimely hours it calleth upon them; whilst mine and my self never misse to call one upon another at our appointment, which is as soone as I get out of my bed, except some urgent business or violent sicknesse trouble me. Therefore, as I said, I judge no place where sicke men may better seate themselves in security then quietly and wisht to hold themselves in that course of life wherein they have been brought up and habituated. Any change or variation soever astonishes and distempereth. Will any believe that Chestnuttes can hurt a Perigordin or a Luquois, or that milke or whit-meates are hurtful unto a mountaine dwelling people? whom if one seek to divert from their natural diet, he shall not only prescribe them a new but a contrary form of life: A change which healthy man can hardly endure? Appoint a Bretton of threescore yeeres of age to drinke water; put a sea-man or Mariner into a Stove; forbid a lackey of Baske to walke: you bring them out of their element, you deprive them of all motion, and in the end of aire, of light, and life. ------ an vivere tanti est? Doe we reckon it so dear, Only living to be here? Cogimur a suctis animum suspendere rebus Atque ut vivamus, vivere desinimus: -- Cor. Gal. El. i. 155. From things erst us’d we must suspend our mind, We leave to live that we may live by kind. Hos superesse reor quibus et spirabilis ær, Et lux quia regimur, redditur ipsa gravis. Doe I think they live longer whom does grieve Both aire they breathe and light whereby they live. If they do no other good, at least they do this, that betimes they prepare their patients unto death, by little undermining and cutting-off the use of life. Both in health and in sicknesse I have willingly seconded and given my self over to those appetites that pressed me. I allow great authority to my desires and propensions. I love not to cure one evil by another mischief. I hate those remedies that importune more than sicknesse. To be subject to the cholike, and to be tied to abstaine from the pleasure I have in eating of oysters, are two mischiefes for one. The disease pincheth us the one side, the rule on the other. Since we are ever in danger to misdoe, let us rather hazard ourselves to follow pleasure. Most men do contrary and think nothing profitable that is not painefull; Facility is by them suspected. Mine appetite has in diverse things very happily accommodated and ranged itself to the health of my stomake. Being yong, acrimony and tartnesse in sawces did greatly delight me, but my stomacke being since glutted therewith, my taste has likewise seconded the same. Wine hurts the sicke; it is the first thing that with an invincible distaste brings my mouth out of taste. Whatsoever I receive unwillingly or distastefully hurts me, whereas nothing does it whereon I feed with hunger and rellish. I never received harme by any action that was very pleasing unto me. And yet I have made all medicinall conclusions largely to yield to my pleasures. And when I was yong - Quem circumcursans huc atque huc sæpe Cupido Fulgebat crocina splendidus in tunica. -- Catul. El. iv. 131. About whom Cupid running here and there, Shinde in the saffron coate which he did weare. I have as licentiously and inconsiderately as any other furthred al such desires as possessed me; Et milita vi non sine gloria. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. xxvi. 2. A Souldier of loves hoast, I was not without boast. More notwithstanding in continuation and holding out, then by snatches or by stealth. Sex me vix mentini sustinuisse vices. I scarce remember past Six courses I could last. It is surely a wonder accompanied with unhappinesse, to confesse how young and weake I was brought under its subjection. Nay, shall I not blush to tell it? It was long before the age of choise or yeeres of discretion; I was so young, as I remember nothing before. And fitly may my fortune be compared to that of Quartilla, who remembred not her maydenhead. Inde tragus celeresque pili, mirandaque matri Barba meæ. Thence goatishnesse, haires over-soone, a beard To make my mother wonder and afear’d. Physitians commonly enfold and join their rules unto profit, according to the violence of sharpe desires or earnest longings, that incidently follow the sicke; No longing desire can be imagined so strange and vicious, but nature will apply herself unto it. And then how easy is it to content ones fantasie? In mine opinion, this part importeth all in all; at least more and beyond all other. The most grievous and ordinary evils are those which fancy chargeth us withall. That Spanish saying does every way please me: Deffienda me Dios de my: ’God defend me from my self.’ Being sicke, I am sory I have not some desire may give me the contentment to satiate and cloy the same; Scarsly would a medicine divert me from it. So do I when I am in health: I hardly see any thing left to be hoped or wished-for. It is pity a man should be so weakned and enlanguished that he has nothing left him but wishing. The art of Physicke is not so resolute, that whatsoever we do, we shall be void of all authority to do it Shee cliangeth and she varieth according to climate; according to the Moones; according to Fernelius, and according to Scala. If your Physitian think it not good that you sleepe, that you drinke wine, or eate such and such meates, Care not you for that, I will find you another that shall not be of his opinion. The diversity of physicall arguments and medicinall opinions embraceth all manner of formes. I saw a miserable sicke man, for the infinite desire he had to recover, ready to burst, indeed and to die with thirst; whom not long since another Physitian mocked, utterly condemning the others counsell as hurtful for him. Had not be bestowed his labor well? A man of that coate is lately dead of the stone, who during the time of his sicknesse used extreme abstinence to withstand his evil; his fellowes affirme that, contrary, his long fasting had withered and dried him up, and so concocted the gravell in his kidnies. I have found that in my hurts and other sicknesses, earnest talking distempers and hurts me as much as any disorder I commit. My voice costs me dear, and wearieth me; for I have it lowd, shrill and forced, So that, when I have had occasion to entertaine the ears of great men about weighty affairs, I have often troubled them with care how to moderate my voice. This story deserveth to be remembred and to divert me. A certain man in one of the Greeke schooles spake very lowde, as I do; the maister of the ceremonies sent him word he should speak lower: let him (quoth he) send me the tune or key in which he would have me speak. The other replied, that he should take his tune from his ears to whom he spake. It was well said, so he understood himself: Speake according as you have to do with your auditory. For if one say, let it suffice that he heareth you, or governe yourselfe by him; I do not think he had reason to say so. The tune or motion of the voice has some expression or signification of my meaning. It is in me to direct the same, that so I may the better represent my self. There is a voice to instruct, one to flatter, and another to chide. I will not only have my voice come to him, but perhaps to wound and pierce him. When I brawle and rate my lackey with a sharpe and piercing tune, were it fit he should come to me and say, ’Master, speak softly, I understand and hear you very well? Est quædam vox ad auditum accommodate non magnitudine sed proprietate: ’There is a kind of voice well applied to the hearing, not by the greatness of it, but by the proprietie.’ The word is halfe his that speaks and halfe his that harkeneth unto it. the hearer ought to prepare himself to the motion or bound it taketh. As betweene those that play at tennis, he who keepes the hazard does prepare, stand stir and march, according as he perceives him who stands at the house, to looke, stand, remoove and strike the ball, and according to the stroake. Experience has also taught me this, that we lose ourselves with impatience. Evils have their life, their limits, their diseases and their health. The constitution of diseases is framed by the patterne of the constitution of living creatures. They have their fortune limited even at their birth, and their dayes allotted them. He that shall imperiously go about, or by compulsion (contrary to their courses) to abridge them, does lengthen and multiply them; and in stead of appeasing, does harsell and wring them. I am of Crantors opinion, that a man must neither obstinately nor frantikely oppose himself against evils; nor through demissenesse of courage faintingly yield unto them, but according to their condition and ours naturally incline to them. A man must give sickenesses their passage. And I find that they stay least with me, because I allow them their swinge, and let them do what they list. And contrary to common received rules, I have without ayde or art ridde my self of some that are deemed the most obstinately lingring and unremoovably-obstinate. Let nature work; Let her have her will; She knows what she has to do, and understands herself better then we do. But such a one died of it, wil you say; so shal you doubtlesse; if not of that, yet of some other disease. And how many have we seen die when they have had a whole Colledge of Pbysitians round about their bed, and looking in their excrements? Example is a bright looking- glasse, universall and for all shapes to looke into. If it be a lushious or taste-pleasing portion, take it hardly; it is ever so much present ease. So it be delicious and sweetly tasting, I will never stand much upon the name or colour of it. Pleasure is one of the chiefest kinds of profit. I have suffered rheumes, gowty defluxions, relaxions, pantings of the heart, megreimes and other such-like accidents, to grow old in me, and die their natural death; all which have left me when I halfe enured and framed my self to foster them. They are better conjured by curtesie then by bragging or threats. We must gently obey and endure the laws of our condition. We are subject to grow aged, to become weake and to fall sicke, in spight of all physicke. It is the first lesson the Mexicans give their children; When they come out of their mothers wombes, they thus salute them: My child, you are come into the world to suffer; Therefore suffer and hold your peace. It is injustice for one to grieve, that any thing has befallen to any one, which may happen to all men. Indignare, si quid in te inique proprie constitutum est: Then take it ill, if any thing be decreed uniustl y against you alone.’ Looke on an aged man, who sueth unto God to maintaine him in perfect, full and vigorous health; that is to say, he will be pleased to make him yong again: Stulte quid hæc frustra votis puerilibus optas? -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. viii. 11. Foole, why do you in vain desire, With childish prayers thus t’ aspire? Is it not folly? His condition will not bear it. The gowt, the stone, the gravell, and indigestion are symptomes or effects of long-continued years; as heats, raines and winds, are incident to long voyages. Plato cannot believe that Æsculapius troubled himself with good rules and diet to provide for the preservation of life, in a weake, wasted, and corrupted body; being unprofitable for his country, inconvenient for his vocation, and unfit to get sound and sturdy Children; and deem not that care inconvenient unto divine justice and heavenly Wisedome, which is to direct all things unto profit. My good sir, the matter is at an end. You cannot be recovered; for the most, you can be but tampered withall, and somewhat under propt, and for some hours have your misery prolonged. Non secus instantem cupiens fulcire ruina Diversis contra nititur obicibus, Donec certa dies, omni compage soluta, Ipsum cum rebus subruat auxilium. -- Corn. Gal. El. clxxiii. So he that would an instant ruine stay With diverse props strives it underlay, Till all the frame dissolv’d a certain day, The props with the edifice does oversway. A man must learne to endure that patiently which he cannot avoyde conveniently. Our life is composed, as is the harmony of the World, of contrary things; so of diverse tunes, some pleasant, some harsh, some sharpe, some flat, some low, and some high. What would that Musition say that should love but some one of them? He ought to know how to use them severally and how to entermingle them. So should we both of goods and evils which are consubstantiall to our life. Our being cannot subsist without this commixture, whereto one side is no less necessary than the other. To go about to kicke against natural necessity were to represent the folly of Ctesiphon, who undertook to strike or wince with his mule. I consult but little about the alterations which I feel: For these kind of men are advantagious when they hold you at their mercy. They glut your ears with their Prognostications, and surprising me heretofore, when by my sicknesse I was brought very low and weake, they have injuriously handled me with their Doctrines, positions, prescriptions, magistrall fopperies, and prosopopeyall gravity; sometimes threatning me with great pain and smart, and other times menacing me with near and unavoydable death; All which did indeede move, stir and touch me near, but could not dismay or remoove me from my place or resolution; If my judgement be thereby neither changed nor troubled, it was at least hindred; It is ever in agitation and combating. Now I entreate my imagination as gently as I can, and were it in my power I would cleane discharge it of all pain and contestation. A man must further, help, flatter, and (if he can) cozen and deceive it. My spirit is fit for that office: There is no want of apparances every where. Did he persuade as he preacheth he should successefully ayde me. Shall I give you an example? He tells me it is for my good that I am troubled with the gravell: That the compositions of my age must naturally suffe some leake or flaw; It is time they begin to relent and gainesay themselves: It is a common necessity, And it had been no new wonder for me. Tha t way I pay the reward due unto age, and I could have no better reckoning of it. That such company ought to comfort me, being fallen into the most ordinary accident incident to men of my dayes. I every where see some afflicted with the same kind of evil, whose society is honorable unto me, forasmuch as it commonly possesseth the better sort of men, and whose essence has a certain nobility and dignity connexed unto it; That of men tormented therewith, few are better cheape quit of it, and yet it costs them the pain of a troublesome dyet, tedious regiment, and daily loathsome taking of medicinall drugges and physicall potions; Whereas I meerely owe it to my good fortune; For some ordinary broths made of Eringos or Sea-Holme, and Burstwort, which twice or thrice I have swallowed down at the request of some Ladies, who, more kindely then my disease is unkind, offred me the moity of theirs, have equally seemed unto me as easy to take as unprofitable in operation. They must pay a thousand vows unto Æsculapius, and as many crownes to their Physition, for an easy profluvion or aboundant running of gravell, which I often receive by the benefit of nature. Let me be in any company, the decency of my countenance is thereby nothing troubled, and I can hold my water full tenne hours and if neede be as long as any man that is in perfect health. The fear of this evil, says he, did heretofore affright you when yet it was unknown to you. The cries and despaire of those who through their impatience exasperate the same, bred a horror of it in you. It is an evil that comes and fals into those limbs by and with which you most most offended. Thou art a man of concience: Quæ venit indigne poena, dolenda venit. -- Ovid. Epist. v. 8. The pain that comes without desart, Comes to us with more grief and smart. Consider but how mild the punishment is in respect of others, and how favourable. Consider his slowenesse in coming, he only incommodeth that state and encombreth that season of your life which (all things considered) is now become barren and lost, having as it were by way of composition, given place unto the sensuall licenciousnesse and wanton pleasures of your youth. The fear and pity men have of this evil may serve you as a cause of glory; A quality whereof, if your judgement be purified and your discourse perfectly sound, your friends do notwithstanding discover some sparkes in your complexion. It is some pleasure for a man to hear others say of him, See there a patterne of true fortitude; lo there a mirroiir of matchlesse patience. Thou art seen to sweate with labor, to grow pale and wanne, to wax red, to quake and tremble, to cast and vomit blood, to endure strange contractions, to brooke convulsions, to trill down brackish and great tears, to make thicke, muddy, blacke, bloody, and fearefull urine, or to have it stopt by some sharpe or rugged stone, which pricketh and cruelly wrin geth the necke of the yarde, entertaining in the meane while the bystanders with an ordinary and undanted countenance, by pawses jesting and by entermissions dallying with your servants, keeping a part in a continued discourse, with words now and then excusing your griefs and abating your painefull sufferance. Dost you remember those men of former ages, who, to keep their virtue in breath and exercise, did with such greedinesse seek after evils? Suppose Nature driveth and brings you unto that glorious School into which you hadst never come of thine own accord and free will. If you tell me it is a dangerous and mortal evil, what others are not so? For it is a kind of physicall cousenage to except any, and so they go directly unto death; what matter it is whether they go by accident unto it, and easily slide on either hand toward the way that leadeth us thereunto? But you diest not because you are sicke; you diest because you are living. Death is able to kill you without the helpe of any sicknesse; Sicknesses have to some prolonged their death, who have lived the longer, inasmuch as they imagined they were still dying; Seeing it is of wounds as of diseases, that some are medicinall and wholesome. The chollike is often no less long- lived than you; Many are seen in whom it has continued even from their infancy unto their extreamest age, who had they, not forsaken her company, she was like to have assisted them further. You oftner kill her than she does you. And if she did present you with the image of neer-imminent death, were it not a kind office for a man of that age to reduce it unto the cogitations of his end? And which is worse, you hast no longer cause to be cured; Thus and however common necessity calls for you against the first day. Consider but how artificially and how mildely she brings you in distaste with life and out of liking with the world, not forcing you with a tyrannical subjection as infinit other diseases do, wherewith you seest old men possessed, which continually hold them fettered and ensnared, and without release of weaknesse nor intermission of paines but by advertisements and instructions, reprised by intervalles, entermixiiig certain pawses of rest, as if it were to give you meane at your ease to meditate and repeat her lesson; To give you leisure and ability to judge soundly, and like a man of a courage to take a resolulution, she presents you with the state of your condition perfect, both in good and evil, and in one same day sometimes a most pleasing, sometimes a most intolerable life. If you embrace not death, at least you shakest her by the hand once a moneth; Whereby you least more cause to hope that she will one aay surprise you without threatning; And that being so often brought into the haven, supposing to be still in your accustomed state, one morning at unawares, both your self and your confidence shall be transported over. A man has no reason to complain against those diseases which so equally divide time with health. I am beholding to Fortune that she so often assailes me with one same kind of weapon: she by long use does fashion and enure me unto it, harden and habituate me thereunto: I now know within a little which way and how I shall be quit. For want of natural memory I frame some of paper, And when some new symptome or accident commeth to my evil I set it down in writing, whence it proceedeth that having now (in a manner) passed over and through all sorts of examples, if any astonishment threaten me, running and turning over these my loose memorialles (as Sibyllæs leaves) I misse no more to find to comfort me with some favourable prognostication in my former past experience. Custome does also serve me to hope the better hereafter; For the conduct of this distribution having so long been constituted, it is to be supposed that Nature will not change this course, and no other worse accident shall follow then that I feel. Moreover, the condition of this disease is not ill seeming to my ready and sodaine complexion. When it but faintly assailes me it makes me afraid, because it is like to continue long; But naturally it has certain vigorous and violent excesses; It does violently shake me for one or two dayes. My reines have continued a whole age without alteration, an other is now well-nigh come, that they have changed state. Evils as well as goods have their periods; this accident is happily come to his last. Age weakneth the heat of my stomacke, his digestion being thereby less perfect he sendeth this crude matter to my reines. Why may not, at a certain revolution, the heat of my reines be likewise infeabled, so that they may no longer putrifie my fleagme, and Nature addresse herself to find some other course of purgation? Yeares have evidently made me drie up certain rheumes, and why not these excrements that minister matter to the stone or gravell. But is there anything so pleasant in respect of this sodaine change when by an extreaine pain I come by the voyding of my stone, to recover, as from a lightning, the fair Sunne-shine of health; so free and full, as it happeneth in our sodaine and most violent cholliks? Is there anything in this pain suffered that may be counter poised to the sweet pleasure of so ready an amendment? By how much more health seems fairer unto me after sicknesse, so near and so contiguous, that I may know them in presence one of another, in their richest ornaments; wherein they attyre themselves avy, as it were confront and counterchecke one another. Even as the Stoices say, that Vices were profitably brought in, to give esteeme and make head unto virtue; So may we with better reason and bold conjecture affirme that Nature has lent us grief and pain, for the honor of pleasure and service of indolency. When Socrates (after he had his yrons or fetters taken from him) felt the pleasure or tickling of that itching which their weight and rubbing had caused in his legs, be rejoiced to consider the near affinity that was between pain and pleasure; how they combined together by a necessary bond, so that at times they enter-engender and succeed one another; and cry out to good Æsope, that he should from that consideration have taken a proper body unto a quaint fable. The worst I see in other diseases is, that they are not so grievous in their effect as in their issue. A man is a whole yeare to recover himself; ever full of weaknesse, alwayes full of fear. There is so much hazard and so many degrees before one can be brought to safety, that he is never at an end. Before you can leave off your coverchiefe and then your nightcap, before you can brooke the air again or leave leave to drinke Wine, or lie with your Wife or eate melons, it is much if you fall not into some relapse or new misery. The gravell has this priviledge, that it is cleane carried away; Whereas other maladies leave ever some impression and alteration, which leaveth the body susceptible or undertaking of some new infirmity, and they lend one an other their hands. Such are to be excused, as are contented with the possession they have over us, without extending the same, and without introducing their sequell; But curteous, kind and gracious are those, whose passage brings some profitable consequence. Since I have had the stone-chollike, I find myself discharged of other accidents; more (as me thinks) then I was before, and never had ague since. I argue that the extreme and frequent vomits I endure, purge me; and on the other side, the distastes and strange abstinences I tolerate, disgest my offending humors; and Nature voydeth in these stones and gravell whatsoever is superfluous and hurtful in her. Let no man tell me that it is a medicine too dear sold; For, what avail so many loath-some pils, stincking potions, cauterizings, incisions, sweatings, setons, dyets, and so diverse fashions of curing, which, because we are not able to undergoe their violence and brooke their importunity, do often bring us unto our graves? And therefore, when I am surprised, I take it as physicke; and when I am free, I take it as a constant and full deliverance. See here an other particular favor of my disease, which is, that he in a manner keepes his play a-part, and lets me keep my own; or else I want but courage to do it. In his greatest emotion I have held out tenne hours on Horse- backe with him. Doe but endure, you neede no other rule or refgiment. Play, dally, dyne, run, be gamesome, do this, and if you can do the other thing, your disorder and debauching will rather avail than hurt it. Say thus much to one that has the pox, or to one that has the gowt, or to one that is belly-broken or cod-burst. Other infirmities have more universall bonds, torment far-otherwise our actions, pervert all our order, and engage all the state of mans life unto their consideration. Whereas this does only twitch and pinch the skin, it neyther meddles with your understanding, nor with your will, tongue, feete, nor hands, but leaves them all in your disposition; it rather rouzeth and awaketh you, then deterre and drouzy you. The mind is wounded by the burning of a feaver, suppressed by an Epilepsie, confounded by a migrane, and in conclusion astonied and dismayed by all the diseases that touch or wound the whole masse of his body and its noblest parts. This never meddles with it. If therefore it go ill with it, his be the blame she bewrayeth, she forsaketh, and she displaceth herself. None but fools will be persuaded that this hard, gretty and massie body, which is concocted and petrified in our kidneis, maybe dissolved by drinks. And therefore after it is stirred there is no way but to give it passage; For if you do not he will take it himself. This other peculiar commodity I observe, that it is an infirmity wherein we have but little to divine. We are dispensed from the trouble whereinto other maladies cast us, by the uncertainty of their causes, conditions, and progresses. A trouble infinitly painfull. We have no need of doctorall consultations or collegian interpretations. Our senses tell us where it is and what it is. By and with such arguments, forcible or weake (as Cicero does the infirmity of his old-age), I endeavor to lull asleepe and study to ammuse my imagination, and supple or annoint her sores. If they grow worse, to morrow, to morrow we shall provide far new remedies or escapes. That this is true, lo afterward again, perhaps the lightest motion wrings pure blood out of my reines. And what of that? I omit not to stir as before, and with a youthfull and insolent heate ride after my hound. And find that I have great reason of so important an accident, which costs me but a deafe heaviness and dombe alteration in that part. It is some great stone that wasteth and consumeth the substance of my kidneis and my life, which I avoyde by little and little; not without some natural pleasure, as an excrement now superfluous and trouble-some. And feel I something to shake? Expect not that I ammuse my self to feel my pulse, or looke into my urine, thereby to find or take some tedious prevention. I shall come time enough to feel the smart, without lengthening the same with the pain of fear. Who feareth to suffer, suffereth already, because he feareth. Seeing the doubt and ignorance of those who will and do meddle with expounding the drifts and shifts of nature, with her internall progresse; and so many false prognostications of their arte should make us understand her means infinitly unknown. There is great uncertainty, variety and obscurity in that she promiseth and menaceth us. Except old-age, which is an undoubted signe of deaths approching, of all other accidents, I see few signes of future things whereon we may ground our divination. I only judge my self by true- feeling sense, and not by discourse. To what end? since I will adde nothing thereunto except attention and patience. Will you know what I gain by it? Behold those who do otherwise, and who depend on so many diverse persuasions and counsels, how oft imagination presseth them without the body. I have diverse times, being in safety and free from all dangerous accidents, taken pleasure to communicate them into physicians, as but then coming upon me. I endured the arrest or doom of their horrible conclusions, and remained so much the more bounden unto God for his grace, and better instructed of the vanity of this arte. Nothing ought so much be recommended unto youth as activity and vigilancy. Our life is nothing but motion, I am hardly shaken, and am slow in all things, be it to rise, to go to bed, or to my meales. Seaven of the clocke in the morning is to me an early hour; And where I may command, I neither dine before eleven, nor sup till after six. I have heretofore imputed the cause of agues or maladies, whereinto I have falne, to the lumpish beavinesse or drowzy dulnesse which my long sleeping had caused me. And ever repented me to fall asleepe again in the morning. Plato condemnes more the excess of sleeping then the surfet of drinking. I love to lie hard and alone, indeed without a woman by me, after the kingly manner; somewhat well and warme covered. I never had my bed warmed, but since I came to be an old man, if need require, I have clothes given me to warme my feete and my stomacke. Great Scipio was taxed to be a sluggard or heavy sleeper (in my conceit) for no other cause but that men were offended; he only should be the man in whom no fault might justly be found. If there be any curiosity in my behaviour or manner of life, it is rather about my going to bed then any thing else; but if neede be, I generally yield and accommodate my self unto necessity, as well and as quietly as any other whosoever. Sleeping has possessed a great part of my life; and as old as I am I can sleepe eight or nine hours together. I do with profit withdraw myself from this sluggish propension and evidently find my self better by it. Indeede, I somewhat feel the stroke of alteration, but in three dayes it is past. And I see few that live with less (when need is), and that more constantly exercise themselves, nor whom toyling and labor offend less. My body is capable of a firme agitation, so it be not vehement and sodaine. I avoide violent exercises, and which induce me to sweate; my limbs will sooner be wearied then heated. I can stand a whole day long, and am seldom weary with walking. Since my first age, I ever loved rather to ride then walke upon paved streets. Going a foote, I shall durty my self up to my waste; and little men, going alongst our streets, are subject (for want of presentiall apparence) to be justled or elhowed. I love to take my rest, be it sitting or lying-along, with my legs as high or higher then my seate. No profession or occupation is more pleasing then the military; A profession or exercise both noble in execution (for the strongest, most generous and prowdest of all vertues, is true valor) and noble in its cause. No utility, either more just or universall then the protection of the repose or defense of the greatness of ones country. The company and dayly conversation of so many noble, young, and active men, cannot but be well-pleasing to you; the dayly and ordinary sight of so diverse tragical spectacles; the liberty and uncontroled freedome of that artelesse and unaffected conversation, masculine and ceremonilesse manner of life; the hourely variety of a thousand ever changing and differing actions; the courageous and mind stirring harmony of warlike music, which at once entertaineth with delight and enflameth with longing, both your ears and your mind; the imminent and matchlesse honor of that exercise; indeed the very sharpnesse and difficulty of it, which Plato esteemeth so little, that in his imaginary commonwealth he imparteth the same both to women and to children. As a voluntary Souldier or adventurous Knight you enter the lists, the bands or particular hazards, according as your self judge of their successes or importance; and you see when your life may therein be excusably employed. Pulchrumque mori succurrit in armis. -- Virg. Æn. [ii]. 317. And nobly it does come in mind, To die in arms may honor find. Basely to fear common dangers, that concerne so numberlesse a multitude, and not to dare what so many men dare, indeed whole nations together, is only incident to base, craven, and milke-sop-hearts. Company and good fellowshipp does harten and encorage children. If some chance to exceed and outgoe you in knowledge, in experience, in grace, in strength, in fortune, you have third and collaterall causes to blame and take hold-of; but to yield to them in constancy of mind and resolution of courage, you have none but your self to find fault with. Death is much more abject, languishing, grisly, and paineful in a down-bed, then in a field-combate; and agues, catarres or apoplexies, as painefull and mortal as an harquebusado. He that should be made undantedly to bear the accidents of common life, should not nee4 to bumbast his courage, to become a man at arms. Vivere, mi Lucilli, militare est: (Sen. Epist. xcvi. f.) ’Friend mine, to live is to go on war-fare.’ I cannot remember that ever I was scabbed, yet is itching one of natures sweetest gratifications, and as ready at hand. But repentance does over-importunately attend on it. I exercise the same in mine ears (and by fits) which within do often itch. I was borne with al my senses sound, almost in perfection. My stomacke is commodiously good, and so is my head; both which, together with my winde, maintaine themselves athwart my agues. I have outlived that age to which some nations have not without some reason prescribed for a just end unto life, that they allowed not a man to exceed the same. I have notwithstanding some remyses or intermissions yet, though unconstant and short, so sound and neate that there is little difference between them and the health and indolency of my youth. I speak not of youthly vigor and chearefull blithnesse; there is no reason they should follow me beyond their limits: Non hæc amplius est liminis, aut aquæ Coelestis, patiens latus. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. x. 15. These sides cannot still sustain Lying without doores, showring raine. My visage and eyes do presently discover me. Thence begin all my changes, and somewhat sharper then t hey are in effect. I often move my friends to pity ere I feel the cause of it. My looking-glasse does not amaze me, for even in my youth it has diverse times befalne me so to put-on a dusky looke, a wan colour, a troubled behaviour and of ill presage, without any great accident; so that physicians perceiving no inward cause to answer this outward alteration, ascribed the same to the secret mind or some concealed passion, which inwardly gnawed and consumed me. They were deceived; were my body directly by me, as is my my mind, we should march a little more at our ease. I had it then, not only exempted from all trouble, but also full of satisfaction and blithenesse, as it is most commonly, partly by its own complexion, and partly by its own design: Nec vitiant artus ægræ contagia mentis. -- Ovid. Trist. iii. El. viii. 25. Nor does sicke mindes infection Pollute strong joints complexion. I am of opinion that this her temperature has often raised my body from his fallings: he is often suppressed, whereas she, if not lasciviously wanton, at least in quiet and reposed estate. I had a quartan ague which held me foure or five moneths, and had altogether disvisaged and altered my countenance, yet my mind held ever out, not only peaceably but pleasantly. So I feel no pain or smart; weakenesse and languishing do not greatly perplex me. I see diverse corporall defailances the only naming of which breede a kind of horror, and which I would fear less then a thousand passions and agitations of the mind which I see in use. I resolve to run no more; it sufficeth me to go-on fair and softly; nor do I complain of their natural decadence or empairing that possesseth me. Quis tumidum guttur miratur in Alpibus? -- Juven. Sat. xiii. 162. Who wonders a swolne throate to see, In those about the Alpes that be? No more then I grieve that my o ntinuance is not as long and sound as that of an oake. I have no cause to find fault with my imagination. I have in my life had very few thoughts or cares that have so much as interrupted the course of my sleepe, except of desire to awaken without dismay or afflicting me. I seldom dreame, and when I do, it is of extravagant things and chymeras, commonly produced of pleasant conceits, rather ridiculous then sorrowfull. And think it true that dreames are the true interpreters of our inclinations; but great skill is required to sort and understand them. Res quæ invita usurpant homines, cogitant, curant, vident, Quæque agunt vigilantes, agitantque ea sicut in somno accidunt Minus mirandum est. It is no wonder if the things which we Care-for, use, think, do-oft, or waking see, Unto us sleeping represented be. Plato says, moreover, that it is the office of wisdom to draw divining instructions from them against future times. Wherein I see nothing but the wonderful experience that Socrates, Xenophon, and Aristotle relate of them - men of unreproovable authority. Histories report that the inhabitants of the Atlantique Iles never dreame, who feed on nothing that has been slain. Which I adde, because it is perhaps the occasion they dreame not. Pythagoras ordained therefore a certain methode of feeding, that dreames might be sorted of some purpose. Mine are tender, and cause no agitation of body or expression of voice in me. I have in my dayes seen many strangely stirred with them. Theon the Philosopher walked in dreaming; and Pericles his boy, went upon the tiles and top of houses. I stand not much on nice choice of meates at the table, and commonly begin with the first and neerest dish, and leape not willingly from one taste to another. Multitude of dishes and variety of services displease me as much as any other throng. I am easily pleased with few messes, and hate the opinion of Favorinus, that at a banquet you must have that dish whereon you feed hungerly taken from you, and ever have a new one set in the place: And that it is a niggardly supper if all the guests be not glutted with pinions and rumps of diverse kinds of fowle, and that only the dainty bird becoafico or snapfig deserveth to be eaten whole at one morsell. I feede much upon salt cates, and love to have my bread somewhat fresh. And my own Baker makes none other for my bord, against the fashion of my country. In my youth my overseers had much a do to reforme the refusall I made of such meats as youth does commonly love best; as sweet meates, confets and marchpanes. My Tutor was wont to find great fault with my lothing of such dainties, as a kind of squeamish delicacy. And to say truth, it is nothing but a difficulty of taste, where it once is applyed. Whosoever remooveth from a child a certain particular or obstinate affection to browne bread, to bakon, or to garlike, taketh friandize from him. There are some that make it a labor and think it a patience to regret a good piece of pawdred beefe, or a good gemmon of bakon, amongst partridges. Are not they wise men in the meane time? It is the chief dainty of all dainties; It is the taste of nice effeminate fortune that wil be distasted with ordinary and usual things. Per quæ luxuria divitiarum tædio ludit: ’Whereby the lavishnesse of plenty playes with tedious pleasure.’ To for-bear to make good cheare, because another does it, for one to have care of his feeding, is the essence of that vice. Si modica cænere times olus omne patella. -- Hor. i. Ep. v. 2. If in a sorry dish to sup You brooke not all the hearbe pottage up. Indeede there is this difference, that it is better for one to tye his desires unto things easiest to be gotten, yet is it a vice to tie himself to any strictnesse. I was heretofore wont to name a kinsman of mine over-delicate, because while he lived in our Gallies, he had unlearn’t and left to lie upon a bedde and to strippe himself to go to bedde. Had I any male children I should willingly wish them my fortune. That good Father it pleased God to allot me (who has nothing of me but thankefulnesse for his goodnesse, which indeed is as great as great may be) even from my cradle sent me to be brought-up in a poore village of his, where he kept me so long as I suckt, and somewhat longer, breeding me after the meanest and simplest-common fashion. Magna pars libertatis est moratus venter: (Sen. Epist. cxxiii.) ’A mannerly belly is a great part of a mans liberty.’ Never take unto your self, and much less never give your wives the charge of your childrens breeding or education. Let fortune frame them under the popular and natural laws; Let custom enure them to frugality and breed them to hardnesse: That they may rather descend from sharpenesse than ascend unto it. His conceipt aymed also at another end, To acquaint and ready me with that people and condition of men that have most need of us; And thought I was rather bound to respect those which extend their arms unto me than such as turn their backe toward me. And that was the reason he chose no other gossips to hold me at the font than men of abject and base fortune, that so I might the more be bound and tied unto them. His purpose has not altogether succeded ill. I willingly give and accost my self unto the meaner sort, whether it be because there is more glory gotten by them, or through some natural compassion, which in me is infinitely powerfull. The faction which I condemne in our civill wars I shall more sharpely condemne when it prospers and flourisheth. I shall in some sort be reconciled unto it when I see it miserably- depressed and overwhelmed. Oh how willingly do I remember that worthy humor of Chelonis, daughter and wife to King of Sparta. While Cleombrotus, her husband, in the tumultuous disorders of his City, had the upper-hand of Leonidas her father, she played the part of a good daughter, allying herself with her father in his exile and in his misery, mainely opposing herself against the Conquerour. Did fortune turn? So changed she her mind, courageously taking her hushand’s part: Whom she never forsooke, whither-soever his ruine or distresse carryed him. Having (in my seeming) no other choise than to follow that side where she might do most good, where she was most wanted, and where she might show herself most truely pitiful. I do more naturally encline toward the example of Flamineus, who more and rather yielded to such as had need of him than to those who might do him good, than I bend unto that of Pyrrhus, who was ever wont demissely to stoop and yield to the mighty and insolently to grow proud over the weake. Long sitting at meales does much weary and distemper me, for be it for want of better countenance and entertainment, or that I used my self unto it when I was a child, I feede as long as I sitte at the table. And therefore, being in my own house, though my board be but short and that we use not to sit long, I do not commonly sit down with the first, but a pretty while after others: According to the form of Augustus, yet I imitate him not in his rising before others. Contrary, I love to sit a great while after, and to hear some discourse or table- talk. Alwayes provided I bear not a part my self, for if my belly be full I shall soone be weary and hurt my self with talking, and I find the exercise of lowde-speaking and contesting before meate very pleasant and wholesome. The ancient Greeks and Romanes had better reason than we, allotting unto feeding, which is a principal action of mans life (if any other extraordinary business did not let or divert them from it), diverse hours, and the best part of the night, eating and drinking more leisurely than we do, who pass and run-over all our actions in posthaste, and extending this natural pleasure unto more leisure and use, entermixing therewith diverse profitable and mind-pleasing offices of civill conversation. Such as have care of me may easily steale from me what soever they imagine may be hurtful for me, inasmuch as about my feeding I never desire or find fault wit h that I see not. That Proverb is verified in me: what eye seeth not, the heart rueth not. But if a dish or any thing else be once set before me, they lose their labor that go about to tell me of abstinence; so that when I am disposed to fast I must be sequestred from eaters, and have no more set before me than may serve for a stinted and regular collation; for if I but sit down at a set table I forget my resolution. If I chance to bidde my cooke change the dressing of some kind of meate or dish, all my men know I inferre my appetit is wallowish and my stomache out of order, and I shall hardly touch it. I love all manner of flesh or fowle but greene rosted and raw sodden, namely, such as may bear it without danger, and love to have them thoroughly mortified, and in diverse of them the very alteration of their smell. Only hardnesse or toughnesse of meate does generally molest me, (of all other qualities I am as carelesse and can as well brooke them as any man that ever I knew,) so that (contrary to received opinion) even amongst fishes I shall find some both too new and over-hard and firme. It is not the fault or want of teeth, which I ever had as perfectly-sound and compleate as any other man, and which but now, being so olde, beginne to threaten me. I have from my infancy learn’d to rubbe them with my napkin, both in the morning when I rise and sitting down and rising from the table. God does them a grace from which by little and little he does substract from them their life. It is the only benefit of old age. Their last death shall be so much the less full, languishing and painefull, it shal then kill but one halfe or a quarter of a man. Even now I lost one of my teeth, which of itself fell out without strugling or pain: it was the natural terme of its continuance. That part of my being with diverse others, are already dead and mortified in me, others of the most active, halfe dead, and which during the vigor of my age held the first rank. Thus I sinke and scape from my self. What foolishnes will it be in my understanding to feel the start of that fall, already so advanced, as it were perfectly whole? I hope it not; verely I receive a speciall comfort in thinking on my death, and that it will be of the most just and natural, and cannot now require or hope other favor of destiny concerning that then unlawfull. Men persuade themselves that, as heretofore they have had a higher stature, so their lives were longer; But they are deceived, for Solon, of those ancient times, though be were of an exceeding high stature, his life continued but seventy yeeres. Shal I, that have so much and so universally adored that αριοτου ετρον, a meane is best, of former times, and have ever taken a meane measure for the most perfect, therefore pretend a most prodigious and unmeasureable life? whatsoever commeth contrary to Natures course may be combersome, but what comes according to her should ever please. Omnia quæ secundum naturam fiunt, sunt habenda in bonis: ’All things are to be accompted good that are done according to nature.’ And therefore, (says Plato), is that death violent which is caused either by wounds or sicknesses; but that of all others the easiest and in some sort delitious which surpriseth us by means of age. Vitam adolescentibus vis aufert, senibus maturitas: ’A forcible violence takes their life from the young, but a ri pe maturity from the old.’ Death entermedleth and every where confounds itself with our life; declination does preoccupate her hour and insinuate itself in the very course of our advancement. I have pictures of my own that were drawne when I was five and twenty, and others being thirty yeeres of age, which I often compare with such as were made by me as I am now at this instant. How many times do I say I am no more my self; how much is my present image further from those then from that of my decease? It is an over-great abuse unto nature to dragge and hurry her so far that she must be forced to give us over, and abandon our conduct, our eyes, our teeth, our legs and the rest, to the mercy of a forraine help and begged assistance; and to put ourselves into the hands of art, weary to follow it. I am not over-much or greedily desirous of sallets or of fruits, except melons. My father hated all manner of sawces; I love them all. Over- much eating does hurt and distemper me, but for the quality I have yet no certain knowledge that any meate offends me; I never observe either a full or waned Moone, nor make a difference betweene the Spring time or Autumne. There are certain inconstant and unknown motions in us. For (by way of example) I have heretofore found redish- rootes to be very good for me, then very hurtful, and now again very well agreeing with my stomacke. In diverse other things I feel my appetit to change , and my stomacke to diversifie from time to time. I have altred my course of drinking, sometimes from white to claret wine, and then from claret to white again. I am very friand and gluttonous of fish, and keep my shroving dayes upon fish dayes, and my feasts upon fasting-dayes. I believe as some others do, that fish is of lighter digestion than flesh. As I make it a conscience to eate flesh upon a fish day, so does my taste to eate fish and flesh together. Tbe diversity betweene them seems to me over- distant. Even from my youth I was wont now and then to steale some repast, either that I might sharpen my stomake against the next day; (for as Epicurus was wont to fast, and made but sparing meales, thereby to accustome his voluptuousness to neglect plenty; I, contrary to him, to enure my sensuality to speede the better, and more merrily to make use of plenty) or else I fasted, the better to maintaine my vigor for the service or performance of some bodily or mental action; for both are strangely dulled and ideled in me, through over-much fulnesse and repleatnesse. (And above all I hate that foolish combination of so sound and bucksome a Goddesse with that indigested and belching God, all puffed with the fume of his liquor) or to recover my crazed stomake, or because I wanted some good company. And I say as Epicurus said, that A man should not so much respect what he eateth as with whom he eateth. And commend Chilon, that he would not promise to come to Perianders feast before he knew certainely who were the other bidden guests. No viands are so sweetly pleasing, no sauce so tastefull, as that which is drawne from conversable and mutual society. I think it wholesome to eate more leisurely, and less in quality, and to feede oftner; But I will have appetit and hunger to be endeared. I should find no pleasure, after a phisicall manner, to swallow three or foure forced and spare meales a day. Who can assure me, if I have a good taste or stomacke in the morning, that I shall have it again at supper? Let us old men, let us, I say, take the first convenient time that commeth; Let us leave hopes and prognostikes unto Almanacke-makers. The extreme fruit of my health is pleasure; Let us hold fast on the present, and to us known. I eschew constancy in these Lawes of fasting. Who so will have a form to serve him, let him avoyd continuance of it; but we harden ourselves unto it and thereunto wholly apply our forces: sixe moneths after, you shall find your stomacke so enured unto it, that you shall have gotten nothing but this, to have lost the liberty to use it otherwise without domage. I use to go with my legs and thighs no more covered in Sommer than in Winter, for I never weare but one pair of single silke stockins. For the easing of my rhume and helpe of my chollike, I have of late used to keep my head and belly warme. My infirmities did in few dayes habituate themselves thereunto, and disdained my ordinary provisions: From a single night-cappe I came to a double coverchef, and from a bonnet to a lined and quilted hat. The bumbasting of my doublet serves me now for no more use than a stomacher; it is a thing of nothing, unless I adde a hare or a vulture’s skin to it, and some warme wrapping about my head. Follow this gradation, and you shall go a fair pace. I will do no such thing. If I durst I could find in my hart to revoke the beginning I have given unto it. Fall you into any ne w inconvenience? This reformation will no longer avail you. You are so accustomed unto it that you are driven to seek some new one. So are they overthrowne that suffer themselves with forced formalities or strict rules to be intangled, and do superstitiously constraine themselves unto them: they have need of more, and of more after that: they never come to an end. It is much more commodious both for our business and for our pleasure (as did our forefathers) to lose our dinner, and deferre making of good cheere onto the hour of withdrawing and of rest, without interrupting the day: So was I wont to do heretofore. I have for my health found out since by experience, that on the contrary it is better to dine, and that one shall digest better being awake. Whether I be in health or in sicknesse, I am not much subject to be thirsty; indeede my mouth is somewhat dry, but without thirst. And commonly I use not to drinke, but when with eating I am forced to desire it, and that is when I have eaten well. For a man of an ordinary stature I drinke indifferent much. In Sommer, and at a hungry meale, I not only exceed the limits of Augustus, who drunke but precisely three times; but, not to offend the rule of Democritus, who forbade us to stay at foure as an unlucky number, if need be, I come to five: Three demisextiers, or thereabouts. I like little glasses best; and I love to empty my glasse, which some others dislike, as a thing unseemely. Sometimes and that very often, I temper my wine one halfe and many times three parts with water. And when I am in my own house, from an ancient custom which my fathers Physitian ordained both for him and himself, looke what quantity of Wine is thought will serve me a meale, the same is commonly tempered two or three hours before it be served in, and so kept in the celler. It is reported that Cranaus, King of the Athenians, was the first that invented the mingling of Wine with Water. Whether it were profitable or no, I will not now dispute or stand upon. I think it more decent and more wholesome that children should drinke no Wine until they be past the age of sixteene or eighteene years. The most usual and common form of life is the best: Each particularity does in mine opinion impugne it. And I should as much detest a Germane that should put Water in his Wine, as a French-man that should drinke it pure. Publike custom gives Law unto such things. I fear a foggy and thicke air, and shunne smoke more than death (the first thing I began to repair when I came to be maister of my own house, was the chimnies and privies, which in most of our buildings is a general and intollerable fault); and [among] mischiefes and difficulties attending on Warre, there is none I hate more than in hot-sweltring wether to ride up and down all the day long in smoky dust, as many times our Soldiers are faine to do. I have a free and easy respiration, and do most commonly pass over my murres and colds without offence to my lungs, or without coughing. The soultry heate of sommer is more offensive to me than the sharpnesse of Winter; for, Besides the incommodity of heat, which is less to be remedied than the inconvenience of cold, and besides the force of the Sunnes beames, which strike into the head, mine eyes are much offended with any kind of glittring or sparkling light, so that I cannot well sit at dinner over against a clear-burning fire. To allay or dim the whiteness of paper, when I was most given to reading, I was wont to lay a piece of greene glasse upon my book, and was thereby much eased. Hitherto I never used spectacles, nor know not what they meane; and can yet see as far as ever I could, and as any other man; true it is, that when night comes, I begin to perceive a dimnes and weakenesse in reading, the continuall exercise whereof, and specially by night, was ever somewhat troublesome unto mine eyes. See here a steppe-backe, and that very sensible. I shall recoyle [one] more from a second to a third, and from a third to a fourth, so gently, that before I feel the declination and age of my sight I must be stark blinde. So artificially do the Fates untwist our lives-threede. Yet am I in doubt that my hearing is about to become thicke, and you shall see that I shall have lost it halfe when yet I shall find fault with their voyces that speak unto me. The mind must be strained to a high pitch to make it perceive how it declineth. My going is yet very nimble, quick, and stout; and I wot not which of the two I can more hardly stay at one instant, either my mind or my body. I must like that preacher well that can tie mine attention to a whole sermon. In places of ceremonies, where every man does so nicely stand upon countenance, where I have seen Ladies hold their eyes so steady, I could never so hold out, but some part of mine would ever be gadding; although I be sitting there, I am not well settled. As Chrysippus the Phylosophers chambermaide said of her Master, that he was never drunke but in his legs; for whersoever he sate, he was ever accustomed to be wagging with them; and this she said at what time store of Wine had made his companions cuppe-shotten, and yet he felt no alteration, but continued sober in mind; It might likewise have been said of me, that even from mine infancy I had either folly or quickesilver in my feete, so much stirring and natural inconstancy have I in them where ever I place them. It is unmannerlinesse and prejudiciall unto health, indeed to pleasure also, to feede grosely and greedily as I do. I shall sometimes through haste bite my tongue and fingers ends. Diogenes meeting with a child that did eate so, gave his tutor a whirret on the eare. There were men in Rome that as others teach youth to go with a good grace, so they taught men to chew with decency. I do sometimes lose the leisure to speak, which is so pleasing an entertainment at the table, provided they be discourses short, witty, and pleasant. There is a kind of jelousie and envy betweene our pleasures, and they often shocke and hinder one another. Alcibiades, a man very exquisitely-skilfull in making good cheere, inhibited all manner of music at tables, because it should not hinder the delight of discourses, for the reason which Plato affords him, that it is a custom of popular or base men to call for minstrels or singers at feasts, and an argument they want witty or good discourses and pleasing entertainment, wherewith men of conceipt and understanding know how to enterfeast and entertaine themselves. Varro requireth this at a banket, an assembly of persons, fair, goodly, and handsome of presence, affable and delightfull in conversation, (which must not be dumbe nor dull, sullaine nor slovenly), cleanlinesse and neatnesse in meates, and fair wether. A good mind-pleasing table-entertainement is not a little voluptuous feast, nor a meanly artificiall banquet. Neither great or stern commanders in Warres, nor famous or strict Philosophers, have disdained the use or knowledge of it. My imagination has bequeathed three of them to the keeping of my memory only, which fortune did at severall times yield exceedingly delightsome unto me. My present state does now exclude me from them. For every one, according to the good temper of body or mind wherein he finds himself, addeth either principal grace or taste unto them. My self, who but grovell on the ground, hate that kind of human Wisedome which would make us disdainful and enemies of the bodies reformation. I deem it an equall injustice either to take natural sensualities against the hart, or to take them too near the hart. Xerxes was a ninny- hammer, who, enwrapped and given to all humane voluptuousness, proposed rewards for those that should devise such as he had never heard of. And he is not much behind him in sottishnesse that goes about to abridge those which nature has devised for him. One should neither follow nor avoyd them, but receive them. I receive them somewhat more amply and graciously, and rather am contented to follow natural inclination. We need not exaggerate their inanity, it will sufficiently be felt and does sufficiently produce itself. Godamercy our weake, crazed, and joy-diminishing spirit, which makes us distaste both them and himself. He treateth both himself and whatsoever he receiveth, sometimes forward and other times backeward, according as himself is either insaciate, vagabond, new fangled, or variable. Sincerum est nisi vas, quodcanque infundis acescit. --- Hor. i. Epist. ii. 54. In no sweet vessell all you poure, In such a vessell soone will sowre. My self, who brag so curiously to embrace and particularly to allow the commodities of life, whensoever I looke precisely into it, I find nothing therein but winde. But what? we are nothing but winde. And the very winde also, more wisely then we loves to bluster and to be in agitation: And is pleased with his own offices, without desiring stability or solidity, qualities that be not his own. The meere pleasures of imagination, as well as displeasure (say some) are the greatest, as the balance of Critolaus did express. It is no wonder she composeth them at her pleasure, and cuts them out of the whole cloath. I see dayly some notable presidents of it, and perhaps to be desired. But I, that am of a commixt condition, homely and plaine, cannot so thoroughly bite on that only and so simple object, but shall grosely and carelesly give myself over to the present delights of the general and humane law, intellectually sensible and sensibly-intellectuall. The Cyrenaique Philosophers are of the opinion that as griefes, so corporall pleasures are more powerfull, and as double, so more just. There are some (as Aristotle says) who, with a savage kind of stupidity, will seem distastefull or squemish of them. Some others I know that do it out of ambition. Why renounce they not also breathing? why live they not of their own, and refuse light, because it commeth of gratuity and costs them neither invention nor vigor? That Mars, or Pallas, or Mercurie should nourish them to see, instead of Ceres, Venus, or Bacchus? Will they not seek for the quadrature of the circle even upon their wives? I hate that we should be commanded to have our minds in the clouds whilst our bodies are sitting at the table; yet would I not have the mind to be fastned thereunto, nor wallow upon it, nor lie along thereon, but apply itself and sit at it. Aristippus defended but the body, as if we had no soul; Zeno embraced but the soul, as if we had no body. Both viciously. Pythagoras (say they) has followed a Philosophie all in contemplation; Socrates altogether in manners and in action; Plato has found a mediocrity between both. But they say so by way of discourse. For the true temperature is found in Socrates, and Plato is more Socratical then Pythagorical, and it becomes him best. When I dance, I dance; and when I sleepe, I sleepe. And when I am solitarie walking in a fair orchard, if my thoughts have a while entertained themselve with strange occurrences, I do another while bring them to walke with me in the orchard, and to be partakers of the pleasure of that solitarinesse and of my self. Nature has like a kind mother observed this, that such actions as she for our necessities has enjoyned unto us should also be voluptuous unto us. And does not only by reason but also by appetite envite us unto them; it were injustice to corrupt her rules. When I behold Cæsar and Alexander in the thickest of their wondrous great labours so absolutely to enjoy humane and corporall pleasures, I say not that they release thereby their mind, but rather strengthen the same, submitting by vigor of courage their violent occupation and laborious thoughts to the customary use of ordinary life. Wise had they been had they beleeved that that was their ordinary vocation and this their extraordinary. What egregious fools are we? He has passed his life in idleness, say we; alas! I have done nothing this day. What, have you not lived? It is not only the fundamentall, but the noblest of your occupation. Had I been placed or thought fit for the managing of great affairs, I would have showed what I could have performed. Have you knowen how to meditate and mannage your life? you have accomplished the greatest work of all. For a man to show and exploit himself nature has no neede of fortune; she equally shewes herself upon all grounds, in all sutes, before and behinde, as it were without curteines, welt, or gard. Have you known how to compose your manners? you have done more than he who has composed bookes. Have you known how to take rest? you have done more than be who has taken Empires and Citties. The glorious masterpiece of man is to live to the repulse. All other things - as to raigne, to governe, to board up treasure, to thrive, and to build - are for the most part but appendixes and supports therunto. It is to you a great pleasure to see a General of an army at the foote of a breach, which ere long intendeth to charge or enter, all whole, undistracted, and carelesly to prepare, himself, while he sits at dinner with his friends about him, to talk of any matter. And I am delighted to see Brutus, having both heaven and earth conspired against him and the liberty of Rome, by stealth to take some hours of the night from his other cares, and walking of the round, in al security to read, to note, and to abbreviate Polibius. It is for base and petty minds, dulled and overwhelmed with the weight of affairs, to be ignorant how to leave them, and not to know how to free themselves from them, nor how to leave and take them again. O fortes pejoraque passi, Mecum sæpe viri, nunc vino pellite curas, Cras ingens iterabimus æquor. -- Hor. Car. i. Od. vii. 30. Valiant compeeres, who oft have worse endured With me, let now with wine your cares be cured: To morrow we again Will launch into the main. Whether it be in jest or earnest that the Sorbonicall or theologicall wine and their feasts or gaudy dayes are now come to be proverbially jested at, I think there is some reason that by how much more profitably and seriously they have bestowed the morning in the exercise of their schooles, so much more commodiously and pleasantly should they dine at noone. A clear conscience to have well employed and industriously spent the other hours is a perfect seasoning and savoury condiment of tables. So have wise men lived. And that inimitable contention unto virtue which so amazeth us in both Catoes, their so strictly-severe humor, even unto importunity, has thus mildly submitted my self, and taken pleasure in the laws of humane condition and in Venus and Bacchus. According to their Sects precepts, which require a perfectly wise man to be fully expert and skillfull in the true use of sensualities, as in other duties or devoires belonging to life. Cui cor sapiat ei et sapiat palatus: (Cic. Fin. ii.) ’Let his palate be savoury whose heart is savoury.’ Easie-yielding and facility does, in my conceit, greatly honor and is best befitting a magnanimous and noble mind. Epaminondas thought it no scorne to thrust himself amongst the boyes of his citie and dance with them, indeed, and to sing and play, and with attention busie himself, were it in things that might derogate from the honor and reputation of his glorious victories, and from the perfect reformation of manners that was in him. And amongst so infinite admirable actions of Scipio the grand father, a man worthy to be esteemed of heavenly race, nothing addeth so much grace unto him as to see him carelesly to dallie and childishly to trifle in gathering and chusing of cockle-shels, and play at cost castle along the seashoare with his friend Lælius; and if it were fowle weather, amusing and solacing himself to represent in writing and comedies the most popular and base actions of men. And having his heade continually busied with that wonderful enterprise against Hanibal and Affricke, yet he still visited the schooles in Cicily, and frequented the lectures of Philosopby, arming his enemies teeth at Rome with envy and spight. Nor any thing more remarkeable in Socrates, then when, being old and crazed, he would spare so much time as to be instructed in the art of dancing and playing upon instruments, and thought the time well bestowed. Who, notwithstanding, has been seen to continue a whole day and night in an extasie or trance, indeed ever standing on his feet in presence of all the Greeke army, as it were surprised and ravished by some deep and mind-distracting thought. He has been noted to be the first amaongst so infinite valiant men in the army headlong to rush out to helpe and bring-off Alcibiades, engaged and enthronged by his enemies, to cover him with his body, and by main force of arms and courage bring him off from the rout; And in the Deliane battle to save and disingage Xenophon, who was beaten from his horse. And in the midst of all the Athenian people wounded, as it were, with so unworthy a spectacle, headlong present himself to the first man to recover Theramenes from out of the hands of the officers and satelites of the thirty tyrants of Athens, who were leading him to his death, and never desisted from his hold attempt until he met with Theramenes himself, though he were followed and assisted with two more. He has been seen (provoked thereunto by a matchlesse beauty, wherewith he was richly endowed by nature) at any time of neede to maintaine severe continency. He has continually been noted to march to the wars on foote, to breake the ice with his bare feete, to weare one same garment in summer and winter, to exceed all his companions in patience of any labor or travell, to eate no more or otherwise at any banquet then at his ordinary. He has been seen seven and twenty years together, with one same undismaid countenance, patiently to bear and endure hunger, poverty, the indocility and stubbornerse of his children, the frowardnes and scratchings of his wife; and in the end malicious detraction, tyranny, enprysonment, shakels, and poyson. But was that man envited to drinke to him by duty of civility? he was also the man of the army to whom the advantage thereof remained? And yet be refused not, nor dis-dained to play for nuts with children, nor to run with them upon a hobby-horse, wherein he had a very good grace; For all actions (says Philosophy) do equally beseeme well and honor a wise man. We have good ground and reason, and should never be weary to present the image of this incomparable man unto al patternes and formes of perfections. There are very few examples of life absolutely full and pure. And our instruction is greatly wronged in that it has certain weak, defective, and unperfect formes proposed unto it, scarcely good for any good use, which divert and draw us backe, and may rather be termed corrupters then correcters. Man is easily deceived. One may more easily go by the sides, where extremity serveth as bound, as a stay and as a guide, then by the midway, which is open and wide, and more according unto art then according unto nature, but therewithall less nobly and with less commendation. The greatness of the mind is not so much to drawe up and hale forward, as to know how to range, direct, and circumscribe itself. It holdeth for great whatsover is sufficient. And sheweth her height in loving meane things better then eminent. There is nothing so goodly, so fair, and so lawfull, as to play the man well and duely; Nor Science so hard and difficult as to know how to live this life well. And of all the infirmities we have the most savage is to despise our being. Whoso will sequester or distract his mind, let him hardily do it, if he can, at what time his body is not well at ease, thereby to discharge it from that contagion. And elsewhere contrary, that she may assist and favor him, and not refuse to be partaker of his natural pleasures, and continually be pleased with them; adding thereunto, if she be the wiser, moderation, lest through indiscretion they might be confounded with [dis]pleasure. Intemperance is the plague of sensuality, and temperance is not her scourge, but rather her seasoning. Eudoxus, who thereon established his chief felicity, and his companions that raised the same to so high a pitch by means of temperance, which in them was very singular and exemplar, savored the same in her most gracious sweetness. I enjoin my mind, with a looke equally regular, to behold both sorrow and voluptuousness; Eodem enim vitio est effugio animi in lætitia, quo in dolore contractio: (Cic. Tusc. Qu. iv.) “As faulty is the enlarging of the mind in mirth, as the contracting it in grief;” and equally constant: But the one merrily and the other severely; And according to that she may bring unto it, to be as careful to extinguish the one, as diligent to quench the other. To have a perfect insight into a good, draws with it an absolute insight into evil. And sorrow has in her tender beginnning something that is unavoydable, and voluptuousness in her excessive end something that is evitable. Plato coupleth them together, and would have it to be the equall office of fortitude to combat against sorrowes, and fight against the immoderate and charming blandishments of sensuality. They are two fountaines at which whoso draweth, whence, when, and as much as he needeth, be it a city, be it a man, be it a beast, he is very happy. The first must be taken for physicke and necessity, and more sparingly; The second for thirst, but not unto drunkennesse. Paine, voluptuousness, love and hate, are the first passions a child feeleth; if reason approach, and they apply themselves unto it, that is virtue. I have a Dictionary severally and wholly to my self. I pass the time when it is foul and incommodious; when it is fair and good I will not pass it. I run it over again, and take hold of it. A man should run the badde, and settle himself in the good. This vulgar phrase of pass time and to pass the time, represents the custom of those wise men who think to have no better account of their life then to pass it over and escape it; to pass it over and bawke it, and so much as in them lyeth to ignore and avoyd it, as a thing of an yrkesome, tedious, and to be disdained quality. But I know it to be otherwise, and find it to be both priseable and commodious, indeed in her last declination, where I hold it. And Nature has put the same into our hands, furnished with such and so favourable circumstances that if it press and molest us, or if unprofitably it escape us, we must blame ourselves. Stulti vita ingrata est, trepida est, tota in futurum fertur: (Sen. Epist. xv.) ’A fooles life is all pleasant, all fearefull, all fond of the future.’ I therefore prepare and compose my self to forgoe and lose it without grudging; but a thing that is loseable and transitory by its own condition, not as troublesome and importunate. Nor beseemes it a man to be grieved when he dieth,except they be such as please themselves to live still. There is a kind of husbandry in knowing how to enjoy it. I enioy it double to others. For the measure in jovissance dependeth more or less on the application we lend it. Especially at this instant, that I perceive mine to be short in time, I wil extend it in weight; I wil stay the readines of her flight by the promptitude of my holdfast by it, and by the vigor of custom recompense the haste of her fleeting. According as the possession of life is more short, I must endeavour to make it more profound and full. Other men feel the sweetness and contentment and prosperity. I feel it as well as they, but it is not in passing and gliding; yet should it be studied, tasted and ruminated, thereby to yield it condigne thanks, that it pleased to grant the same unto us. They enjoy other pleasures, as that of sleep without knowing them. To the end that sleepe should not dully and unfeelingly escape me, and that I might better taste and be acquainted with it, I have heretofore found it good to be troubled and interrupted in the same. I have a kind of contentment to consult with my self, which consultation I do [not] superficially run over, but considerately sound the same, and apply my reason to entertaine and receive it, which is now become froward, peevish and distasted. Doe I find my self in some quiet moode? is there any sensuality that tickles me? I do not suffer the same to busie itself or dally about sences, but associate my mind unto it. Not to engage or plunge itself therein, but therein to take delight; not to lose, but therein to find itself. And for her part I employ her to view herself in that prosperous state, to ponder and esteeme the good fortune she has, and to amplifle the same. She measureth how much she is beholding unto God, for that she is at rest with her conscience, and free from other [in]testine passions, and has in her body her natural disposition; orderly and competently enjoying certain flattering and effeminate functions, with which it pleaseth him of his grace to recompence the griefes wherewith his justice at his pleasure smiteth us. Oh, how availfull is it unto her to be so seated, that [wher]ever she casteth her eyes, the heavens are calme round about her, and no desire, no fear, or doubt, troubleth the air before her; here is no difficulty, either past, or present, or to come, over which her imagination passeth no[t] without offence. This consideration takes a great lustre from the comparison of different conditions. Thus do I in a thousand shapes propose unto my self those to whom either fortune or their own error does transport and torment. And these nearer, who so slackly- and incuriously receive their good fortune. They are men which indeed pass their time; they overpasse the present and that which they possesse, thereby to serve their hopes with shadowes and vain images, which fancy sets before them, Morte oblita quales fama est volitare figuras Aut quæ sopitos deludunt somnia sensus. -- Virg. Æn. x. 641. Such walking shapes we say, when men are dead, Dreames, whereby sleeping senses are misse-led. which hasten and prolong their flight according as they are followed. The fruit and scope of their pursuit is to pursue. As Alexander said, ’The end of his Travell was to travell.’ Nil actum credens cum quid superesset agendum. -- Lucan. ii. 656. Who thought that nought was done When ought remain’d undone. As for me, then, I love my [life] and cherish it, such as it has pleased God to graunt it us. I desire not he should speak of the necessity of eating and drinking. And I would think to offend no less excusably, in desiring it should have it double. Sapiens divitiarum naturalium quæsitor acerrimus: (Sen. Epist. cxix.) “A wise man is a most eager and earnest searcher of those things that are natural.” Not that we should sustain ourselves by only putting a little of that drug into our mouth wherewith Epimenedes was wont to allay hunger, and yet maintained himself. Nor that we should insensibly produce children at our fingers ends or at our heels, but rather (speaking with reverence) that we might with pleasure and voluptuousness produce them both at our heels and fingers ends. Nor that the body should be void of desire and without tickling delight. They are ungrateful and impious complaints. I cheerfully and thankfully, and with a good heart, accept what nature has created for me, and am therewith well pleased and am proud of it. Great wrong is offered unto that great and all-puissant Giver, to refuse his gift, which is so absolutely good; and disanull or disfigure the same, since he made perfectly good. Omnia quæ secundum naturam sunt, estimatione digna sunt: (Cic. Fin. Bon. iii.) “All things that are according to nature, are worthy to be esteemed.” Of Philosophy’s opinions I more willingly embrace those which are the most solid, and that is to say such as are most humane and most ours. My discourses are suitable to my manner—slow and humble. She then brings forth a child well-pleasing me, when she betakes herself to her Quiddities and Ergoes, that it is a barbarous alliance to marry what is divine with that which is terrestrial; wed reasonable with unreasonable; combine severe with indulgent, and couple honest with unhonest; that voluptuousness is a brutal quality, unworthy the taste of a wiseman. The only pleasure he draws from the enjoying of a fair young bride is the delight of his conscience, by performing an action according unto order, As to put on his boots for a profitable riding. Oh that his followers had no more right, or sinews, or pith, or juice, at the dismaidening of their wives than they have in his Lesson. It is not that which Socrates, both his and our Master, says. He valueth rightly as he ought corporall voluptuousness; but he preferreth that of the mind, as having more force, more constancy, facility, variety and dignity. This according to him goeth nothing alone, he [is] not so phantasticall, but only first. For him temperance is a moderatrix, and not an adversary of sensualities. Nature is a gentle guide, yet not more gentle then prudent and just. Intrandum est in rerum naturam, et penitus quid ea postulet, pervidendum: (Ibid. v.) ’We must enter into the nature of things, and throughly see what she inwardly requiers.’ I quest after her track; we have confounded her with artificiall traces. And that Academicall and Peripateticall summum bonum or sovereign felicity, which is to live according to her rules by this reason becomes difficult to be limited, and hard to be expounded. And that of the Stoics, first cousin to the other, which is to yield unto nature. Is it not an error to esteeme some actions less worthy forasmuch as they are necessary? Yet shall they never remove out of my head that it is not a most convenient marriage to wed Pleasure unto Necessity. With which (says an ancient Writer) the Gods do ever complot and consent. To what end do we by a divorce dismember a frame contented with so mutual, coherent, and brotherly correspondency. Contrariwise, let us repair and renew the same by interchangable offices, that the spirit may awake and quicken the dull heaviness of the body, and the body stay the lightness of the spirit, and settle and fix the same. Qui velut summum bonum, laudat animæ naturam, et tanquam malum, naturam carnis accusat, profecto et animam carnaliter appetit, et carnem incarnaliter fugit; quoniam id vanitate sentit humana, non veritate divina: (Aug. Verb. Apostol. ser. xiii. c. 6.) “He that praises the nature of the soul as his principal good, and accuses nature of the flesh as evil, assuredly he both carnally affects the soul and carnally eschews the flesh, since he is of this mind not by divine verity, but humane vanity.” There is no part or parcel unworthy of our care in that present which God has bestowed upon us. We are accountable even for the least hair of it. And it is no commission for fashion’s sake for any man to direct man according to his condition it is express, natural, and principal: And the Creator has seriously and severely given the same unto us. Only authority is of force with men of common reach and understanding, and is of more weight in a strange language. But here let us charge again. Stultitiæ proprium quis non dixerit, ignave et contumaciter facere quæ facienda sunt; et alio corpus impellere, alio animum, distrahique inter diversissimos motus? “Who will not call it a property of folly to do slothfully and fro-wardly what is to be done, and one way to drive the body and an other way the mind, and himself to be distracted into most diverse motions?” Which the better to see let such a man one day tell you the ammusements and imaginations which he puts into his own head, and for which he diverteth his thoughts for a good repast, and bewaileth the hour he employeth in feeding himself; you shall find there is nothing so wallowish in all the messes of your table as is that goodly entertainement of the mind (It were often better for us to be sound a sleepe, than awake unto that we do), and you shall find that his discourses and intentions are not worth your meanest dish. Suppose they were the entrancings of Archimedes himself, and what of that? I here touch not nor do I blend with that rabble or raskality of men, as we are, nor with that vanity of desires and cogitations which divert us, only those venerable mindes which through a fervency of devotion and earnestnesse of religion, elevated to a constant and consciencious meditation of heavenly-devine things, and which, by the violence of a lively and virtue of a vehement hope, preoccupating the use of eternall soul-saving nourishment; the finall end, only stay and last scope of Christian desires; the only constant delight and incorruptible pleasure; disdaine to rely on our necessitous, fleeting, and ambiguous commodities; and easily resigne the care and use of sensuall and temporall feeding unto the body. It is a priviledged study. Super-celestiall opinions and under- terrestriall manners are things that amongst us I have ever seen to be of singular accord. Æsope, that famous man, saw his Master pisse as he was walking; What (said he) must we not, etc., when we are running? Let us husband time as well as we can. Yet shall we employ much of it both idely and ill. As if our mind had not other hours enough to do her business without disassociating herself from the body in that little space which she needeth for her necessity. They will be exempted from them and escape man. It is meere folly; insteade of transforming themselves into Angels, they trans-change themselves into beastes; in lieu of advancing, they abase themselves. Such transcending humors affright me as much as steepy, high, and inaccessible places. And I find nothing so hard to be disgested in Socrates his life as his extasies and communication with Dæmones. Nothing so humane in Plato as that which they say he is called divine. And of our sciences those which are raised and extolled for the highest seem to me the most basest and terrestriall. I find nothing so humble and mortal in Alexanders life as his concepts about his immortalization. Philotas by his answer quipped at him very pleasantly and wittily. He had by a letter congratulated with him, and rejoiced that the Oracle of Jupiter Hammon had placed him amongst the Gods; to whom he answered, that in respect and consideration of him he was very glad; but yet there was some cause those men should be pitied that were to live with a man and obey him who out-went others, and would not be contented with the state and condition of mortal man. -----Diis te minorem quod geris, imperas. -- Hor. Car. iii. Od. vi. Since you less then the Gods Bear’st you, you rul’st with ods. The quaint inscription wherewith the Athenians honored the coming of Pompey into their City agrees well and is conformable to my meaning. D’autant es tu Dieu comme Tu te recognois homme. -- Plut. vit. Pomp. So far a God you mayest accompted be As you a man doest reacknowledge you. It is an absolute perfection, and as it were divine for a man to know how to enjoy his being loyally. We seek for other conditions because we understand not the use of ours, and go out of ourselves forasmuch as we know not what abiding there is. We may long enough get upon stilts, for be we upon them, yet must we go with our own legs. And sit we upon the highest throne of the World, yet sit we upon our own tail. The best and most commendable lives and best pleasing men are (in my conceit) those which with order are fitted, and with decorum are ranged to the common mould and humane model, but without wonder or extravagancy. Now has old age need to be handled more tenderly. Let us recommend it unto that God who is the protector of Health and fountain of all wisdom, but blithe and social: Frui paratis et valido mihi Latoe dones; et precor integra Cum mente, nec turpem senectam Degere, nec cithara carentem. -- Hor. Car. i. Od. xxxi. 17. Apollo graunt enjoy the health I may That I have got, and with sound mind, I pray; Nor that I may with shame spend my old years, Nor wanting music to delight mine ears.